<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Pkcj6qv">BASED EVALUATION</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Johanna</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Birckmayer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Poudre Health Services District Harvard University Harvard University Graduate School of Education , Cambridge , MA 02138 ;</note>
								<orgName type="department">Poudre Health Services District</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Harvard University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Harvard University Graduate School of Education</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02138</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hirschon</forename><surname>Carol</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Poudre Health Services District Harvard University Harvard University Graduate School of Education , Cambridge , MA 02138 ;</note>
								<orgName type="department">Poudre Health Services District</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Harvard University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Harvard University Graduate School of Education</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02138</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Poudre Health Services District Harvard University Harvard University Graduate School of Education , Cambridge , MA 02138 ;</note>
								<orgName type="department">Poudre Health Services District</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Harvard University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Harvard University Graduate School of Education</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02138</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Carol</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
							<email>carol_weiss@harvard.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Poudre Health Services District Harvard University Harvard University Graduate School of Education , Cambridge , MA 02138 ;</note>
								<orgName type="department">Poudre Health Services District</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Harvard University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Harvard University Graduate School of Education</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02138</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_8RKV9Bs">BASED EVALUATION</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">1DF8F5E9080C00CEFEB84F5D861922FD</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T05:32+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_usnQ2KG"><p xml:id="_ugqyH9V"><s xml:id="_5p5BCuX">Theory-based evaluation (TBE) explores the how and why of program success or failure.</s><s xml:id="_STwyEzh">Advocates of TBE claim that it produces information unavailable in traditional process and outcome studies.</s><s xml:id="_MzpTZ2Q">This article examines six published papers of TBEs.</s><s xml:id="_Fm3JDWX">It finds that the authors of the papers do not always make explicit the relation of their data to the theory of the program.</s><s xml:id="_pfUngfK">Nevertheless, it was evident in one or more cases that TBE identified unnecessary program components, located intermediary changes, raised new questions, contributed to a paradigm shift, highlighted the difficulties of taking successful pilot programs to scale, and provided clarity and focus for the evaluation.</s><s xml:id="_FMQz8Na">Interestingly, in none of the studies was the original theory completely right.</s><s xml:id="_YgxqDFZ">Lessons for the future of TBE are drawn.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="10" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="11" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="12" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="13" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="14" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="15" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="16" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="17" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="18" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="19" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="20" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="21" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="22" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="23" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="24" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="25" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_KcXnfgq"><p xml:id="_emfzgWv"><s xml:id="_DHbegfs">based approach has accomplished and we extract lessons learned regarding the application of TBE.</s></p><p xml:id="_CDXXeuu"><s xml:id="_yHTN9FA">A brief word on what TBE is.</s><s xml:id="_xNJYHqS">It is an approach to evaluation that requires surfacing the assumptions on which the program is based in considerable detail: what activities are being conducted, what effect each particular activity will have, what the program does next, what the expected response is, what happens next, and so on, to the expected outcomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Suchman 1967;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Weiss 1972</ref><ref type="bibr">Weiss , 1995</ref><ref type="bibr">Weiss , 1997</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Weiss , 1998;;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bickman 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Chen 1990</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Chen and Rossi 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Costner 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Finney and Moos 1989)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_VDnswhz">The evaluation then follows each step in the sequence to see whether the expected ministeps actually materialize.</s></p><p xml:id="_GsTxugx"><s xml:id="_dgm5wvX">For example, a counseling program for youngsters at risk of school failure aims to give the participants greater self-confidence in their own abilities and greater motivation to study and learn.</s><s xml:id="_8Sng6Jq">It does this through recruiting counselors of the same race and ethnicity as the at-risk students, so that they can be role models of successful adults; the counselors establish a "big brother/big sister" relationship with the students to engender a sense of trust; they offer a series of learning activities, ranging from easy to hard, to demonstrate to students that they can be successful at learning; and it offers field trips to workplaces and colleges to show students the wide possibilities available to them if they do well in school.</s><s xml:id="_U5u2Pw9">The program is thus based on a series of little theories about what is important to do if the participants are to achieve success.</s></p><p xml:id="_RSPz5ab"><s xml:id="_3Y8et9M">An evaluation that investigates the theories underlying this program thus collects data at many points along the course of the program.</s><s xml:id="_5BtzWhE">Does the program succeed in matching counselors to students by race/ethnicity, and if so, do students see the counselors as models to emulate?</s><s xml:id="_XQ6rMHt">Do the students see the counselors more as "big brothers/big sisters" than, say, as teachers or authority figures, and if so, does the nature of the relationship bring about a sense of trust?</s><s xml:id="_bytH59V">Do the counselors implement the suggested set of learning activities in the order planned, and if so, do students experience success in moving through the sequence?</s><s xml:id="_g8Rq5Ur">Do they gain confidence in their academic abilities?</s><s xml:id="_tbGhPpd">Does the program provide the planned kinds of field trips, and do students gain from the experience a better knowledge of possible educational and vocational futures?</s><s xml:id="_pTJYmkK">Do students have greater motivation to work hard at their school work?</s><s xml:id="_qAH2eQa">The outcome question will be the following: Do students, in fact, do better in school?</s><s xml:id="_rbdaU7c">Any evaluations would ask that question and collect relevant data.</s><s xml:id="_vksaAQQ">What TBE does, in addition, is to track the steps along the route.</s><s xml:id="_ZwQYY9D">It seeks to find out whether the theories on which the program is based are realized in action (for further examples of TBEs, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Feindler et al. 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Pentz et al. 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Goodman and Wandersman 1994)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_ZE74HMq"><s xml:id="_m5krJrH">The theories in TBE can come from various sources.</s><s xml:id="_hbAHPua">Some writers suggest that they should be social science theories with a reasonable scientific pedigree <ref type="bibr">(Chen and Rossi, 1992)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_Um9Etz7">Others authors try simply to set forth the logic that must be involved if a program is going to work, and they may even name the program theory a "logic model" <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Coffman 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">McLaughlin and Jordan 1999)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_GbWrhcK">For example, a program that aims to increase safety in a public housing project by giving tenants representation on the managing board must assume something like the following: If tenants are members of the managing board, they will (a) demand greater security precautions and, because they are on the board, will be able to get additional security staff; or (b) keep their eyes on the property and residents and interlopers to forestall crime and <ref type="bibr">vandalism; or (c)</ref> encourage their neighbors to take more responsibility for security.</s><s xml:id="_F7mdavW">Nothing fancy or high falutin in the way of theory is involved here.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_4SfPj8B">POSITED BENEFITS OF TBE</head><p xml:id="_4hA5CqE"><s xml:id="_AUUqhZM">The benefits that advocates of TBE claim for this approach are of three kinds: advantages to program planning and modification, advantages for the growth of knowledge about human behavior and behavior change, and advantages for the planning and conduct of the evaluation of the specific program.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_G4jAp7F">ADVANTAGES FOR PROGRAM PLANNING AND PROGRAM IMPROVEMENT</head><p xml:id="_fRZHGMM"><s xml:id="_YNqfD3s">TBE provides information about the mechanisms that intervene between program activities and the achievement (or nonachievement) of expected results.</s><s xml:id="_55QJUEg">When the theory on which the evaluation is based is fine grained, the evaluation can track each link in the chains of assumptions.</s><s xml:id="_TjdH4RJ">The results of such an evaluation will show which chains of assumptions are well supported by the data collected, which chains of assumptions break down, and where in the chain they break down.</s><s xml:id="_TfCW738">The information should lead to the development of different, and hopefully more effective, strategies in the future.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_FP6w78d">ADVANTAGES FOR KNOWLEDGE DEVELOPMENT</head><p xml:id="_UzCHpz9"><s xml:id="_yFu6aFu">Advocates of TBE hope that better knowledge about the mechanisms of change will benefit not only the specific program (or type of program) studied.</s><s xml:id="_ehJQTG5">The hope is that the knowledge will generalize to a wider array of change efforts.</s><s xml:id="_Q4hr6kn">Even though each evaluation study is prisoner of the unique characteristics of its setting <ref type="bibr">(time, place, staff, participants, etc.)</ref>, repeated evaluations over time may be able to build a corpus of knowledge about which mechanisms work well and which work poorly.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_YPeAQbe">ADVANTAGES FOR PLANNING THE EVALUATION STUDY</head><p xml:id="_YV7qDx5"><s xml:id="_DxMGbvb">Most immediately, a theory-based approach highlights the elements of program activity that deserve attention in the evaluation.</s><s xml:id="_vQ3AjXJ">The evaluator uses the program's assumptions as the scaffolding for the study.</s><s xml:id="_D9S9yZ9">The evaluator can choose to collect data on the linkage mechanisms assumed to be operative in one theory, or in several theories, or she can select one set of particularly central (or problematic) assumptions and direct the evaluation toward investigating that specific link in the theory chain.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Pg9SJ5P">EXAMPLES OF TBE</head><p xml:id="_DupdfwK"><s xml:id="_vAHRBfK">In the following sections, we explore both the advantages and inherent difficulties of conducting TBE.</s><s xml:id="_cndege6">First, we briefly describe six evaluations of programs that use a theory-based approach.</s><s xml:id="_WZAUtYq">All deal with programs in health promotion because we found this a field in which TBE began early and is most often practiced.</s><s xml:id="_qf6nSBG">A summary of each program's design, theory, measures and findings is presented in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_6sEKTgK">These studies represent fairly large, well-funded efforts by social scientists to evaluate programs in which the program theory is developed during the planning process and tested during the evaluation.</s><s xml:id="_smTVy6D">At the end of this section, we discuss what was learned from the TBE approach.</s><s xml:id="_Gt9hFyW">We then discuss the application of TBE in smaller, less formal programs for which program theory is not clearly defined before the program is implemented.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_27a9TUg">Brug et al. (1996)</head><p xml:id="_QSJ6Sp2"><s xml:id="_vGm3Myd">A study by <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Brug et al. (1996)</ref> presents a theory-based approach to evaluating a nutrition education program in the Netherlands.</s><s xml:id="_eaYQjaG">The program aimed to reduce fat intake and increase fruit and vegetable consumption among study participants by programming computers to ask questions about participants' dietary intake and determinants of and barriers to changing their behaviors.</s><s xml:id="_aUtfj9R">The computer then generated messages specifically tailored to individuals' needs.</s><s xml:id="_n7fcAcf">The program theory posited that the tailored messages would change</s></p><p xml:id="_RbER9dB"><s xml:id="_xmV4G2A">TABLE 1: A Summary of Six Theory-Based Evaluations Author Program Design Theory Measures Findings Brug et al.</s><s xml:id="_3g8PTNm">Nutrition Random assignment to Change in attitudes to-Self-reports of attitudes, Program group more positive (1996) education program or general ward desired diet, per-social influences, attitudes to vegetable and nutrition information.</s><s xml:id="_T52q4w3">ceived social influences, and self-efficacy fruit consumption (p &lt; .01);</s><s xml:id="_B9XfD7c">347 employees in the self-efficacy beliefs, and expectations; No effect on self-efficacy or Netherlands Royal intentions to change dietary fat, fruit, and social influences; Shell laboratory survey-diet ®®® reduce fat vegetable intake Program group strongest ined before and 3 weeks intake and increase tention to change consumppostintervention vegetable and fruit tion in recommended direcconsumption tion (p &lt; .01);</s><s xml:id="_7DH2asa">Program group lower fat scores (26.9 vs. 27.2</s><s xml:id="_chGkub5">grams of fat, p &lt; .01);</s><s xml:id="_UpKGkSX">Greatest effect among preintervention high fat eaters (9% vs. 3% fat reduction (p &lt; .01);</s><s xml:id="_4zuJCh2">Both groups increased vegetable but not fruit consumption Flay et al.</s><s xml:id="_X3gRfwW">Antismoking 47 schools randomly as-IOC ®®® increase in Self-reports of smoking Higher smoking knowledge in (1995) signed to one of five knowledge of effects of knowledge, awareness IOC group at T2 to T4 (p &lt; conditions: Social resis-smoking ®®® de-of social influences to .001);</s><s xml:id="_AUTfmAh">tance curriculum (SR), crease in smoking smoke, knowledge of Positive effect on social in-(continued)</s></p><p xml:id="_V9SzhpC"><s xml:id="_dXjw7n6">TABLE 1 Continued Author Program Design Theory Measures Findings TV campaign (TV), SR resistance skills, refusal fluences awareness and reand TV combined (SR/ SR, TV, and SR/TV self-efficacy, efforts to sistance skill knowledge in TV), information only ®®® increase in resist smoking, smoking SR (p &lt; .001)</s><s xml:id="_vxX8RxM">and TV (p &lt; curriculum (IOC), and knowledge of effects of prevalence estimates .03)</s><s xml:id="_NXFd64y">groups and SR/TV at no-treatment group smoking, awareness of (as indicator of smoking T2-T4 compared to NOT, (NOT).</s><s xml:id="_Rpr8nXq">340 seventh-influences to smoke, norms), approval of par-SR and TV greater effect on grade classrooms in skills to resist, efforts/ ental smoking, inten-social influences and resisstudy.</s><s xml:id="_fhFVY2x">Students survey-confidence to refuse to tions to smoke, and tance knowledge at T2 than ed preintervention (T1), smoke and decrease past and current SR/TV, difference faded by postintervention (T2), perception of smoking smoking T4; No differences across 1 year after (T3), and acceptability (norm) groups on refusal self-2 years after (T4) ®®® decrease in be-efficacy; havioral intentions to TV/SR positive effect on efsmoke ®®® decrease forts at T2 (p &lt; .009)</s><s xml:id="_zs34J5N">and T in smoking (p &lt; .02),</s><s xml:id="_MC5uBPv">effect faded by T4; Smoking prevalence estimates lowest for SR (p &lt; .001)</s><s xml:id="_DmkF53p">and TV (p &lt; .006)</s><s xml:id="_NtZApf5">at T2, effect continued for SR at T4 (p &lt; .007);</s><s xml:id="_ncp8XdV">No difference across groups in intentions to smoke; No difference in smoking rates Eisen, Sex education Random assignment to Increase awareness of Self-reports of sexual Knowledge in both HBM and Zellman, and curriculum either Health Belief probability and negative and contraceptive comparison class increased, McAlister Model (HBM) curricu-consequences of preg-knowledge, attitudes, HBM class greater increase (1992) lum or agencies' usual nancy, benefits of de-and behavior (p &lt; .05);</s><s xml:id="_fy8T9vm">sex education program.</s><s xml:id="_9pdYsqs">layed sexual activity or Health perceptions in both 1,444 13-to 19-year-contraceptive use, and HBM and comparison group olds attending six family decrease in percep-increased (p &lt; .01),</s><s xml:id="_T5GnjRB">no difplanning services and tions of barriers to ab-ference between groups; 1 school surveyed be-stinence or contracep-No difference in continued fore (T1), after (T2), tive use ®®® abstinence between groups; and 12 months after decrease sexual activity T1 female virgins in compar-(T3) intervention.</s><s xml:id="_NnGm5bC">and increase contracep-ison group more likely to tive use ®®® de-use effective contraceptives crease in pregnancy at T2-T3; T1 male virgins no difference between programs on outcomes at T2-T3; Both programs increased contraceptive efficiency T1 to T3 for nonvirgins, males in HBM group greater increase in contraceptive efficiency than comparison program (p &lt; .05),</s><s xml:id="_w3XCGh9">no difference between programs for females Puska, Heart disease Program community Change in individuals' Self-reports of knowl-Knowledge of risk factors in-Nissinen, prevention compared to contiguous knowledge and atti-edge, attitudes and be-creased, but change was and comparison community tudes and providing so-havior; physical exam only slightly higher in pro-Tuomilehto in Finland.</s><s xml:id="_4HDdrBr">Independent cial and environmental measuring height, gram community; (1985) random samples of support for behavior weight, blood pressure, No major changes in health (continued) TABLE 1 Continued Author Program Design Theory Measures Findings adults preintervention change ®®® reduc-and cholesterol attitudes; (T1), 5 years postinter-tions in individuals' risk Net reduction in smoking for vention (T2), and 10 factors (smoking, serum program community (27%, years postintervention cholesterol, and blood p &lt; .001)</s><s xml:id="_c4ReYt7">(T3) pressure) ®®® re-Net reduction in serum choduced mortality at lesterol for program men population level (p &lt; .01);</s><s xml:id="_aehdaPU">Net reduction for blood pressure (p &lt; .01);</s><s xml:id="_X4uPNmT">From 1974 to 1979, coronary heart disease mortality decreased (22% in program vs. 12% in control, p &lt; .05)</s><s xml:id="_eR9KvwM">Murray, Antismoking Ninth-grade students in Increase in antismoking Self reports of exposure 90% of schools implemented Prokhorov, Minnesota compared to activities in school and to protobacco and anti-activities, but implementaand Harty students in Wisconsin.</s><s xml:id="_qSZuEn7">media ®®® increase tobacco messages, tion was short-term; 95% of (1994) Random survey of in exposure to anti-antitobacco beliefs youth saw and/or heard anti-3,600 students in both smoking messages (health consequences tobacco ad in 1989-1990, states conducted each ®®® change in be-to others, passive smok-on average saw 50 ads per year from 1986 to 1990.</s><s xml:id="_7rA5GEd">liefs about health risks ing hazard, personal year; Minnesota increased ®®® decrease health risk), and exposure to antitobacco smoking rates tobacco use; expired air messages over Wisconsin test for carbon monox-(TV programming: net ide to confirm smoking change = +6.9%,</s><s xml:id="_JmmZw4C">p = .007;</s><s xml:id="_ffr6MVJ">self-reports radio: net change = +18.8%,</s><s xml:id="_VcuVHdd">p &lt; .001;</s><s xml:id="_mVSTmtC">newspaper and magazine ads: net change = +4.6%,</s><s xml:id="_HkNtw73">p = .006;</s><s xml:id="_pBWNYw4">billboards: net change 3.8%, p = .09);</s><s xml:id="_SRNvRdb">No difference in antitobacco beliefs; 2.4% decrease in tobacco use in Minnesota, not significant compared to Wisconsin (p = .32)</s><s xml:id="_TZUUSAK">Holder et al.</s><s xml:id="_Fp4rtEp">Prevention of Three experimental Five main program com-Random digit telephone Results not yet available (1997) alcohol-related communities compared ponents ®®® produce surveys of adults, youth injuries and to matched comparison short-term effects, e.g.</s><s xml:id="_UzQ9DP3">telephone and school death communities in the alcohol server training surveys, roadside sur-United States over results in fewer drinks veys, and media coding 5-year period from served to intoxicated analysis measured 1992 to 1997 patrons, alcohol law mediating variables; changes result in fewer emergency room sursales to youth ®®®</s></p><p xml:id="_qDDJtym"><s xml:id="_eUfDY4T">veys, records of hospicombined effect of ac-tal admissions, commutivities reduce alcohol nity surveys and death availability and con-certificate data measumption, youthful sured alcohol-related drinking and drunk trauma and death driving, and so on ®®® reduced alcoholrelated morbidity and mortality individuals' attitudes toward the desired diet, perceived social influences, beliefs about their ability to perform the behavior (self-efficacy), and intentions to make dietary changes.</s><s xml:id="_znKuytE">In turn, these changes would lead participants to reduce their fat intake and increase their vegetable and fruit consumption.</s></p><p xml:id="_tAqpuxR"><s xml:id="_WJD5CwK">In the evaluation, employees in a Royal Shell laboratory were randomly assigned to receive the program or to receive general nutrition information.</s><s xml:id="_cVxZQWR">Questionnaires were used preintervention and 3 weeks postintervention to assess changes in dietary fat, in fruit and vegetable intake, and in attitudes, social influences, and self-efficacy expectations.</s></p><p xml:id="_f8cHuTV"><s xml:id="_4nYQqz7">At posttest, the program group that had received tailored messages had more positive attitudes toward increasing consumption of vegetable, fruits, and fat than the comparison group.</s><s xml:id="_HGJXrfd">No effects were found for self-efficacy or social influences.</s><s xml:id="_2a2g5sf">Program participants expressed stronger intentions to change their consumption of fat and fruit in the recommended direction than the comparison group.</s><s xml:id="_ffcWNv5">At posttest, the program group had significantly lower fat scores than the comparison group.</s><s xml:id="_VhMjARQ">Both groups increased their reported vegetable but not their fruit consumption, with no difference found between the change in the two groups.</s></p><p xml:id="_GU6rYZB"><s xml:id="_sGsPdsz">The authors conclude that interventions targeting psychosocial beliefs may be more effective than programs providing dietary feedback alone.</s><s xml:id="_MHec9m8">They suggest that general information regarding recommended consumption of fruit and vegetables may be adequate to induce change, whereas messages tailored to the individual may be more effective for influencing the more complex issue of fat intake.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_J5svmFk">Flay et al. (1995)</head><p xml:id="_aJnxqsZ"><s xml:id="_bATd7pj">In an antismoking program, <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Flay et al. (1995)</ref> assessed the combined effects of a school and media smoking prevention and cessation program for seventh graders.</s><s xml:id="_wzBY3w3">Schools were randomly assigned to one of five conditions: a social resistance curriculum only (SR), a TV campaign only (TV), a combination of the social resistance curriculum and TV (SR/TV), an information-only curriculum (IOU), and a no-treatment control group.</s></p><p xml:id="_NFuq8qq"><s xml:id="_pDNT6wt">The program theory was defined at the outset.</s><s xml:id="_jq8V55n">The IOU, SR, TV, and combined SR/TV programs were expected to increase knowledge about the effects of smoking.</s><s xml:id="_aByCdpP">This knowledge alone was expected to lead to changes in smoking behaviors in the IOU program.</s><s xml:id="_DnWDQj9">The SR, TV, and combined SR/TV programs included activities designed to increase youths' awareness of factors that influence smoking and to increase youths' skills to resist smoking.</s><s xml:id="_FvEq8Wx">In turn, students' efforts and confidence in their ability to refuse to smoke were expected to increase.</s><s xml:id="_HjZNvMd">In addition, the program sought to change smoking norms.</s><s xml:id="_u6k6A3h">The combined effect of changes in these factors was expected to increase behavioral intentions to reduce, quit, or not start smoking, which in turn, were hypothesized to lead to reduced smoking.</s></p><p xml:id="_5nw8Ywn"><s xml:id="_Wqykc4M">Questionnaires were used to measure all mediating and outcome measures before the intervention, immediately after, and 1 and 2 years after.</s><s xml:id="_xGMGFBf">For the SR, TV, and combined SR/TV programs, the evaluators found significant positive effects on health and resistance skills knowledge, estimates of the prevalence of smoking (which was assumed to reflect community norms), and efforts to quit.</s><s xml:id="_e7A4P4X">The knowledge and prevalence estimates effects decayed partially but remained significant at the 2-year follow-up.</s><s xml:id="_dRT6hn3">The effect of the programs on efforts to quit did not persist at the 1-and 2-year follow-ups.</s><s xml:id="_e2xfneM">The programs had no effect on confidence to quit or smoking intentions.</s><s xml:id="_JVK8HE8">None of the programs was related to actual smoking at any posttest.</s><s xml:id="_dVquPM4">The only predictors of smoking at posttest were smoking at pretest and strong intentions to smoke in the future.</s></p><p xml:id="_tzqQqUC"><s xml:id="_nPpkKrz">The authors have some difficulty interpreting the results of this study.</s><s xml:id="_EYAGjqJ">First, they note that the group targeted, seventh graders, have very low rates of smoking and strong antitobacco beliefs, effectively reducing the chances of finding a program effect on attitudes or behavior.</s><s xml:id="_zd5ZBJh">They suggest that either programs for this group are not necessary or need to continue into later grades.</s><s xml:id="_5sWR2ZA">Second, a process evaluation found variability in the curriculum delivery and poor execution of the television programming.</s><s xml:id="_RSswW6r">However, because of the strong effects of the program on certain mediators, the authors are reluctant to attribute the shortcomings to implementation problems alone.</s><s xml:id="_BmdEwGm">They point out that the program affected knowledge about resistance skills and prevalence estimates.</s><s xml:id="_qJRNZAn">Although these effects decayed slightly, they persisted over time.</s><s xml:id="_HbybJqF">Effects on skills were smaller and decayed more quickly.</s><s xml:id="_8uQcwYY">Based on these findings, they suggest that an effective preventive program will need to commit to long-term reinforcement of both knowledge and skills.</s><s xml:id="_h3jteW8">They conclude, however, given the lack of program impact on smoking rates, that the field has more to learn about how programs work.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_8XRYmss">Eisen, Zellman, and McAlister (1992)</head><p xml:id="_wYZ7ZK2"><s xml:id="_9AuCn5E">A well-known individual-level theory of health behavior, the Health Belief Model (HBM), posits that a person's behavior is influenced by perceptions of his or her own susceptibility to the effects of an action, the potential seriousness of these effects, and perceived benefits and barriers to action.</s><s xml:id="_teHf7Vf">Applying the HBM to the issue of adolescent pregnancy, <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Eisen, Zellman, and McAlister (1992)</ref> developed a school curriculum to target the mediating factors identified in the theory.</s><s xml:id="_j8GzEZ9">The curriculum developed was intended to increase students' awareness of the probability of becoming pregnant or causing a pregnancy, the serious negative consequences of pregnancy, and the benefits of delayed sexual activity or contraceptive use.</s><s xml:id="_7vd2VVC">It was also designed to decrease participants' perceptions of barriers to abstinence or contraceptive use.</s><s xml:id="_8Wda6gg">Changes in these mediating factors were expected to lead to changes in contraceptive and sexual behavior.</s><s xml:id="_cjkfTSD">Past research led the authors to believe that males and females and virgins and nonvirgins would respond differently to the program.</s></p><p xml:id="_QuYD99y"><s xml:id="_yE5fVkh">The evaluation was designed to assess the impact of the program on sexual behavior and the importance of the mediating factors in the HBM.</s><s xml:id="_nD3sjcK">Six family planning services and one school were selected to participate in the project.</s><s xml:id="_GEzaaPb">Youth aged 13-19 participating in these agencies' programs were randomly assigned to receive the HBM curriculum or the agencies' usual sex education program.</s></p><p xml:id="_saJadz3"><s xml:id="_AD4TGeS">The evaluation measured sexual and contraceptive knowledge, the sexuality-related beliefs identified by the HBM model, and contraceptive and sexual behavior (the targeted outcomes) before, immediately after, and 12 months after program completion.</s><s xml:id="_BaB8cvz">Knowledge in both the experimental and control groups increased at posttest, with the experimental group showing a greater increase.</s><s xml:id="_mfdpR3P">Participants' health perceptions preintervention to postintervention improved in both the control and experimental groups; the experimental group showed no greater increase than the control group.</s></p><p xml:id="_rKtvzWt"><s xml:id="_t5wp8uW">All behavioral results were presented by gender and previous sexual experience.</s><s xml:id="_h8S9S3v">The HBM program produced significantly greater positive changes among males who were sexually active before the program, in terms of their self-reported contraceptive efficiency (a measure of the consistency with which teens used effective birth control methods).</s><s xml:id="_8JRkw9B">Females in the comparison group who became sexually active after the initial baseline survey reported significantly more effective contraceptive use than those in the program group.</s></p><p xml:id="_VBfqwTt"><s xml:id="_tk8pzZC">Similar to the <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Flay et al. (1995)</ref> study, the authors cite the low rate of sexual activity among the age group included in the study as one possible explanation for the limited postintervention differences found between the two programs (more than half of the teens were still virgins at follow-up).</s><s xml:id="_yXCwxJR">In addition, the authors note that the number and length of sessions of the comparison and intervention program were similar and acknowledge that the two programs may have had the same potential for impact.</s><s xml:id="_k8knxtx">In part because of these design problems, the authors do not reject the potential importance of the HBM beliefs.</s><s xml:id="_uX6uTBS">In addition, although the evaluators did not find difference in postintervention measures of the HBM beliefs between the HBM curriculum and comparison groups, fewer perceived barriers and greater perceived benefits of birth control use preintervention predicted postintervention abstinence (among virgins) and greater contraceptive use (among sexually active teens).</s><s xml:id="_wDEq8vG">This finding suggests that at least some of the HBM beliefs are important in determining sexual behavior.</s></p><p xml:id="_QGvKSd9"><s xml:id="_YA3J6rR">The authors go on to suggest that the program theory may operate differently for the specific groups in the study.</s><s xml:id="_HmpQRxQ">They hypothesize that the HBM program may have been more effective than the comparison program for sexually active males because it focused on increasing males' awareness of and sense of susceptibility to pregnancy risks.</s><s xml:id="_7r2u5Yg">They suggest that in contrast, females may be saturated with messages about the threat of pregnancy and so learned less from the HBM program.</s><s xml:id="_6cmXpbq">The authors conclude that differences in program impact by previous sexual experience and gender indicate that programs must be tailored to specific groups.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_BQN46ET">Puska, Nissinen, and Tuomilehto (1985)</head><p xml:id="_VJSH4tJ"><s xml:id="_v2KC4R4">The North Karelia project in Finland is a much-cited study of a community-based approach to the reduction of heart disease.</s><s xml:id="_v3AttVW">The project team implemented mass media campaigns and worked with health and community groups to provide health education information to individuals and to initiate changes in the social and physical environment to motivate and maintain behavior change.</s><s xml:id="_MjnPVhf">The basic theory of the program was that targeting individuals' knowledge and attitudes and providing social and environmental support for behavior change would lead individuals to reduce their risk factors for cardiovascular disease.</s><s xml:id="_5EgJHC6">In turn, reductions in individual risk factors, specifically smoking, serum cholesterol, and blood pressure, would lead to reduced morbidity and mortality at the population level.</s><s xml:id="_CcDxVYT">The authors state that the theory of how the program would work was only partially developed at the outset of the program because of the paucity of theories related to community interventions.</s><s xml:id="_GWZWq5W">Thus, the evaluation tracked individuals' knowledge, attitudes, and behavior-the most developed part of the program theory-while documenting program-related activities in the community through a process evaluation.</s></p><p xml:id="_z9JEb9Y"><s xml:id="_cyVE38J">Independent random samples of adults were surveyed before the intervention in 1972 and again 5 and 10 years later.</s><s xml:id="_cZkpVnF">Results for North Karelia were compared to those of a comparison community.</s><s xml:id="_zm7tWbU">The surveys asked questions about health knowledge, attitudes, and behavior and included an exam to measure height, weight, blood pressure, and cholesterol.</s><s xml:id="_nrA5nTZ">Finally, mortality rates for the two communities were compared.</s></p><p xml:id="_Vq3Xk7C"><s xml:id="_MUk7CfJ">The evaluation showed that knowledge of risk factors increased somewhat, but the change was only slightly higher in North Karelia.</s><s xml:id="_rDKJ5Mt">The evaluators report no major changes in health attitude measures, with little difference between the two communities.</s><s xml:id="_8JjzA97">A net reduction in smoking and blood pressure was found in North Karelia over the 10-year period.</s><s xml:id="_4g3Z8QW">A net reduction in serum cholesterol was found for men in North Karelia.</s><s xml:id="_rKPmfSg">Coronary heart disease mortality decreased by 22% compared to 12% in the comparison community.</s></p><p xml:id="_waYJQpJ"><s xml:id="_UeNDWay">The lack of change in individual's knowledge and attitudes led the authors to attribute the success of the project more to its community organization aspects than to the project's efforts to target individuals.</s><s xml:id="_T7kuWNf">They believe that health education messages disseminated through the media and opinion leaders gradually created an environment promoting healthier lifestyles and that these environmental changes gradually influenced individual behavior.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_yP62swT">Murray, Prokhorov, and Harty (1994)</head><p xml:id="_RqrX69z"><s xml:id="_KnnrYyX">Murray, Prokhorov, and Harty (1994) used a relatively simple theory to evaluate the effects of a statewide antismoking campaign.</s><s xml:id="_ThFWcXQ">A tax initiative passed in 1985 by the Minnesota Legislature designated the use of tax money from tobacco products for antitobacco programs.</s><s xml:id="_ywjp4jj">The initiative was expected to spur local communities and schools to develop a variety of tobacco control programs targeting school age children.</s><s xml:id="_4UqKP8y">Concurrently, the Department of Health was funded to implement a statewide antismoking mass media campaign.</s><s xml:id="_Vs7M3fe">Although schools and groups receiving money from the initiative were asked to develop activities using a social influence model of smoking, programs varied across the state.</s></p><p xml:id="_YZE5RR3"><s xml:id="_jXHbTbU">The evaluators tracked whether the initiative resulted in increased antismoking activities in schools.</s><s xml:id="_TNvfAwY">Exposure to these activities coupled with the media campaign was expected to change beliefs about the health risks of smoking.</s><s xml:id="_BDJ8TCD">Changes in beliefs were hypothesized to result in lower smoking rates among youth.</s></p><p xml:id="_qBDCxF5"><s xml:id="_Mn5drB3">A process evaluation found that the Department of Health implemented a mass-media campaign from 1986 to 1990.</s><s xml:id="_4KbnQRF">However, schools made only short-term and erratic increases in antismoking activities.</s></p><p xml:id="_zgBdA3F"><s xml:id="_m4CEhe3">The evaluators compared Minnesota ninth graders to Wisconsin ninth graders in terms of exposure to school-based and mass-media programming, beliefs, and tobacco use each year from 1986 to 1990.</s><s xml:id="_tn8wdzE">Minnesota students reported greater increases in exposure to antismoking messages than Wisconsin students.</s><s xml:id="_sqwRZEm">However, there was no difference between the two states in the pattern of change in antitobacco beliefs.</s><s xml:id="_gwCcNGV">Ninth graders in both states expressed strong antitobacco beliefs, which were stable over time.</s><s xml:id="_K3SPGGT">Reports of tobacco use in Minnesota declined, but the decrease was not significantly different from that in Wisconsin.</s></p><p xml:id="_GZtVcFy"><s xml:id="_tkY9TeR">The tax initiative increased students' exposure to antismoking messages in mass media.</s><s xml:id="_7QV9ahB">However, the increase in exposure had not lead to changes in beliefs or behavior.</s><s xml:id="_wn6Q2Zp">The tax initiative, however, did not lead to widespread school-based programming.</s><s xml:id="_jrzrTsu">Because of the lack of full implementation of the school-based program, the authors cannot fully determine whether or how a combined school or mass media campaign of this type can work.</s><s xml:id="_QW8FStx">They did learn that a mass media campaign, while reaching children on its own, does not produce changes in attitudes associated with smoking.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_CWtFuGt">Holder et al. (1997)</head><p xml:id="_WU59VEj"><s xml:id="_JGhePpG">The Community Prevention Trial provides a final example of a theorybased approach to evaluation.</s><s xml:id="_uqB93x2">The study has only recently concluded, and as study results are not yet available, the authors' article described here reviews only the evaluation plan.</s><s xml:id="_MkCAavq">The project used a combination of community awareness and policy-related activities to reduce alcohol-involved injuries and deaths.</s><s xml:id="_bnajUjw">The program consisted of five main components that were expected to reinforce each other: working with community groups to plan and implement prevention activities and develop public awareness of alcohol-related trauma; working with alcohol beverage servers and retailers to design and implement safer beverage service policies; developing community programs to reduce underage drinking; working with law enforcement, retail establishments, and others to reduce drinking and driving; and using municipal control policies to reduce alcohol availability.</s></p><p xml:id="_YPMNbaB"><s xml:id="_GekUnSP">The hypothesized program model is presented in Table <ref type="table">2</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_enPYxYy">Each component of the program is hypothesized to lead to certain short-term effects.</s><s xml:id="_Ccsut3u">The combined effects of the components are expected to lead to changes in intervening variables such as alcohol availability and consumption, youthful drinking, and drinking and driving.</s><s xml:id="_6E4pP3m">These changes in turn are expected to lead to reductions in alcohol-related morbidity and mortality.</s></p><p xml:id="_KpBeEXg"><s xml:id="_NdDkBVf">A process evaluation monitored the extent of implementation of the different components in each of three communities to assess the timing and quality of the intervention activities.</s><s xml:id="_UZJNJqS">Surveys and media content analyses were used to measure changes in the mediating variables in Table <ref type="table">2</ref>. Alcohol-related trauma and death were measured using hospital and community records and surveys.</s><s xml:id="_M5AN2A9">Results from the three experimental communities will be compared to matched comparison communities for a 5-year period from 1992 to 1997.</s></p><p xml:id="_vzEjE2S"><s xml:id="_DHmsE3E">Results of the trial are not yet available.</s><s xml:id="_XRmH6C6">Therefore, we cannot yet tell how well the program theory represents the actual processes that were implemented nor how well the program theory produces the expected results.</s><s xml:id="_rYp94g8">The authors make several statements relevant to the use of TBE.</s><s xml:id="_yX5yEak">First, they state that community-based approaches are complex efforts and little is known about how they work.</s><s xml:id="_ZTdVAVW">They argue that a theory-based approach is essential to build a better understanding of these processes.</s><s xml:id="_T28C2nh">Second, they argue that when the processes by which an intervention work are not well understood, it is preferable to make an in-depth study of a few communities rather than a larger multicommunity study.</s></p><p xml:id="_PVnvuvx"><s xml:id="_Usf3Fgz">TABLE 2: Theory of Program to Reduce Alcohol-Related Mortality Program Mediating Intervention Component Activity "Process Variable" Outcome Community Media advocacy Media coverage of knowledge, Community alcohol-related values, and organization issues mobilization Responsible Establishment of Changes in server Traffic-related trauma beverage RBS standards behavior service (RBS) Server training Reduction in DWI Underage drinking In-school programs Restricted youth Zero tolerance access Decreased youth drinking Risk of drinking Increased DWI Lowered blood Non-traffic-related and driving enforcement alcohol contents trauma among drivers Reductions in DWI Access to alcohol Density restrictions Decreased density Licensing require-Decreased adult ments drinking SOURCE: Adapted from Holder et al. (1997) NOTE: DWI = driving while intoxicated.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_WpstACh">WHAT WAS LEARNED FROM THESE TBES?</head><p xml:id="_upygxG6"><s xml:id="_gASYrtX">Although each of the evaluations has some modicum of theory involved, the authors are not always explicit about what they learned from TBE over and above what they would have learned without it.</s><s xml:id="_6bTWzHJ">Here, we draw conclusions about findings from the theory-based approach to evaluation based on our own interpretation of the published evaluation reports.</s><s xml:id="_nXcfYGh">One of the incidental learnings we derive from this review is that authors do not always make explicit the relation of their data to the theory of the program.</s><s xml:id="_V4TU8qx">They report in traditional ways without necessarily emphasizing insights about mechanisms of change that the theory-based approach provides.</s><s xml:id="_BBnCMaX">At times, our interpretation ranges beyond the authors' reported conclusions (with all the perils of such extrapolation).</s><s xml:id="_PZXPdnc">We offer the following interpretations in the spirit of examining the types of learning TBE can provide.</s><s xml:id="_G8zXB77">We highlight particular lessons from each study (with the understanding that more than one study may illustrate the point).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_PeWGkJn">ADVANTAGES FOR PROGRAM PLANNING AND IMPROVEMENT</head><p xml:id="_T9JdBzx"><s xml:id="_hkHE6f8">Identifying inadequate or unnecessary program components.</s><s xml:id="_NPu52yc">The <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Brug et al. (1996)</ref> evaluation of the computer-generated nutrition program found that although certain mechanisms of change identified by the theory were affected among program participants, others were not.</s><s xml:id="_GWRzPfa">Nonetheless, participants made significant improvements in their consumption of fat.</s><s xml:id="_nF4xVyU">An outcome evaluation would have indicated only that the program was successful.</s><s xml:id="_JmVvYpP">The additional findings contributed by TBE suggest the need to explore whether those program elements that were not implicated in the dietary improvement can be eliminated in future programs.</s><s xml:id="_9dFffeg">Alternatively, future research might explore means to influence all factors identified in the program theory and test the full theory effects.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_7azyRKC">ADVANTAGES FOR KNOWLEDGE DEVELOPMENT</head><p xml:id="_sd6SWXX"><s xml:id="_DCA86nF">Finding intermediary changes.</s><s xml:id="_x4buueb">The study by <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Flay et al. (1995)</ref> confronted the endemic question of the appropriate age to begin prevention activities, an issue common to smoking, sex, and drug and alcohol programs.</s><s xml:id="_x7Zn6dt">An outcome evaluation of the smoking program evaluated by Flay et al. would have discovered no impact on the smoking rates of seventh graders.</s><s xml:id="_MtTrKgy">This finding, coupled with low rates of smoking in the study age group, led the authors to question the utility of targeting such a young group.</s><s xml:id="_fczbV85">However, as the authors note, results from the TBE indicating a change in attitudes among the youth suggest that programs targeting this age group may have future effects on smoking.</s><s xml:id="_TAs5eG3">The additional finding that skills and knowledge have differential attrition rates suggests the need to reinforce attitude changes over time.</s><s xml:id="_qQYErye">Although the two findings do not conclusively answer the question of whether seventh grade is the appropriate age to begin smoking prevention efforts, they suggest that some effects do appear in seventh graders and that perhaps program efforts need to be reinforced over time.</s></p><p xml:id="_kCXDBJ6"><s xml:id="_KBvrXZ5">Raising questions.</s><s xml:id="_85KW2Nj">The TBE of the sex education course evaluated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Eisen, Zellman, and McAlister (1992)</ref> raises many questions about how both the HBM curriculum and the comparison program work.</s><s xml:id="_YrSZhWz">An outcome evaluation that broke down study results by gender and previous sexual experience would have discovered the differential impact of the programs.</s><s xml:id="_mCzSsuH">Given the explicitly theory-based design of the program, it would have been reasonable to assume that participants' health beliefs were differentially affected by the program.</s><s xml:id="_dQr7AhP">However, the assessment of these beliefs indicates that this was not the case and leads us to question the underlying mechanisms by which both programs worked.</s><s xml:id="_Zz9K8P5">Was the HBM curriculum simply inadequate to change important HBM beliefs?</s><s xml:id="_PpFkzwQ">If indeed the preintervention HBM beliefs found to be associated with positive outcomes in both groups were able to be changed by the program, would the program outcomes have been different?</s><s xml:id="_22fhBTz">What accounts for the difference between the two program groups by gender and past sexual experience when little difference was found in health beliefs?</s><s xml:id="_tZJ3mMS">What are possible alternative intervening factors that led to the changes in behaviors found?</s></p><p xml:id="_gmDaBwK"><s xml:id="_9cvPtah">Contributing to a paradigm shift.</s><s xml:id="_sbZCkXd">The North Karelia study was one of the first large-scale health promotion studies to attempt to influence the health of individuals through community change efforts.</s><s xml:id="_v6zQU7z">The authors state that the program theory was only partially developed at the start of the project because of an absence of theories at the level of community change.</s><s xml:id="_MgjNkRp">Systematically tracking one of the proposed mechanisms of change at the individual level-and discovering little change-coupled with the overall impact of the program on health outcomes, provided support for the movement to focus on changing the social and cultural environments in which individuals live rather than on changing only individual knowledge and attitudes.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_wv32qWd">ADVANTAGES FOR PLANNING THE EVALUATION</head><p xml:id="_jdcrcCz"><s xml:id="_GRbNV28">The difficulties of going to scale.</s><s xml:id="_ZJkAU3s">The lack of implementation of a key component of the intervention in the <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Murray, Prokhorov, and Harty (1994)</ref> study highlights the need for program theory to reach back to the often-unstated early premises, in this case that making funds available to schools would lead to good antismoking school programs.</s><s xml:id="_BEN54dT">The study revealed that the school-based part of the program was inadequately implemented.</s><s xml:id="_shqezak">Using state tax money to stimulate antismoking programs was an attempt to extend earlier positive findings from small-scale school programs to the state level.</s><s xml:id="_GXqrR9k">However, because schools did not consistently follow through, the full theory could not receive an adequate test.</s><s xml:id="_gTkJcZf">Taking advantage of large-scale programs, such as a statewide initiative, to test theories is a researcher's dream.</s><s xml:id="_H2JUTG5">A careful assessment of the program theory at the onset of these types of programs may lead researchers to focus on the necessary mechanisms of change between state funding and local programming before moving to theory links at the local program level.</s></p><p xml:id="_jVCeJyv"><s xml:id="_k7BacWK">Providing clarity and focus for evaluation.</s><s xml:id="_4tHaDeM">In an evaluation of a community-level health promotion effort, <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Holder et al. (1997)</ref> explicitly discuss the importance of laying out a program theory for the evaluation of large-scale community based programs.</s><s xml:id="_YnTad6H">With the results not yet in, the full benefits of the TBE approach for exploring outcomes in this study cannot be assessed.</s><s xml:id="_wyd4JjT">However, the delineation of the program theory of such a complex change effort provides the evaluator with clear guidelines for data collection and analysis and should assist in the clarity of interpreting results and drawing conclusions.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_T7FUn3P">IS TBE APPLICABLE IN OTHER SETTINGS?</head><p xml:id="_DF2kzeS"><s xml:id="_Qc4xNWJ">The evaluations described above represent well-funded, primarily research-oriented projects.</s><s xml:id="_eMyFDvM">The programs themselves were developed based on theory and the evaluations test the theory embedded in the program.</s><s xml:id="_dDXrs3E">However, most programs are not explicitly based on theories of change, and many are not well defined at the planning stage.</s><s xml:id="_KudA8yN">They are often small programs, based on practitioner experience, and funded at relatively low levels.</s><s xml:id="_PUfYW4g">Is TBE relevant to them?</s><s xml:id="_TN5e4yZ">Can it be applied in these settings, and what can be gained?</s><s xml:id="_rM7eTQ9">It is our provisional belief that TBE can be applied in these settings and that it has the potential to provide benefits that match those provided for programs with well-articulated theory.</s><s xml:id="_ktAHNyN">Even if the evaluators do not adopt the language of TBE, they can incorporate elements of it into their studies.</s></p><p xml:id="_WdKRMtu"><s xml:id="_jw6kQG5">Here are some kernels of advice gleaned from this review that we believe apply to even small, atheoretical, marginally funded programs.</s></p><p xml:id="_6vm5qjk"><s xml:id="_kxqUPQt">Do not expect theories to be completely right.</s><s xml:id="_wxenacb">Remember when conducting a TBE that at this stage, the theory is primarily a guide to the evaluation.</s><s xml:id="_CPtYWBV">One of the learnings from these studies is that in no case were the program theories quite right.</s><s xml:id="_NUMMT6Z">Some of the programs activated the mechanisms that were assumed to trigger desired outcomes, but the desired outcomes did not appear.</s><s xml:id="_UFEPM65">Some of the programs produced the desired outcomes but not through the mechanisms that were assumed to be causal; there were no significant changes in the mechanisms.</s><s xml:id="_NnuxKe9">Obviously much remains to be learned about good programming and good theory.</s></p><p xml:id="_6SDqJnw"><s xml:id="_s7GrfZa">Discovering that a theory is not quite right should not discourage program personnel.</s><s xml:id="_S3dTvxS">A program theory serves many purposes.</s><s xml:id="_yW7CqVH">It helps clarify how a program is expected to work, it helps focus the evaluation on key results, and it provides structure to the interpretation of results.</s><s xml:id="_Hd8gwKV">In the end, whether or not the theory is right, it will have provided a framework for thinking about how the program is working.</s><s xml:id="_9zDpvmk">Hopefully, this will lead to the development of creative ways to improve programs or design new approaches-and program theories-for future programs.</s></p><p xml:id="_yA3KbzC"><s xml:id="_hVMn3kS">Consider theory development as a stage in the evaluation.</s><s xml:id="_VmVWRAZ">An emphasis on theory development at the start of the evaluation may be in and of itself the most beneficial aspect of the theory-based approach.</s></p><p xml:id="_DwW2x35"><s xml:id="_QMz3xtg">In many fields, programs are planned on the basis of experience, professional savvy, intuition, and beliefs in fashion in the field.</s><s xml:id="_Vfj8xnV">There is little in this melange that is easily characterized by the name of theory.</s><s xml:id="_Pf6xdvN">But all programs have a theoretical basis, no matter how weakly the assumptions are articulated.</s><s xml:id="_GDze5Ux">Program people make some assumptions about why the set of activities they plan will lead to desirable outcomes.</s><s xml:id="_GvEFEHt">When the assumptions are tacit rather than consciously expressed, the evaluator has the task of eliciting or constructing the theoretical assumptions underlying the program.</s><s xml:id="_fvcDB3m">The evaluator usually undertakes this theory-surfacing exercise in conjunction with program planners and program staff.</s></p><p xml:id="_k5cqbU4"><s xml:id="_WjWmd3h">When program staff describe their assumptions about the mechanisms by which the program will bring about change, the evaluator has to see whether the theories offered are operative.</s><s xml:id="_VvbkGMN">She has to learn enough about program activities-real activities in action and not just espoused ideas of activities-to figure out whether practitioners' theories are being operationalized in the program.</s><s xml:id="_qGCtr2y">If the program claims that its prevention goals will be realized by increasing participants' sense of self-efficacy, but the evaluator finds no activities dedicated to increasing self-efficacy, she will doubt that the theory is "real" for this program.</s><s xml:id="_3zSbtb4">She will have to seek an alternative theory that explains why the real activities are expected to lead to the intended effects.</s><s xml:id="_tWjZyXs">Or she may call the absence of efficacy-building activities to the attention of program staff and perhaps encourage them to alter the program to fit their theory (or alter their theory to fit the program).</s></p><p xml:id="_4KwjMY7"><s xml:id="_QGyUFmz">Possible sources of program theories are social science theories and research, prior evaluations, planner and practitioner expectations, the evaluator's knowledge and experience with programs of similar type, and her or his own logical thinking.</s><s xml:id="_hmXpv2D">Often, the evaluator will cycle through several of these sources-asking program planners and program managers, reviewing existing theories in the field, reviewing previous research and evaluations, hypothesizing a theory on the basis of this information, and then negotiating her formulation with program managers and staff to come to an agreement that accords with their thinking.</s></p><p xml:id="_qtfkKwp"><s xml:id="_pm5zwEZ">When people do not agree on their assumptions, the evaluator may incorporate several different chains of reasoning into the study.</s><s xml:id="_2VrMNQd">For example, staff in a pregnancy prevention program may expect the program to work because it provides information about contraception, teaches young women to be more assertive in demands on their partners, or makes chastity more socially acceptable within the program group, or for a number of other reasons.</s><s xml:id="_gK3aDmu">Rather than demanding that program staff agree on a single theory, the evaluator can design the study to collect data on several different assumptions.</s><s xml:id="_KfKdQFu">The study can then show which of the theories, if any, is supported by the data.</s></p><p xml:id="_PpwJyTr"><s xml:id="_N7uaWnq">Identifying poorly defined, implausible, or hotly debated links in how a program is expected to work can force practitioners and managers to define and agree on what they believe they are doing.</s><s xml:id="_x4PZvCC">With greater clarity about what they are trying to accomplish, and how, program people should do a better job of developing and improving the program.</s><s xml:id="_Zk8hd8f">And with a greater understanding of how the program is expected to work, the evaluator can better structure the evaluation to answer relevant questions and interpret study results.</s><s xml:id="_V8268fV">Even if resources are inadequate to collect data on the mediating variables identified in a program theory, developing the program theory as the starting point in evaluation would be of value for program development, improvement, and evaluation.</s></p><p xml:id="_HBYBVwV"><s xml:id="_drsWSVz">Include a process evaluation.</s><s xml:id="_JeXCBMQ">A TBE study should include a description of program implementation generally called a process evaluation.</s><s xml:id="_Ng7GEt9">Some programs do not work because planned activities are not carried out regularly or not carried out well.</s><s xml:id="_MkVXqAp">If an evaluation fails to collect data on the processes of the program, it will be unable to distinguish between "program failure" (the program was not carried out well and therefore did not lead to the desired effects) and "theory failure" (the idea underlying the program was wrong, and therefore expected results did not materialize) <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Suchman 1967)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_gEAyMbQ">If the study of implementation is foregone, the evaluator loses the ability to tell whether this particular realization of the program or the basic theory is at fault.</s></p><p xml:id="_dGfWV8X"><s xml:id="_CE9SZ72">One possible reason for the observed outcomes of the TBE studies we have reviewed is that programs work differently for different subgroups.</s><s xml:id="_qyP24Ss">Or outcomes may differ according to the type and frequency of activities to which participants are exposed.</s><s xml:id="_vnYy8HY">Again, process evaluation is essential.</s><s xml:id="_QSuDyy8">The evaluator is well advised to collect data on those characteristics of participants, staff, activities, settings, and time that are likely to be salient to success.</s><s xml:id="_9MzkC7U">In the analysis, the evaluator can compare outcomes and measures of the intervening mechanisms linking program processes to these outcomes according to the features of people and activities, and thus come to estimates of which activities work best for which groups, under which conditions, and how and why they work.</s></p><p xml:id="_MRJ4urz"><s xml:id="_CYthE8F">When a program is poorly implemented, there may not be a great need to delve deeply into all the hypothesized causal links in the theory chain.</s><s xml:id="_SzXRbXy">Sometimes even with a poorly conducted program, some later expectations are realized.</s><s xml:id="_sbSAJQY">But it is difficult to explain the data by assuming that they were brought about by a weak or incompetent program.</s><s xml:id="_646aEQE">If the outcomes are disappointing, as one might expect, the immediate lesson is to do a better job of conducting the program-and evaluate the program in its superior version.</s></p><p xml:id="_h4dfh8M"><s xml:id="_qave2NV">Use the information TBE can provide.</s><s xml:id="_FXygB7W">Although many funders of small-scale programs ask for outcome evaluations, the results of these evaluations are rarely used to make go/no-go decisions about the program's future.</s><s xml:id="_R5kG5DR">Rather than using evaluative information for continuing or discontinuing the program, funders and program managers usually want information about how to improve the program.</s><s xml:id="_qTz9fjT">The results of TBE may prove to be more useful than evaluations of outcomes only.</s><s xml:id="_bVrtfVv">Knowledge of how or why a program is failing provides managers with leads on how to improve the existing program.</s><s xml:id="_3exvXbv">They can use the information to discuss why programs should work and where they are breaking down.</s><s xml:id="_U94xMRa">This type of information communicates easily to policy makers and may be more convincing than the results of outcome evaluations only.</s></p><p xml:id="_GvCdyCZ"><s xml:id="_wEKRyhc">TBE has a longer tradition among academic researchers developing and testing program approaches than among program evaluators called in after a program is in process.</s><s xml:id="_RgwyRjV">We noted that traditional methods of reporting results sometimes got in the way of clearly associating the evaluation results to the theory in the evaluations reviewed.</s><s xml:id="_HSkR7Hr">As TBE becomes more widely used in practice, evaluators will need to develop effective ways to report on the findings.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_CJyxKQK">CONCLUSION</head><p xml:id="_66VU9zn"><s xml:id="_qjKkTdV">How well the evaluator is able to test a program theory is likely to be a function of three factors.</s><s xml:id="_rc2JWxV">The first is how well the theory is defined.</s><s xml:id="_6jZwb8y">The evaluator may have to consult many stakeholder groups to identify and secure agreement on the definition of the theory underlying the program.</s><s xml:id="_CufTvVU">Second is how well program activities reflect the assumptions embedded in the theory.</s><s xml:id="_SRJhgmP">Third is the grubby matter of money and time.</s><s xml:id="_eajH9eG">If TBE is carried out in full detail, it is apt to be an expensive and time-consuming enterprise.</s></p><p xml:id="_JWWKXhk"><s xml:id="_3ebFFEX">As several of the examples show, even if an evaluation is able to track a specific theory, the interpretation of results may not be straightforward.</s><s xml:id="_kHEpJc5">Findings that indicate that the program altered some of the hypothesized intervening factors but not others do not lead to easy interpretation.</s><s xml:id="_tQs6Wmc">Assessing exactly where the hypothesized theory breaks down, and why, calls for more finely grained study than most evaluations have yet included.</s><s xml:id="_f4M8fNS">A basic limitation is the state of knowledge in the field about which factors are effectual in bringing about change and how factors interact to change human beings and human communities.</s><s xml:id="_FFvdSWH">Advocates of TBE hope that over time, results from TBE will lead to cumulative knowledge of change processes and consequently the development of more effective programs.</s><s xml:id="_wN4Ykm8">As the examples show, even within its limitations TBE is contributing modest increments to program improvement, growth in knowledge, and improved planning of further evaluations.</s></p></div>			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="408" xml:id="foot_0"><p xml:id="_44yzn3t"><s xml:id="_mDBKBy3">EVALUATION REVIEW / AUGUST 2000</s></p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p xml:id="_PA94wtn"><s xml:id="_cEjsvss">Birckmayer, Weiss / THEORY-BASED EVALUATION</s></p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="420" xml:id="foot_2"><p xml:id="_xfRmkCd"><s xml:id="_dUSC9Vp">EVALUATION REVIEW / AUGUST 2000</s></p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="428" xml:id="foot_3"><p xml:id="_NGegaz5"><s xml:id="_jSK7WGh">EVALUATION REVIEW / AUGUST 2000</s></p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_cKGw6Ag">Advances in program theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bickman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/ev.1555</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_tcaUTSq">New directions for program evaluation</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Francisco</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Jossey-Bass</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bickman, L., ed. 1990. Advances in program theory. New directions for program evaluation, no. 47. San Francisco: Jossey-Bass.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Je5a9Wf">The impact of a computer-tailored nutrition intervention</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Brug</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Steenhuis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Van Assema</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">De</forename><surname>Vries</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1006/pmed.1996.0052</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_JDrJy4b">Preventive Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="236" to="242" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Brug, J., I. Steenhuis, P. Van Assema, and H. De Vries. 1996. The impact of a computer-tailored nutrition intervention. Preventive Medicine 25:236-42.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_dNPVhCG">Theory-driven evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<publisher>Sage</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Newbury Park, CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Chen, H. 1990. Theory-driven evaluation. Newbury Park, CA: Sage.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ja36E3b">The theory-driven approach to validity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Rossi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0149-7189(87)90025-5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_vMEqsWm">Evaluation and Program Planning</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="95" to="103" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Chen, H., and P. H. Rossi. 1987. The theory-driven approach to validity. Evaluation and Pro- gram Planning 10:95-103.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>¾¾¾</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_UAFWTVP">Using theory to improve program and policy evaluations</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Greenwood</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">¾¾¾, eds. 1992. Using theory to improve program and policy evaluations. New York: Greenwood.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_We76MS9">Learning from logic models: An example of a family/school partnership program</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Coffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Harvard Family Research Project</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Coffman, J. 1999. Learning from logic models: An example of a family/school partnership pro- gram. Cambridge, MA: Harvard Family Research Project.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_m7z8Kyu">The validity of conclusions in evaluation research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Costner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0149-7189(89)90051-7</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_pqjkhyb">Evaluation and Program Planning</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="345" to="353" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Costner, H. L. 1989. The validity of conclusions in evaluation research. Evaluation and Program Planning 12:345-53.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_5RgEQTD">A health belief model-social learning theory approach to adolescents&apos; fertility control: Findings from a controlled field trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Eisen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Zellman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mcalister</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/109019819201900208</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_277s8PS">Health Education Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="249" to="262" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Eisen, M., G. Zellman, and A. McAlister. 1992. A health belief model-social learning theory approach to adolescents&apos; fertility control: Findings from a controlled field trial. Health Edu- cation Quarterly 19 (2): 249-62.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_TKdd5NN">Group anger control training for junior high school delinquents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Feindler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Marriott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Iwata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/bf01173000</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_gx2xsaT">Cognitive Therapy and Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="299" to="311" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Feindler, E. L., S. A. Marriott, and M. Iwata. 1984. Group anger control training for junior high school delinquents. Cognitive Therapy and Research 8:299-311.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_kkUTTZ8">Theory and method in treatment evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Finney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Moos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0149-7189(89)90047-5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_PSD9X47">Evaluation and Program Planning</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="307" to="316" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Finney, J. W., and R. H. Moos. 1989. Theory and method in treatment evaluation. Evaluation and Program Planning 12:307-16.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_TdKHakX">The Television, School and Family Smoking Prevention and Cessation Project, VIII. Student outcomes and mediating variables</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Flay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hedeker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Siddiqui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Britton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Brannon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sussman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Dent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1006/pmed.1995.1005</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_uJ87Xbd">Preventive Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="40" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Flay, B. R., T. Q. Miller, D. Hedeker, O. Siddiqui, C. F. Britton, B. R. Brannon, A. Johnson, W. B. Hansen, S. Sussman, and C. Dent. 1995. The Television, School and Family Smoking Prevention and Cessation Project, VIII. Student outcomes and mediating variables. Preven- tive Medicine 24:29-40.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_5ny8zsG">FORECAST: A formative approach to evaluating community coalitions and community-based initiatives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Goodman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wandersman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/bf02511882</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_zV6Px4d">Journal of Community Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6" to="25" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>special issue</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Goodman, R. M., and A. Wandersman. 1994. FORECAST: A formative approach to evaluating community coalitions and community-based initiatives. Journal of Community Psychology (special issue): 6-25.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_kUSpY72">Evaluation design for a community prevention trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Holder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Saltz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Treno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Grube</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Voas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0193841x9702100202</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_82Wq2j4">Evaluation Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="140" to="166" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Holder, H. D., R. F. Saltz, A. J. Treno, J. W. Grube, and R. B. Voas. 1997. Evaluation design for a community prevention trial. Evaluation Review 21 (2): 140-66.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_t6drRvX">Logic models: A tool for telling your program&apos;s performance story</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mclaughlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Jordan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0149-7189(98)00042-1</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_qCef8dp">Evaluation and Program Planning</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">McLaughlin, J., and G. Jordan. 1999. Logic models: A tool for telling your program&apos;s perfor- mance story. Evaluation and Program Planning 22:65-72.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_GmJxQhj">Effects of a statewide antismoking campaign on mass media messages and smoking beliefs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Prokhorov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Harty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1006/pmed.1994.1008</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_PexW6XX">Preventive Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="54" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Murray, D. M., A. V. Prokhorov, and K. C. Harty. 1994. Effects of a statewide antismoking cam- paign on mass media messages and smoking beliefs. Preventive Medicine 3:54-60.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_NxxHER7">Primary prevention of chronic diseases in adolescence: Effects of the Midwestern prevention project on tobacco use</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Pentz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Dwyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mackinnon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Flay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/oxfordjournals.aje.a115393</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_QPQrWUZ">American Journal of Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">130</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="713" to="724" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Pentz, M. A., J. H. Dwyer, D. P. MacKinnon, B. R. Flay, W. B. Hansen, E. Wang, and C. A. Johnson. 1989. Primary prevention of chronic diseases in adolescence: Effects of the Midwestern pre- vention project on tobacco use. American Journal of Epidemiology 130:713-24.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_pmpKCPh">The community-based strategy to prevent coronary heart disease: Conclusions for the ten years of the North Karelia Projects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Puska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nissinen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tuomilehto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1146/annurev.publhealth.6.1.147</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_6shyfaR">Annual Review of Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="147" to="193" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Puska, P., A. Nissinen, and J. Tuomilehto. 1985. The community-based strategy to prevent coro- nary heart disease: Conclusions for the ten years of the North Karelia Projects. Annual Review of Public Health 6:147-93.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_NjWhZ3f">Evaluative research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Suchman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1967">1967</date>
			<publisher>Russell Sage</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Suchman, E. A. 1967. Evaluative research. New York: Russell Sage.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_wWVdZfJ">Evaluation research: Methods for assessing program effectiveness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
			<publisher>Prentice Hall</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Weiss, C. H. 1972. Evaluation research: Methods for assessing program effectiveness. Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice Hall.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_5usQjuK">Nothing as practical as a good theory: Exploring theory-based evaluation for comprehensive community initiatives for children and families</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>¾¾¾</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_Mdv22DM">New approaches to evaluating community initiatives: Concepts, methods &amp; contexts</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Connell</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kubich</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Schorr</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Washington, DC</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Aspen Institute</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995. 1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="501" to="524" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>How can theory-based evaluations make greater headway?</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">¾¾¾. 1995. Nothing as practical as a good theory: Exploring theory-based evaluation for com- prehensive community initiatives for children and families. In New approaches to evaluating community initiatives: Concepts, methods &amp; contexts, edited by J. P. Connell, A. C. Kubich, L. Schorr, and C. H. Weiss. Washington, DC: Aspen Institute. ¾¾¾. 1997. How can theory-based evaluations make greater headway? Evaluation Review 21:501-24.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_tetfZ62">Evaluation: methods for studying programs and policies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>¾¾¾</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<publisher>Prentice Hall</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Upper Saddle River, NJ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">¾¾¾. 1998. Evaluation: methods for studying programs and policies. Upper Saddle River, NJ: Prentice Hall.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Johanna</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_cpgZK5N">implementation, and evaluation of health programs and now serves as a program evaluator for a public health organization in Colorado</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Department of Health Behavior and Health Education at the University of North Carolina</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>completing her dissertation on the Birckmayer received her Ph.D. in health policy at Harvard University She has worked in Africa in the design effects of changes in alcohol policies on youth violence. She holds a masters in public health from the</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Johanna D. Birckmayer received her Ph.D. in health policy at Harvard University, completing her dissertation on the effects of changes in alcohol policies on youth violence. She holds a mas- ters in public health from the Department of Health Behavior and Health Education at the Uni- versity of North Carolina. She has worked in Africa in the design, implementation, and evalua- tion of health programs and now serves as a program evaluator for a public health organization in Colorado.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Carol</forename><surname>Hirschon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Weiss</forename><surname>Professor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ww/9780199540884.013.u7797</idno>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_vkfmKun">Methods for Studying Programs and Policies</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Prentice Hall</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Harvard University Graduate School of Education ; Columbia University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>She holds a doctorate in sociology from She has published 11 books, the most recent of which is Evaluation and almost 100 articles and book chapters. She has been a senior fellow at the U.S. Department of Education, a guest scholar at the Brookings Institution, a congressional fellow, a fellow at the Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences, and a member of seven panels of the National Academy of Sciences</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Carol Hirschon Weiss is a professor at Harvard University Graduate School of Education. She holds a doctorate in sociology from Columbia University. She has published 11 books, the most recent of which is Evaluation: Methods for Studying Programs and Policies (Prentice Hall, 1998), and almost 100 articles and book chapters. She has been a senior fellow at the U.S. Department of Education, a guest scholar at the Brookings Institution, a congressional fellow, a fellow at the Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences, and a member of seven pan- els of the National Academy of Sciences.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
