<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ySAcyK8">The Precaution Adoption Process</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Neil</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Weinstein</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Departments of Human Ecology and Psychology Rutgers , the State University of New Jersey Department of Human Ecology , Cook College , Rutgers , the State University of New Jersey , P.O. Box 231 , New Brunswick , NJ 08903 .</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Departments of Human Ecology and Psychology Rutgers</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Human Ecology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">the State University of New Jersey</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Cook College</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Rutgers</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">the State University of New Jersey</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 231</postBox>
									<postCode>08903</postCode>
									<settlement>New Brunswick</settlement>
									<region>NJ</region>
									<country></country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Departments of Human Ecology and Psychology Rutgers , the State University of New Jersey Department of Human Ecology , Cook College , Rutgers , the State University of New Jersey , P.O. Box 231 , New Brunswick , NJ 08903 .</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Departments of Human Ecology and Psychology Rutgers</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Human Ecology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">the State University of New Jersey</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Cook College</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Rutgers</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">the State University of New Jersey</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 231</postBox>
									<postCode>08903</postCode>
									<settlement>New Brunswick</settlement>
									<region>NJ</region>
									<country></country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_cqk2dvf">The Precaution Adoption Process</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">3ED95E3F2A2565752140B0D470030188</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T05:59+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term xml:id="_qsfF9Tq">preventive behavior</term>
					<term xml:id="_4fxKNqn">self-protective behavior</term>
					<term xml:id="_S24FrUV">stages of belief</term>
					<term xml:id="_eAy6CWJ">cues to action</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_ThKZKjR"><p xml:id="_UMJekj4"><s xml:id="_YD7vydT">This article presents a critique of current models of preventive behavior.</s><s xml:id="_dgZPTaK">It discusses a variety of factors that are usually overlooked -including the appearance of costs and benefits over time, the role of cues to action, the problem of competing life demands, and the ways that actual decision behavior differs from the rational ideal implicit in expectancy-value and utility theories.</s><s xml:id="_8xRYXAS">Such considerations suggest that the adoption of new precautions should be viewed as a dynamic process with many determinants.</s><s xml:id="_DW2F7XX">The framework of a model that is able to accommodate these additional factors is described.</s><s xml:id="_SAKpQYx">This alternative model portrays the precaution adoption process as an orderly sequence of qualitatively different cognitive stages.</s><s xml:id="_kbdbckY">Data illustrating a few of the suggestions made in the article are presented, and implications for prevention programs are discussed.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="432.0" lry="648.0"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="432.0" lry="648.0"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="432.0" lry="648.0"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="432.0" lry="648.0"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="432.0" lry="648.0"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="432.0" lry="648.0"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="433.0" lry="649.0"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="432.0" lry="648.0"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="432.0" lry="648.0"/>
		<surface n="10" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="432.0" lry="648.0"/>
		<surface n="11" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="432.0" lry="648.0"/>
		<surface n="12" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="432.0" lry="648.0"/>
		<surface n="13" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="432.0" lry="648.0"/>
		<surface n="14" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="432.0" lry="648.0"/>
		<surface n="15" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="435.0" lry="650.0"/>
		<surface n="16" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="434.0" lry="649.0"/>
		<surface n="17" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="432.0" lry="648.0"/>
		<surface n="18" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="435.0" lry="650.0"/>
		<surface n="19" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="432.0" lry="648.0"/>
		<surface n="20" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="433.0" lry="648.0"/>
		<surface n="21" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="434.0" lry="649.0"/>
		<surface n="22" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="432.0" lry="648.0"/>
		<surface n="23" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="432.0" lry="648.0"/>
		<surface n="24" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="435.0" lry="650.0"/>
		<surface n="25" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="432.0" lry="648.0"/>
		<surface n="26" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="432.0" lry="648.0"/>
		<surface n="27" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="433.0" lry="649.0"/>
		<surface n="28" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="432.0" lry="648.0"/>
		<surface n="29" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="432.0" lry="648.0"/>
		<surface n="30" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="432.0" lry="648.0"/>
		<surface n="31" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="432.0" lry="648.0"/>
		<surface n="32" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="432.0" lry="648.0"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_84ExydF"><p xml:id="_a4SEEkX"><s xml:id="_87M37c5">This article is a critique of these theories -an examination of the issues the theories tend to overlook and of the limitations inherent in their structure.</s><s xml:id="_ZmWgeuB">Because current theories appear so logical and self-contained, it is not obvious how they can be modified to handle additional complexities.</s><s xml:id="_N5R3Gd7">Thus, the present discussion also introduces an alternative model of preventive behavior.</s><s xml:id="_RDugK66">This new model is not fully prescribed or tested, but it does provide a framework that can accommodate both the insights of current theories and the phenomena ignored by these theories.</s><s xml:id="_GDJFMyx">A specific feature that sets this analysis apart from most others is its dynamic perspective -its emphasis on the development over time of the beliefs and intentions that lead to action.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_T6ThuQE">CURRENT MODELS OF INDIVIDUAL SELF-PROTECTIVE BEHAVIOR</head><p xml:id="_c6KmKkq"><s xml:id="_JScN9XP">Current work on individual preventive behavior is dominated by a cost-benefit, decision-making perspective.</s><s xml:id="_2QfkfMZ">The health belief model <ref type="bibr">(Becker, 1974;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Janz &amp; Becker, 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Maiman &amp; Becker, 1974;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">Rosenstock, 1974)</ref>, Fishbein and Ajzen's theory of reasoned action <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Ajzen &amp; Fishbein, 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Fishbein, 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Fishbein &amp; Ajzen, 1975)</ref>, subjective expected utility theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Beach, Campbell, &amp; Townes, 1979;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Edwards, 1954;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">Sutton, 1982)</ref>, and Rogers's protection motivation theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Maddux &amp; Rogers, 1983;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Rogers, 1975</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Rogers, , 1983;;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Rogers &amp; Mewborn, 1976)</ref> share this basic view.</s><s xml:id="_fDqcHPw">All have received considerable empirical support (for reviews, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Becker &amp; Maiman, 1983;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Cleary, 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Pagel &amp; Davidson, 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b72">B. S. Wallston &amp; K. A. Wallston, 1984)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_fWg9Xwg">At their core, these theories assume that people weigh the expected benefits of a precaution against its costs and adopt the precaution if the balance appears favorable.</s><s xml:id="_egM9Js7">The theories differ mainly in the range of costs and benefits considered and in the specific equation used to predict action likelihood.</s><s xml:id="_hXq2Ew7">When investigators apply protection motivation theory, subjective expected utility theory, or the health belief model to preventive behaviors, they tend to focus narrowly on the perception of the threat and the perception of the precaution under consideration.</s><s xml:id="_VqhwCdc">The principal variables in these theories are the individual's perceived susceptibility (the likelihood of being harmed if no action is taken), the perceived severity of the threat (the amount of harm that would be experienced if no action is taken), the perceived effectiveness of the precaution (in terms of reduced susceptibility or severity), and the perceived costs of adopting the precaution (time, energy, money).</s><s xml:id="_bQVk5de">A great many investigations have demonstrated that these variables are important predictors of preventive health behavior (for summaries, see <ref type="bibr">Becker, 1974;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Janz &amp; Becker, 1984)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_yXXdeGv"><s xml:id="_eZT2AFG">Studies based on Fishbein and Ajzen's theory of reasoned action, in contrast, include all outcomes salient to respondents.</s><s xml:id="_735mj4c">They consider not only the direct effect of the precaution on the risk but other consequences of performing the behavior, including the possibility of approval or disapproval from friends and family.</s></p><p xml:id="_AJP4Km4"><s xml:id="_zHgnR2f">Despite some differences in detail, these theories share several limitations.</s><s xml:id="_cuRpprC">All four assume that the relative probability of action is an algebraic function of the individual's beliefs.</s><s xml:id="_kbpTaWV">Relying on a single prediction equation, however, implies that nothing changes during the entire precaution adoption process except the values of the variables in the equation.</s><s xml:id="_vmagRMJ">Which variables are involved, the weights they receive, and the ways they interact are presumed to remain constant from the moment when the person first learns of the threat to the time when action begins.</s><s xml:id="_twmgkCP">By focusing on the numerical value of the decision equation, these theories imply that this is all we need to know about progress toward action.</s><s xml:id="_KFAsUeU">The origin of the beliefs that enter the equation and the possibility that such beliefs have implications for other behaviors (e.g., information seeking) that can alter the eventual hazard response lie outside the scope of these theories.</s></p><p xml:id="_uVnyR8e"><s xml:id="_etJAcYq">A further limitation of all these theories, except the theory of reasoned action, is the focus on a single threat and on a single preventive response.</s><s xml:id="_P9Tf6QC">Studies usually ignore other actions that might be taken against this threat, other threats that must be faced, and other life responsibilities that compete for time, energy, and material resources.</s></p><p xml:id="_tYQzhwx"><s xml:id="_yzmrXkd">Not all treatments of protective behavior share these limitations.</s><s xml:id="_bQKmzKT">Some point out stages in the response to threats <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(DiClemente, Prochaska, &amp; Gibertini, 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Janis &amp; Mann, 1976</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">, 1977;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Kunreuther, 1976;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">McGuire, 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Perry, Lindell, &amp; Greene, 1981;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Perry &amp; Mushkatel, 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Safer, Tharps, Jackson, &amp; Leventhal, 1979;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">Velicier, DiClemente, Prochaska, &amp; Brandenburg, 1985)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_dHsQ3PX">Some discuss the roles of information seeking <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Janis &amp; Mann, 1976</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">, 1977;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Kunreuther, 1976)</ref>, cognitive representations of hazards <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Leventhal, Meyer, &amp; Nerenz, 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Leventhal, Safer, &amp; Panagis, 1983)</ref>, and information processing limitations <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">(Slovic, Kunreuther, &amp; White, 1974)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_xATJQye">Others point out situations in which people must cope with the fears generated by threats <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Janis, 1967;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Lazarus, 1966;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Leventhal, 1970;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Leventhal et al., 1983)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_HEvy9PD">To consider such features requires more than the description of a decision rule.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Cmf6yWF">A DYNAMIC PERSPECTIVE</head><p xml:id="_FM94MA4"><s xml:id="_3Spj3JC">The goal of the discussion that follows is to examine the processes that lead individuals to adopt new preventive health behaviors and other precautions.</s></p><p xml:id="_U5nqvfz"><s xml:id="_gzgwTHZ">To concentrate on individual behavior, the presentation ignores economic, cultural, and social forces.</s><s xml:id="_zwKxS7w">Thus, it excludes many of the factors that shape people's beliefs, that determine which hazards people face, and that limit the protective options people have available.</s></p><p xml:id="_Bb3jAZp"><s xml:id="_bunUyDB">The discussion must also overlook the fact that many risk-influencing behaviors are undertaken for reasons unrelated to risk.</s><s xml:id="_QQH3FbV">Although selfprotection may motivate the purchase of smoke detectors and flood insurance, it certainly plays a minor role in most weight-loss diets.</s></p><p xml:id="_KD3WXvR"><s xml:id="_Xmg3NCb">If avoiding future harm is the major goal of an action, then beliefs about the need for protection and beliefs about the ability of a given action to provide protection are certainly central issues.</s><s xml:id="_FpaUpx8">The cognitive emphasis suggested by this statement and found in this article requires some explanation.</s><s xml:id="_Cnc4PtY">The ideas presented here concern the initiation of new and relatively complex behaviors.</s><s xml:id="_B4kjAWa">These behaviors are not already part of the person's response repertoire, nor are they emotions, biologically determined reflexes, habitual, or "mindless" <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Langer, Blank, &amp; Chanowitz, 1978)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_CjHd5Ns">New preventive actions usually involve high-level cognitive functioning and advance planning.</s><s xml:id="_GJKGEvR">Such characteristics, plus the success of existing models based on hazard beliefs, justify an emphasis on cognitive issues.</s></p><p xml:id="_4azUH66"><s xml:id="_fz5Hnn8">The theoretical framework to be sketched here is much more complex than the cost-benefit models introduced earlier.</s><s xml:id="_CR9WPj3">Those models treat beliefs about costs and benefits as continuous dimensions and assume that progress from ignorance to action is adequately explained by quantitative differences in the value of the decision equation.</s><s xml:id="_UGrg4Bv">The alternative approach taken in this article is to represent the precaution adoption process as a series of distinct stages.</s></p><p xml:id="_ya8uC8s"><s xml:id="_VJVPwgP">A stage theory of preventive behavior has at least two important differences from a theory based on a single prediction equation.</s><s xml:id="_uVAz5mf">A stage theory suggests (a) that people at different points in the precaution adoption process behave in qualitatively different ways and (b) that the kinds of interventions and information needed to move people closer to action will vary from stage to stage.</s><s xml:id="_MfaVugF">In fact, because it can be difficult to get people to move from one stage to the next, transitions between stages can be viewed as barriers that must be overcome before action is taken.</s></p><p xml:id="_dvx4uus"><s xml:id="_99KzRRk">The remainder of the discussion is broken into six major sections.</s><s xml:id="_yhkZKr7">The first section describes a sequence of stages in the development of a person's beliefs about his or her susceptibility to harm.</s><s xml:id="_eZxeRQX">Beliefs about susceptibility are important in all current theories of self-protective behavior.</s><s xml:id="_wj3taNt">This section offers some data suggesting that distinct stages in the evolution of such beliefs exist and shows how a stage model has advantages over attempting to describe these beliefs with a single scale.</s><s xml:id="_2nAgvQ5">The second section briefly describes how a stage perspective might be applied to issues of risk severity, precaution effectiveness, and cost.</s></p><p xml:id="_f7cGMg5"><s xml:id="_VCfnE5h">The third section discusses the decision to act.</s><s xml:id="_HcanqeY">It examines the factors that influence the decision and the form of the decision rule.</s><s xml:id="_HFyVgxd">This section also considers the time span over which costs and benefits appear and the implications of differences in their time of arrival.</s><s xml:id="_tNPhBpC">The fourth section focuses on the difficulty of transforming intentions into actions.</s><s xml:id="_NpX7KBq">It presents a "messy desk" analogy to help understand situations in which multiple intentions and life demands compete for attention.</s><s xml:id="_pKCfKmA">The fifth and sixth sections examine testable aspects of the theoretical notions offered here and implications for prevention programs.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_XphyPF9">Stages of Belief About Personal Susceptibility</head><p xml:id="_YmG7tNn"><s xml:id="_fsdVMMZ">Most investigations of preventive behavior have focused on well-known hazards like smoking, floods, or automobile accidents.</s><s xml:id="_BRwDte5">In these studies, subjects describe their beliefs on simple scales.</s><s xml:id="_6UhcW7k">Each belief is described by its placement along a continuum.</s><s xml:id="_BMQs3Eu">For example, beliefs about susceptibility might be indicated on a rating scale that ranges from very unlikely to very likely.</s><s xml:id="_FJxyfFY">Focusing on familiar hazards, however, leads one to overlook the important period of time when people have no opinions about a hazard because they have not even heard of it.</s><s xml:id="_BZt6Zpk">A don't know option is seldom provided to research subjects.</s><s xml:id="_NafzvjW">Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> suggests that beliefs about susceptibility should be described by a series of stages, not by their location along a continuum.</s><s xml:id="_cu3tJhh"><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Perry &amp; Mushkatel, 1984</ref>, described similar stages for responses to natural hazard warnings.)</s><s xml:id="_Qzv6cfy">The stages are defined in terms of beliefs people hold about the risk situation. 1</s><s xml:id="_Yh99c4j">A person reaches a stage when he or she accepts the idea that defines that stage.</s><s xml:id="_nms99UX">The stages are cumulative in that a person at a given stage 'Stages are dichotomous variables; a person has either reached a stage or has not.</s><s xml:id="_APcJFNd">This does not mean, however, that the criteria that define the stages (e.g., awareness of risk, belief in general susceptibility, belief in personal susceptibility) have only two levels.</s><s xml:id="_vhSeJze">People certainly do distinguish among the risks to which they are vulnerable, recognizing some as more likely than others.</s><s xml:id="_XdT4VNF">However, a stage model implies that a qualitative change occurs in behavior and thought when each of these beliefs passes a threshold and that it is natural for people to distinguish between "serious risks" and "negligible risks" even though they recognize differences within each category.</s></p><p xml:id="_QURjKZX"><s xml:id="_NvXTB4w">Radon provides a particularly clear example of cognitive stages as dichotomous variables.</s><s xml:id="_qTQ2ftz">People who test their homes and find radon levels exceeding 4 picocuries/liter (the level at which the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency recommends mitigation action) seem to take this issue much more seriously than people whose test results are just below this level.</s><s xml:id="_hVHmMY3">Home owners are not blind to the differences between 0.5 and 3.5, and 4.5 is not regarded as identical to 45, but most people with 0.5 or 3.5 seem to believe that they do not have a problem, and most people with either of the higher levels act as if they do.</s><s xml:id="_rmb4D6w">Thus, individuals with radon levels below and above 4 picocuries/liter seem to be in qualitatively different cognitive states.</s><s xml:id="_Mp9xgeM">Although the radon example portrays the stage transition as a sharply defined step function, with individuals changing stage at the same level of underlying risk, a less abrupt, S-shaped transition, with individual differences in the level of risk that leads to a change in stage, is probably much more common.</s></p><p xml:id="_u6JYcXv"><s xml:id="_dsmkyNJ">This document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers.</s></p><p xml:id="_fVE2mtb"><s xml:id="_mazxqzs">This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.</s></p><p xml:id="_m3cRhFh"><s xml:id="_n4Ph6Ac">Stage 1: HAS HEARD OF HAZARD Stage 2: BELIEVES IN SIGNIFICANT LIKELIHOOD FOR OTHERS Stage 3: ACKNOWLEDGES PERSONAL SUSCEPTIBILITY Example: "I have heard of the radon problem.</s><s xml:id="_aCBhnxR">"I've never heard of the radon problem."</s><s xml:id="_PNBgASQ">"Radon is a problem for quite a few people."</s><s xml:id="_4GGuyYU">vs. "The number of people who have a radon problem is negligible."</s><s xml:id="_MC4uKvD">"There is a real chance that I could have a radon problem in my home.</s><s xml:id="_hW8Qdjk">vs. "There isn't much of a chance that I could have a radon problem in my own home."</s><s xml:id="_Qu7Dm2H">Major determinants: Communications about hazard Experience with hazard Credibility and clarity of communications about prevalence Experience with hazard Risk factor information Personalized risk information Experience with hazard Information about peers' status on risk factors FIGURE 1 Stages of belief about susceptibility to harm.</s><s xml:id="_NhN48Us">Examples of the questions used to identify the stage an individual is at are given for a particular hazard -the risk of home contamination by radioactive radon.</s><s xml:id="_VTXqtBM">An individual has reached a stage if he or she agrees with the underlined statement associated with that stage.</s><s xml:id="_gTRweZy">The factors listed as determinants govern whether an individual will progress to that stage from the preceding stage.</s></p><p xml:id="_tJkU5Qf"><s xml:id="_swAMztG">CO also agrees with the statements that define all earlier stages.</s><s xml:id="_8XHDXx4">As the individual is exposed to new information and experiences, however, movement between stages may be backward as well as forward.</s></p><p xml:id="_fCAWd58"><s xml:id="_ZdQeXtg">The statements appearing in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> illustrate how stages of belief might be defined for a particular hazard-the risk of lung cancer from naturally occurring radon gas.</s><s xml:id="_gUGrqjR">This is a problem that first received public attention in 1984, when it was found that radioactive radon from the ground can reach dangerous levels in buildings.</s><s xml:id="_VTUwJhr">Millions of homes are affected.</s><s xml:id="_rqBkPp6">Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> also lists factors that seem likely to determine whether people progress from one stage to the next.</s></p><p xml:id="_JYACm3P"><s xml:id="_dXd8bJc">Stage 1 in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> reminds us that people must first learn that a hazard exists.</s><s xml:id="_yw6xKZc">In many cases, a failure to protect oneself reflects ignorance of the threat, not a conviction that the threat is small.</s><s xml:id="_TjfhJfR">The distinction is important; there is a qualitative difference between the person who knows nothing about a hazard and the individual who has thought about the issue and has concluded that there is no risk.</s><s xml:id="_vUgufjS">Someone who never considered the risks from nuclear waste, for example, is not equivalent to one who is convinced that the danger is negligible.</s><s xml:id="_Qvd9swf">The first person, according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Janis and</ref><ref type="bibr">Mann (1976, 1977)</ref>, will be open-minded about the hazard but will not actively seek out information.</s><s xml:id="_vScKWK4">In contrast, the second person's commitment to a particular point of view will tend to produce a biased response.</s><s xml:id="_Astejff">The second person will selectively attend to messages that support his or her own position <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Festinger, 1957;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Frey, 1986;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b83">Wicklund &amp; Brehm, 1976)</ref> and will show counterarguing and belief perseverance when faced with disconfirming evidence <ref type="bibr">(Nisbett &amp; Ross, 1980, Chap. 8)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_pjK6ETm"><s xml:id="_txGkWvg">Research on reactions to messages linking coffee to pancreatic cancer and messages about the risk of environmental cancer <ref type="bibr" target="#b74">(Weinstein, 1979</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b79">(Weinstein, , 1985) )</ref> support these assertions about the differences between people who are unaware and people who believe there is no risk.</s><s xml:id="_NPaW8u9">For example, until the research on coffee and cancer was first publicized, no one knew about this (since disproved) problem.</s><s xml:id="_fk22EdG">As predicted by the preceding discussion, coffee drinkers' initial reactions to this threatening message were unbiased.</s><s xml:id="_Qgu2bxb">They were no more likely than nondrinkers to dispute the research or to avoid the news articles.</s><s xml:id="_Ek9FjbY">Coffee drinkers who eventually come to the conclusion that the threat has been exaggerated, however, would be expected to prefer reassuring messages over new, potentially alarming information.</s></p><p xml:id="_FnzrdFb"><s xml:id="_p7MqKSY">After people have reached Stage 1, additional hazard messages and hazard experiences must convince them that the risk is significant. 2</s><s xml:id="_jARBRQg">2 The figure does not show all possible cognitive stages; it shows only those that represent milestones on the path to adoption.</s><s xml:id="_xUp9gay">As a reviewer has noted, progress is not necessarily from ignorance to action.</s><s xml:id="_XwT8Jvw">People who are aware of a risk may beome convinced that they are not susceptible and may only later recognize their vulnerability.</s></p><p xml:id="_yfjnsxj"><s xml:id="_fAchquF">Communications from the mass media and from acquaintances usually address the questions of whether something is really hazardous and whether it is a hazard for many people, thus influencing movement toward Stage 2. But these messages seldom establish clearly who is likely to be affected.</s><s xml:id="_hEbRBsQ">Given this ambiguity, it is relatively easy for people to conclude that it is not their problem.</s><s xml:id="_qeqJnaR">Empirical research supports this assertion.</s><s xml:id="_R5VHafd">People who acknowledge that a hazard poses a substantial threat show a consistent tendency to deny that they, personally, are at risk <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Drake, 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Kulik &amp; Mahler, 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Perloff &amp; Fetzer, 1986;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Svenson, Fischhoff, &amp; MacGregor, 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b75">Weinstein, 1980</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b78">Weinstein, , 1984</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b80">Weinstein, , 1987))</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_JANZp8A">A description of reactions to flood warnings illustrates this point well:</s></p><p xml:id="_v3dF38C"><s xml:id="_2vBCJCh">Gradually it was accepted that a flood of some type was going to occur, but families then defined the situation so as to grossly underestimate the scope and destructiveness of the disaster.</s><s xml:id="_mH7FzKD">Additional information led them to conclude more accurately the enormity of the threat, but they countered with a redefinition of personal invulnerability, i.e., "It won't hit our house."</s><s xml:id="_HvEK7Ac"><ref type="bibr">(Drabek &amp; Boggs, 1968, p. 455)</ref> To demonstate this idea further, data were collected from 342 college students (18 to 35 years old) in four different courses.</s><s xml:id="_ESMegew">The students were asked questions that correspond to the risk susceptibility stages in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_EyVnzgt">A variety of hazards was used.</s><s xml:id="_gxu6gEs">The questions and response options were projected onto a screen, and subjects recorded a letter on an answer sheet to indicate the response option they had selected.</s><s xml:id="_3sDt3Ae">Questions were presented in random order with many filler items.</s><s xml:id="_JnhwrBt">These procedures were designed to reduce the likelihood that subjects would alter their response to a given question in order to appear consistent with answers to earlier, related questions.</s></p><p xml:id="_7eTS4yd"><s xml:id="_vJqBSJ9">The results in the first column of Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref> show that many students believe that they themselves are not vulnerable even though they acknowledge the significance of the hazard for others.</s><s xml:id="_MKTjphj">Such individuals have not passed beyond Stage 2.</s></p><p xml:id="_ZTrTBPy"><s xml:id="_wStAS4j">When people watch an approaching hurricane, there is genuine uncertainty about where it will strike, and the difficulty of determining personal risk is obvious.</s><s xml:id="_BxWU67C">The data in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref> and those reported in research cited earlier show that there is more than uncertainty involved; there is also a consistent optimistic bias.</s><s xml:id="_Umt835c">This bias can present a major barrier to the adoption of precautions <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Janz &amp; Becker, 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Perry &amp; Mushkatel, 1984)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_KRUQZHE">Furthermore, as long as people do not see themselves as being at risk, they will not seek out information and will pay relatively little attention to hazard communications <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Janis &amp; Mann, 1976</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">, 1977;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Kunreuther, 1976;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Kunreuther et al., 1978)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_8aexnY6">Individualized "health hazard appraisals" <ref type="bibr">(Weiss,</ref><ref type="bibr">61.7</ref>  a "There is a real chance that it could happen to me" (percentage of those who say that there is a significant risk for others).</s><s xml:id="_gfMRMsF">b "Taking this precaution would reduce my risk" (percentage of those who say that it could happen to them and that the precaution generally reduces people's risk).</s></p><p xml:id="_azCRZyP"><s xml:id="_Yr3GBDq">C "I plan to take this precaution" (percentage of those who say that it would reduce their own risk).</s><s xml:id="_rSj6Y7W">d Different groups of subjects were asked different sets of questions.</s><s xml:id="_fH3V7bB">Dash indicates question was not asked.</s></p><p xml:id="_CCzqECg"><s xml:id="_tfFgCMK">1984) and personalized risk messages (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Cohen, Colligan, &amp; Berger, 1985)</ref> represent attempts to encourage protective action by overcoming these convictions of personal invulnerability.</s></p><p xml:id="_AAz2qkY"><s xml:id="_Kmnk2mQ">Optimistic biases -erroneous beliefs that our own risk is less than the risk faced by others-appear to have a variety of sources <ref type="bibr" target="#b75">(Weinstein, 1980</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b76">(Weinstein, , 1982</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b80">(Weinstein, , 1987))</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_bVB6WFX">They can result from incorrect information ("Epilepsy appears during childhood; if I don't have it now, I can't get it") and a from a variety of other cognitive errors.</s><s xml:id="_xtMde9G">Unrealistic optimism may also have motivational origins: the need to protect self-esteem or the desire to avoid feeling afraid <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Janis &amp; Mann, 1977)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_SwZPWm8"><s xml:id="_u52FSrP">Research has shown that the hazards most likely to evoke optimistic biases are ones that we seldom encounter, that we think are preventable, and that we believe appear relatively early in life <ref type="bibr" target="#b80">(Weinstein, 1987)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_ChBMvTN">Consequently, Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> suggests that both personal experience and information about the factors that determine susceptibility should help to reduce optimistic biases.</s><s xml:id="_fvNXRNU">Information about the precautions that peers are taking can also help people to see that their own risk may be as great or greater than the risk faced by others <ref type="bibr" target="#b77">(Weinstein, 1983)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_WT5mCYD">However, general facts about a hazard (e.g., what radon is, which states have radon problems, how radon causes cancer, etc.) are unlikely to move people beyond Stage 2.</s></p><p xml:id="_bKm3jHw"><s xml:id="_syXqBbT">Although Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> depicts acceptance of personal susceptibility (Stage 3) as coming after the recognition of others' susceptibility (Stage 2), the order may sometimes be reversed.</s><s xml:id="_qTDcJeq">For example, a doctor might tell a patient she has an illness that she had never heard of previously.</s><s xml:id="_EYSUB3r">Nevertheless, such an inverted sequence is unusual.</s></p><p xml:id="_HKKmagU"><s xml:id="_mstMpse">As the preceding discussion has shown, the stages described in Figure 1 contain three types of information.</s><s xml:id="_EHg3GKx">They describe a temporal pattern in the development of beliefs about susceptibility; they alert us to barriers that discourage preventive action; and they suggest that the factors important in overcoming these barriers differ at each stage.</s><s xml:id="_UvM4bpH">This is quite different from treating beliefs about susceptibility as lying along a single continuum.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_9FDtwVB">Beliefs About Severity, Precaution Effectiveness, and Cost</head><p xml:id="_wWaGB94"><s xml:id="_auvSHEp">It is possible to differentiate similar stages of belief about hazard severity and precaution effectiveness (e.g., Stage 1 = awareness that the precaution exists, Stage 2 = belief that the precaution is generally effective, and Stage 3 = belief that the precaution would be personally effective).</s><s xml:id="_Pr3hNjV">Which hazard-severity or precaution-effectiveness stage a person is at would have implications for his or her open-mindedness and interest in further information, just as would the susceptibility stage a person is at.</s><s xml:id="_qMuuSR3">Although beliefs about susceptibility, severity, effectiveness, and cost can develop simultaneously, little interest in precautions would be expected until the hazard is thought to present a significant personal threat.</s><s xml:id="_9s94695">This temporal precedence of risk perception over precaution assessment is similar to <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Lazarus's (1966)</ref> distinction between primary (threat) appraisal and secondary (coping) appraisal.</s></p><p xml:id="_sJ6F2V7"><s xml:id="_q68qSCY">Although research has demonstrated a consistent tendency for people to assert that they are less susceptible than others, there is only limited data about a similar self-other distinction for perceived severity or perceived effectiveness.</s><s xml:id="_QZqDnqS">Many people living in areas with radon who know that radon causes lung cancer nevertheless claim that a radon-caused illness in their families would not be serious <ref type="bibr">(Weinstein, Sandman, &amp; Klotz, in press</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_GSCqpWT">We do not know, however, whether people tend generally to believe that the harm they would experience is less than the harm others would suffer (i.e., whether the transition from Stage 2 to Stage 3 in beliefs about hazard severity represents a major barrier to preventive action).</s></p><p xml:id="_ynxrc9p"><s xml:id="_NerNWVS">With regard to precaution effectiveness, the data in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref> suggest that people who believe they are at risk and who say that an action is effective for others usually acknowledge that it would help in their own case as well.</s><s xml:id="_GJda6zw">Still, it is easy to think of cases in which precautions that are beneficial for some individuals would be inappropriate for others.</s><s xml:id="_QrzvQaS">Although we do not know whether people resist the transition to Stage 3 beliefs about precau-tion effectiveness, a difference between Stage 2 and Stage 3 is likely to have a significant effect on behavior.</s></p><p xml:id="_M4uZHDR"><s xml:id="_aKFVS87">Another crucial characteristic of a preventive behavior is its perceived cost.</s><s xml:id="_a4EEUQw">"Cost" as used here includes the time and effort required to carry out the precaution, the expense, any undesirable side effects, the loss of pleasure from the behavior that must change, the possibility that the precaution is unavailable to the individual, and similar obstacles.</s><s xml:id="_MRcGghb">Because "cost" encompasses the notion of difficulty, it includes the possibility that an individual may doubt his or her ability to carry out the precaution.</s><s xml:id="_q23BUcV">Some people with radon-contaminated homes, for example, are able to develop elaborate remediation strategies on their own; others feel that understanding the simplest brochure is too difficult for them.</s><s xml:id="_nUp3T65">This concept of cost thus incorporates the notion of self-efficacy <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Bandura, 1977;</ref><ref type="bibr">DiClemente et al., 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Maddux &amp; Rogers, 1983;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Rogers, 1983;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b84">Wilson, 1980)</ref>, an important determinant of preventive actions that require skill or perseverance.</s><s xml:id="_Yev3DsN">Although distinct stages in beliefs about cost seem unlikely, different people may believe they face, and may actually face, very different obstacles.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_XSkCATK">Deciding to Act</head><p xml:id="_crmGcY8"><s xml:id="_FBBasCc">As stated earlier, in the prevailing models of protective behavior, beliefs about susceptibility, severity, efficacy, and cost are combined in some explicit or empirically derived decision equation.</s><s xml:id="_NAU6AeM">The more favorable the value of the equation, the greater the likelihood of action.</s><s xml:id="_KdK38A8">A stage theory takes a somewhat different approach.</s><s xml:id="_audnRfJ">According to the present perspective, the decision to act -Stage 4 in the precaution adoption process -will not occur until people have reached the final stages of all three relevant beliefs: susceptibility, severity, and precaution effectiveness.</s><s xml:id="_naxavsf">In other words, the beliefs that I am susceptible, that the hazard would have personally negative consequences, and that the precaution would be personally effective are necessary conditions for the decision to act.</s><s xml:id="_DEXb6NU">Each variable would have to exceed some minimum value before an individual would decide to take the precaution.</s><s xml:id="_XtrNdbC">This would not be a sufficient condition for action, however, because the decision to act would also take into account the extent to which the minimum values are exceeded and thus reflect the perceived magnitude of the severity and likelihood, the degree of effectiveness, and the size of the cost that would be incurred.</s></p><p xml:id="_KPd7ZqN"><s xml:id="_BEkyGga">A decision to act may be reversed.</s><s xml:id="_hhPyftV">Still, those who have decided to act have not just a "tendency" to act but an "intention" to act.</s><s xml:id="_6gyfn4r">The formation of such an intention brings self-regulatory processes into effect that help translate the intention into action <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Kuhl, 1985)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_Yxg3B5d">Behavioral intention is also the crucial intervening variable in the theory of reasoned action.</s><s xml:id="_q6nv5sg">This section discusses the way in which different beliefs are combined to reach a decision and describes variables other than those traditionally used in cost-benefit models that enter the decision process.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_yaYMped">Decision Rules</head><p xml:id="_AQDyz8S"><s xml:id="_wXegAD2">There is no agreement among current theories as to how people combine their beliefs about costs and benefits.</s><s xml:id="_kMD6YSK">Health belief model studies either look just at the correlations between predictor variables and the measure of behavior or employ multiple-regression analysis to decide how the predictors should be combined.</s><s xml:id="_CUSye2Z">As used, the health belief model is not a model at all, just a list of variables.</s><s xml:id="_Tn5szGN">The theory of reasoned action <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Ajzen &amp; Fishbein, 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Fishbein &amp; Ajzen, 1975)</ref> and expected utility theory multiply the perceived likelihood by the perceived value of the outcome and sum such products over the potential outcomes.</s><s xml:id="_jThQFjX">The former uses regression analysis to determine one arbitrary parameter -the relative weight of direct personal consequences as opposed to social consequences (i.e., approval or disapproval).</s></p><p xml:id="_BKKZua3"><s xml:id="_xnuhJGg">Combining likelihood and severity.</s><s xml:id="_ED5NYRU">According to the theory of reasoned action and expected utility theory, perceived likelihood and perceived severity should be multiplied together to determine the seriousness of the hazard.</s><s xml:id="_yNceQc4">Several authors (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Leventhal et al., 1983</ref>; B. S. Wallston &amp; K. A. <ref type="bibr" target="#b72">Wallston, 1984)</ref> have suggested that the logic underlying the health belief model implies a multiplicative relationship for this theory as well.</s><s xml:id="_DEqS9pA">On the other hand, <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Rogers (1983;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Maddux &amp; Rogers, 1983;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Rogers &amp; Mewborn, 1976</ref>; see also <ref type="bibr">Weinstein, 1982, pp. 454-456)</ref> has failed to find evidence for a multiplicative (i.e., interaction) term in his own research and has concluded that the contributions of likelihood and severity are independent.</s></p><p xml:id="_SU3geWG"><s xml:id="_7PXUGkQ">The logic behind a multiplicative model seems convincing.</s><s xml:id="_mxX3WwA">According to elementary statistics, when a risk is uncertain, the average loss over many trials is the product of the risk's probability and the magnitude of the loss that would occur.</s><s xml:id="_HqUe3yA">A decision maker who wished to maximize his or her benefits over an extended period of time would use this measure of seriousness.</s><s xml:id="_nYAetQe">At a commonsense level, too, the argument that the effects of these two variables ought to be interdependent seems compelling.</s><s xml:id="_fEtWcVV">For example, a severe earthquake in Boston is a real possibility, but there is no market there for earthquake insurance.</s><s xml:id="_rWmgW5C">The chance of this happening seems too small to Bostonians.</s><s xml:id="_HZmPtkZ">And even high-probability events will not stimulate protective action if the damage produced is trivial.</s><s xml:id="_2jVUmmN">In such examples, we see that the effects of either likelihood or severity cannot be determined without reference to the other variable; they interact.</s><s xml:id="_wWzKAzP">But why does empirical evidence often suggest that their effects are independent?</s></p><p xml:id="_zAtxvTk"><s xml:id="_PRVad9c">One way out of this dilemma is to postulate a more complex decision rule, one that incorporates the notion of cutoffs and that therefore is consistent with the stage perspective presented here.</s><s xml:id="_BpFkcFs">People may regard a problem as undeserving of preventive action if either likelihood or severity is below a minimum level (in such a rule, the two variables are not independent), but once both variables exceed the cutoffs, seriousness may be an additive (independent) function of the two factors.</s><s xml:id="_KfyKqAd">The hazards that are serious enough to become the object of scientific study usually involve levels of likelihood and severity large enough so that their contributions, by this rule, would appear to be independent.</s><s xml:id="_jX3v5MB"><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Janz and Becker's (1984)</ref> report that perceived severity was seldom correlated with preventive behavior in the studies they reviewed suggests a variation of this rule.</s><s xml:id="_drqqRvp">As <ref type="bibr">Kruglanski and Klar (1985, p. 49)</ref> proposed, people may sometimes use a decision rule in which severity must reach a certain level to be of concern, but above that level the decision is only a function of perceived susceptibility.</s></p><p xml:id="_MhX9mHn"><s xml:id="_bxu9Aa4">Current views of decision rules.</s><s xml:id="_tyh7JqJ">Such nonstandard rules for deciding whether a threat is serious are consistent with the results of research in behavioral decision theory.</s><s xml:id="_ahPD8FY">The notion that people always attempt to maximize utility (and determine utility by multiplying probability by value) has been disproved repeatedly <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">(Schoemaker, 1982)</ref>, and investigators have found many other ways that people combine perceptions of probability and value.</s></p><p xml:id="_zGAcqya"><s xml:id="_yhFjHB2">Terms such as "satisficing," "elimination by aspects," and "additive difference" have been coined to denote some of the choice strategies that have been observed (for discussions, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Beach &amp; Mitchell, 1978;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kuhl, 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">Svenson, 1979)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_G8KrhD6">Often it seems that people employ these alternative decision rules to help them avoid the computational burdens and heavy informational requirements of expectancy-value and expected-utility theories.</s><s xml:id="_qGcyZRc">Studies have only begun to identify the features (e.g., the time pressure, the display of information, and the similarity of alternatives) that favor particular decision rules <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Payne, 1982</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_hSZaXfY">Yet, even in the laboratory it is clear that people often reach decisions without ever combining the expected outcomes into a single measure of value, as is assumed by most theories of protective behavior <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Fischhoff, Goitein, &amp; Shapira, 1982)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_pGJw4dP">If people cannot employ the optimizing approach implicit in these theories when the probabilities and utilities are handed to subjects, the applicability of these models outside the laboratory, where there are many more consequences to consider and information is far more difficult to obtain, needs to be questioned.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Myhm85y">Certain versus probabilistic outcomes.</head><p xml:id="_F2vkyb5"><s xml:id="_9JphxsC">One issue overlooked by standard theories is the qualitative difference between costs and benefits in most hazard situations.</s><s xml:id="_DuTmRCy">Usually, the costs (particularly short-term costs) are certain: the dollars needed to install a burglar alarm, the time required to exercise, the pleasure lost in giving up salt to avoid hypertension.</s><s xml:id="_Ygw7bev">The benefits, in contrast, are mainly hypothetical.</s><s xml:id="_zBhPpa4">An individual has no assurance that taking the precaution will make any difference in the long run because there is only a possibility that the hazard will ever appear.</s><s xml:id="_FmE3fjS"><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Kahneman and Tversky (1979)</ref> showed that people give outcomes that are certain more weight than probabilistic outcomes even when the expected values (i.e., probability X value) are the same.</s><s xml:id="_dCurk89">Consequently, a message proclaiming that a precaution offers complete protection against lung cancer should be more effective than one telling how the same precaution decreases the total cancer risk by 20%, even if people believe that 20% of all cancers are lung cancer.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_pvQJkAm">Other Influences on the Decision Process</head><p xml:id="_G5xcgVa"><s xml:id="_4D4SBCH">Several other factors not included in traditional cost-benefit analyses are listed under Stage 4 in Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_zy5geJM"><s xml:id="_cbDQnDY">Salience.</s><s xml:id="_bED4tfd">The extent to which different aspects of the hazard problem hold our attention is difficult to measure but may have important consequences.</s><s xml:id="_j86ef37">For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">Tversky and Kahneman (1981)</ref> showed that decisions are affected by the way in which problems are "framed."</s><s xml:id="_RzJGtWK">Describing a medical procedure in terms of the probability of survival, for example, leads to different choices than describing the same procedure in terms of the probability of death.</s><s xml:id="_44m7Dfe">The change in wording apparently alters the attributes that are salient, changing the perceived attractiveness of the procedure (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Payne, 1982)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_7Pq9nGp">There is a great deal of evidence showing a powerful impact of factors like vividness and concreteness on various social judgments <ref type="bibr">(Nisbett &amp; Ross, 1980, Chap. 3)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_EpwQVD3">Accurate theories of preventive action will have to determine which of many relevant factors people are actually thinking about when they reach their decisions.</s><s xml:id="_jkkdqv9">Time dependency of costs and benefits.</s><s xml:id="_TUSGfSX">None of the models used to explain self-protective behavior deals explicitly with the fact that benefits and costs do not appear instantaneously.</s><s xml:id="_jjbpgmv">When research subjects are asked whether a precaution is worth taking, what time period should they have in mind when they answer?</s><s xml:id="_tzMzKha">Is there a time period that they use naturally when answering such a question?</s><s xml:id="_7JgqskR">The desirability of treating lung cancer with radiation therapy or with surgery, to cite one example, depends on the time interval considered <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(McNeil, Weichselbaum, &amp; Pauker, 1978)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_mXBwCXS">These au-Stage 4: DECIDES TO TAKE PRECA UTION Stage 5: TAKES PRECA UTION Example: "I plan to ventilate my home to reduce the radon level."</s><s xml:id="_JBU3phd">vs" I don't plan to increase the ventilation in my home."</s><s xml:id="_ge8GTdy">Major determinants: Beliefs about seriousness of threat Beliefs about personal susceptibility * Beliefs about personal severity Behaviors of others and communications directly indicating threat seriousness Salience of short-and long-term threat Beliefs about precaution * Beliefs about precaution effectiveness for oneself * Beliefs about barriers to adoption of precaution Behavior of others and communications directly indicating desirability of precaution Salience of short-and long-term costs Alternative precautions available "I have added extra ventilation to reduce the radon level."</s><s xml:id="_wkrgr9F">vs. "I haven't added extra ventilation."</s><s xml:id="_GtmeD9x">Factors determining strength of intention to act (all those listed for Stage 4) Complexity of precaution Ease of obtaining information required to carry out precaution Time, effort, and resources required by precaution Time, effort, and resources available considering competing life demands Time until hazard appears Opportunities that decrease costs of acting Reminders of threat Reminders to take precaution FIGURE 2 Stages of decision and action.</s><s xml:id="_rhMkhqz">A person has reached a given stage if he or she agrees with the statement underlined.</s><s xml:id="_qU4bcGV">The factors listed as determinants govern whether an individual will progress to that stage from the preceding stage.</s><s xml:id="_jg4dabZ">The determinants marked with an asterisk are the ones considered in expectancy-value and expected-utility theory.</s></p><p xml:id="_ySKdpqp"><s xml:id="_WPUT4y8">thors suggest that physicians prefer surgery due to the greater 5-year survival rate for this procedure but that patients give more emphasis to short-term consequences and would probably choose radiation to avoid the significant risk of death during surgery.</s></p><p xml:id="_DdW7WAk"><s xml:id="_at9cjV7">Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> shows several patterns for the changes in risk and cost over time.</s><s xml:id="_YfxxsUP">The dotted, bottom region of each panel indicates the perceived danger.</s><s xml:id="_3zsmVfd">The width of the striped band indicates the perceived cost of protective efforts.</s></p><p xml:id="_D52NWvZ"><s xml:id="_GnyH9SZ">FIGURE <ref type="figure">3</ref> Common patterns for the appearance of costs and risk over time.</s><s xml:id="_XY6TCss">The horizontal axis in each panel is time, with the tic mark indicating the point at which the precaution is adopted.</s><s xml:id="_xzusBvS">The vertical axis depicts the magnitude of the risk (dotted area) and the amount of effort involved in carrying out preventive activities (striped area).</s></p><p xml:id="_GRTzZ9Z"><s xml:id="_dwNQcBt">Thus, the upper curve is the sum of the cost plus the danger, a sum people want to minimize. 3</s><s xml:id="_zE69KHy"> To a first approximation, the upper curve determines the attractiveness of a new precaution.</s><s xml:id="_k82zd5x">The lower the curve becomes, the more attractive the action.</s><s xml:id="_FBCKXUH">When precautions are initiated, costs typically go up and risks go down.</s><s xml:id="_NRJSxvG">The sizes of these changes and the rates at which they appear determine the net advantage at any moment of having taken the protective action.</s></p><p xml:id="_VTfsdcK"><s xml:id="_VR7d2Hj">The panels in Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> show that common situations involve very different patterns.</s><s xml:id="_3VnHW9r">In Panel a, the precaution has negligible cost and the benefits appear quickly.</s><s xml:id="_Cz7fGRd">Examples include switching from an unfluoridated toothpaste to a fluoridated brand to reduce the risk of tooth decay and giving acetaminophen rather than aspirin to a child with influenza to reduce the risk of Reyes syndrome.</s><s xml:id="_pDzFW3h">The shape of the upper curve in Panel a makes it clear why this type of change is easy to bring about.</s><s xml:id="_gdYD3JP">Panel b depicts a precaution that has only short-term costs and that reduces risk quickly.</s><s xml:id="_g5xBye5">Obtaining a vaccination and installing a smoke detector fit this pattern.</s><s xml:id="_RnxUwwy">The figure suggests that helping people over the barrier by temporarily reducing the cost can bring about a major change in protection.</s></p><p xml:id="_78k95D5"><s xml:id="_DF5SS96">In Panel c, the threat is reduced quickly, but the precaution involves 3</s></p><p xml:id="_scxQujx"><s xml:id="_TXGyFRH">Because decreases in danger are benefits, the upper curve falls whenever benefits exceed costs.</s><s xml:id="_Pa43Gmv">The curves assume, as do most decision models, that costs and benefits are similar enough to be combined algebraically.</s><s xml:id="_FFDYPsu">This may not be entirely realistic, and it is possible to design cost-benefit decision models that do not involve this assumption.</s><s xml:id="_AxDQxcg">persistent, extra work.</s><s xml:id="_uWFCZJZ">As shown, the precaution is attractive; with greater costs, however, the situation could be reversed.</s><s xml:id="_SSRYeZm">The use of dental floss and automobile seat belts are relevant examples.</s><s xml:id="_dH4cxQB">Panel d portrays a situation in which the benefits appear slowly and the initial cost is high but may decline as time passes.</s><s xml:id="_QnsZWXu">Life-style modifications like changing to a low-salt diet and quitting smoking exemplify this pattern.</s><s xml:id="_WP4Bfst">Even though the action is beneficial in the long run, the net result is unattractive for a considerable length of time.</s></p><p xml:id="_AZy9azj"><s xml:id="_Z8daPEX">Implicit in all panels of Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> is the idea that the risk remains constant if protective action is not taken.</s><s xml:id="_bDet7X6">Different patterns appear with risks that change with age (e.g., heart attacks) or that are cyclical (e.g., hurricanes).</s></p><p xml:id="_N5bN9g2"><s xml:id="_SnyuFbX">It is hoped that these figures demonstrate that the attractiveness of a precaution depends very strongly on the time period considered.</s><s xml:id="_mSM6kQf">Too often, prevention advocates look only at the long-term endpoint or at the time of greatest risk and fail to consider the costs and benefits in more immediate time periods.</s><s xml:id="_EzW8bEz">In such cases, it should not be surprising if the public fails to share the advocate's enthusiasm for the recommended action.</s></p><p xml:id="_Un9daCj"><s xml:id="_2MYvE4B">Although the diagrams make the issue of time dependency more obvious, they do not tell us how it should be taken into account.</s><s xml:id="_Kq7uWBt">We do know, however, that behavior is not just a function of immediate consequences.</s><s xml:id="_cRDdZZh">If it were, no one would take precautions when costs precede benefits, as in Panels b and d in Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_KZZZf3v">At least some of the time, people think into the future.</s></p><p xml:id="_vJDywD3"><s xml:id="_HTqTEnp">A more plausible hypothesis is that people differ in the extent to which they take long-term consequences into account.</s><s xml:id="_jSm9gjv">Part of the impact of time on the decision to act -Stage 4 in the present conceptual framework-might be described by the time horizon or time perspective of an individual <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(de Voider, 1979;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Svenson, 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">Wallace &amp; Rabin, 1960)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_2FzGCJX">Situational factors can also affect the salience of short-and long-term consequences.</s></p><p xml:id="_TQ92Rrx"><s xml:id="_GkyD9Uf">Even if people sometimes consider long-term effects, there is evidence that they weigh short-term consequences more heavily in making decisions <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(McNeil et al., 1978;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b85">Wright &amp; Weitz, 1977)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_ftU2YXj">To explain this phenomenon, writers have called upon the economics concept of discounting <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Christensen-Szalanski &amp; Northcraft, 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Svenson, 1984)</ref>, the animal studies notion of approach and avoidance gradients <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Ajzen, 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Svenson, 1984)</ref>, and the research on delay of gratification (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Mischel &amp; Grusec, 1967)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_VTGhwMj"><s xml:id="_ezxYejV">We do not yet know how the different patterns in Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> affect perceptions of risk and cost -or what increases in preventive behavior could be achieved by altering the temporal arrival of costs -but diagrams like those in Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> might aid researchers studying these questions.</s><s xml:id="_TXmaVVm">Such diagrams could also encourage prevention programs to give more attention to the barriers people face.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_2RsFCw4">Fundamental Elements in the Decision to Act</head><p xml:id="_wM2xAEs"><s xml:id="_qtyeRcg">The argument to this point has implicitly accepted the notion that beliefs about susceptibility, severity, effectiveness, and cost are the basic determinants of the decision to adopt a precaution.</s><s xml:id="_G66d4fd">There is abundant empirical evidence that they are important, but their centrality can be questioned.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_7hpd7xv">Hazard "seriousness."</head><p xml:id="_C4C34zt"><s xml:id="_ZkCQu4h">In real life, people often appear to acquire their notion of risk seriousness directly from acquaintances or from the media rather than deriving it from separate beliefs about susceptibility and severity.</s><s xml:id="_JAJheeQ">For example, many people are convinced that refined sugar is unhealthy-and act in accordance with this belief-but have no notion whatsoever of the diseases that might be caused, the likelihoods of these diseases, or their severities.</s><s xml:id="_HbbttPC">Clearly, people can be convinced that something is good or bad (risky or not risky) without having derived their opinions from separate beliefs about the probabilities and desirabilities of possible outcomes.</s></p><p xml:id="_BaTSCSW"><s xml:id="_674FUWr">Perhaps the driving force behind the adoption of precautions is not some algebraic function of likelihood and severity but a more global appraisal of the hazard suggested by such ill-defined terms as "seriousness," "threat," "concern," and "danger."</s><s xml:id="_jh26KdT">The empirical evidence suggests that beliefs about susceptibility and severity often contribute to perceptions of hazard seriousness, but important roles for other factors need to be recognized too.</s><s xml:id="_fGkKuU9">For example, messages often refer to the seriousness of a hazard without mentioning outcome likelihood or severity (e.g., "My cousin says coffee is awful for you").</s><s xml:id="_pK8MCjR">Variables that increase salience (vivid images and frequent reminders) or that heighten affect <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">(Rogers, 1983)</ref> might increase perceptions of seriousness.</s><s xml:id="_HF9kjYb">A growing literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">(Slovic, Fischhoff, &amp; Lichtenstein, 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b69">Vaughan, 1986)</ref> has identified numerous hazard attributes that influence perceptions of the risk of death presented by different technologies, chemicals, and activities.</s><s xml:id="_PSaU6Mq">It seems likely that these attributes also influence perceptions of personal risks.</s><s xml:id="_ryZ5YxE">Research on the notion of risk "seriousness" is needed to clarify the nature and usefulness of this intervening construct.</s></p><p xml:id="_wzAfQFc"><s xml:id="_jQrt63q">A theory that assumes beliefs about likelihood and severity are the only two variables determining perceptions of seriousness will be an inadequate predictor of preventive behavior in many situations.</s><s xml:id="_EQeeXxR">In perhaps the most careful study of natural hazards preparedness ever undertaken <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Kunreuther et al., 1978)</ref>, respondents' answers to a question about hazard "seriousness" made a large contribution to the prediction of their flood and earthquake insurance purchases beyond that provided by their views of hazard probabilities and potential losses.</s><s xml:id="_jA7Ktr8">In fact, researchers often find that respondents have great difficulty just answering questions about how likely they are to be harmed and how much harm they would experience, a hint that people do not necessarily base their decisions on such concepts.</s></p><p xml:id="_4aZjqyY"><s xml:id="_RDxaMag">Direct influences on the decision to act.</s><s xml:id="_8rwJvFC">Just as beliefs about seriousness do not have to be derived from conceptions of likelihood and severity, intentions to act need not be based on distinct ideas about risks and benefits.</s><s xml:id="_U6tQPM4">Information about risks, costs, and the effectiveness of precautions is often extremely difficult to obtain and understand.</s><s xml:id="_9wRRjJ2">In real life, people sometimes bypass the whole decision process and rely on the opinions and behavior of others to guide their own actions: "Is it really necessary to buy bottled water?</s><s xml:id="_33KerYE">It must be a good idea; all my neighbors do it."</s></p><p xml:id="_rTH9BPm"><s xml:id="_Q75eCqk">The direct influence of others, rather than a cost-benefit analysis, appears more likely when (a) issues are complex, (b) the requisite information is difficult to obtain, (c) the choices of others are apparent, (d) experience with the hazard is limited, and (e) the cost of the action is relatively small.</s><s xml:id="_FFMgqga">Of course, the media and personal contacts often provide information about hazard likelihood and severity and about precaution effectiveness, availability, and cost (cf.</s><s xml:id="_aRjwHM5"><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Kunreuther, Sanderson, &amp; Vetschera, 1985)</ref>, but it seems that these sources can affect decisions independent of their effects on the specific beliefs that are part of expectancy-value and expected-utility theories.</s></p><p xml:id="_5mjHEa9"><s xml:id="_Weax7nk">The role of emotions.</s><s xml:id="_EHGDjZn">Many effects of worry, fear, and "fear appeals" can be understood in terms of their impact on variables that have already been introduced (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Averill, 1987)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_cseCsNZ">For example, fear appeals provide information, focus attention on the hazard, encourage the individual to spend more time thinking about the situation, and make the threat vivid and personal, thereby reducing tendencies to deny vulnerability.</s><s xml:id="_43jprGU">However, emotions may sometimes have a direct impact on precautionary behavior, as when actions are motivated by the desire to reduce the aversive sensations produced by fear.</s><s xml:id="_m5TGbCf">If fear reduction or avoidance is a distinct motive, an appropriate model would need a separate, emotion-mediated path between appraisal and action <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Leventhal et al., 1983;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Rogers, 1983)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_kQrGTRn">Such a path does not appear to be important for most preventive measures because the threat is not imminent (prophylactic mastectomy may be an exception).</s><s xml:id="_SVGJBfC">However, emotions do seem important (as impediments) for actions (e.g., breast self-examination) that are intended to detect a serious, existing problem rather than to prevent it.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Ndshk83">Moving From Intentions to Action</head><p xml:id="_pm8MvEw"><s xml:id="_F4BEq76">Of course, deciding to act is not the same as acting.</s><s xml:id="_FuvygZD">Decision making may consider the future, but the success of behavior modification programs shows that actual behavior is much more influenced by short-term consequences (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">Slovic, Fischhoff, Lichtenstein, Corrigan, &amp; Combs, 1977)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_7UjKNFF">Prevention campaigns try hard to make the long-term benefits salient and often ignore the short-term costs.</s><s xml:id="_DpueQRM">Given these considerations, it is not surprising to discover that many individuals concerned about the future decide to adopt precautions but find it unexpectedly difficult to modify their behavior.</s></p><p xml:id="_RJ8mM9D"><s xml:id="_suCESvq">The last column of Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref> suggests that this situation is not uncommon.</s><s xml:id="_B7zmSRD">Many people claim to be convinced that a precaution is worthwhile, state that they intend to act, but admit that they have yet to carry through on their intentions.</s><s xml:id="_kbTMX6R">Some "plans" may just be attempts to create a good impression by giving a socially desirable answer.</s><s xml:id="_5kMuyyn">But many respondents seem genuinely convinced that they ought to act and seem frustrated that they have not been able to carry out plans they believe are worthwhile.</s><s xml:id="_K73eryH">Obviously, translating intentions into actions often involves overcoming a significant barrier <ref type="bibr">(Kuhl &amp; Beckmann, 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b73">Warshaw &amp; Davis, 1985)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_dsmeDCC">In fact, <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ajzen (1985)</ref> recently proposed a modification of the theory of reasoned action -the theory of planned behavior-to acknowledge the special problems faced in moving from a stage of decision to a stage of action.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_fDEVWyb">The Gap Between Intentions and Action</head><p xml:id="_mECdrMk"><s xml:id="_PRcnKV2">What factors intervene between the decision to act and the behavior itself?</s><s xml:id="_3ZA9hUg">All the people in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref> who said they intended to act were asked why they had not already carried out their plans.</s><s xml:id="_haFy3ec">The reasons they gave are categorized in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_g5RntCU">The three reasons in the first category imply that the action has a relatively low priority because the risk is rather small or the precaution is not particularly effective.</s><s xml:id="_MV6S2tH">The other reasons listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2</ref> do not contest the value of acting.</s><s xml:id="_fbTzHVD">Instead, they concern (a) situational obstacles (e.g., a student living on campus with little control over the cholesterol in dining hall menus), (b) problems in initiating the action (learning what should be done, remembering to do it, finding the time required), and (c) difficulties in maintaining precautions that prove arduous, time-consuming, or unpleasant.</s></p><p xml:id="_F2gKQkA"><s xml:id="_SyMeqY2">The reasons people have for not acting depend on the type of action involved.</s><s xml:id="_K9myNZA">The precautions listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref> are life-style changes that are relatively easy to begin but that require continued effort.</s><s xml:id="_XXsWW7N">If we studied precautions that require people to overcome a substantial barrier, as in Panel b in Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref>, we would find many more people mentioning situational obstacles.</s></p><p xml:id="_CMZh7aw"><s xml:id="_6m75zaD">The problem of maintaining preventive behaviors has received considerable attention.</s><s xml:id="_zN5FQgR">Discussions have emphasized the lack of concrete rewards Notes.</s><s xml:id="_wyY4C29">Reasons were given by people who said they plan to do one of the following: wear automobile seat belt, stop drinking coffee, floss teeth regularly, adopt low-salt diet, adopt low-cholesterol diet.</s><s xml:id="_Fnx2Ve7">Total of percentages exceeds 100 because more than one reason could be given.</s></p><p xml:id="_3mBnEKe"><s xml:id="_EnxkQYR">and the punishment of repeatedly experienced costs (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Slovic, Fischhoff, &amp; Lichtenstein, 1979)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_7PqFaJF">In fact, <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Robertson (1975)</ref> divided protective measures according to the number of repetitions required.</s><s xml:id="_vHnQ25X">He suggested that protection motivation is usually insufficient to sustain any precaution that requires continued effort.</s><s xml:id="_vnW9Wsa">Reflecting this point of view, many health promotion programs emphasize positive motivations (e.g., look good, feel good about yourself) rather than harm avoidance in their attempts to maintain life-style changes.</s></p><p xml:id="_BdfS2qp"><s xml:id="_DVCnG2N">Only recently have theoreticians begun to look carefully at the problem of initiating preventive measures (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Kuhl &amp; Beckmann, 1985)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_x3h7rZe">Major barriers like access to medical care and cost are well recognized <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Janz &amp; Becker, 1984)</ref>, but the less impressive, "minor" problems of locating the necessary information and finding the time and energy to carry out plans are omitted from most discussions.</s><s xml:id="_JjGea2D">A plausible hypothesis is that these "major" and "minor" barriers operate at different points in the precaution adoption process.</s><s xml:id="_ZwuvUMc">The more apparent, major obstacles may deter people from deciding to take the precaution, thus keeping people from ever reaching Stage 4. The less striking, minor problems may not alter decisions to act but may help to explain why good intentions do not get carried out.</s></p><p xml:id="_AJBgv3d"><s xml:id="_nCEN77A">we can think of each precaution as a project the executive is asked to consider.</s></p><p xml:id="_zUaaNNr"><s xml:id="_FunDmNj">In the simplest version of this analogy, the executive has unlimited resources.</s><s xml:id="_bbCKEbD">When an action is suggested, the executive considers its costs and likely benefits.</s><s xml:id="_DYq2GxR">Many proposals are discarded as bad ideas.</s><s xml:id="_a82PCrC">If the proposed plan looks attractive, it is carried out.</s><s xml:id="_jCNWA9S">This is the picture implied by models that look only at one risk, one precaution, and the net value of the cost-benefit equation.</s><s xml:id="_mchfKPf">Such models recognize no limits on the individual's ability to carry out every action that seems worthwhile.</s><s xml:id="_3Jmq68N"><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Fishbein and Ajzen (1975;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Ajzen &amp; Fishbein, 1980)</ref>, for example, have stated that no variables of importance intervene between the intention to act and the action itself.</s><s xml:id="_5F9G9Nq">(The theory of planned behavior, however, does not make such an assumption; <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ajzen, 1985.)</ref></s><s xml:id="_swufJHy">Because few people have unlimited resources to carry out their plans, a more realistic analogy is needed.</s><s xml:id="_mwFQNRH">In this second, more sophisticated version, the executive reviews proposals and keeps a list of all those that are approved.</s><s xml:id="_4sPENnp">Each approved plan is given a priority score based on its expected payoff.</s><s xml:id="_n6CUreU">As resources become available, the executive carries out the plans in order of priority.</s><s xml:id="_WG8uC2Q">This may seem like an effective response to the reality of limited resources, but such a rational, orderly, and rigid process should be considered suspect as a model for everyday behavior.</s></p><p xml:id="_C2VDahN"><s xml:id="_7yCa6x4">The final analogy for understanding preventive action places the busy executive at a messy desk.</s><s xml:id="_bAKcaFG">Proposals for new initiatives arrive every day, but there are also mundane responsibilities that must be carried out.</s><s xml:id="_688nzyW">A good idea may get approved, but constraints on time and resources make it impossible to carry it out immediately.</s><s xml:id="_DWG7n6s">Letters to be written, calls to make, reports to read, and plans to improve the business lie on the desk, waiting for an opportune moment.</s><s xml:id="_7MuBvqP">As new tasks and plans are placed on the desk, even high-priority items may be hidden from view by less important matters.</s><s xml:id="_9b6TQNn">When some free time becomes available, the executive looks at the desk and picks whatever in sight can be accomplished in the time available.</s><s xml:id="_jJB4RQJ">Even if a high-priority plan is lying in full view, it may be passed over in favor of some low-priority task that can be accomplished quickly.</s></p><p xml:id="_wvXnPDq"><s xml:id="_VUUzD9F">A call from the boss may remind the executive to look for a proposal that had been buried and to place it on top of the messy desk, but it may get buried again before it can be carried out.</s><s xml:id="_49EnMTa">A phone call from a colleague may bring to mind a project that the colleague had initiated.</s><s xml:id="_2J7MWND">The project did not have high priority, but our executive takes this opportunity to find it on the desk and discuss it while the colleague is still on the phone.</s></p><p xml:id="_TZBSmWX"><s xml:id="_zDX6d3j">If we can agree that life is more like this third picture than the previous two, we gain some insights into the types of factors that can intervene between intention and action.</s><s xml:id="_j95MS3G">Action is certainly a function of perceived costs and benefits; if the precaution does not offer more good than harm, the idea will go in the wastebasket, not on the desk.</s><s xml:id="_wgq7QV7">Once on the desk, it will have some sort of priority attached to it, a function of the net benefits expected.</s><s xml:id="_9Xntbcn">But the delay in carrying out the plan will depend on a variety of additional factors, including many that are not very dramatic and that are ignored in most theories.</s></p><p xml:id="_959xxQY"><s xml:id="_zNsfc5M">Action here will depend on the complexity of the precaution, on events that make information about the action available, and on reminders.</s><s xml:id="_kBvrghm">The American Lung Association, for example, gets a burst of calls about its Freedom From Smoking program every time advertisements appear on television.</s><s xml:id="_UZAVS84">It is very unlikely that the advertisements convince anyone to quit; instead, they show how information about quitting can be obtained easily.</s></p><p xml:id="_RW54u5Q"><s xml:id="_jPWawhK">The power of reminders in the right situation was demonstrated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Larson, Olsen, Cole, and Shortell (1979)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_k62vQ39">They found that a simple postcard reminder doubled the proportion of people obtaining influenza vaccine even though it did not alter subjects' beliefs about the risk or the benefits of vaccination.</s><s xml:id="_GDxarPM">The concept of prompts -familiar from behavior modification -is another illustration of this same phenomenon.</s><s xml:id="_ZAFADT7">Other potent reminders include intrusive mental images concerning unpleasant, past experiences and physical signs and sensations that, although not indicating an existing problem, make the possibility of that problem more real.</s><s xml:id="_2bhwBVM">For example, bleeding that an individual knows is caused by hemorrhoids may nonetheless stimulate attempts to prevent colorectal cancer.</s></p><p xml:id="_QenmHkY"><s xml:id="_78fy596">In the health belief model, prompts are called cues to action.</s><s xml:id="_Y2ebM6Y">However, because the rest of the health belief model implies that preventive actions are the result of a rational, cost-benefit decision, "cues to action" must seem a superfluous addition to many who use this theory.</s><s xml:id="_yQwkxyW">The concept has certainly received little research attention <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Janz &amp; Becker, 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b72">B. S. Wallston &amp; K. A. Wallston, 1984)</ref>, and no one has attempted to integrate the concept into the rest of the model.</s><s xml:id="_GgBJXQ6">It is hoped that the messy desk analogy demonstrates an important role for such cues.</s></p><p xml:id="_by8Ud2u"><s xml:id="_2RKZmhT">Unspectacular events can provide favorable opportunities to carry out plans.</s><s xml:id="_rXduuMe">A display of smoke detectors near a store's check-out counter, for example, may finally end months of delay.</s><s xml:id="_9nCrmtr">Retail store owners recognize how powerful availability and salience can be and charge manufacturers extra to place their products in favorable locations.</s><s xml:id="_y6CpqDh">The transition from intention to action is also influenced by the resources needed and by those available.</s><s xml:id="_EKWN7yX">Preexisting responsibilities and other new initiatives compete for these same resources. 4</s><s xml:id="_jdQSWkw">4 Previous sections have also implied that the decision to adopt a new precaution (Stage 4) is independent of other plans.</s><s xml:id="_XYgste8">In reality, our criteria for accepting new precautions are likely to reflect the time and resources available.</s><s xml:id="_2ATdVdy">When we feel overwhelmed by incomplete plans, we Finally, there are some situations in which people need to develop special skills before they can carry out their intentions successfully.</s><s xml:id="_7TPVKWS">Weight loss and breast self-examination are examples of protective measures that benefit from training.</s></p><p xml:id="_UK9pxwE"><s xml:id="_HTye7qE">The messy desk analogy thus incorporates a surprising number of interacting variables.</s><s xml:id="_jyJ9vx3">They are summarized under Stage 5 in Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>. Other variables that may impede the enactment of intentions are given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ajzen (1985)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_mCx4hJA"><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Leventhal (1970)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Leventhal et al. (1983)</ref> share with the present discussion an emphasis on the importance of providing detailed information to people to help them carry out recommended behaviors.</s><s xml:id="_rtXqjrb">In effect, Leventhal has suggested that, even when people are convinced that action is desirable and even when information about the precaution seems available, the effort required to get that information can be great enough to inhibit preventive action.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_dHGZXXS">Testable Predictions</head><p xml:id="_TQkChp9"><s xml:id="_BNDaGjX">The following paragraphs point out several testable aspects of the present argument, addressing only those features that are not already part of existing cost-benefit models.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_vyTzChQ">Consistency Among Stages</head><p xml:id="_UvMBXYp"><s xml:id="_74xEUz4">If people in one stage agree with the statements that define all previous stages, the statements should form a Guttman scale.</s><s xml:id="_24XSQMU">Using data from the sample of college students described earlier, Guttman scale analysis was carried out.</s><s xml:id="_fJJ7BVf">One Guttman scale included risk-susceptibility stages (Stages 2 and 3) and the decision to act (Stage 4).</s><s xml:id="_edrQN28">(Stage 1 risk-susceptibility questions were not asked because all the hazards studied were well known.)</s><s xml:id="_4SeJXUf">A second scale included perceived-effectiveness stages (Stages 1, 2, and 3) and the decision to act.</s><s xml:id="_DbgGdTT">The coefficients of reproducibility and scalability in Table <ref type="table">3</ref> are quite high, showing that the statements do form Guttman scales.</s><s xml:id="_MzTZkbv">Although the consistency observed here may seem obvious, there are several plausible alternatives that would lead to different predictions.</s><s xml:id="_Mm9QRrP">For example, if preventive behavior frequently followed a "better safe than sorry" philosophy, people might decide to take a precaution before being convinced that they were personally at risk.</s><s xml:id="_3JZpXKz">Furthermore, if the decisions to take the actions indicated did not reflect self-protection motivation, there will be more reluctant to agree to new projects.</s><s xml:id="_bgfjbkr">An expert's advice to adopt a particular precaution may seem like a good idea when only one risk and one precaution are considered, but in the context of a person's life, it may represent an unwise use of scarce resources.</s></p><p xml:id="_pQajfWS"><s xml:id="_fwWpg5v">TABLE 3 Guttman Scale Measures of Progress Toward Action (Coefficents of Reproducibility/Scalability) Risk Precaution Risk Scale Precaution Scale High blood pressure Low-salt diet" .95/.85 .96/.81 Heart attack Low-cholesterol diet b .91/.74 .94A77</s><s xml:id="_P3UjaWr">Coffee consumption -c .96/.87 -Automobile injury Seat belt use d .97/.88 .96/.81 Notes.</s><s xml:id="_CuV97P9">Guttman risk scales were based on questions tapping susceptibility (Stages 2 and 3) and the decision to act (Stage 4), except that the scale for coffee also included Stage 1. Guttman precaution scales were based on questions referring to precautions (Stages 1,2, and 3) and Stage 4 (decision to act). a n = 93.</s><s xml:id="_ZXspaBd">b n = 118.</s><s xml:id="_Uf9Vtwh">c n = 113.</s><s xml:id="_Ee4MrsW">d n = 53.</s></p><p xml:id="_HuSAmhU"><s xml:id="_Y2B654F">would be no necessary relationship between perceived susceptibility or perceived effectiveness and plans to act.</s><s xml:id="_egPzcHg">In neither of these cases would the data fit Guttman scales.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_fncBfyY">Determinants of Movement From Stage to Stage</head><p xml:id="_WGpdPzE"><s xml:id="_weUjVU6">According to the ideas presented here, the type of intervention most effective in moving individuals from one stage to the next, thereby promoting protective action, depends on the stage the individual is at.</s><s xml:id="_VjRUG23">Figures <ref type="figure">1</ref> and <ref type="figure">2</ref> list major considerations for reaching each stage.</s><s xml:id="_HwmsYUB">Thus, implicit in these figures are many separate hypotheses.</s><s xml:id="_4kX9drR">All the hypotheses take the form that interventions including one of the variables listed will be more effective in moving people to subsequent stages than interventions that lack this ingredient.</s><s xml:id="_rkEYYxd">In nonexperimental research, the hypotheses would suggest that path models or regression analyses will be improved by adding these variables.</s><s xml:id="_VfGSNK8">Note that these variables are assumed to influence the precaution adoption process independently of the specific beliefs that are already part of cost-benefit models.</s><s xml:id="_X7qafXn">For example, the correlation between a measure of preventive action and a measure of perceived seriousness (one based on questions referring to "seriousness," "danger," and "concern") should be positive and significant even after controlling for judgments of likelihood and severity.</s></p><p xml:id="_9T2RK35"><s xml:id="_v3v8jnm">Among the noncost-benefit factors emphasized here are the actions and statements of friends and neighbors, the length of time until the risk becomes serious, small differences in the effort required to carry out a precaution, and the number of repetitions of the protective action required.</s><s xml:id="_zEFKzJs">For example, according to the discussion of "minor" barriers in a previous section, one would predict that the time it takes to activate a burglar alarm will not play an important role in the purchase decision as long as that time is relatively short.</s><s xml:id="_sRTVM7E">But if the alarm must be activated each time the person leaves home, a difference between 5 sec and 30 sec can determine whether it falls into disuse.</s></p><p xml:id="_Dy29r6x"><s xml:id="_9SqXpH8">Theoretical models normally ignore the salience and vividness of risks, costs, and benefits.</s><s xml:id="_3VgUndR">Increased home ventilation is a precaution against radon that has a relatively low initial cost but that leads to long-term increases in fuel bills.</s><s xml:id="_M33qCc3">Messages that alter the salience of the initial versus the long-term costs should influence decisions about this strategy even if they leave estimates of these costs unchanged.</s></p><p xml:id="_9gYU2bY"><s xml:id="_rNADrqZ">Research referring to some of the factors listed in Figures <ref type="figure">1</ref> and <ref type="figure">2</ref> was mentioned as the factors were introduced; others remain to be tested.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_baWhp5T">Interest in Information</head><p xml:id="_rqpp4fb"><s xml:id="_9pz5WKK">Taking a precaution almost always entails some cost.</s><s xml:id="_C2aqqpH">People who have decided to take a precaution but who have not yet acted should be particularly interested in information that could help them decrease the cost, maximize their benefits by choosing the best precaution, or further clarify the need for action.</s><s xml:id="_fyaNhTs">A similar prediction was made by <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Janis and</ref><ref type="bibr">Mann (1976, 1977)</ref>, who suggested that people in a stage they call "vigilance" will be especially active information seekers.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_hcgSxkn">Applications</head><p xml:id="_GRr6Zsr"><s xml:id="_Uc3bnNH">Most of the testable aspects of this conceptual framework also provide ideas for interventions.</s><s xml:id="_5EUF7Kx">The notion that people pass through qualitatively different stages as they move toward preventive action suggests that an effective program in one situation may be inappropriate in another.</s><s xml:id="_zQuBZCT">Successful interventions will not thoughtlessly repeat warnings about the seriousness of the hazard or repeatedly remind listeners about the benefits of acting but will be tailored to the beliefs of the audience.</s><s xml:id="_TzEpSuB">For example, a woman who believes that the absence of heart disease in her family excludes her from risk will not respond to information about the benefits of cardiovascular exercise.</s><s xml:id="_q6FcMBr">A man whose main difficulty is understanding the difference between a photoelectric smoke detector and an ionization detector does not need statistics on the number of lives lost in fires each year.</s></p><p xml:id="_Up3rtGF"><s xml:id="_3rwJre6">The idea of matching the communication to the audience follows naturally from a stage model.</s><s xml:id="_wCxrwXP">But it is not an obvious result of a decision equation perspective.</s><s xml:id="_bj9p8Tw">In an algebraic decision model, only the total value of the equation counts and an increase in one term is just as likely to promote action as an increase in another.</s><s xml:id="_xaRbN4n">Unfortunately, it is rare for a prevention program to start by examining the thoughts of the intended audience.</s><s xml:id="_fc5affx">Even carefully designed interventions (particularly those testing behavior modification procedures; e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Geller, 1983;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Lund &amp; Kegeles, 1984)</ref> seldom make an attempt to determine what people already believe.</s><s xml:id="_m6HQjSA">Specific ingredients that may help tailor prevention programs to the needs of people at each stage in the precaution adoption process can be derived from Figures <ref type="figure">1</ref> and <ref type="figure">2</ref>. If the intended audience is spread over a range of stages, multiple messages focusing on different factors may be needed.</s><s xml:id="_j4KcUeX">When a program to encourage action has been in effect for a while, the audience may have progressed to a different stage, and a new message may be needed to get the best results.</s></p><p xml:id="_g8wyu6d"><s xml:id="_ZeXFxJa">The view of preventive behavior presented in this article suggests that factors other than beliefs about costs and benefits can be crucial.</s><s xml:id="_ztB664V">Communications that increase the salience of risks or benefits or that simply remind people to take precautions may be quite effective in appropriate circumstances.</s><s xml:id="_4v327Vq">In some instances, reducing "minor" obstacles by providing information about how to act and about opportunities that make the precaution more convenient should be the focus of the prevention program.</s></p><p xml:id="_TDhZntp"><s xml:id="_JcjXcXj">Finally, it is worth repeating that people in earlier stages of hazard responses will be less attentive to information about the hazard and protective measures.</s><s xml:id="_xBDNph7">For such an audience, more ambitious communication programs will be needed.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_ppHSZZ8">CONCLUSION</head><p xml:id="_a36EQqn"><s xml:id="_W88uz8P">The present argument applies to a wide range of risk situations, but it does have limits.</s><s xml:id="_jysnPCE">This discussion is mainly relevant to relatively complex, nonhabitual behaviors for which the present emphasis on cognitive issues is justified.</s><s xml:id="_tNaM75N">The only motivation that has been considered is self-protection.</s><s xml:id="_kNEHfSB">Microtheories will often be needed to deal adequately with the additional motives involved in specfic hazard situations <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Cleary, 1987)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_mPpCtbh"><s xml:id="_qaan2sP">The analysis has also assumed that precautions are available.</s><s xml:id="_dqXJJ3w">When effective precautions do not exist or when the behaviors advocated are designed to detect already existing problems, fear or anger will be more important elements.</s><s xml:id="_VuTKSGF">They can produce ego-defensive reactions and behavioral responses addressed more to the negative emotions being experienced than to the threat itself <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Janis, 1967;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Janis &amp; Mann, 1976</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">, 1977;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Lazarus, 1966;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Leventhal, 1970;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Leventhal et al., 1983)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_9k4uMzB">Such situations are not adequately described by the framework presented here.</s></p><p xml:id="_C4uhuaB"><s xml:id="_fh2zDX5">The principal goal of this article has been to offer a comprehensive view of the precaution adoption process.</s><s xml:id="_Nc4vnVR">It has not offered new equations to replace the models that have been criticized; that would be premature.</s><s xml:id="_Uj6k98s">Nevertheless, the ideas presented here about such issues as stages of belief, This document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers.</s></p><p xml:id="_UDUYfUj"><s xml:id="_7pdPGBT">This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.</s></p><p xml:id="_4yZDAUu"><s xml:id="_r4a7A2B">cues to action, time, and multiple life demands have immediate implications for prevention campaigns and for the development of more detailed models.</s><s xml:id="_j4fqDKj">It is hoped that these ideas will help us move toward a theory of preventive behavior that can accommodate all its complexities.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>TABLE 1 Potential</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s xml:id="_ZkU4xua">Barriers to the Adoption of PrecautionsNotes.</s><s xml:id="_vK4Sm7k">Only subjects who have not taken the indicated precaution are included in this table.</s><s xml:id="_QRbeCwg">Entries give the percentage of respondents agreeing with the statement indicated, n = 132 to 162, depending on item.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">THE PRECAUTION ADOPTION PROCESS</cell><cell>363</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Accepting</cell><cell>Acknowledging</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Personal</cell><cell>Personal</cell><cell>Deciding</cell></row><row><cell>Risk/Precaution</cell><cell>Susceptibility*</cell><cell>Efficacy"</cell><cell>to Acf</cell></row><row><cell>Heart attack/low-cholesterol diet Injury in auto accident/wear seat belt</cell><cell>91.1</cell><cell>78.3 94.4</cell><cell>22.5 38.7</cell></row><row><cell>High blood pressure/low-salt diet</cell><cell>53.8</cell><cell>81.0</cell><cell>17.6</cell></row><row><cell>Health problem from coffee drinking/reduce</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>coffee consumption</cell><cell>41.6</cell><cell>_d</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Drinking (alcohol) problem/reduce drinking</cell><cell>20.3</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>11.5</cell></row><row><cell>Tooth decay/not eating sweets</cell><cell></cell><cell>84.2</cell><cell>18.5</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>TABLE 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_H4mPqJQ"><s xml:id="_aB5KrNV">Reasons for Not Carrying Out Intentions to Act</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">THE PRECAUTION ADOPTION PROCESS</cell><cell>375</cell></row><row><cell>General Topic and Subcategories</cell><cell>Percentage</cell><cell>n</cell></row><row><cell>Low need for action</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Risk is low</cell><cell>9.4</cell><cell>11</cell></row><row><cell>Precaution is risky/not very beneficial</cell><cell>1.7</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>Low priority/not motivated/not concerned</cell><cell>18.8</cell><cell>22</cell></row><row><cell>Action unavailable or circumstances interfere</cell><cell>14.5</cell><cell>17</cell></row><row><cell>Action proves difficult to initiate</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Lack of information</cell><cell>4.3</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>Forget</cell><cell>15.4</cell><cell>18</cell></row><row><cell>Not habitual</cell><cell>4.3</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>Action proves burdensome</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Action unpleasant/uncomfortable</cell><cell>17.9</cell><cell>21</cell></row><row><cell>Enjoy present behavior/hard to give up</cell><cell>10.3</cell><cell>12</cell></row><row><cell>Action difficult/time-consuming</cell><cell>21.4</cell><cell>25</cell></row><row><cell>Other</cell><cell>12.8</cell><cell>15</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p xml:id="_V94XhVA"><s xml:id="_SPD65dF">This document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers.This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.</s></p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head xml:id="_EG3yaUr">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p xml:id="_AfjbVJF"><s xml:id="_6ygnPXq">I am grateful for the helpful suggestions of <rs type="person">Paul Cleary</rs>, <rs type="person">Howard Kunreuther</rs>, <rs type="person">Baruch Fischhoff</rs>, <rs type="person">Thomas Rudel</rs>, <rs type="person">Robert Woolfolk</rs>, <rs type="person">Carol Weinstein</rs>, and reviewers during the preparation of this article and for the hospitality of <rs type="person">Joseph Matarazzo</rs> and the <rs type="institution">Department of Medical Psychology of the Oregon Health Sciences University</rs>, where this project was begun.</s></p></div>
			</div>			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_JZjx9Vt">From intentions to actions: A theory of planned behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ajzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-3-642-69746-3_2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_YpmB9dA">Action control: From cognition to behavior</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kuhl</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Beckmann</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin, Federal Republic of Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="40" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ajzen, I. (1985). From intentions to actions: A theory of planned behavior. In J. Kuhl &amp; J. Beckmann (Eds.), Action control: From cognition to behavior (pp. 11-40). Berlin, Federal Republic of Germany: Springer-Verlag.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_3NUSSEt">Understanding attitudes and predicting behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ajzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fishbein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ajzen, I., &amp; Fishbein, M. (1980). Understanding attitudes and predicting behavior. Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice-Hall.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qvEbmuA">The role of emotion and psychological defense in self-protective behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Averill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1017/cbo9780511527760.005</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_dSEYMAd">Taking care: Understanding and encouraging selfprotective behavior</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Weinstein</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="54" to="78" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Averill, J. R. (1987). The role of emotion and psychological defense in self-protective behavior. In N. D. Weinstein (Ed.), Taking care: Understanding and encouraging self- protective behavior (pp. 54-78). New York: Cambridge University Press.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Dknxxmx">Self-efficacy: Toward a unifying theory of behavioral change</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bandura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037//0033-295x.84.2.191</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_2wAJYnb">Psychological Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="215" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bandura, A. (1977). Self-efficacy: Toward a unifying theory of behavioral change. Psycho- logical Review, 84, 191-215.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_6WMx6Zu">Subjected expected utility and the prediction of birth planning decision</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Beach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Townes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0030-5073(79)90012-6</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_VD3Rcte">Organizational Behavior and Human Performance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Beach, L. R., Campbell, F. L., &amp; Townes, B. D. (1979). Subjected expected utility and the prediction of birth planning decision. Organizational Behavior and Human Performance, 24, 18-28.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_EGNaSyB">A contingency model for the selection of decision strategies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Beach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_EsGvb6r">Academy of Management Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="439" to="449" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Beach, L. R., &amp; Mitchell, T. R. (1978). A contingency model for the selection of decision strategies. Academy of Management Review, 3, 439-449.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_HvbbepZ">The health belief model and personal health behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/109019817400200407</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_hd52fze">Health Education Monographs</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Becker, M. H. (Ed.). (1974). The health belief model and personal health behavior. Health Education Monographs, 2(4).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_4HcPv7G">Models of health-related behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Maiman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_KtvkE7x">Handbook of health, health care, and the health professions</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mechanic</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Free Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="539" to="568" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Becker, M. H., &amp; Maiman, L. A. (1983). Models of health-related behavior: In D. Mechanic (Ed.), Handbook of health, health care, and the health professions (pp. 539-568). New York: Free Press.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_tPNkggq">Patient compliance behavior: The effect of time on patients&apos; values of treatment regimens</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J J</forename><surname>Christensen-Szalanski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Northcraft</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_XYu7SVq">Social Science and Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="273" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Christensen-Szalanski, J. J. J., &amp; Northcraft, G. B. (1985). Patient compliance behavior: The effect of time on patients&apos; values of treatment regimens. Social Science and Medicine, 21, 263-273.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_TJCgHjQ">Why people take precautions against health risks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Cleary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1017/cbo9780511527760.009</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_7Sw35f6">Taking care: Understanding and encouraging self-protective behavior</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Weinstein</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="149" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Cleary, P. (1987). Why people take precautions against health risks. In N. D. Weinstein (Ed.), Taking care: Understanding and encouraging self-protective behavior (pp. 119-149). New York: Cambridge University Press.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_FgsbJk8">Psychology in health risk messages to workers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Colligan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Berger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_eQeQC2U">Journal of Occupational Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="543" to="551" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Cohen, A., Colligan, M. J., &amp; Berger, P. (1985). Psychology in health risk messages to workers. Journal of Occupational Medicine, 27, 543-551.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_8wKAeQr">Time orientation: A review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>De Voider</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_hwwRbRd">Psychologie Beligique</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="79" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">de Voider, M. (1979). Time orientation: A review. Psychologie Beligique, 19, 61-79.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_wt3gNxZ">Self-efficacy and the stages of self-change of smoking</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Diclemente</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Prochaska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gibertini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/bf01204849</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_6EE6RyD">Cognitive Therapy and Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="181" to="200" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">DiClemente, C. D., Prochaska, J. O., &amp; Gibertini, M. (1985). Self-efficacy and the stages of self-change of smoking. Cognitive Therapy and Research, 9, 181-200.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_dZvsxCG">Families in disaster: Reactions and relatives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Drabek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Boggs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_X8GTT2d">Journal of Marriage and the Family</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="443" to="451" />
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Drabek, T., &amp; Boggs, K. (1968). Families in disaster: Reactions and relatives. Journal of Marriage and the Family, 30, 443-451.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_wmRbhSd">Lateral asymmetry of personal optimism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Drake</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0092-6566(84)90008-4</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_dMa8UT8">Journal of Research in Personality</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="497" to="507" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Drake, R. (1984). Lateral asymmetry of personal optimism. Journal of Research in Person- ality, 18, 497-507.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_KrEXmzt">The theory of decision making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_G8vGPfw">Psychological Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="380" to="417" />
			<date type="published" when="1954">1954</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Edwards, W. (1954). The theory of decision making. Psychological Bulletin, 51, 380-417.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Festinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_bAT4QAG">A theory of cognitive dissonance</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Stanford, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Stanford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1957">1957</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Festinger, L. (1957). A theory of cognitive dissonance. Stanford, CA: Stanford University Press.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_H3Srfq6">The experienced utility of expected utility approaches</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Fischhoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Goitein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shapira</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_YFdc9sA">Expectations and actions: Expectancy-value models in psychology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Feather</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Hillsdale, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Inc</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="315" to="339" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Fischhoff, B., Goitein, B., &amp; Shapira, Z. (1982). The experienced utility of expected utility approaches. In N. T. Feather (Ed.), Expectations and actions: Expectancy-value models in psychology (pp. 315-339). Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Inc.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_U7AZQB6">A theory of reasoned action: Some applications and implications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fishbein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/1520-6807(196707)4:3&lt;286::aid-pits2310040321&gt;3.0.co;2-k</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_gVYGFe6">Nebraska Symposium on Motivation</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Howse</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Lincoln</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="110" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Fishbein, M. (1980). A theory of reasoned action: Some applications and implications. In H. E. Howse, Jr. (Ed.), Nebraska Symposium on Motivation (Vol. 27, pp. 65-110). Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_VmGtsVa">Belief, attitude, intention and behavior: An introduction to theory and research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fishbein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ajzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Reading, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Fishbein, M., &amp; Ajzen, I. (1975). Belief, attitude, intention and behavior: An introduction to theory and research. Reading, MA: Addison-Wesley.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_H5cWxSm">Recent research on selective exposure to information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Frey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s" xml:id="_wg2wDGY">Advances in experimental social psychology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Berkowitz</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="79" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
			<publisher>Academic</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Frey, D. (1986). Recent research on selective exposure to information. In L. Berkowitz (Ed.), Advances in experimental social psychology (Vol. 19, pp. 41-79). New York: Academic.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_2EEWWmd">Rewarding safety belt usage at an industrial setting: Tests of treatment generality and response maintenance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Geller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_gHmgQEN">Journal of Applied Behavior Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="189" to="202" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Geller, E. S. (1983). Rewarding safety belt usage at an industrial setting: Tests of treatment generality and response maintenance. Journal of Applied Behavior Analysis, 16, 189-202.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_JrjHf9S">Effects of fear arousal on attitude change: Recent developments in theory and experimental research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Janis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_s8Md2gY">Advances in experimental social psychology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Berkowitz</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1967">1967</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="166" to="224" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Janis, I. L. (1967). Effects of fear arousal on attitude change: Recent developments in theory and experimental research. In L. Berkowitz (Ed.), Advances in experimental social psychology (Vol. 4, pp. 166-224). New York: Academic.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_3HXACvm">Coping with decisional conflict</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Janis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Mann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ZBtKDQF">American Scientist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="657" to="667" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Janis, I. L., &amp; Mann, L. (1976). Coping with decisional conflict. American Scientist, 64, 657-667.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Janis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Mann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_j4GQh3U">Decision making: A psychological analysis of conflict choice, and commitment</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Free Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Janis, I. L., &amp; Mann, L. (1977). Decision making: A psychological analysis of conflict choice, and commitment. New York: Free Press.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_pETdh5H">The health belief model: A decade later</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Janz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/109019818401100101</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_6sMYAzB">Health Education Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Janz, N. K., &amp; Becker, M. H. (1984). The health belief model: A decade later. Health Education Quarterly, 11(1), 1-47.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_z6DdHnK">Prospect theory: An analysis of decision under risk</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kahneman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tversky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/1914185</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_n98MXsB">Econometrica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="291" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kahneman, D., &amp; Tversky, A. (1979). Prospect theory: An analysis of decision under risk. Econometrica, 47, 263-291.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_JYFUu8b">Knowing what to do: On the epistemology of actions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kruglanski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Klar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-3-642-69746-3_3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_pJ6GemT">Action control: From cognition to behavior</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kuhl</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Beckmann</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin, Federal Republic of Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="60" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kruglanski, A. W., &amp; Klar, Y. (1985). Knowing what to do: On the epistemology of actions. In J. Kuhl &amp; J. Beckmann (Eds.), Action control: From cognition to behavior (pp. 41-60). Berlin, Federal Republic of Germany: Springer-Verlag.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_fYBseUU">The expectancy-value approach within the theory of social motivation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kuhl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4324/9781003150879-6</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_qeVzyPY">Expectations and actions: Expectancy-value models in psychology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="middle">N T</forename><surname>Critique. In</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Feather</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Hillsdale, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Inc</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Elaborations, extensions</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kuhl, J. (1982). The expectancy-value approach within the theory of social motivation. Elaborations, extensions, critique. In N. T. Feather (Ed.), Expectations and actions: Expectancy-value models in psychology. Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Inc.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_FYNCQdp">Volitional mediators of cognitive-behavior consistency: Self-regulatory processes and action versus state orientation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kuhl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_Fw52xxC">Action control: From cognition to behavior</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kuhl</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Beckmann</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin, Federal Republic of Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="128" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kuhl, J. (1985). Volitional mediators of cognitive-behavior consistency: Self-regulatory processes and action versus state orientation. In J. Kuhl &amp; J. Beckmann (Eds.), Action control: From cognition to behavior (pp. 101-128). Berlin, Federal Republic of Germany: Springer-Verlag.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_Ce4JeE9">Action control: From cognition to behavior</title>
		<editor>Kuhl, J., &amp; Beckmann, J.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Berlin, Federal Republic of Germany</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kuhl, J., &amp; Beckmann, J. (Eds.). (1985). Action control: From cognition to behavior. Berlin, Federal Republic of Germany: Springer-Verlag.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_wfXFhtt">Health status, perceptions of risk, and prevention interest for health and nonhealth problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kulik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">I M</forename><surname>Mahler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_heaMJvh">Health Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kulik, J. A., &amp; Mahler, H. I. M. (1987). Health status, perceptions of risk, and prevention interest for health and nonhealth problems. Health Psychology, 6, 15-27.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_5gP6g4T">Limited knowledge and insurance protection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kunreuther</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1017/bpp.2018.26</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_sjVPbfb">Public Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="261" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kunreuther, H. (1976). Limited knowledge and insurance protection. Public Policy, 24, 227-261.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_ZzNuTeD">Disaster insurance protection: Public policy lessons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kunreuther</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ginsberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sagi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Slovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Borkan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Katz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/3135009</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kunreuther, H., Ginsberg, R., Miller, L., Sagi, P., Slovic, P., Borkan, B., &amp; Katz, N. (1978). Disaster insurance protection: Public policy lessons. New York: Wiley.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_grAy4us">A behavioral model of the adoption of protective activities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kunreuther</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Sanderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Vetschera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_qnjfgv2">Journal of Economic Behavior and Organization</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kunreuther, H., Sanderson, W., &amp; Vetschera, R. (1985). A behavioral model of the adoption of protective activities. Journal of Economic Behavior and Organization, 6, 1-15.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_9YJaSaQ">The mindlessness of ostensibly thoughtful action: The role of &quot;placebic&quot; information in interpersonal interaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Langer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Blank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Chanowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_tAz3MmC">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="635" to="642" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Langer, E., Blank, A., &amp; Chanowitz, B. (1978). The mindlessness of ostensibly thoughtful action: The role of &quot;placebic&quot; information in interpersonal interaction. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 36, 635-642.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_9rk7f9N">The relationship of health beliefs and a postcard reminder to influenza vaccination</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Larson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Olsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Cole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shortell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/00005650-198206000-00010</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ZGMFbae">Journal of Family Practice</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1207" to="1211" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Larson, E. B., Olsen, E., Cole, W., &amp; Shortell, S. (1979). The relationship of health beliefs and a postcard reminder to influenza vaccination. Journal of Family Practice, 8, 1207-1211.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lazarus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_HzNDy9p">Psychological stress and the coping process</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1966">1966</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lazarus, R. S. (1966). Psychological stress and the coping process. New York: McGraw-Hill.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qTGHeGC">Findings and theory in the study of fear communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Leventhal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0065-2601(08)60091-x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_NxXCwZ4">Advances in experimental social psychology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Berkowitz</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1970">1970</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="186" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Leventhal, H. (1970). Findings and theory in the study of fear communications. In L. Berkowitz (Ed.), Advances in experimental social psychology (Vol. 5, pp. 119-186). New York: Academic.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_BapjfNS">The common sense representation of illness danger</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Leventhal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Nerenz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s" xml:id="_ejDSV9M">Medical psychology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rachman</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
			<publisher>Pergamon</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Leventhal, H., Meyer, D., &amp; Nerenz, D. (1980). The common sense representation of illness danger. In S. Rachman (Ed.), Medical psychology (Vol. 2, pp. 7-30). New York: Pergamon.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_kRzrXBw">The impact of communications on the self-regulation of health beliefs, decisions, and behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Leventhal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Safer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Panagis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Trs2pd2">Health Education Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Leventhal, H., Safer, M., &amp; Panagis, F. D. (1983). The impact of communications on the self-regulation of health beliefs, decisions, and behavior. Health Education Quarterly, 70(1), 3-29.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_yfE27CP">Rewards and adolescent health behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Lund</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kegeles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/0278-6133.3.4.351</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_7eunJFM">Health Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="351" to="369" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lund, A. K., &amp; Kegeles, S. S. (1984). Rewards and adolescent health behavior. Health Psychology, 3, 351-369.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_CZVdfP8">Protection motivation and self-efficacy: A revised theory of fear appeals and attitude change</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Maddux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_6SS3SUK">Journal of Experimental Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="469" to="479" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Maddux, J. E., &amp; Rogers, R. W. (1983). Protection motivation and self-efficacy: A revised theory of fear appeals and attitude change. Journal of Experimental Social Psychology, 19, 469-479.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_f7sAsaj">The health belief model: Origins and correlates in psychological theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Maiman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_p36YAGn">Health Education Monographs</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="336" to="353" />
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Maiman, L. A., &amp; Becker, M. H. (1974). The health belief model: Origins and correlates in psychological theory. Health Education Monographs, 2, 336-353.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_umGPSzJ">The communication-persuasion model and health-risk labeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mcguire</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_aHttTwE">Product labeling and health risks (Banbury Report</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Mazis</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Barofsky</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cold Spring Harbor, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cold Spring Laboratory</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="122" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">McGuire, W. J. (1980). The communication-persuasion model and health-risk labeling. In L. A. Morris, M. B. Mazis, &amp; I. Barofsky (Eds.), Product labeling and health risks (Banbury Report No. 6, pp. 99-122). Cold Spring Harbor, NY: Cold Spring Laboratory.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_W5UaBpY">Fallacy of the five-year survival rate</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mcneil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Weichselbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Pauker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1056/nejm197812212992506</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_HAsHgzT">New England Journal of Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">229</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1397" to="1401" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">McNeil, B. J., Weichselbaum, R., &amp; Pauker, S. G. (1978). Fallacy of the five-year survival rate. New England Journal of Medicine, 229, 1397-1401.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_CXVxm69">Waiting for rewards and punishments: Effects of time and probability on choice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Mischel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Grusec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/h0024180</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_3W8DCFJ">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="31" />
			<date type="published" when="1967">1967</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mischel, W., &amp; Grusec, J. (1967). Waiting for rewards and punishments: Effects of time and probability on choice. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 5, 24-31.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_kPzfq9u">Human inference: Strategies and shortcomings of social judgment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Nisbett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nisbett, R., &amp; Ross, L. (1980). Human inference: Strategies and shortcomings of social judgment. Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice-Hall.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_cg5yCgB">A comparison of three social-psychological models of attitudes and behavioral plans: Prediction of contraceptive behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Pagel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Davidson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_fhhxX3P">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="517" to="533" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Pagel, M. D., &amp; Davidson, A. R. (1984). A comparison of three social-psychological models of attitudes and behavioral plans: Prediction of contraceptive behavior. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 47, 517-533.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_fvmjgPQ">Contingent decision behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Payne</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_r65TGSt">Psychological Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="382" to="402" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Payne, J. W. (1982). Contingent decision behavior. Psychological Bulletin, 92, 382-402.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_TgWPFpD">Self-other judgments and perceived vulnerability to victimization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Perloff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Fetzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_eu7rKN4">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="502" to="511" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Perloff, L. S., &amp; Fetzer, B. K. (1986). Self-other judgments and perceived vulnerability to victimization. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 50, 502-511.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Perry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Lindell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Greene</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_2zCgrgR">Evacuation planning in emergency management</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Lexington, MA; Lexington</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Perry, R. W., Lindell, M. K., &amp; Greene, M. R. (1981). Evacuation planning in emergency management. Lexington, MA: Lexington.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Perry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Mushkatel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_SXXRwky">Disaster management: Warning response and community relocation</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Westport, CT</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Quorum</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Perry, R. W., &amp; Mushkatel, A. H. (1984). Disaster management: Warning response and community relocation. Westport, CT: Quorum.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_D37rmqT">Behavioral research and strategies in public health: A demur</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Robertson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_mgwN7RJ">Social Science and Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="165" to="170" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Robertson, L. S. (1975). Behavioral research and strategies in public health: A demur. Social Science and Medicine, 9, 165-170.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_KvAeVkf">A protection motivation theory of fear appeals and attitude change</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/00223980.1975.9915803</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_eAkwP3q">Journal of Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="114" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rogers, R. W. (1975). A protection motivation theory of fear appeals and attitude change. Journal of Psychology, 91, 93-114.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_cT3cDqD">Cognitive and psychological processes in fear appeals and attitude change: A revised theory of protection motivation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_CsFGUgQ">Social psychophysiology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Cacioppo</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Petty</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Guilford</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="153" to="176" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rogers, R. W. (1983). Cognitive and psychological processes in fear appeals and attitude change: A revised theory of protection motivation. In J. T. Cacioppo &amp; R. E. Petty (Eds.), Social psychophysiology (pp. 153-176). New York: Guilford.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_7KA4G7b">Fear appeals and attitude change: Effects of a threat&apos;s noxiousness, probability of occurrence, and the efficacy of coping responses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mewborn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_8PXGd2H">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="54" to="61" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rogers, R. W., &amp; Mewborn, C. R. (1976). Fear appeals and attitude change: Effects of a threat&apos;s noxiousness, probability of occurrence, and the efficacy of coping responses. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 34, 54-61.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_H6TaddB">Historical origins of the health belief model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rosenstock</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ZHgsxhS">Health Education Monographs</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="328" to="335" />
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rosenstock, I. M. (1974). Historical origins of the health belief model. Health Education Monographs, 2, 328-335.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_XCZzN45">Determinants of three stages of delay in seeking care at a medical clinic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Safer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Tharps</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Jackson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Leventhal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_z8CAWvg">Medical Care</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Safer, M. A., Tharps, Q., Jackson, T., &amp; Leventhal, H. (1979). Determinants of three stages of delay in seeking care at a medical clinic. Medical Care, 17, 11-29.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_tzxsyQP">The expected utility model: Its variants, purposes, evidence and limitations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J H</forename><surname>Schoemaker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-94-017-5040-0_2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_6wpSRu5">Journal of Economic Literature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="529" to="563" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Schoemaker, P. J. H. (1982). The expected utility model: Its variants, purposes, evidence and limitations. Journal of Economic Literature, 20, 529-563.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_bGzUHee">Accident probabilities and seat belt usage: A psychological perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Slovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Fischhoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lichtenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0001-4575(78)90030-1</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_wVDA3Dr">Accident Analysis and Prevention</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="281" to="285" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Slovic, P., Fischhoff, B., &amp; Lichtenstein, S. (1979). Accident probabilities and seat belt usage: A psychological perspective. Accident Analysis and Prevention, 10, 281-285.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Z6pjMQA">Characterizing perceived risk</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Slovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Fischhoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lichtenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_VHwUHuA">Perilous progress: Managing the hazards of technology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kates</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hohenemser</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kasperson</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Boulder, CO</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Westview</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="125" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Slovic, P., Fischhoff, B., &amp; Lichtenstein, S. (1985). Characterizing perceived risk. In R. Kates, C. Hohenemser, &amp; J. Kasperson (Eds.), Perilous progress: Managing the hazards of technology (pp. 91-125). Boulder, CO: Westview.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_zrhnEbW">Preference for insuring against probably small scale loss: Implications for the theory and practice of insurance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Slovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Fischhoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lichtenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Corrigan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Combs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_VDtkUqn">Journal of Risk and Insurance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="237" to="258" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Slovic, P., Fischhoff, B., Lichtenstein, S., Corrigan, B., &amp; Combs, B. (1977). Preference for insuring against probably small scale loss: Implications for the theory and practice of insurance. Journal of Risk and Insurance, 44, 237-258.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_reeba7f">Decision processes, rationality, and adjustment to natural hazards</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Slovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kunreuther</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_hYEvnqd">Natural hazards: Local, national</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="187" to="205" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Slovic, P., Kunreuther, H., &amp; White, G. F. (1974). Decision processes, rationality, and adjustment to natural hazards. In G. F. White (Ed.), Natural hazards: Local, national, global (pp. 187-205). New York: Oxford University Press.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_9KmH8Sa">Fear arousing communications: A critical examination of theory and research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Sutton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_6NxcVNd">Social psychology and behavioral medicine</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Eiser</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="303" to="338" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sutton, S. R. (1982). Fear arousing communications: A critical examination of theory and research. In J. R. Eiser (Ed.), Social psychology and behavioral medicine (pp. 303-338). New York: Wiley.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_5psDvwP">Process descriptions of decision making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Svenson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_MhDay4k">Organizational Behavior and Human Performance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="86" to="112" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Svenson, O. (1979). Process descriptions of decision making. Organizational Behavior and Human Performance, 23, 86-112.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_yVXgYzB">Time perception and long-term risks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Svenson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_CPGeZk8">Canadian Journal of Operations Research and Information Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="196" to="214" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Svenson, O. (1984). Time perception and long-term risks. Canadian Journal of Operations Research and Information Processing, 22, 196-214.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_9tuZhE8">Perceived driving safety and seatbelt usage</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Svenson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Fischhoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Macgregor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Wx9CMBt">Accident Analysis and Prevention</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="133" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Svenson, O., Fischhoff, B., &amp; MacGregor, D. (1985). Perceived driving safety and seatbelt usage. Accident Analysis and Prevention, 17, 119-133.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_hCWV6xY">The framing of decisions and the psychology of choice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tversky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kahneman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_kpWedqE">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">211</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1453" to="1458" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Tversky, A., &amp; Kahneman, D. (1981). The framing of decisions and the psychology of choice. Science, 211, 1453-1458.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_qzaqMd9">Some factors influencing the nonexpert&apos;s perception and evaluation of environmental risk</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Vaughan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
			<pubPlace>Stanford, CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Stanford University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Unpublished doctoral dissertation</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Vaughan, E. (1986). Some factors influencing the nonexpert&apos;s perception and evaluation of environmental risk. Unpublished doctoral dissertation, Stanford University, Stanford, CA.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_BTpj8YA">A decisional balance model for assessing and predicting smoking status</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Velicier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Diclemente</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Prochaska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Brandenburg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_PGDy8mJ">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1279" to="1289" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Velicier, W. F., DiClemente, C. C, Prochaska, J. O., &amp; Brandenburg, N. (1985). A decisional balance model for assessing and predicting smoking status. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 48, 1279-1289.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_3vQygVX">Temporal experience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wallace</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Rabin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_bJU5eFW">Psychological Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="213" to="236" />
			<date type="published" when="1960">1960</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Wallace, M., &amp; Rabin, A. I. (1960). Temporal experience. Psychological Bulletin, 57, 213-236.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_bU8PfcV">Social psychological models of health behavior: An examination and integration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Wallston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wallston</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_HWZMcHj">Handbook of psychology and health</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Baum</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Singer</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Hillsdale, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Inc</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="54" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Wallston, B. S., &amp; Wallston, K. A. (1984). Social psychological models of health behavior: An examination and integration. In A. Baum, S. E. Taylor, &amp; J. E. Singer (Eds.), Handbook of psychology and health (Vol. 4, pp. 23-54). Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Inc.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Aw6MugR">Disentangling behavioral intention and behavioral expectation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Warshaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_vz4BgEQ">Journal of Experimental Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="213" to="228" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Warshaw, P. R., &amp; Davis, F. D. (1985). Disentangling behavioral intention and behavioral expectation. Journal of Experimental Social Psychology, 21, 213-228.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_32NVTKs">Seeking reassuring or threatening information about environmental cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Weinstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_SrdEv3R">Journal of Behavioral Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="139" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Weinstein, N. D. (1979). Seeking reassuring or threatening information about environmental cancer. Journal of Behavioral Medicine, 2, 125-139.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_gxbnU4k">Unrealistic optimism about future life events</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Weinstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_WKA9fsm">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="806" to="820" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Weinstein, N. D. (1980). Unrealistic optimism about future life events. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 39, 806-820.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_EaWBTm7">Unrealistic optimism about susceptibility to health problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Weinstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_rS77hK9">Journal of Behavioral Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="441" to="460" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Weinstein, N. D. (1982). Unrealistic optimism about susceptibility to health problems. Journal of Behavioral Medicine, 5, 441-460.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b77">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_npBFDMr">Reducing unrealistic optimism about illness susceptibility</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Weinstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_kYES3VA">Health Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Weinstein, N. D. (1983). Reducing unrealistic optimism about illness susceptibility. Health Psychology, 2, 11-20.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b78">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_jdKVwgp">Why it won&apos;t happen to me: Perceptions of risk factors and illness susceptibility</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Weinstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_XCJ9kev">Health Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="431" to="457" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Weinstein, N. D. (1984). Why it won&apos;t happen to me: Perceptions of risk factors and illness susceptibility. Health Psychology, 3, 431-457.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b79">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_REUsdgB">Reactions to lifestyle warnings: Coffee and cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Weinstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_saAG6tY">Health Education Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="134" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Weinstein, N. D. (1985). Reactions to lifestyle warnings: Coffee and cancer. Health Education Quarterly, 12, 129-134.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b80">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_uSsbkfP">Unrealistic optimism about illness susceptibility: Conclusions from a community-wide sample</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Weinstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_xSaYTDp">Journal of Behavioral Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="481" to="500" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Weinstein, N. D. (1987). Unrealistic optimism about illness susceptibility: Conclusions from a community-wide sample. Journal of Behavioral Medicine, 10, 481-500.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b81">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_RjCUXTd">Optimistic biases in public perceptions of the risk from radon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Weinstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sandman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Klotz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_X2v2xR9">American Journal of Public Health</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Weinstein, N. D., Sandman, P. M., &amp; Klotz, M. L. (in press). Optimistic biases in public perceptions of the risk from radon. American Journal of Public Health.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b82">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ZB3PnH6">Health hazard/health risk appraisals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_NxsGNvw">Behavioral health: A handbook of health enhancement and disease prevention</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Matarazzo</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Herd</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="275" to="294" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Weiss, S. M. (1984). Health hazard/health risk appraisals. In J. D. Matarazzo, S. M. Weiss, J. A. Herd, N. E. Miller, &amp; S. M. Weiss (Eds.), Behavioral health: A handbook of health enhancement and disease prevention (pp. 275-294). New York: Wiley.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b83">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_VyPTxHV">Perspectives on cognitive dissonance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wicklund</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Brehm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
			<publisher>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Inc</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Hillsdale, NJ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Wicklund, R. A., &amp; Brehm, J. W. (1976). Perspectives on cognitive dissonance. Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Inc.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b84">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_wVDj3bS">Cognitive factors in lifestyle changes: A social learning perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_GxPWKdt">Behavioral medicine: Changing health lifestyles</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Davidson</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Davidson</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Brunner/Mazel</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="37" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Wilson, G. T. (1980). Cognitive factors in lifestyle changes: A social learning perspective. In P.O. Davidson &amp; S. M. Davidson (Eds.), Behavioral medicine: Changing health lifestyles (pp. 3-37). New York: Brunner/Mazel.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b85">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_c3YevtY">Time horizon effects on product evaluation strategies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Weitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/002224377701400401</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_VMBsXaB">Journal of Marketing Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="429" to="443" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Wright, P., &amp; Weitz, B. (1977). Time horizon effects on product evaluation strategies. Journal of Marketing Research, 14, 429-443.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
