<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_NpGcmYJ"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">8FEDB44F79930D2B325B46C42CC3FBA4</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T06:12+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="329.0" lry="596.0"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="329.0" lry="596.0"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="329.0" lry="596.0"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="329.0" lry="596.0"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="329.0" lry="596.0"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="329.0" lry="596.0"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="329.0" lry="596.0"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="329.0" lry="596.0"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="329.0" lry="596.0"/>
		<surface n="10" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="329.0" lry="596.0"/>
		<surface n="11" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="329.0" lry="596.0"/>
		<surface n="12" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="329.0" lry="596.0"/>
		<surface n="13" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="329.0" lry="596.0"/>
		<surface n="14" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="329.0" lry="596.0"/>
		<surface n="15" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="329.0" lry="596.0"/>
		<surface n="16" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="329.0" lry="596.0"/>
		<surface n="17" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="329.0" lry="596.0"/>
		<surface n="18" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="329.0" lry="596.0"/>
		<surface n="19" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="329.0" lry="596.0"/>
		<surface n="20" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="329.0" lry="596.0"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_rCv4HnP">EVALUATING WITH SENSE</head><p xml:id="_8evs4sP"><s xml:id="_bVD4Bh5">The Theory-Driven Approach HUEY-TSYH CHEN Johns Hopkins University PETER H. ROSSI University of Massachusetts at Amherst Arguing for more serious theorizing in connection with evaluation, this article shows that although the randomized controlled experiment conceptualized as a "black box" approach has dominated the discussions of impact assessment since the classic statements of Campbell and Stanley (1966), the use of theoretical models in connection with impact assessment can both heighten the power of experimental designs and compensatefor some of the major deficiencies of quasi-experimental designs.</s><s xml:id="_V7DDdH4">The article also emphasizes the importance of theoretical models of implementation processes, arguing that this process often constitutes the major obstacle to the full realization of effective programs.</s></p><p xml:id="_97TjWAf"><s xml:id="_4Hu3KGS">AUTHORS' NOTE: This article is a revised version of a paper presented at the 1982 meeting of the Evaluation Research Society.</s><s xml:id="_9dBj4uS">Preparation of this article was aided by a grant from the National Science Foundation (Grant SES-8121745), of which P. H. Rossi is the Principal Investigator.</s></p><p xml:id="_vHHKtJP"><s xml:id="_w9RqyEW">or more than two decades discussions about the appropriate ~ methodology for estimating the net effects of social programs have been dominated by the paradigm of the randomized controlled experiment.</s><s xml:id="_D9Gcxae">For some evaluation commentators (e.g., Suchman, 1969;  Campbell and Stanley, 1966; Cook and Campbell, 1979) alternative designs for impact assessment are valued to the extent that such designs mimic the validity advantages of randomized experiments.</s><s xml:id="_R4MQgCJ">For others (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Scriven, 1972</ref>; Guba and Lincoln, 1981; Deutscher, 1977) the paradigm is used as an example of what not to do in assessing the effects of programs-arguments that often stress the artificiality of standardized treatments and accompanying data collection strategies, especially for labor-intensive human services programs.</s></p><p xml:id="_ySDDcjv"><s xml:id="_HN8uY83">The domination of the experimental paradigm in the program eval- uation literature has unfortunately drawn attention away from a more important task in gaining understanding of social programs, namely, developing theoretical models of social interventions.</s><s xml:id="_YeVcqYb">A very seductive and attractive feature of controlled experiments is that it is not necessary to understand how a social program works in order to estimate its net effects through randomized experiments, provided that the goals and objectives of a program can be specified in reasonably measurable terms.</s><s xml:id="_gDdssJH">Thus cookbook evaluation manuals (e.g., Morris et al., 1978) can outline how to proceed in an evaluation with scarcely a mention of any theory underlying the programs in question.</s><s xml:id="_UGKVvft">Or evaluability assessments (Wholey et al., 1975) can concentrate on whether or not goals are sufficiently defined to permit the application of experimental or quasiexperimental evaluation methods.</s><s xml:id="_YBBAEsk">Even the critics of the experimental paradigm have had their attention distracted from seriously considering the theoretical issues in social programs by concentrating on the false issue of artificial data collection methods and the old social science finding that the actual goals of human organizations are often not their professed goals.</s></p><p xml:id="_wqPk6QU"><s xml:id="_SjzfQBs">An unfortunate consequence of this lack of attention to theory is that the outcomes of evaluation research often provide narrow and sometimes distorted understandings of programs.</s><s xml:id="_FSekHYd">It is not usually clear whether the recorded failures of programs are due to the fact that the programs were built on poor conceptual foundations, usually preposterous sets of &amp;dquo;causal&amp;dquo; mechanisms (e.g., the Impact Cities program); or because treatments were set at such low dosage levels that they could not conceivably affect any outcomes (e.g., Title I); or because programs were poorly implemented.</s><s xml:id="_WXVnTNv">Note that the emphasis in the above statements is on deficiencies in the theoretical underpinnings of the treatment or of the treatment delivery systems.</s></p><p xml:id="_AtxG8ZN"><s xml:id="_4Qw2wNJ">The purpose of this article is to bring theory back into program evaluation.</s><s xml:id="_6y8v2us">Our aim is not to make a case for basic research-there is enough justification for that goal-but to make a case that neglect of existing theoretical knowledge and of thinking theoretically has retarded both our understanding of social programs and the efficient employment of evaluation designs in impact assessment.</s><s xml:id="_H648JPr">This perspective on evaluation research we have called elsewhere (Chen and Rossi, 1980) the &amp;dquo;theory-driven&amp;dquo; approach to evaluation-a perspective, we believe, that has promise to yield better information on social programs, as well as rich yields to the basic social science disciplines.</s></p><p xml:id="_u7y4PQp"><s xml:id="_upERGr3">Of course the kind of theory we have in mind is not the global conceptual schemes of the grand theorists, but much more prosaic theories that are concerned with how human organizations work and how social problems are generated.</s><s xml:id="_CSmhmtu">It advances evaluation practice very little to adopt one or another of current global theories in attacking, say, the problem of juvenile delinquency, but it does help a great deal to understand the authority structure in schools and the mechanisms of peer group influence and parental discipline in designing and evaluating a program that is supposed to reduce disciplinary problems in schools.</s><s xml:id="_YvU6Ppu">Nor are we advocating an approach that rests exclusively on proven theoretical schema that have received wide acclaim in published social science literatures.</s><s xml:id="_wNtnACV">What we are strongly advocating is the necessity for theorizing, for constructing plausible and defensible models of how programs can be expected to work before evaluating them.</s><s xml:id="_vs9Sm5w">Indeed the theory-driven perspective is closer to what econometricians call &amp;dquo;model specification&amp;dquo; than are more complicated and more abstract and general theories.</s></p><p xml:id="_vkBKras"><s xml:id="_PGdfQ5V">Nor do we argue for uncritically using the theories that may underlie policymakers' and program designers' views of how programs should work.</s><s xml:id="_QQ2Va4F">Often enough policymakers and program designers are not social scientists and their theories (if any) are likely to be simply the current folklore of the upper-middle-brow media.</s><s xml:id="_GU64YFf">The primary criterion for identifying theory in the sense used in this article is consistency with social science knowledge and theory.</s><s xml:id="_FNqjfrw">Indeed theoretical structures constructed out of social science concerns may directly contradict what may be the working assumptions of policymakers and program designers.</s></p><p xml:id="_tMGeveq"><s xml:id="_9jmuhC7">It is an acknowledged embarrassment to our viewpoint that social science theory is not well enough developed that appropriate theoretical frameworks and schema are ordinarily easily available &amp;dquo;off the shelf.&amp;dquo;</s><s xml:id="_rXQdnxE">But the absence of fully developed theory should not prevent one from using the best of what is already at hand.</s><s xml:id="_RSQWacC">Most important of all, it is necessary to think theoretically, that is, to rise above the specific and the particular to develop general understandings of social phenomena.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_pQnYk8Q">FOR PROGRAM EVALUATION</head><p xml:id="_vAVj98e"><s xml:id="_2bwadhU">A useful general scheme for identifying the main components of any social program is shown in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_vaeExP5">The main causal relationships that would have to be worked out in any useful model of a program are shown in that diagram as arrows connecting the main components.</s></p><p xml:id="_dwMewKp"><s xml:id="_Kq2k53J">Central to the diagram are &amp;dquo;delivered treatment variables,&amp;dquo; which constitute the program to be evaluated insofar and inasmuch as has been delivered.</s><s xml:id="_tQDJr38">Note that treatment is conceived not as designed but as actually delivered, the delivery being affected by an implementation system that includes organizations, personnel, facilities, clients, and regulations concerning eligibility.</s></p><p xml:id="_kXnJUwN"><s xml:id="_CjPfQbu">At the far right of the diagram are &amp;dquo;outcome variables,&amp;dquo; those aspects-intended and unintended-that are affected either directly by treatment variables and/or mediated through a set of intervening variables, represented by the box so labeled.</s><s xml:id="_zrXUupa">Whether or not intervening processes are present is a matter of conceptualization.</s><s xml:id="_3Cq6GdX">Thus the provision of transfer payments as a treatment directly affects the incomes of clients, but the introduction of a new payment incentive system into a work organization will only affect incomes if the appropriate intervening processes postulated come into play.</s></p><p xml:id="_53sEUpd"><s xml:id="_yYdCpct">The classic statement of the problem of inferring treatment effects centers around the contents of the box labeled &amp;dquo;exogenous variables.&amp;dquo;</s></p><p xml:id="_H7Q5US2"><s xml:id="_fxhX8xj">The outcomes of social programs are rarely, if ever, attributable solely to treatments and intervening processes but are also determined by other sources: those exogenous variables correlated with the treatment variables and stochastic disturbances that are independent of the treatment exogenous variables.</s><s xml:id="_Yxevykr">The exogenous processes may or may not be correlated with treatment, but they often are.</s><s xml:id="_kz3xXYg">Confounded estimates of the treatment effects usually result from the failure to control for correlated exogenous variables, which leads to a correlation between the disturbance and the treatment.</s><s xml:id="_h3Z7nXK">Indeed, one of the great virtues of the classic Campbell and Stanley (1966) statement is the identification of some very general ways in which exogenous processes may be correlated with treatment variables, thereby confounding estimates of effects except under special circumstances.</s><s xml:id="_FqKBmpX">Indeed it is the special (but not unique) quality of the classical randomized experiment that its use can make exogenous variables uncorrelated with treatment variables.</s></p><p xml:id="_HDu5pcm"><s xml:id="_Sxf6pG3">' I .!2 d b 0 $ E 1% 1 3 1 ) 0 ... 0. &lt;-0 c:: 0 i r 0 1. 9 0. Q) 0:: U m E Q) ..c u cn d Y ¡¡: OUTCOME VARIABLES: SPECIFYING THE GOALS * OF PROGRAMS</s></p><p xml:id="_QFjbWcB"><s xml:id="_TYd6W8t">The problem of specifying outcome variables is usually phrased as goal specification-the determination of those outcomes that policymakers and/or program designers envisaged as the intended outcomes of the program.</s><s xml:id="_CQbQ5sD">This issue constitutes one of the important distinctions between basic and applied social research.</s><s xml:id="_5UUxhzv">In basic research, outcome variables express the disciplinary interests of the researcher; in applied social research, outcome variables are those of interest to policymakers or other sponsors of applied work.</s></p><p xml:id="_P6p5U7a"><s xml:id="_TkxTyaS">As traditionally viewed, goal specification in evaluation research tends to be a search for appropriate operational definitions of the intended effects of programs.</s><s xml:id="_QC89JAs">Since such definitions are sometimes cloaked in obscure and ambiguous statements, goal specification can be a separate empirical research enterprise of its.own, as Wholey's (1975)  evaluability assessments exemplify.</s><s xml:id="_QCk2FX5">Some of the consequences of searching for those intentions that are measurable have been noted by many commentators (e.g., Deutscher, 1977; Scriven, 1972; Chen and  Rossi, 1980).</s><s xml:id="_m2HbSgS">First of all, outcome variables tend to be narrower than the connotative intentions of program designers and/or policymakers.</s><s xml:id="_rUZUagh">Thus the goals of Head Start were defined by the evaluators (Cicirelli et  al., 1969) in cognitive terms mainly because such goals could be more easily operationalized than others that were more vaguely formulated.</s><s xml:id="_heUdEkY">Second, there is a large gap between enabling legislation and the actual design of programs.</s><s xml:id="_Safey3H">Designers may narrow the goals of legislators, elaborate upon them, or substitute entirely different goals.</s><s xml:id="_Yyw9KGC">Sometimes the enabling legislation deliberately fosters diversity in the processes of implementation, as in Head Start.</s><s xml:id="_NwMjSqk">In other cases local conditions may appear to require extensive adaptation, as, for example, in the Planned Variation Education Program.</s><s xml:id="_UeXVWkw">Some of the critics of the experimental paradigm were among the first to note these program changes in execution (e.g., Scriven, 1972; Deutscher, 1977; Chen and Rossi, 1980)  recommending that the goals also be inferred from actual program operations, rather than solely from policymaker statements or legislative intents.</s><s xml:id="_7z8dRWJ">Indeed in the case of some programs, program operators are encouraged to develop specific goals as the program is designed (e.g., High Impact and Head Start); hence the goals of programs cannot be described in any specific sense through a consideration of legislative intent or policymaker statements alone.</s></p><p xml:id="_aH7UvED"><s xml:id="_abDUPb9">Most of the commentators who have advocated specifying goals through empirical observation of programs in operation have been strangely silent on how goals should be inferred through observation.</s><s xml:id="_pSbEnxw">Some come close to advocating connoisseurial approaches, i.e., &amp;dquo;Anyone with any experience and smarts will obviously see that ... &amp;dquo;</s></p><p xml:id="_zdg46ZZ"><s xml:id="_SE8FQjp">We believe that there is some wisdom to the admonition that goal specification be empirically based.</s><s xml:id="_pp5KgcB">However, the process whereby it is possible to go from observations to goal specification is through social science theory and knowledge, not by the craftlore of experts and consultants-a point to which we will return at a later point in this article.</s><s xml:id="_ruXeab7">Nor are we advocating ignoring the goals of policymakers in filling out the content of the goals specified in an evaluation.</s><s xml:id="_HyDKgjU">Indeed it is useful to conceptualize goals as falling into one or the other of the following three classes.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_dQtSQw2">Policy-Directed, Plausible Goals</head><p xml:id="_Xhg9BMc"><s xml:id="_sJyp6Bu">These are goals explicitly formulated by those who designed and/ or authorized the program and that are plausible in the following senses:</s></p><p xml:id="_jSzA68a"><s xml:id="_kdatpfF">(1) The goals are consonant with current knowledge of the problem to which the program is directed; (2) the program is designed so that it can be implemented without heroic efforts; (3) the resources allocated to the program are sufficient to deliver the treatment at reasonable dosage levels.</s></p><p xml:id="_8gU7X9t"><s xml:id="_a4sCbBx">For example, the policy goal of the current speed limit 55 miles per hour was to lower the consumption of gasoline by motor vehicles.</s><s xml:id="_HuPwdDX">The goal was plausible in the sense that prior knowledge of the gas consumption characteristics of typical gas engines indicated that consumption would be so lowered.</s><s xml:id="_wpMkZhs">The mechanism of implementation involved tying the passage of appropriate state laws to continuing federal highway fund allocations-a reasonable strategy.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_zrUw6ZQ">Policy-Directed, Implausible Goals</head><p xml:id="_5TGwqEG"><s xml:id="_zVbmR7A">These are goals specified explicitly by those who designed/ authorized a program and which are not plausible in the following senses: (1) The goal is so vague that a relatively large number of specific operationalizations, some of which are mutually contradictory, are possible; (2) the goals are not consonant with current knowledge about the problem in question;</s></p><p xml:id="_8b3etat"><s xml:id="_6mwqf9c">(3) the program is not designed so that it can be implemented by the agency given responsibility; (4) the resources allotted to the program are not sufficient to deliver the treatment at reasonable dosage levels.</s></p><p xml:id="_jrb6zzy"><s xml:id="_79weSbU">For example, although the major goals of the 1968 Federal Firearms Regulation Act were specific enough (i.e., to restrict access to firearms on the part of felons, the insane, and certain other categories of persons), the mode of implementation, namely, requiring the registration of gun dealers and forbidding them to sell to the proscribed social categories, was bound to fail since it was based on the assumptions that gun-using criminals obtained their weapons through gun dealers, that gun dealers could discern which of their potential customers fit into the proscribed categories, and that gun registration records could be easily accessed to trace gun ownership.</s><s xml:id="_3R6sW8D">None of these assumptions was tenable and some went quite contrary to existing established knowledge (Wright et al.,   1983).</s></p><p xml:id="_8tZBrJU"><s xml:id="_hPmBQ5W">Theory-Derived Goals, Not Specified by Policy These are goals that are plausible but not specified in policy directives, and which can be discerned either through the a priori examination of policy and program or through the empirical study of the program (Chen and Rossi, 1980).</s></p><p xml:id="_DYtFDQy"><s xml:id="_D55r8Hh">For example, in the TARP experiments (Rossi et al., 1980), official goals included the reduction of recidivism among released felons through the extending to this group eligibility for unemployment bene- fits payments.</s><s xml:id="_m6byQp9">Consideration of the potential work disincentive effects of such payments, as strongly suggested in the writing of labor economists, led the investigators to postulate work disincentive effects.</s><s xml:id="_yqXJWmW">Except for political reasons, it obviously makes little sense to evaluate a program whose goals were only policy directed and implausible; but there is no way to decide whether a program's goals fall into such a category without careful consideration of whether or not existing social science theory and knowledge would support such a judgment of plausibility.</s><s xml:id="_pxEyFKU">The main point of making such distinctions among goals, however, is to highlight the fact that programs may be accomplishing some things that were not intended by their designers and that such effects may be either desirable or undesirable, may sometimes (as in the case of the TARP experiments) produce effects that offset those intended, and that a good evaluation should take into account inferred effects as well as those directly intended.</s></p><p xml:id="_sbcbCdB"><s xml:id="_dZupkyG">As indicated above, the judgment whether or not a set of policydirected goals is plausible depends on examining the total program in light of existing social theory and knowledge.</s><s xml:id="_bPAVsBQ">We turn to that task in the next two sections of this article.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_sQJG2hz">SPECIFYING THE TREATMENT MODEL</head><p xml:id="_pWSSVe5"><s xml:id="_dAB525e">The treatment model consists of the treatment-as-delivered character- istics, other related exogenous factors, intervening processes, and outcome variables along with the postulated relationships among these component parts.</s><s xml:id="_AemYrvv">An appropriate treatment model lays out in detail how delivered treatments work (see Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>).</s></p><p xml:id="_3KPYJzW"><s xml:id="_N3wETBW">As shown in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> the treatment variables2 are likely correlated with exogenous variables, which may also independently affect inter- vening processes and/or outcome variables.</s><s xml:id="_3RZdPnX">This is simply a formal statement of the truism that most social phenomena are the outcomes of many interrelated processes.</s><s xml:id="_bBKV6gm">For example, whether or not a person quits smoking may depend not only on a particular antismoking program to which he or she may be exposed, but also on factors such as the participant's personal health problems believed to be caused by smoking, whether family members and friends are smokers, and past smoking history, any or all of which may be correlated with participation in the program.</s><s xml:id="_MhwXB6F">Hence if we are modeling the outcome of an antismoking program, we have to take such exogenous factors &amp;dquo;into account&amp;dquo; in estimating the effects of that antismoking program upon participants.</s><s xml:id="_f68y2H2">From a technical viewpoint, unbiased estimates of a program's effects can only be obtained when treatment variables are adequately purged of correlated exogenous variables.</s></p><p xml:id="_pBnGFve"><s xml:id="_DRgNrY4">It is the real and present danger that treatment variables are correlated with exogenous variables that affect intervening processes and outcome variables which make the randomized controlled experiment so attractive.</s><s xml:id="_HJtggmS">By randomly assigning target units of a program (usually persons) to experimental and control groups, the naturally existing correlations between treatment variables and exogenous vari- ables are forced to be essentially zero.</s><s xml:id="_SVR26Yq">If the only concern in a program evaluation is to obtain unbiased treatment effects, then a randomized controlled experiment that maintains its integrity need not be designed with any knowledge of the relationships among exogenous, treatment, intervening, and outcome variables.</s><s xml:id="_BmMpmUg">Hence randomized experiments can be designed as &amp;dquo;black box&amp;dquo; researches in which how treatments affect outcomes is unknown.</s></p><p xml:id="_PFmjhm6"><s xml:id="_xyWYp9U">But black box randomized experiments are not the only realization of the experimental paradigm and, indeed, may often be an inefficient form of that paradigm.</s><s xml:id="_DeBWHdH">This arises because advocates of the black box experimental paradigm often neglect the fact that after randomization exogenous variables are still correlated with outcome variables.</s><s xml:id="_DhPwyBV">Knowing how such exogenous factors affect outcomes makes it possible to construct more precise estimates of experimental effects by controlling for such exogenous variables.</s><s xml:id="_8BQWMhj">For example, an experiment on the recidivism of released prisoners can estimate treatment effects with smaller standard errors by taking into account the fact that age, education, and previous work experiences of the released prisoners ordinarily affect tendencies to recidivate.</s><s xml:id="_vV7U4Qm">For a given N, a randomized experiment that takes into account existing theory and knowledge can have considerably more power than a black box randomized experiment.3 3</s></p><p xml:id="_3tNraea"><s xml:id="_g6AzsbA">The black box paradigm also dominates classical discussion of nonexperimental approaches (Campbell and Stanley, 1966).</s><s xml:id="_Y6tyGqq">Such  discussions center around what are the inherent dangers of black box quasi-experimental approaches.</s><s xml:id="_7dsG3jb">This may be appropriate if one is estimating the effectiveness of a program for which there is no underlying sensible rationale, but it is not sensible to ignore existing knowledge when its use can increase the power of the research design.</s></p><p xml:id="_jaeqatz"><s xml:id="_wCaJ7hW">Indeed, at best, it may be possible to obtain unbiased estimates of effects from quasi-experimental approaches if one can model with some degree of accuracy the relationships among all the elements of the treatment model.</s><s xml:id="_EJzJDBB">For example, an evaluation of an unemployment insurance program in California (Rauma and Berk, 1982) was able to control for the exogenous factors that determined the size of a released prisoner's benefit eligibility, because such benefits were completely determined by the number of days worked while in prison.4</s><s xml:id="_HBWTeCm">By holding constant the number of days worked while in prison, it was possible to hold constant the exogenous factors that determined receiving the treatment and hence to construct unbiased estimates of the effects of the treatment on subsequent recidivism.</s></p><p xml:id="_Ay38ZGx"><s xml:id="_pH2WMmS">The general issue of controlling for self-selection bias has been discussed thoroughly in recent literature (Barnow et al., 1980) and more recently by Berk and Ray (1982).</s><s xml:id="_jfRhPsS">How successfully such approaches can be applied in particular cases is determined by how well known are the exogenous processes and how well they can be measured.</s><s xml:id="_RwmHPRx">Furthermore, it is somewhat obvious, but bears emphasis, that knowledge and theory concerning the effects of exogenous processes need to be built into evaluations ab initio and not constructed ad hoc from the selections available in a given data set.</s></p><p xml:id="_7YVqUNX"><s xml:id="_gtVnNF7">The dangers of black box quasi-experiments are real, but they flow from the fact that they are black box efforts and not from their quasiexperimental character.</s><s xml:id="_va4attB">Theory-driven randomized and quasi-experiments both are superior to their black box counterparts in power and efficiency.</s><s xml:id="_dhupz23">At best the distinction between randomized experiments and quasi-experiments becomes blurred to the extent that correctly specified theory-driven treatment models are employed.</s><s xml:id="_9PswQVm">This last statement has a number of important implications.</s><s xml:id="_Vtj9mB4">Randomized experimental designs applied to field situations have a distressing tendency to deteriorate rapidly into quasi-experiments.</s><s xml:id="_gras3m3">For example, one may randomly assign persons to treatment groups, but if treatment acceptance depends even partially on target population cooperation, differential cooperation can easily change the research design into a quasi-experiment.</s><s xml:id="_QcUfD5k">Witness the effects that attrition rates have had on the income maintenance and housing allowance experiments (Watts and Rees, 1976).</s><s xml:id="_Je4W5Rk">Randomized experiments are difficult to install and carry out except on proposed but not yet enacted programs.</s><s xml:id="_vTKAPgJ">Existing, full-coverage programs can usually only be evaluated for impact assessment by quasi-experimental designs.</s></p><p xml:id="_JrPqQ5m"><s xml:id="_7SHznJm">Finally, theory-driven treatment modeling can meet the objections of many evaluators who are concerned that programs once in place develop goals that replace those officially proclaimed by policymakers and program designers.</s><s xml:id="_Hb6rnbb">The truism that every program has some effects can be given some substance if treatment modeling can be used to uncover them.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_NADuRRY">THE PROBLEM OF GENERALIZATION</head><p xml:id="_cB2xZ3N"><s xml:id="_ejNQX2Z">A given social program ordinarily is a complex bundle of specific items lumped together as a treatment.</s><s xml:id="_dmbc6ng">Even very simple-appearing treatments can become quite complex in implementation.</s><s xml:id="_hXkJkHS">For example, although the transfer payments were conceived as the treatments in income maintenance or housing allowance experiments, the treatments as delivered consisted of the payments of varying amounts, methods of establishing and validating eligibility, housing inspections, and so on through the entire apparatus of the experiments that dealt directly with the families in the experiment.</s><s xml:id="_UFUkVyU">Without careful specification of the treatment as delivered, interpretation of treatment effects may become very muddy indeed.</s><s xml:id="_n7MPqbm">More important; an experiment may be fatally flawed by confounding the intended treatment with administrative trappings that might nullify intended treatment effects.</s><s xml:id="_KgYJJT6">A priori analysis of the treatment as delivered should lead to an experimental design that can separate out the effects of various components of the treatment as delivered.</s><s xml:id="_tsERTaB">A very good example exists again in the TARP experiment in which the administrative regulations of the unemployment benefit systems of the states of Georgia and Texas negated the beneficial effects of the payments (Rossi et al., 1980).</s></p><p xml:id="_vUYdHJX"><s xml:id="_k5AvV68">Of course any treatment as delivered can be broken down analytically into a very large number of identifiable components, the vast majority of which may have trivial impacts upon outcomes.</s><s xml:id="_7Tf3Jhf">Identifying the important compenents is again the task of applying a priori knowledge and theory.</s><s xml:id="_zu4awyc">Thus in the income maintenance experiments, the guarantee level and the implicit tax rates were identified on the basis of microeconomic theories concerning labor force participation as critically important components and hence were systematically varied within the experimental design.</s><s xml:id="_DGJ4c9M">Similarly in the housing allowance experiments, the use of housing standards as a criterion for eligibility was conceived to be an important device and hence built into the experimental design.</s></p><p xml:id="_G4y6A94"><s xml:id="_gR9gw6Y">These considerations, it should be noted, apply with equal force to quasi-experiments, especially those in which the design of treatments can be influenced by the evaluation researcher.</s></p><p xml:id="_ZSaerWv"><s xml:id="_NjzxeJb">One of the main benefits of departing from the black box treatment- as-unit approach to evaluation is an enhanced ability to generalize from the researches in question to other circumstances.</s><s xml:id="_w5A5TBe">The end result of a black box evaluation is to know whether or not a given treatment-as- unit is effective and to what extent it is so.</s><s xml:id="_GtUFmca">A transfer into a different administrative environment and subsequent modifications to fit the requirements of that environment may drastically alter the treatment's effectiveness, if the elements changed are among the more important within the treatment-as-unit.</s><s xml:id="_PeuAQ9S">Indeed, since the translation of a proposed program into an enacted program always requires modification to fit the administrative environment into which it is placed, as well as to the political acceptability constraints of the policymakers, it is important to be able to point out what are the essential and nonessential components of a proposed program.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_3VMwEPk">MODELING INTERVENING PROCESSES</head><p xml:id="_v3wKJV2"><s xml:id="_WNpaGga">The main points made with respect to the modeling of the treatment processes and components of delivered treatments apply as well as to the modeling of intervening processes.</s><s xml:id="_GkJjfsX">Indeed any model of the treatment process necessarily includes modeling intervening processes.</s><s xml:id="_WgqZtA2">From some viewpoints it hardly makes any sense to distinguish intervening processes except that, for programs that may be expected to have very long time effects, whether or not intervening processes occur may be the first sign of whether or not a program is working.</s><s xml:id="_WUaTFu2">For example, if a manpower training program is to be installed to increase the earning power of participants over the long run, it may be useful as a first step to specify what has to change in the short run in order that the long-range effects of the desired sort may be eventually captured.</s><s xml:id="_KrjUaSb">Thus, if a training program does not increase the job-relevant skills of participants, it seems unlikely that long-run wages will also increase.</s><s xml:id="_X6cJyzh">In short, the specification of intervening processes provides the opportunities for the more sensitive testing of the effectiveness of programs and also for their redesign in the unhappy eventuality that postulated intervening steps do not occur.</s><s xml:id="_aC7QyJ2">, RESPONSE FUNCTIONAL FORMS Another issue in modeling centers around the functional forms that relate program variables to each other and to outcome variables.</s><s xml:id="_GHZyBBh">Recursive models postulate one-way relations among variables and nonrecursive models postulate that at least some of the relations involve reciprocal effects.</s></p><p xml:id="_YJ8N6vp"><s xml:id="_q9c3uqv">In program evaluation it is possible to find that modeling causal processes of the intervention requires postulating reciprocal relations among outcome variables and/or between the outcome variables and the intervening variables.</s><s xml:id="_KgCaqB9">For example, an educational program might affect students' test scores and self-esteem.</s><s xml:id="_jVuhhXS">However, if existing knowledge suggests that a reciprocal process exists between test scores and self-esteem, then a nonrecursive model should be proposed for evaluating this program.</s></p><p xml:id="_rxNqMTN"><s xml:id="_82drbgW">Interactive effects may also be postulated in which treatment variables are differentially effective among subgroups of targets.</s></p><p xml:id="_3jADyCM"><s xml:id="_jd7MRCk">Interactions are sufficiently well known that evaluators routinely look for them, but the search for interactions should not be a matter of systematically testing out all possible interactions-a strategy that maximizes Type I errors-but one which looks for those interactions that one has a good a priori reason to suspect exist.</s></p><p xml:id="_mvjTEjm"><s xml:id="_JYGafQv">Finally, linear additive models of response effects are popular because they are both easy to compute and simple to interpret when found.</s><s xml:id="_SuYTaba">But in some cases there may be good reason to suspect that polynomial models may be more appropriate.</s><s xml:id="_GD4ZG56">For example, increasing the amount of treatments may lead one to expect a point of maximum effect per unit of treatment with lower rates of return for points above and below the maximum.</s><s xml:id="_nq9akec">Thus transfer payments that are too small may not affect labor force supply at all, while transfer payments that are very large may not affect labor force supply any more than modest transfer payments, as the diminishing marginal returns formulation suggests.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_NF5E4sq">Implementation Modeling</head><p xml:id="_2mdna27"><s xml:id="_pXe3h2h">Implementation systems traditionally have not been given the amount of attention they fully deserve in evaluation research.</s><s xml:id="_jEjHbsW">As pointed out earlier, experimental evaluations of prospective programs involve setting up arrangements for delivering programs (or treatments); hence even programs set up for testing purposes by researchers involve implementation systems.</s><s xml:id="_7fAB8Jq">Even more important is the fact that a program once enacted must be carried out through an implementation system that includes administrative rules and regulations, bureaucratic structures, and personnel who have been given the responsibility to administer the program in question.</s></p><p xml:id="_8sW6y9Z"><s xml:id="_UvtYYvG">An understanding of program implementation is important in program evaluation, since successful implementation is also a necessary condition in assessing program theory success.</s><s xml:id="_p6UwX9q">Only when treatment variables are implemented successfully, at least to some extent, can we test whether or not the treatment variables have had any impact upon outcome variables.</s></p><p xml:id="_BtPfnXP"><s xml:id="_PwQAMPJ">In the evaluation 1_iterature there has been no dearth of interest in implementation, but too much of the attention has been given to worrying about whetiier programs have be~!1 delivered as intended, and not enough attention has been given to understanding the process of implementation.</s><s xml:id="_E29H8zH">Thus Levine ( 1972) stated that the main prob!em of the War on Poverty was the failure of programs to be implemented in the field.</s><s xml:id="_xqzGt5V"><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Gramlich and Koshel ( 1975)</ref> found that the performance contract- ing experiments failed to the extent that they were not implemented (or implemented incorrectly) in the field.</s><s xml:id="_nW2TeB8">Part of the problem of integrating a concern for implementation process into evaluation stems from the fact that evaluators tend to be specialists in the disciplines relevant to treatment processes.</s><s xml:id="_6mWYKfc">Thus an evaluator concerned with the outcome of educational programs usually knows a great deal about educational processes, but may know very little about theories of organization; hence the organizational contexts of the program may be neglected or unspecified.</s></p><p xml:id="_bytktJe"><s xml:id="_N3gX5q6">In Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> we have designated an implementation system as the organizational arrangement that is either specially designed to deliver treatments (or programs) or given the responsibility to do so.</s><s xml:id="_EBTan9X">We do not mean to imply that this box represents a simple system.</s><s xml:id="_fJrruAV">Indeed at least six subsystems have been identified in the existing literature (e.g., Van  Meter and Van Horn, 1975; Williams and Elmore, 1976; Scheirer, 1981 ), and these are detailed below.</s><s xml:id="_P9HRkpN">, Implementing organization.</s><s xml:id="_BsgGjRZ">An agency of some sort, either newly created for the purpose or already existing, is usually given the mandate to administer a program.</s><s xml:id="_4REaV2w">Its characteristics, such as the particular type of authority structure, the composition of personnel, existing standard operating procedures, and the system of incentives employed to achieve coordination of activities among personnel and departments may all affect how much and what specific forms of a given treatment are delivered.</s><s xml:id="_xkRqZPC">For example, schools are considered to be loosely coupled systems in which component personnel (e.g., teachers) are not linked together into an extensive division of labor in which the work of one member is closely dependent in time on the work of another member.</s><s xml:id="_xbbeuMJ">Hence the activities of teachers in their classrooms are notoriously difficult to control (and affect).</s><s xml:id="_pvHB5Ym">In contrast, a public welfare agency in which caseworkers each handle only part of the treatment of a case may be more easily changed, since it is easier to detect caseworkers who are not performing according to plan.</s></p><p xml:id="_7WqnEwb"><s xml:id="_7Zspa8P">Organizational theory is not the best developed of social sciences and tends to be heavily dominated by theories that were developed in connection with the study of industrial and business enterprises.</s><s xml:id="_Sxtpp75">The study of public sector organizations that process people rather than material objects has been relatively neglected.</s></p><p xml:id="_hv9U5ZR"><s xml:id="_VPnuc9y">Target groups.</s><s xml:id="_277kK7k">Every program defines a target population consisting of some human units-persons, households, communities, and so on- in which its effects are to be manifested in the form of specified changes.</s><s xml:id="_9WS5eQz">Target groups affect the implementation of programs to the extent that such implementation implies the cooperation, compliance, or participation of the groups in question.</s><s xml:id="_HKATPr9">If targets, for whatever reasons, refuse to accept delivery of a program's treatment, clearly the program can have no effect.</s><s xml:id="_apFPbZS">Participation rates, therefore, are extremely important characteristics of programs.</s><s xml:id="_pmhvACg">For example, the fact that Sesame Street achieved so large a penetration of its intended audience of nurseryschool-age children in poor families contributed greatly to its overall success, even though the effects of viewing on each child may have been relatively slight.</s><s xml:id="_wgvzTR5">In contrast, the failure of Feeling Good (Mielke and  Swinehart, 1976) was largely caused by its inability to reach more than a very small proportion of its intended target of poor adults.</s><s xml:id="_nza8NTw">Understand- ing the conditions under which targets of various sorts will or will not participate in programs may involve knowing how subgroups within the population receive information, subcultural beliefs concerning partici- pation in similar programs, and so on.</s></p><p xml:id="_DyZjfFr"><s xml:id="_BK8NZYM">Environmental context.</s><s xml:id="_R6CN9C3">Implementation takes place within an environment containing other organizations, competing activities and programs, political structures, and so on.</s><s xml:id="_FRbJgRc">All these exogenous contextual processes can affect whether or not a program can be effectively implemented.</s><s xml:id="_4j9gWGr">Thus the Community Action Program of the Office of Economic Opportunity was eventually handed over to local political control after mayors protested against the federal government's setting up independent political entities in their domains <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Moynihan, 1969)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_F4yR3Jr">Also, the fact that the health education television program Feeling Good was broadcast at prime viewing times means that it had to compete with extremely popular programs for the attention of its intended audiences <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Mielke and Swinehart, 1976</ref>).</s></p><p xml:id="_Q4ekBYf"><s xml:id="_suXdu9j">Characteristics of treatments.</s><s xml:id="_xARADv4">Some treatments are intrinsically difficult and others much easier to deliver.</s><s xml:id="_KExkEKw">Perhaps the critical element is the extent to which the treatment is &amp;dquo;operator-robust&amp;dquo;-capable of being delivered relatively intact as intended, regardless of the activities of the persons in whose hands responsibility for delivery is given.</s><s xml:id="_ExuFtYE">Thus, at one extreme, transfer payments are relatively robust treatments, since there are limited numbers of ways in which checks can be delivered to persons through the mail.</s><s xml:id="_7mPmeZK">At the other extreme, treatments that involve tailoring interventions to the characteristics of targets usually involve allowing considerable discretion to the frontline implementer, a circum- stance that may considerably distort program intentions.</s><s xml:id="_3Un6bcs">Indeed for most human services programs the dilemma is what is the optimum level of discretion to be allowed?</s><s xml:id="_rdjeQqK">If too little discretion is allowed, inappropriate treatments may be administered to clients.</s><s xml:id="_aa4y54Z">If too much discretion is allowed, it may become very difficult to determine precisely what was delivered, as is the case with many educational programs designed to alter the teaching practices in the classroom.</s></p><p xml:id="_hfaDSZG"><s xml:id="_z2Y6JNS">Another characteristic of treatments that bears attention is the matter of dosage.</s><s xml:id="_3DbdJ3k">Thus a transfer payment that amounts to $100 per week is simply worth a lot more than 100 times a transfer payment of $1 per week.</s><s xml:id="_3w3VC7w">Or, just becuase we know that three hours of counseling per week may help a client does not mean that one hour per week will simply do one-third less.</s><s xml:id="_8EPp6wT">The amount of an intervention, especially as actually delivered, ought to be an important concern of evaluators.</s></p><p xml:id="_ccSxdPs"><s xml:id="_H2gFUPK">Resources.</s><s xml:id="_s64e4a3">Obviously a program requires-sufficient resources to enable it to accomplish the delivery of treatment.</s><s xml:id="_tThqPuP">Funds are used to hire persons, physical facilities, and so on.</s><s xml:id="_5NpYprQ">An underfunded program simply will not be able to deliver the treatments as prescribed.</s></p><p xml:id="_7B9uH9s"><s xml:id="_SYSnM5B">Interorganizational transactions.</s><s xml:id="_fNK8htZ">An implementing organization may have to deal with other organizations in order to be able to deliver treatments.</s><s xml:id="_QzYsZhr">For example, treatments that call for the cooperation of other organizations may not be able to function if cooperation is withheld; or an organization may be under the jurisdiction of a more superordinate organization whose command superiority may either interfere with or facilitate the implementation of the program.</s></p><p xml:id="_zzP4TtG"><s xml:id="_gY3CsHM">All of the above characteristics of implementation systems may need to be taken into account in developing a model of implementation in particular cases.</s><s xml:id="_v5AERrT">We cannot pretend that the construction of implementation models will be easy at this stage in our understanding of the public sector human services organizations.</s><s xml:id="_snnGrA3">All that is clear to us is that neglect of understanding implementation has made it ambiguous in many cases of evaluation researches whether the program or the implementation system or both were at fault in a demonstrated failure to achieve outcomes.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_mcMcuTu">CONCLUSIONS</head><p xml:id="_vf79z54"><s xml:id="_8CKd8Xa">This article presents a set of arguments for a new appraisal of the dominant experimental paradigm as applied to evaluations.</s><s xml:id="_TmcMGfd">A central feature of that paradigm as elaborated has been to emphasize black box randomized experiments and quasi-experiments.</s><s xml:id="_WEp4afY">We have argued for a paradigm that accepts experiments and quasi-experiments as dominant research designs, but that emphasizes that these devices should be used in conjunction with a priori knowledge and theory to build models of the treatment process and implementation system to produce evaluations that are more efficient and that yield more information about how to achieve desired effects.</s></p><p xml:id="_fQ6HBBc"><s xml:id="_UPHqFyg">It should also be emphasized that this article does not argue for postponing evaluations until the most adequate theory and knowledge have been constructed.</s><s xml:id="_bjVtATV">It argues, rather, that we make do with what we have, at least for the time being, drawing upon existing stocks of theory and knowledge to the extent relevant.</s><s xml:id="_BQyJDWq">We also make a special plea for more intensive attention to developing knowledge and theory concerning how human services organizations work, so that our general under- standing of implementation systems will be advanced</s></p><p xml:id="_t2RcKap"><s xml:id="_HtpFVDJ">In sum, we hope that what we have to say here will inspire evaluators to spend more effort on understanding how programs work than on the effort to find out whether or not they actually work in some specific and nongeneralizable instance.</s></p><p xml:id="_TVMCkRP"><s xml:id="_fBrHNQY">. NOTES 1.</s><s xml:id="_yNwaNsB">It has become increasingly clear with experience in social experimentation (as opposed to short-term laboratory experiments) that the beneficial effects of randomization can be undermined seriously by exogenous factors operating on the delivery of treatments, as exemplified in nonrandom attrition in treatment and control groups in the income maintenance experiments (Watts and Rees, 1976; Rossi and Lyall, 1976).</s><s xml:id="_HpWS3k9">2. Treatment variables include treatment characteristics as delivered.</s><s xml:id="_zpMMABU">In order to make the discussion in this article flow more smoothly, we will simply refer to "treatment factors" with the understanding that such terms refer to treatments as delivered.</s></p><p xml:id="_CqkyUz9"><s xml:id="_yrw7aam">3. A similar argument against black box experiments was made recently in a commentary on experiments on the effectiveness of seeding clouds with silver iodide crystals in order to produce rainfall <ref type="bibr">(Kerr, 1982a</ref><ref type="bibr">(Kerr, , 1982b))</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_gjshmSs">The author made the point that without good knowledge of the processes that take place within clouds that ordinarily lead to rainfall, the very expensive experiments were not powerful enough to detect treatment effects.</s><s xml:id="_VFv4WXx">A strong argument was then advanced against any additional black box experiments on the effects of cloud seeding.</s></p><p xml:id="_vg8buNH"><s xml:id="_qMARjjK">4. Since prisoners did not know that their working would affect their eligibility for and amount of benefits (the legislation had been enacted at the time of imprisonment), they could not have worked in prison because they anticipated postrelease benefits.</s><s xml:id="_Pt3F4bA">Of course, for subsequent cohorts of prisoners, the possibility of prison work being affected by anticipated benefits will have to be taken into account.</s></p></div>		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_NJprtTu">Issues in the analysis of selectivity bias</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Barnow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Cain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Goldberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_N39nsWq">Evaluation Studies Review Annual</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Stormsdorfer</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Farkas</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Beverly Hills, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Sage</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">BARNOW, B., G. G. CAIN, and A. GOLDBERGER (1980) &quot;Issues in the analysis of selectivity bias,&quot; in E. W. Stormsdorfer and G. Farkas (eds.) Evaluation Studies Review Annual, Vol. 5. Beverly Hills, CA: Sage.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ycK4w3j">Selection biases in sociological data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Berk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Ray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0049-089x(82)90003-5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_u9mwmVb">Social Science Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="352" to="398" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">BERK, R. and S. C. RAY (1982) &quot;Selection biases in sociological data.&quot; Social Science Research 11, 4: 352-398.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Stanley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_5KX7RTV">Experimental and Quasi-Experimental Designs for Research</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Chicago</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Rand McNally</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1966">1966</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">CAMPBELL, D. T. and J. C. STANLEY (1966) Experimental and Quasi-Experimental Designs for Research. Chicago: Rand McNally.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_DMj4pDS">Multi-goal theory-driven approach: a model linking basic and applied social science</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Rossi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/2577835</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_W2ycdbV">Social Forces</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="106" to="122" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">CHEN, H. and P. H. ROSSI (1980) &quot;Multi-goal theory-driven approach: a model linking basic and applied social science.&quot; Social Forces 51, 1 : 106-122.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_mZqUyXz">The Impact of Head Start</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Cicirelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Associates</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.22606/jaer.2018.33003</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1969">1969</date>
			<pubPlace>Athens, OH</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Westinghouse Learning Corporation and Ohio University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">CICIRELLI, V. G. and Associates (1969) The Impact of Head Start. Athens, OH: Westinghouse Learning Corporation and Ohio University.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5479/sil.776754.39088011383783</idno>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_4SJHGDC">Quasi-Experimentation: Design and Analysis Issues for Field Setting</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Chicago</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Rand McNally</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">COOK, T. D. and D. T. CAMPBELL (1979) Quasi-Experimentation: Design and Analysis Issues for Field Setting. Chicago: Rand McNally.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_dCVWNn8">Toward avoiding the goal trap in evaluation research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Deutscher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4324/9781351290722-12</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_AN5YP5Q">Readings in Evaluation Research</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Caro</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Russell Sage</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">DEUTSCHER, I. (1977) &quot;Toward avoiding the goal trap in evaluation research,&quot; in F. G. Caro (ed.) Readings in Evaluation Research. New York: Russell Sage.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_jCsVc8j">Is real-world experimentation possible? The case of educational performance contracting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gramlich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Koshel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_j6FyMXD">Policy Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="511" to="530" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975. Summer</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">GRAMLICH, E. M. and P. P. KOSHEL (1975) &quot;Is real-world experimentation possible? The case of educational performance contracting.&quot; Policy Analysis 1 (Summer): 511-530.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Guba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lincoln</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_nsvnJC5">Effective Evaluation</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Francisco</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Jossey-Bass</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">GUBA, E. G. and Y. LINCOLN (1981) Effective Evaluation. San Francisco: Jossey-Bass.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_vtuzrke">Test fails to confirm cloud seeding effect</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kerr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1126/science.217.4556.234</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_V7M63hc">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">217</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4559</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982. 1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Cloud seeding: one success in 35 years Science</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">KERR, R. A. (1982a) &quot;Test fails to confirm cloud seeding effect.&quot; Science 217, 4557. &amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash; (1982b) &quot;Cloud seeding: one success in 35 years.&quot; Science 217, 4559.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Levine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_65jbh9A">Public Planning: Failure and Redirections</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Basic Books</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">LEVINE, R. A. (1972) Public Planning: Failure and Redirections. New York: Basic Books.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_pSNjSqd">Evaluation of the Feeling Good Television Series</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Mielke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Swinehart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.7560/728448-008</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
			<publisher>Children&apos;s Television Workshop</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">MIELKE, K. W. and J. W. SWINEHART (1976) Evaluation of the Feeling Good Television Series. New York: Children&apos;s Television Workshop.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Fitz-Gibbon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Henerson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_6Rd7TxZ">Program Evaluation Kit</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Beverly Hills, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Sage</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">MORRIS, L. L., C. T. FITZ-GIBBON, and M. E. HENERSON (1978) Program Evaluation Kit. Beverly Hills, CA: Sage.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Moynihan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_TdMkbN8">Maximum Feasible Misunderstanding</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Free Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1969">1969</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">MOYNIHAN, D. P. (1969) Maximum Feasible Misunderstanding. New York: Free Press.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_sww7fXU">Crime and poverty in California</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rauma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Berk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0049-089x(82)90002-3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_mMpNyhF">Social Science Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="318" to="351" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">RAUMA, D. and R. BERK (1982) &quot;Crime and poverty in California.&quot; Social Science Research 11, 4: 318-351.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_Qsu2k5b">Social Experimentation-A Method for Planning and Evaluating Social Intervention</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Riecken</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Boruch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
			<publisher>Academic</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">RIECKEN, H. W. and R. F. BORUCH (1974) Social Experimentation-A Method for Planning and Evaluating Social Intervention. New York: Academic.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_HGuwyMV">Reforming Social Welfare</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Rossi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lyall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
			<publisher>Russell Sage</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">ROSSI, P. H. and K. LYALL (1976) Reforming Social Welfare. New York: Russell Sage.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Rossi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Berk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lenihan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_H6rQBSR">Money, Work and Crime</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">ROSSI, P. H., R. A. BERK, and K. J. LENIHAN (1980) Money, Work and Crime. New York: Academic.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_ByEeS2b">Program Implementation: The Organizational Context</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Scheirer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
			<publisher>Sage</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Beverly Hills, CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">SCHEIRER, M. A. (1981) Program Implementation: The Organizational Context. Beverly Hills, CA: Sage.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_2UdBaN8">Pros and cons about goal-free evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Scriven</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/109821409101200108</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_KAUvX2u">Evaluation Comment</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="4" />
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">SCRIVEN, M. (1972) &quot;Pros and cons about goal-free evaluation.&quot; Evaluation Comment 3: 1-4.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_gescKWM">Evaluating educational programs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Man</forename><surname>Such</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/bf02322249</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_JjhfS2z">Urban Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="17" />
			<date type="published" when="1969">1969</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">SUCH MAN, E. A. (1969) &quot;Evaluating educational programs.&quot; Urban Review 3, 4 : 15-17.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_c6G6UYE">The policy implementation process: a conceptual framework</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Van Meter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Van Horn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/009539977500600404</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_3ytC4WP">Administration and Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="445" to="488" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">VAN METER, D. S. and C. E. VAN HORN (1975) &quot;The policy implementation process: a conceptual framework.&quot; Administration and Society 6, 4: 445-488.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_jsETx75">The New Jersey Income Maintenance Experiment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Watts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rees</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
			<publisher>Academic</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">WATTS, H. and A. REES (1976) The New Jersey Income Maintenance Experiment, Vols. 2 and 3. New York: Academic.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ak74y7R">Evaluation: where is it really needed?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Wholey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Nay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Schmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4135/9781412950596.n585</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_9uNthTF">Evaluation Magazine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="89" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">WHOLEY, J. S., J. N. NAY, and R. E. SCHMIDT (1975) &quot;Evaluation: where is it really needed?&quot; Evaluation Magazine 2, 2: 89-93.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_zxt3BWP">Implementation analysis and assessment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.7249/tr1228</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_TGuCEuw">Social Program Implementation</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Elmore</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Academic. &amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">WILLIAMS, W. (1976) &quot;Implementation analysis and assessment,&quot; in W. Williams and R. F. Elmore (eds.) Social Program Implementation. New York: Academic. &amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/c2013-0-07643-8</idno>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_CgQTnEV">Social Program Implementation</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Elmore</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">and R. F. ELMORE [eds.] (1976) Social Program Implementation. New York: Academic.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Rossi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Daly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_b4Pp6cd">Under the Gun</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Hawthorne, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Aldine</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">WRIGHT, J. D., P. H. ROSSI, and K. DALY (1983) Under the Gun. Hawthorne, NY: Aldine.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_hd3Dawj">He is interested in developing theoretical models in program evaluation and implementationfor policy decisions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Huey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Peter H. Rossi</editor>
		<imprint/>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Department of Social Relations at the Johns Hopkins University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Currently he is editing an evaluation book with</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Huey-tsyh Chen is Associate Research Scientist of the Center for Metropolitan Planning and Research and an Assistant Professor of the Department of Social Relations at the Johns Hopkins University. He is interested in developing theoretical models in program evaluation and implementationfor policy decisions. Currently he is editing an evaluation book with Peter H. Rossi.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_FN9bw9Z">Professor of Sociology and Director of Research at the Social and Demographic Research Institute of the University of Massachusetts at Amherst. He is coauthor (with Howard Freeman) of Evaluation: A Systematic Approach (Sage</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Peter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Rossi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_Z6rhkzU">S. Nock) of Measuring Social Judgments: The Factorial Survey Approach</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Sage</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982. 1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>He is past president of the American Sociological Association and recipient of the 1981 Alva and Gunnar Myrdal Prize of the Evaluation Research Society, awarded for contributions to evaluation research methods</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Peter H. Rossi is Professor of Sociology and Director of Research at the Social and Demographic Research Institute of the University of Massachusetts at Amherst. He is coauthor (with Howard Freeman) of Evaluation: A Systematic Approach (Sage, 1982) and (with S. Nock) of Measuring Social Judgments: The Factorial Survey Approach (Sage, 1982). He is past president of the American Sociological Association and recipient of the 1981 Alva and Gunnar Myrdal Prize of the Evaluation Research Society, awarded for contributions to evaluation research methods.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
