<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qdgfXEC">Participation Rates With Opt-out Enrollment in a Remote Monitoring Intervention for Patients With Myocardial Infarction</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
					<p type="raw">Copyright 2016 American Medical Association. All rights reserved. Copyright 2016 American Medical Association. All rights reserved. Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by University of Iowa user on 07/28/2025 Copyright 2016 American Medical Association. All rights reserved.</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2016-09-07">September 7, 2016.</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>MD, MBA, MSHP</roleName><forename type="first">Shivan</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mehta</surname></persName>
							<email>shivan.mehta@uphs.upenn.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>ScD</roleName><forename type="first">Andrea</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Troxel</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MA</roleName><forename type="first">Noora</forename><surname>Marcus</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>BS</roleName><forename type="first">Christina</forename><surname>Jameson</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>BS</roleName><forename type="first">Devon</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD, MBA</roleName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Asch</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Kevin</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Volpp</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Troxel, Taylor</roleName><surname>Mehta</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Marcus</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Asch, Volpp</roleName><surname>Jameson</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Asch, Volpp</roleName><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Asch</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Marcus</forename><surname>Mehta</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Taylor</forename><surname>Jameson</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Volpp</forename><surname>Asch</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Marcus</forename><surname>Troxel</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Volpp</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Department of Medicine , Perelman School of Medicine , University of Pennsylvania , Philadelphia );</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Perelman School of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pennsylvania</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Center for Health Incentives and Behavioral Economics , Leonard Davis Institute of Health Economics , University of Pennsylvania , Philadelphia</note>
								<orgName type="department">Center for Health Incentives and Behavioral Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Leonard Davis Institute of Health Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Pennsylvania</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Penn Medicine Center for Health Care Innovation , Philadelphia , Pennsylvania Department of Biostatistics and Epidemiology ,</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics and Epidemiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Penn Medicine Center for Health Care Innovation</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
									<region>Pennsylvania</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Perelman School of Medicine , University of Pennsylvania , Philadelphia (</note>
								<orgName type="department">Perelman School of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pennsylvania</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Troxel ); Center for Health Equity Research and Promotion , Philadelphia VA Medical Center , Philadelphia , Pennsylvania</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Troxel</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Center for Health Equity Research and Promotion</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Philadelphia VA Medical Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
									<region>Pennsylvania</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Department of Medicine , Perelman School of Medicine , University of Pennsylvania , 1318 Blockley Hall , 423 Guardian Dr , Philadelphia , PA 19104</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Perelman School of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pennsylvania</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1318 Blockley Hall 423 Guardian Dr</addrLine>
									<postCode>19104</postCode>
									<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_GjTgxa7">Participation Rates With Opt-out Enrollment in a Remote Monitoring Intervention for Patients With Myocardial Infarction</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2016-09-07">September 7, 2016.</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">BC60099DB9432EDC5220BBD5C8020B51</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1001/jamacardio.2016.2374.</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T06:16+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_SGnz58x"><p xml:id="_W2wSWPW"><s xml:id="_m92tDku">Many research studies are limited by low participation rates, threatening the generalizability of findings because participants likely differ greatly from nonparticipants. 1 Low rates of participation could be a function of the opt-in approach to enrollment, in which the default is to not participate.</s><s xml:id="_aXxb5JA">Behavioral economics research has shown that an opt-out approach can increase participation in retirement savings and organ donation while maintaining informed choice. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref></s><s xml:id="_ZeyaUcb">We evaluated whether an opt-out approach to enrollment will increase participation in a remote monitoring intervention among patients with myocardial infarction.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_gaxsTat"><p xml:id="_STWZ596"><s xml:id="_kUtcJ3s">Methods | This prospective cohort study compared enrollment rates in a remote monitoring intervention using an opt-in vs an opt-out approach.</s><s xml:id="_656ZwTX">The intervention offered remote monitoring of medication adherence for patients recently discharged after myocardial infarction, as in a larger trial with opt-in enrollment.</s><s xml:id="_YKp9mMT">Those in the opt-in cohort were patients in a larger study <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> with fee-for-service Medicare coverage who were discharged from the University of Pennsylvania Health System with a principal diagnosis of myocardial infarction.</s><s xml:id="_7emfAwY">Participants were recruited from March 23, 2013, to January 4, 2016, in the 60 days after discharge by sending a recruitment letter to introduce the study, followed by up to 5 telephone calls by research staff (N.M. and D.T.) who obtained verbal consent to participate.</s><s xml:id="_jFbArbr">Patients who consented were sent remote monitoring medication bottles in a system configured with reminders, financial incentives, and social support to promote adherence.</s><s xml:id="_MEASQH8">Those in the opt-out cohort were similar patients discharged from the University of Pennsylvania Health System with myocardial infarction but with insurance types making them ineligible for the larger study.</s><s xml:id="_wke5ftV">To create an opt-out frame, these patients received the remote monitoring medication bottles with the initial mailing to simulate participation as the default, but otherwise received the same recruitment processes and the same intervention if they agreed to participate.</s></p><p xml:id="_zbkn3JS"><s xml:id="_yzeRC2Y">The primary outcome was the proportion of patients mailed recruitment material who agreed to participate in the clinical study.</s><s xml:id="_uuPRS6A">We used a χ 2 test to compare the intervention and control groups, with P &lt; .05</s><s xml:id="_sevRtcg">considered statistically significant.</s><s xml:id="_buXCVCN">We also compared the daily rates of opening the medication bottle for both groups in the 3 months after device setup.</s><s xml:id="_Z8Bfptg">Demographics and data on race/ethnicity were obtained from the patients' electronic health record.</s><s xml:id="_6myETHD">We received approval from the University of Pennsylvania institutional review board and registered the protocol on clinicaltrials.gov</s><s xml:id="_HpekE6n">(NCT02139202).</s></p><p xml:id="_sybawaN"><s xml:id="_GTsNj5m">Results | We approached 235 patients in the opt-in cohort and 52 in the opt-out cohort (Table ).</s><s xml:id="_KE6nDXc">The opt-in group included only patients with fee-for-service Medicare coverage, with 140 men (59.6%) and 192 patients (81.7%) older than 65 years.</s><s xml:id="_Y85dMga">The optout group, whose members had a broader mix of insurance types, included 36 men (69.2%) and 12 patients (23.1%) older than 65 years.</s><s xml:id="_GkrmPEH">Thirty-seven patients (15.7%; 95% CI, 11.1%-20.4%)</s><s xml:id="_CfzN4ww">agreed to participate in the opt-in group compared with 20 patients (38.5%; 95% CI, 24.8%-52.1%) in the opt-out group (P &lt; .001).</s><s xml:id="_a8tQHuh">Patient-days of opening the medication bottle were similar between participants in the opt-in and opt-out groups during the 3 months after device set-up (1512 of 1709 [88.5%] vs 1635 of 1820 patient-days [89.8%], respectively; P = .67).</s></p><p xml:id="_7f6KtWg"><s xml:id="_m54t64t">Discussion | Results of this study suggest that an opt-out approach to enrollment can significantly increase participation in trials of health system interventions.</s><s xml:id="_uSFdhQm">More important, rates of adherence to use of the remote monitoring medication bottle after enrollment in the opt-out group were similar to those in the opt-in group, reflecting comparable engagement among the additional participants.</s><s xml:id="_MdKgPXZ">Opt-out procedures may increase participation by shifting the perceived default to participation because the immediate provision of the remote monitoring medication bottles creates an endowment effect (which leads individuals to place more value on an item in their possession), or by implying that the social norm is to enroll in the trial. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref></s><s xml:id="_4Q8tdv9">owever, there was a greater loss of equipment in the opt-out group (21 of 37 participants in the opt-in group [56.8%] who received devices actually used them, vs 20 of 52 participants in</s></p><p xml:id="_d6STbkn"><s xml:id="_hyNG8gH">Table.</s><s xml:id="_KhfASRb">Characteristics of Eligible Participants Characteristic Value a Opt-in Group (n = 235) Opt-out Group (n = 52) Male sex 140 (59.6)</s><s xml:id="_X723Gzw">36 (69.2) Age &gt;65 y b 192 (81.7) 12 (23.1)</s><s xml:id="_KxJRVEb">Annual income, mean, $ c 55 916 46 732 Race/ethnicity White 143 (60.9) 25 (48.1)</s><s xml:id="_pprr7An">Black 54 (23.0) 17 (32.7)</s><s xml:id="_V2qukwU">Other 12 (5.1) 4 (7.7)</s><s xml:id="_PVBnwKn">Unknown 26 (11.1) 6 (11.5)</s><s xml:id="_82gKDaP">Mailed study information Unreachable 80 (34.0) 15 (28.8)</s><s xml:id="_3UFnwRv">Declined 96 (40.9) 13 (25.0)</s><s xml:id="_ss4cD6H">Ineligible 22 (9.4) 4 (7.7)</s><s xml:id="_AfaG94y">Enrolled 37 (15.7)</s><s xml:id="_uj76YRs">20 (38.5) a Data are presented as number (percentage) of patients unless otherwise indicated.</s><s xml:id="_Pr4KTcu">b Age at date of discharge.</s><s xml:id="_HBnJVBv">c Household income data taken from Census Bureau 2007-2011 release.</s><s xml:id="_cgpGmbn">jamacardiology.com</s><s xml:id="_EdSAT4r">(Reprinted) JAMA Cardiology October 2016 Volume 1, Number 7 COMMENT &amp; RESPONSE Overtreatment of Low-Risk Patients With Atrial Fibrillation-The Quality Coin Has 2 Sides To the Editor I read with interest the article by Hsu et al 1 in the April issue of JAMA Cardiology.</s><s xml:id="_5B33BvZ">The article highlighted that less than 50% of patients with atrial fibrillation with CHADS 2 scores exceeding 3 received oral anticoagulation therapy with warfarin or a nonvitamin K antagonist anticoagulant, even in the American College of Cardiology National Cardiovascular Data Registry Practice Innovation and Clinical Excellence Registry.</s><s xml:id="_bj9sUeJ">While I agree with the authors that this represents an important undertreatment gap in high-risk patients, I would like to draw attention to another gap that receives far less attention.</s><s xml:id="_mWJrXbV">Examining Figure 2 1 illustrates a phenomenon we found in 42 834 Canadian patients with atrial fibrillation 2 : almost onethird of low-risk individuals with CHADS 2 or CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc scores of 0 received warfarin or a nonvitamin K antagonist anticoagulant.</s></p><p xml:id="_rVAEuZu"><s xml:id="_SeeHaQU">As the risks of full anticoagulation therapy exceed the potential benefits in patients at low risk for stroke, this is another example of overtreatment that deserves increased attention from researchers and policy makers.</s><s xml:id="_THvryQX">This issue is not specific to atrial fibrillation nor to cardiology.</s><s xml:id="_Y5GPzns">As pointed out by Newton et al, 3 92% of 521 national clinical performance measures for outpatient care focus on underuse, thereby "fostering a culture of more is better and inadvertently encouraging overuse."</s><s xml:id="_YCTNn5h">Moreover, all current payfor-performance programs provide incentives for meeting treatment targets, and we are not aware of any such programs that currently reward deimplementation of therapy or treating some patients less. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref></s><s xml:id="_5Wzggnn">Although overtreatment of lowrisk patients with atrial fibrillation has not yet been identified as a priority issue for Choosing Wisely, we should always be cognizant of the fact that focusing solely on undertreatment care gaps fosters a culture of intensification across the entire risk spectrum, which adversely affects overuse, the other side of the quality coin.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Finlay 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_yAM7ZqJ"><s xml:id="_EQQkVDu">A. McAlister, MD, MScAuthor Affiliation: Division of General Internal Medicine, University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada.Corresponding Author: Finlay A. McAlister, MD, MSc, Division of General Internal Medicine, University of Alberta, 11350 83 Ave NW, 5-134 C Clinical Sciences Bldg, Edmonton, AB T6G 2R7, Canada (finlay.mcalister@ualberta.ca).</s><s xml:id="_JVfu8gk">Published Online: August 17, 2016.</s><s xml:id="_wKEZDEt">doi:10.1001/jamacardio.2016.2270.</s><s xml:id="_ShKEqS8">Conflict of Interest Disclosures: The author has completed and submitted the ICMJE Form for Disclosure of Potential Conflicts of Interest and none were reported.</s><s xml:id="_npQ8ypQ">Hsu JC, Maddox TM, Kennedy KF, et al.</s><s xml:id="_fZXSgek">Oral anticoagulant therapy prescription in patients with atrial fibrillation across the spectrum of stroke risk: insights from the NCDR PINNACLE Registry.</s><s xml:id="_CrQN23a">JAMA Cardiol.</s><s xml:id="_TXUGhuU">2016;1(1):55-62.</s><s xml:id="_S4yjXaN">doi: 10.1001/jamacardio.2015.0374.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_3Csre9y"><s xml:id="_rJfDMFp">Sandhu RK, Bakal JA, Ezekowitz JA, McAlister FA.</s><s xml:id="_4FmerAg">Risk stratification schemes, anticoagulation use and outcomes: the risk-treatment paradox in patients with newly diagnosed non-valvular atrial fibrillation.</s><s xml:id="_VFYaWF4">Heart.</s><s xml:id="_k9yQzu7">2011;97(24):2046-2050.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p xml:id="_dbMTZfZ"><s xml:id="_8j4u79V">JAMA Cardiology October 2016 Volume 1, Number 7 (Reprinted) jamacardiology.com</s><s xml:id="_Vd6yYRw">Copyright 2016 American Medical Association.</s><s xml:id="_gBhFhSh">All rights reserved.</s><s xml:id="_5NUnJwd">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com</s><s xml:id="_4gXU3N6">by University of Iowa user on 07/28/2025</s></p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_q8p4pzn"><p xml:id="_J4VDGrM"><s xml:id="_x7swNtk">Role of the Funder/Sponsor: The funding source had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_hUDTTCP">Participation in cancer clinical trials: race-, sex-, and age-based disparities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Murthy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Krumholz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Gross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1001/jama.291.22.2720</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_eQHN67s">JAMA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">291</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2720" to="2726" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Murthy VH, Krumholz HM, Gross CP. Participation in cancer clinical trials: race-, sex-, and age-based disparities. JAMA. 2004;291(22):2720-2726.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_As9uKqs">Asymmetric paternalism to improve health behaviors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Loewenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Brennan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Volpp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1001/jama.298.20.2415</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_754tdWx">JAMA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">298</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2415" to="2417" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Loewenstein G, Brennan T, Volpp KG. Asymmetric paternalism to improve health behaviors. JAMA. 2007;298(20):2415-2417.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_hUEBsu6">Medicine. Do defaults save lives?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Goldstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1126/science.1091721</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_fWdZH5N">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">302</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5649</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1338" to="1339" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Johnson EJ, Goldstein D. Medicine. Do defaults save lives? Science. 2003;302 (5649):1338-1339.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_fnAQNWc">Rationale and design of a randomized trial of automated hovering for post-myocardial infarction patients: the HeartStrong program</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Troxel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Asch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mehta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ahj.2016.06.006</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_FZeKWkH">Am Heart J</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>In press</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Troxel AB, Asch DA, Mehta SJ, et al. Rationale and design of a randomized trial of automated hovering for post-myocardial infarction patients: the HeartStrong program. Am Heart J. In press.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_vaWY4tN">Experimental tests of the endowment effect and the Coase theorem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kahneman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Knetsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Thaler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1086/261737</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_k48kBKN">J Polit Econ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1325" to="1348" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kahneman D, Knetsch JL, Thaler RH. Experimental tests of the endowment effect and the Coase theorem. J Polit Econ. 1990;98(6):1325-1348. doi:10.1086 /261737.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
