<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_7zs9N92">CHEERS Checklist Items to include when reporting economic evaluations of health interventions The ISPOR CHEERS Task Force Report, Consolidated Health Economic Evaluation Reporting Standards (CHEERS)-Explanation and Elaboration: A Report of the ISPOR Health Economic Evaluations Publication Guidelines</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_bc9m7TQ">CHEERS Checklist Items to include when reporting economic evaluations of health interventions The ISPOR CHEERS Task Force Report, Consolidated Health Economic Evaluation Reporting Standards (CHEERS)-Explanation and Elaboration: A Report of the ISPOR Health Economic Evaluations Publication Guidelines</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">22837D4836567936BCD4DA837AF05442</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T06:23+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_SMmDzCF"><p xml:id="_dCqCM5v"><s xml:id="_a3YEche">Identify the study as an economic evaluation or use more specific</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_gznxBAf">Introduction</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_pTxGrHE">Background and objectives 3</head><p xml:id="_h8ezKhM"><s xml:id="_nSBru8n">Provide an explicit statement of the broader context for the study.</s></p><p xml:id="_NXpfued"><s xml:id="_m5kHvaU">Present the study question and its relevance for health policy or practice decisions.</s><s xml:id="_RyrN2dU">1 2 3 8 7 7 7 8 8 13 11b Synthesis-based estimates: Describe fully the methods used for identification of included studies and synthesis of clinical effectiveness data.</s><s xml:id="_useXNz5">Measurement and valuation of preference based outcomes 12 If applicable, describe the population and methods used to elicit preferences for outcomes.</s><s xml:id="_t3ZZFus">Estimating resources and costs 13a Single study-based economic evaluation: Describe approaches used to estimate resource use associated with the alternative interventions.</s><s xml:id="_jN7mZTM">Describe primary or secondary research methods for valuing each resource item in terms of its unit cost.</s><s xml:id="_C2sPEZM">Describe any adjustments made to approximate to opportunity costs.</s><s xml:id="_ZZsNjec">13b Model-based economic evaluation: Describe approaches and data sources used to estimate resource use associated with model health states.</s><s xml:id="_R5Hqy44">Describe primary or secondary research methods for valuing each resource item in terms of its unit cost.</s><s xml:id="_9FAw6qC">Describe any adjustments made to approximate to opportunity costs.</s><s xml:id="_xH2GQ37">Currency, price date, and conversion 14 Report the dates of the estimated resource quantities and unit costs.</s><s xml:id="_uwhFPVG">Describe methods for adjusting estimated unit costs to the year of reported costs if necessary.</s><s xml:id="_vfC52ay">Describe methods for converting costs into a common currency base and the exchange rate.</s><s xml:id="_CWtamtt">Choice of model 15 Describe and give reasons for the specific type of decisionanalytical model used.</s><s xml:id="_MtU7jSr">Providing a figure to show model structure is strongly recommended.</s><s xml:id="_Jgv4zfH">Assumptions 16 Describe all structural or other assumptions underpinning the decision-analytical model.</s><s xml:id="_7DmwPsA">Analytical methods 17 Describe all analytical methods supporting the evaluation.</s><s xml:id="_dvXmKKR">This could include methods for dealing with skewed, missing, or censored data; extrapolation methods; methods for pooling data; approaches to validate or make adjustments (such as half cycle corrections) to a model; and methods for handling population heterogeneity and uncertainty.</s><s xml:id="_d6Sn6AX">Results Study parameters 18 Report the values, ranges, references, and, if used, probability distributions for all parameters.</s><s xml:id="_Vsabtck">Report reasons or sources for distributions used to represent uncertainty where appropriate.</s><s xml:id="_DdAQbsH">Providing a table to show the input values is strongly recommended.</s><s xml:id="_ZnsWJYY">Incremental costs and outcomes 19 For each intervention, report mean values for the main categories of estimated costs and outcomes of interest, as well as mean differences between the comparator groups.</s><s xml:id="_t7s82aw">If applicable, report incremental cost-effectiveness ratios.</s><s xml:id="_hu9gqn8">Characterising uncertainty 20a Single study-based economic evaluation: Describe the effects of sampling uncertainty for the estimated incremental cost and incremental effectiveness parameters, together with the impact 9 12-15 9 12-16 10,11 13,14 12,15 of methodological assumptions (such as discount rate, study perspective).</s><s xml:id="_nE3HuT2">20b Model-based economic evaluation: Describe the effects on the results of uncertainty for all input parameters, and uncertainty related to the structure of the model and assumptions.</s><s xml:id="_s73fqpX">Characterising heterogeneity 21 If applicable, report differences in costs, outcomes, or costeffectiveness that can be explained by variations between subgroups of patients with different baseline characteristics or other observed variability in effects that are not reducible by more information.</s><s xml:id="_CddbyKf">Discussion Study findings, limitations, generalisability, and current knowledge 22 Summarise key study findings and describe how they support the conclusions reached.</s><s xml:id="_f7C7kVG">Discuss limitations and the generalisability of the findings and how the findings fit with current knowledge.</s><s xml:id="_xF67khR">Other Source of funding 23 Describe how the study was funded and the role of the funder in the identification, design, conduct, and reporting of the analysis.</s><s xml:id="_uV7vybJ">Describe other non-monetary sources of support.</s><s xml:id="_QsF8Qtv">Conflicts of interest 24 Describe any potential for conflict of interest of study contributors in accordance with journal policy.</s><s xml:id="_8SHTGpS">In the absence of a journal policy, we recommend authors comply with International Committee of Medical Journal Editors recommendations.</s><s xml:id="_85WHjyy">For consistency, the CHEERS Statement checklist format is based on the format of the CONSORT statement checklist The ISPOR CHEERS Task Force Report provides examples and further discussion of the 24-item CHEERS Checklist and the CHEERS Statement.</s><s xml:id="_Dmx8356">It may be accessed via the Value in Health link or via the ISPOR Health Economic Evaluation Publication Guidelines -CHEERS: Good Reporting Practices webpage: <ref type="url" target="http://www.ispor.org/TaskForces/EconomicPubGuidelines.asp">http://www.ispor.org/TaskForces/EconomicPubGuidelines.asp</ref></s><s xml:id="_YkE9q42">The citation for the CHEERS Task Force Report is: Husereau D, Drummond M, Petrou S, et al.</s><s xml:id="_uqDsce9">Consolidated health economic evaluation reporting standards (CHEERS)-Explanation and elaboration: A report of the ISPOR health economic evaluations publication guidelines good reporting practices task force.</s><s xml:id="_d3ZxhJy">Value Health 2013;16:231-50.</s><s xml:id="_wCeakAc">18,19 20-22</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_jqQsv6P">Methods</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_2PaQTMe"><s xml:id="_2YTyr28">the base case population and subgroups analysed, including why they were chosen.</s><s xml:id="_rN7jcZb">Setting and location 5 State relevant aspects of the system(s) in which the decision(s) need(s) to be made.</s><s xml:id="_wekzEdR">Study perspective 6 Describe the perspective of the study and relate this to the costs being evaluated.</s><s xml:id="_HUeVHEn">Comparators 7 Describe the interventions or strategies being compared and state why they were chosen.</s><s xml:id="_zN9k3Md">Time horizon 8 State the time horizon(s) over which costs and consequences are being evaluated and say why appropriate.</s><s xml:id="_2qCNaMk">Discount rate 9 Report the choice of discount rate(s) used for costs and outcomes and say why appropriate.</s><s xml:id="_ccwmqwF">Choice of health outcomes 10 Describe what outcomes were used as the measure(s) of benefit in the evaluation and their relevance for the type of analysis performed.</s><s xml:id="_mfT7ecp">Measurement of effectiveness 11a Single study-based estimates: Describe fully the design features of the single effectiveness study and why the single study was a sufficient source of clinical effectiveness data.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>


			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_6KfShwn"><p xml:id="_cCECCPA"><s xml:id="_RsuAqrM">Good Reporting Practices Task Force, provides examples and further discussion of the 24-item CHEERS Checklist and the CHEERS Statement.</s><s xml:id="_BuPRCqd">It may be accessed via the Value in Health or via the ISPOR Health Economic Evaluation Publication Guidelines -CHEERS: Good Reporting Practices webpage: <ref type="url" target="http://www.ispor.org/TaskForces/EconomicPubGuidelines.asp">http://www.ispor.org/TaskForces/EconomicPubGuidelines.asp</ref></s><s xml:id="_zTtZ7em">Section/item Item No Recommendation Reported on page No/ line No</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
