<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_9jSrpHz">A Randomized, Controlled Trial of Financial Incentives for Smoking Cessation</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">General Electric</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">GE</orgName>
					<idno type="DOI" subtype="crossref">https://doi.org/10.13039/100004313</idno>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Aetna</orgName>
					<idno type="DOI" subtype="crossref">https://doi.org/10.13039/100003601</idno>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Pennsylvania Department of Health</orgName>
					<idno type="DOI" subtype="crossref">https://doi.org/10.13039/100004897</idno>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_a4f2HVq #_Ssc9nTj">
					<orgName type="full">Korea Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">KCDC</orgName>
					<idno type="DOI" subtype="crossref">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100003669</idno>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Pfizer</orgName>
					<idno type="DOI" subtype="crossref">https://doi.org/10.13039/100004319</idno>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Merck and MedStar</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Kevin</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Volpp</surname></persName>
							<email>volpp70@wharton.upenn.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Andrea</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Troxel</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Sc.D</roleName><forename type="first">Mark</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Pauly</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Henry</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Glick</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Andrea</forename><surname>Puig</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Asch</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.B</roleName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Galvin</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.B</roleName><forename type="first">Jingsan</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.S</roleName><forename type="first">Fei</forename><surname>Wan</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jill</forename><surname>Deguzman</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Elizabeth</forename><surname>Corbett</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Janet</forename><surname>Weiner</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Janet</forename><surname>Audrain-Mcgovern</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">From the Center for Health Equity Re- search and Promotion , Philadelphia Vet- erans Affairs Medical Center Center for Health Incentives , Leonard Davis Institute of Health Econom- ics Department of Health Care Management , the Wharton School the Center for Clinical Epidemiology and Biostatistics and Department of Biosta- tistics and Epidemiology (A. University of Pennsylvania ; the Depart- ment of Medicine ( Transdisciplinary Tobacco Use Research Center , Depart- ment of Psychiatry (J.A.-M.) , University of Pennsylvania School of Medicine -all in Philadelphia; General Electric , Fairfield , CT</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Center for Health Equity Re- search and Promotion</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Center for Health Incentives</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Department of Health Care Management</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep4">Center for Clinical Epidemiology and Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep5">Department of Biosta- tistics and Epidemiology (A</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep6">Depart- ment of Medicine (</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep7">Depart- ment of Psychiatry (J.A.-M.)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Philadelphia Vet- erans Affairs Medical Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Leonard Davis Institute of Health Econom- ics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">the Wharton School</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">University of Pennsylvania</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit5">Transdisciplinary Tobacco Use Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit6">University of Pennsylvania School of Medicine -all in Philadelphia; General Electric</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Fairfield</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Yale University School of Medicine , New Haven , CT sion of General Internal Medicine and De- partment of Health Care Management ,</note>
								<orgName type="department">sion of General Internal Medicine and De- partment of Health Care Management</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">University of Pennsylvania School of Med- icine and the Wharton School , 1232 Block- ley Hall , 423 Guardian Dr. , Philadelphia , PA 19104-6021 ,</note>
								<orgName type="department">School of Med- icine and the Wharton School</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pennsylvania</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1232 Block- ley Hall 423 Guardian Dr.</addrLine>
									<postCode>19104-6021</postCode>
									<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Mabf8fk">A Randomized, Controlled Trial of Financial Incentives for Smoking Cessation</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">33DA772832D61F8C571BCD2AD8904B73</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T07:15+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_8mmdADe"><p xml:id="_mBrNwA9"><s xml:id="_pthwGEg">In this study of employees of one large company, financial incentives for smoking cessation significantly increased the rates of smoking cessation.</s><s xml:id="_AbUdHuw">(ClinicalTrials.gov</s><s xml:id="_HPfqpHM">number, NCT00128375.)</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="756.0"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="756.0"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="756.0"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="756.0"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="756.0"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="756.0"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="756.0"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="756.0"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="756.0"/>
		<surface n="10" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="756.0"/>
		<surface n="11" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="756.0"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_BF2RKWS">Background</head><p xml:id="_5mg73ap"><s xml:id="_qENQfD7">Smoking is the leading preventable cause of premature death in the United States.</s><s xml:id="_RWqZGY3">Previous studies of financial incentives for smoking cessation in work settings have not shown that such incentives have significant effects on cessation rates, but these studies have had limited power, and the incentives used may have been insufficient.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_cUfbF8E">Methods</head><p xml:id="_HcmKEsu"><s xml:id="_Pdx8Khy">We randomly assigned 878 employees of a multinational company based in the United States to receive information about smoking-cessation programs (442 employees) or to receive information about programs plus financial incentives (436 employees).</s><s xml:id="_AacyYCJ">The financial incentives were $100 for completion of a smoking-cessation program, $250 for cessation of smoking within 6 months after study enrollment, as confirmed by a biochemical test, and $400 for abstinence for an additional 6 months after the initial cessation, as confirmed by a biochemical test.</s><s xml:id="_t5zHqYG">Individual participants were stratified according to work site, heavy or nonheavy smoking, and income.</s><s xml:id="_MKF94Qn">The primary end point was smoking cessation 9 or 12 months after enrollment, depending on whether initial cessation was reported at 3 or 6 months.</s><s xml:id="_JGXKfS5">Secondary end points were smoking cessation within the first 6 months after enrollment and rates of participation in and completion of smoking-cessation programs.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_6VxJPgM">Results</head><p xml:id="_P7nGu9t"><s xml:id="_Xhz9CqU">The incentive group had significantly higher rates of smoking cessation than did the information-only group 9 or 12 months after enrollment (14.7% vs. 5.0%, P&lt;0.001) and 15 or 18 months after enrollment (9.4% vs. 3.6%, P&lt;0.001).</s><s xml:id="_NDbUH6c">Incentive-group participants also had significantly higher rates of enrollment in a smoking-cessation program (15.4% vs. 5.4%, P&lt;0.001), completion of a smoking-cessation program (10.8% vs. 2.5%, P&lt;0.001), and smoking cessation within the first 6 months after enrollment (20.9% vs. 11.8%,</s><s xml:id="_aEuxaD2">P&lt;0.001).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_5WVeGnq">S</head><p xml:id="_VGj6YAP"><s xml:id="_U4ndBMe">moking remains the leading preventable cause of premature death in the United States, accounting for approximately 438,000 deaths each year. 1 Seventy percent of smokers report that they want to quit, 2 but annually only 2 to 3% of smokers succeed. <ref type="bibr">3,</ref><ref type="bibr">4</ref></s><s xml:id="_c7892m5">Although smoking-cessation programs and pharmacologic therapies have been associated with higher rates of cessation, rates of participation in such programs and use of such therapies are low. <ref type="bibr">5,</ref><ref type="bibr">6</ref></s><s xml:id="_CgGBfGb">ork sites offer a promising venue for encouraging smoking cessation because employers are likely to bear many of the excess health care costs and productivity losses that are due to missed work among smokers.</s><s xml:id="_7H82rBN">In addition, existing channels of communication can be used to reach smokers and reinforce healthful behavior choices.</s><s xml:id="_TvcJB6a">Previous studies have shown that providing smokers with financial incentives to stop smoking increases enrollment in smoking-cessation programs and short-term cessation rates, 7-10 but the studies have not shown significant increases in long-term cessation rates.</s><s xml:id="_55nJMfP">Similarly, studies of financial-incentive programs in work settings have not shown significant differences in long-term cessation rates, 11 though the studies generally were limited by small sample sizes and weak financial incentives.</s></p><p xml:id="_T3fy3a5"><s xml:id="_tnHCJqY">In this randomized, controlled trial involving employees at a large, multinational company based in the United States, we tested the effectiveness of a financial incentive of up to $750 in improving long-term rates of smoking cessation.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_DFga4G9">Me thods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_UPkHayh">Study Population</head><p xml:id="_2zkW9bE"><s xml:id="_3bqEvdj">We recruited study participants from February 2005 through November 2006 among employees at company work sites throughout the United States.</s><s xml:id="_DdVRgrD">Potential participants were identified with the use of a survey that asked employees about their smoking habits, their use of other tobacco products, and their willingness to be contacted by researchers from the University of Pennsylvania about participation in a smoking-cessation study.</s><s xml:id="_uMbMfhN">These surveys were distributed through the firm's intranet and, at sites with high proportions of employees who did not have intranet access, through on-site recruiting.</s><s xml:id="_gZ34RQ2">Employees were eligible to participate if they were at least 18 years of age and if they reported that they were currently smoking five or more cigarettes per day.</s><s xml:id="_Dp4EsuQ">Employees were not included in the study if they were currently using tobacco products other than cigarettes or if they planned to leave the firm within 18 months.</s><s xml:id="_txyFDPP">All participants were followed for at least 12 months; only those with a confirmed negative result within the first 12 months on a cotinine test, a test that is used for biochemical verification of self-reported abstinence, were followed for an additional 6 months.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_wXJ3T6r">Study Protocol</head><p xml:id="_ZmuJxpy"><s xml:id="_FNXAkMa">The protocol was approved by the institutional review board at the University of Pennsylvania, and all participants provided written informed consent before randomization.</s><s xml:id="_24ysMBX">All study participants received information about community-based smoking-cessation resources within 20 miles of their work site, as well as the standard health benefits provided by the firm, such as coverage of physician visits and bupropion or other drugs prescribed to promote cessation of tobacco use.</s><s xml:id="_ygesAyg">Participants in the incentive group were also informed that they would receive financial incentives for completion of a community-based smoking-cessation program ($100); for smoking cessation, confirmed with the use of a cotinine test, within 6 months after study enrollment ($250); and for continued abstinence for an additional 6 months after the initial cessation ($400).</s></p><p xml:id="_dHGXT4b"><s xml:id="_X5TRn8d">All participants were contacted 3 months after enrollment and asked whether they had stopped smoking.</s><s xml:id="_fSB2vby">Participants who reported complete abstinence (not even a puff of a cigarette) for at least 7 days before being contacted were interviewed so that we could obtain a more extensive assessment of smoking behavior.</s><s xml:id="_GmK6q9V">Participants who did not report complete abstinence were recontacted 3 months later (i.e., 6 months after enrollment) for the full follow-up assessment.</s><s xml:id="_MgGxSAY">Six months after completing their first full interview (i.e., at 9 months for those who reported quitting at 3 months; at 12 months for those who were interviewed at 6 months), everyone was interviewed again.</s><s xml:id="_jTbuT2M">Participants who reported during any follow-up interview that they had stopped smoking were asked to provide a saliva or urine sample for confirmation of smoking cessation with the use of a cotinine test.</s><s xml:id="_QfUBHhh">Participants with negative results of cotinine tests at both the interview conducted at 3 or 6 months and the interview conducted at 9 or 12 months were also interviewed 12 months after completion of their initial full interview (i.e., at 15 or 18 months).</s></p><p xml:id="_SGbsSYg"><s xml:id="_4T9HMRZ">Participants received $20 per interview for participating in telephone interviews at baseline, at 3 or 6 months, at 9 or 12 months, and at 15 or 18 months.</s><s xml:id="_DMkh7ed">After each interview, participants who reported that they had stopped smoking received $25 for submitting a sample for biochemical verification of the cotinine level.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_uskMCq5">Randomization Procedures</head><p xml:id="_p8ZhfPN"><s xml:id="_tZStwBf">Participants were randomly assigned to a study group after they provided informed consent.</s><s xml:id="_ZhmsbtD">Randomization was performed in permuted blocks of four and was stratified according to work site, income (&lt;200%, 200 to 500%, or &gt;500% of the federal poverty level, which was $9,800 for a single person and $20,000 for a family of four in 2006), and heavy or nonheavy smoking (with heavy smoking defined as two or more packs of cigarettes per day).</s><s xml:id="_NnfXzKW">The randomized assignments were concealed until all eligibility criteria had been entered in an electronic tracking system; however, blinding could not be maintained after this point because of the nature of the intervention.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Kmj2MkB">Assessments of End Points</head><p xml:id="_YuP4rdU"><s xml:id="_5RDHNTy">The primary end point was the participant's selfreport of abstinence at both 3 and 9 months or at both 6 and 12 months after study enrollment.</s><s xml:id="_uBrWcdf">Abstinence was biochemically confirmed by a negative result of a cotinine test performed on a saliva or urine sample.</s><s xml:id="_VazFHX4">Self-reported continuous abstinence from all tobacco products was defined as abstinence for a minimum of 7 days before the 3-or 6-month interview (point prevalence) and abstinence for the duration of the period from the 3-or 6-month interview to the 9-or 12-month interview (prevalence of prolonged abstinence).</s></p><p xml:id="_m5TvxEh"><s xml:id="_48fQQ4U">Secondary end points included enrollment in a smoking-cessation program; completion of a smoking-cessation program; rates of smoking cessation within 6 months after study enrollment; and rates of smoking cessation at 3, 9, and 15 months or 6, 12, and 18 months after study enrollment.</s><s xml:id="_KEgE9je">Participants were classified as having completed the smoking-cessation program if they provided a certificate of completion from the sponsoring organization.</s></p><p xml:id="_Ug3zPbF"><s xml:id="_TmJEKSZ">All follow-up assessments were conducted with</s></p><p xml:id="_bgKgu2c"><s xml:id="_hFxV4zg">Table 1.</s><s xml:id="_wqd9xya">Characteristics of the Study Participants.*</s><s xml:id="_gaEQWjm">Characteristic Control Group (N = 442) Incentive Group (N = 436) Mean age (yr) 44.4 45.5 Male sex (%) 64.9 65.6 Race or ethnic group (%) † White 89.3 91.5 Black 5.2 4.4 Hispanic 4.1 4.1 Other 5.4 4.1 Level of education (%) High school or lower 25.6 25.2 Some college or completion of college 39.6 40.8</s><s xml:id="_s9vNaZf">Beyond college 34.8 33.9 Income (%) &lt;200% of the poverty level 1.6 1.8 200-500% of the poverty level 34.6 32.1 &gt;500% of the poverty level 63.8 66.1 Smoking habits Mean cigarettes per day (no.)</s><s xml:id="_ChKjfCC">19.7 20.1 Smoking &gt;2 packs per day (%) 6.1 5.1 Mean previous attempts to quit (no.) 6.7 5.7 Stage of change (%) ‡ Precontemplation 15.6 15.1 Contemplation 63.8 67.0 Preparation 20.6 17.9 Self-assessed health (%) Poor 2.0 1.2 Fair 9.3 8.5 Good 32.1 33.7 Very good 45.9 42.7 Excellent 10.6 14.0 Fagerström score for nicotine dependence (%) § &lt;6 68.1 66.5 ≥6 31.9 33.5</s></p><p xml:id="_hm9FbBd"><s xml:id="_7G3fenh">* There were no significant differences between the control and incentive groups for any of the variables listed.</s><s xml:id="_4csmxgU">† Race or ethnic group was self-reported.</s><s xml:id="_W5cwsHU">One participant in the control group did not report race or ethnic group and therefore was not included in the denominator for the percentages.</s><s xml:id="_ns82H4v">‡ Stage of change refers to the smoker's readiness, at baseline, to quit, as defined by DiClemente et al. <ref type="bibr">16</ref> and Prochaska et al. 17 § The Fagerström Test for Nicotine Dependence 14 has a range of 0 to 10, with higher scores indicating more nicotine dependence; a score of 6 or greater was used to classify participants as highly dependent on nicotine. 15</s></p><p xml:id="_ns7qnbR"><s xml:id="_UQdykSy">The New England Journal of Medicine is produced by NEJM Group, a division of the Massachusetts Medical Society.</s><s xml:id="_F9J4PWD">Downloaded from nejm.org on July 31, 2025.</s><s xml:id="_udVpRUf">Copyright © 2009 Massachusetts Medical Society.</s><s xml:id="_zS6wdNy">All rights reserved, including those for text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies.</s></p><p xml:id="_3PcfdUf"><s xml:id="_aVFTMjf">the use of a telephone interview.</s><s xml:id="_3Nu8Cxk">Self-reported cessation was verified by saliva cotinine tests (with a cotinine level of &lt;15 ng per milliliter considered to be an indication of smoking cessation) 12 or by urine cotinine tests (with a level of &lt;2 ng per milliliter considered to be an indication of smoking cessation). 13</s><s xml:id="_ZDzbaXG">Urine cotinine tests were used only in the case of participants who were using nicotine-replacement therapy, in whom testing of anabasine and anatabine levels in the urine was performed.</s><s xml:id="_Ed3sdHC">Participants who reported abstinence but who had saliva or urine cotinine levels above the cutoff points were classified as smokers.</s><s xml:id="_FEDCG5h">Participants who were lost to follow-up were classified as relapsed smokers.</s></p><p xml:id="_y89xK7h"><s xml:id="_xUPEK9P">The collection of samples was coordinated by the study staff in conjunction with the health-promotion staff at the firm and, at small work sites that did not have onsite health facilities, through contract with Examination Management Services (Scottsdale, AZ).</s><s xml:id="_PwnSRtJ">Participants' identities were confirmed and samples were analyzed at the Clinical Pharmacology Laboratory at the University of California, San Francisco.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_E8f3Y2s">Baseline Variables</head><p xml:id="_jYtSrtK"><s xml:id="_EPTyp6F">The pretreatment level of nicotine dependence was assessed according to the number of cigarettes smoked per day, the number of years of smoking, and the score on the Fagerström Test for Nicotine Dependence 14 (which has a range of 0 to 10, with higher scores indicating more nicotine dependence); participants with a score of 6 or greater were classified as highly dependent on nicotine.</s></p><p xml:id="_e4twHqA"><s xml:id="_nn4GCGV">15 33p9 878 Underwent randomization 1903 Patients were assessed for eligibility 1025 Were excluded 771 Were ineligible 254 Did not give consent 436 Were assigned to incentive group 50 Were lost to follow-up by 6 mo 16 Withdrew by 6 mo 43 Were lost to follow-up between 6 and 12 mo 13 Withdrew between 6 and 12 mo 4 Were lost to follow-up between 12 and 18 mo 1 Withdrew between 12 and 18 mo 442 Were assigned to control group 47 Were lost to follow-up by 6 mo 12 Withdrew by 6 mo 35 Were lost to follow-up between 6 and 12 mo 12 Withdrew between 6 and 12 mo 2 Were lost to follow-up between 12 and 18 mo 0 Withdrew between 12 and 18 mo AUTHOR: FIGURE: JOB: ISSUE: 4-C H/T RETAKE SIZE ICM CASE EMail Line H/T Combo Revised AUTHOR, PLEASE NOTE: Figure has been redrawn and type has been reset.</s><s xml:id="_fUqNWJv">Please check carefully.</s><s xml:id="_WJN6yJe">REG F Enon 1st 2nd 3rd Volpp 1 of 2 01-29-09 ARTIST: ts 36005 Figure 1.</s><s xml:id="_SHFmtG6">Assessment for Eligibility, Randomization, and Follow-up.</s><s xml:id="_x9hRPt5">The New England Journal of Medicine is produced by NEJM Group, a division of the Massachusetts Medical Society.</s><s xml:id="_esArudd">Downloaded from nejm.org on July 31, 2025.</s><s xml:id="_CETNcag">Copyright © 2009 Massachusetts Medical Society.</s><s xml:id="_KWkzHgu">All rights reserved, including those for text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies.</s></p><p xml:id="_Rrn9ySU"><s xml:id="_42C8b4f">We also collected information on income, work site, baseline health status, and interest in quitting, as measured by baseline readiness to stop smoking (i.e., the "stage of change," as defined by DiClemente et al. <ref type="bibr">16</ref> and Prochaska et al. 17 ).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_YDAXNXN">Statistical Analysis</head><p xml:id="_nQxFsAF"><s xml:id="_MrQf4kH">The primary analysis was an unadjusted intentionto-treat analysis of the difference in biochemically confirmed cessation rates between the incentive and control groups at both 3 and 9 months or at both 6 and 12 months.</s><s xml:id="_S9MHkQQ">The analysis was performed with the use of Pearson's chi-square test, or with the use of Fisher's exact test, if there were five or fewer participants per cell.</s><s xml:id="_hd9v6S6">We used a similar approach to estimate differences in rates of cessa-tion within 6 months after enrollment; rates of enrollment in and completion of smoking-cessation programs; and cessation rates at 3, 9, and 15 months or 6, 12, and 18 months after study enrollment.</s><s xml:id="_pSGQqXJ">Unadjusted odds ratios for cessation were estimated and were compared with odds ratios that were adjusted for the stratification variables (work site, degree of nicotine dependence, and income) as well as the set of baseline covariates shown in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>; variable-selection methods were not applied.</s><s xml:id="_8fnvHy4">The similarity of the study groups with respect to covariates at baseline was analyzed by the chi-square test for categorical variables and the Student's t-test or Wilcoxon rank-sum test for continuous variables, as appropriate.</s></p><p xml:id="_GdvvKhC"><s xml:id="_VMJ9D9T">Although subgroup analyses were not prespeci-</s></p><p xml:id="_QW9J8tn"><s xml:id="_Aka6v8y">Table 2. Smoking-Cessation End Points According to Group Assignment.*</s><s xml:id="_AH2CjwR">End Point Control Group (N = 442) Incentive Group (N = 436) P Value no.</s><s xml:id="_YrwT2aF">(%) Enrollment in smoking-cessation program Participation in program 24 (5.4) 67 (15.4) &lt;0.001 Completion of program 11 (2.5) 47 (10.8) &lt;0.001 Smoking cessation at 3 or 6 mo Self-reported 62 (14.0) 102 (23.4) &lt;0.001 Confirmed 52 (11.8) 91 (20.9) &lt;0.001</s><s xml:id="_4AwN8Dq">No sample submitted 9 (2.0) 9 (2.1) 0.79 Positive sample submitted 1 (0.2) 2 (0.5) 0.56 Smoking cessation at 3 or 6 mo with continued abstinence through 9 or 12 mo Self-reported 27 (6.1)</s><s xml:id="_ZbaRjrV">66 (15.1) 0.002 Confirmed 22 (5.0) 64 (14.7) &lt;0.001</s><s xml:id="_VbZGkS4">No sample submitted 5 (1.1) 2 (0.5) 0.06 Positive sample submitted 0 0 Self-reported relapse 21 (4.8)</s><s xml:id="_cqnP5yz">21 (4.8) 0.96 Continued abstinence at 15 or 18 mo among participants who quit at 3 or 6 mo and remained abstinent through 9 or 12 mo Self-reported 17 (3.8)</s><s xml:id="_kwqUeUh">47 (10.8) &lt;0.001 Confirmed 16 (3.6)</s><s xml:id="_Q6j9PPS">41 (9.4) &lt;0.001</s><s xml:id="_ZN3BkPn">No sample submitted 1 (0.2) 6 (1.4) 0.03 Positive sample submitted 0 0 Self-reported relapse 3 (0.7) 12 (2.8)</s><s xml:id="_h5Zsc3p">0.02 * Smoking cessation was confirmed by means of a negative result on a cotinine test.</s><s xml:id="_cMuuXHF">The New England Journal of Medicine is produced by NEJM Group, a division of the Massachusetts Medical Society.</s><s xml:id="_CX3wUct">Downloaded from nejm.org on July 31, 2025.</s><s xml:id="_xdErf7t">Copyright © 2009 Massachusetts Medical Society.</s><s xml:id="_PTuVvgV">All rights reserved, including those for text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies.</s></p><p xml:id="_qRYdKJT"><s xml:id="_5s5NSeJ">Table 3.</s><s xml:id="_rynTupv">Odds Ratios for Long-Term (9-or 12-Month) Smoking Cessation.</s><s xml:id="_FBAYSjm">Variable Odds Ratio (95% CI) P Value Unadjusted model Incentive group 3.28 (1.98-5.44)</s><s xml:id="_qJ6MnkK">&lt;0.001</s><s xml:id="_vnvGaB2">Control group 1.00 Model adjusted for stratification variables only Study group &lt;0.001 Incentive 3.19 (1.91-5.30)</s><s xml:id="_ewpB5Jr">Control 1.00 Work site* 0.12 Smoking status † 0.15 Heavy 0.34 (0.08-1.45)</s><s xml:id="_gr9eJTK">Nonheavy 1.00 Poverty level 0.02 &gt;500% of the poverty level 0.96 (0.20-4.63) 200-500% of the poverty level 0.43 (0.08-2.16) &lt;200% of the poverty level 1.00 Model adjusted for all variables ‡ Study group &lt;0.001 Incentive 3.16 (1.88-5.32)</s><s xml:id="_g9VJmUV">Control 1.00 Work site* 0.20 Age 0.87 ≥40 yr 1.05 (0.58-1.90) &lt;40 yr 1.00 Sex 0.39 Male 0.80 (0.48-1.33)</s><s xml:id="_jtjeqg4">Female 1.00 Race 0.69 Black 1.02 (0.32-3.20) White 1.00 Other 0.50 (0.10-2.44)</s><s xml:id="_HwcDdvT">Ethnic group 0.80 Hispanic 1.20 (0.30-4.88)</s><s xml:id="_kBcKz6D">Non-Hispanic 1.00 Level of education 0.69 Beyond college 0.92 (0.49-1.74)</s><s xml:id="_XVtPGST">College 0.78 (0.42-1.43)</s><s xml:id="_zssnXCb">High school or less 1.00 Poverty level 0.04 &gt;500% of the poverty level 1.03 (0.18-5.79) 200-500% of the poverty level 0.48 (0.08-2.75) &lt;200% of the poverty level 1.00 The New England Journal of Medicine is produced by NEJM Group, a division of the Massachusetts Medical Society.</s><s xml:id="_V2NE3AN">Downloaded from nejm.org on July 31, 2025.</s><s xml:id="_7RcZepM">Copyright © 2009 Massachusetts Medical Society.</s><s xml:id="_VCwMmYj">All rights reserved, including those for text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies.</s></p><p xml:id="_WUzd29Z"><s xml:id="_SreqxR5">fied, we looked at cessation rates in subgroups that were defined by seven baseline variables: sex, income (&lt;200%, 200 to 500%, and &gt;500% of the federal poverty level), heavy smoking (≥2 packs per day) or nonheavy smoking, number of previous attempts to quit (0 to 2, 3 or 4, or ≥5), stage of quitting as defined by Prochaska et al. 17 (precontemplation, contemplation, or preparation), selfassessed health (poor, fair, good, very good, or excellent), and nicotine dependence as assessed by the score on the Fagerström Test for Nicotine Dependence (&lt;6 or ≥6).</s><s xml:id="_uGdNwur">The homogeneity of the association (i.e., interaction) between the group assignment and cessation rates across subgroups was assessed with the use of the Cochran-Mantel-Haenszel test.</s><s xml:id="_3mDxvfZ">Within each subgroup, rates of cessation in the incentive and control groups were compared with the use of chi-square tests.</s></p><p xml:id="_bYNWMYj"><s xml:id="_s7yEWSY">Our power calculations were based on expected 12-month cessation rates of 3.0% in the control group and 9.4% in the incentive group.</s><s xml:id="_P2KNr7N">To have 80% power to show a difference between groups, with a 1% two-sided type I error, we needed to have 360 participants in each group; we increased that number by 15%, to 425 in each group, to account for loss to follow-up resulting from expected employee turnover.</s><s xml:id="_zGTg8EN">No interim analyses were planned or conducted.</s><s xml:id="_NeVt8Yy">All reported P values are two-sided and were not adjusted for multiple comparisons.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_t9WVNF6">R esult s</head><p xml:id="_TQfcgSN"><s xml:id="_CQxqqpJ">Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> shows the numbers of subjects who were screened and who participated in the study intervention and follow-up.</s><s xml:id="_DfmmSwr">Of the 1903 people who initially expressed interest in participating, 878 (46%) were enrolled; 436 participants were randomly assigned to the incentive group, and 442 to the control group.</s><s xml:id="_udhh6jN">Demographic characteristics, smoking behavior, degree of nicotine dependence, readiness to quit, and health status were similar in the incentive and control groups (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_2hcRhsy">Participants in both groups smoked approximately one pack of cigarettes per day, and approximately 5 to 6% of the participants were heavy smokers.</s><s xml:id="_bUzQPMz">The majority of the sample had incomes that were greater than 500% of the poverty level, and ap-</s></p><p xml:id="_TuaTeCu"><s xml:id="_EBnNZGh">Table 3. (Continued.)</s><s xml:id="_gzw74fG">Variable Odds Ratio (95% CI) P Value Smoking status † 0.20 Heavy 0.38 (0.09-1.67)</s><s xml:id="_w5Cpwqv">Nonheavy 1.00 Previous attempts to stop smoking 0.09 ≥5 (top third) 2.00 (1.08-3.71) 3 or 4 (middle third) 1.58 (0.81-3.06) 1 or 2 (bottom third) 1.00 Stage of change § 0.10 Preparation 2.61 (1.02-6.62)</s><s xml:id="_gbHKSSh">Contemplation 1.64 (0.71-3.83)</s><s xml:id="_XT3vQ65">Precontemplation 1.00 Self-reported health 0.37 Excellent 1.85 (0.21-16.54)</s><s xml:id="_Ar7eKzc">Very good 1.14 (0.13-9.66)</s><s xml:id="_zWqzurf">Good 1.09 (0.13-9.37)</s><s xml:id="_sdAq43F">Fair 0.58 (0.06-6.08)</s><s xml:id="_QH9YWh5">Poor 1.00 * Odds ratios for work-site groups are not reported, owing to the large number of sites included.</s><s xml:id="_rkU8djk">† Heavy smoking was defined as 40 cigarettes or more per day.</s><s xml:id="_9yKffcz">‡ One study participant was not included in this analysis, owing to missing data on race or ethnic group.</s><s xml:id="_Qnqznfu">§ Stage of change refers to the smoker's readiness to quit, as defined by DiClemente et al. 16 and Prochaska et al. 17 The New England Journal of Medicine is produced by NEJM Group, a division of the Massachusetts Medical Society.</s><s xml:id="_9XGeevW">Downloaded from nejm.org on July 31, 2025.</s><s xml:id="_HHXShTT">Copyright © 2009 Massachusetts Medical Society.</s><s xml:id="_br6WMMV">All rights reserved, including those for text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies.</s></p><p xml:id="_GGa8m8R"><s xml:id="_HGGgeyW">proximately 90% of the participants were white.</s><s xml:id="_8BsGCZd">A similar number of participants in the incentive and control groups were lost to follow-up or withdrew in the first 6 months (66 and 59 participants, respectively; P = 0.45) and through month 12 (56 and 47, respectively; P = 0.25).</s></p><p xml:id="_ptjUKPd"><s xml:id="_BsGVD7Q">The 9-month or 12-month rate of cessation, as confirmed by cotinine testing, was 14.7% in the incentive group, as compared with 5.0% in the control group (P&lt;0.001)</s><s xml:id="_vRFFZ2N">(Table <ref type="table">2</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_F8u3BdR">In both the incentive group and the control group, very few of the participants who reported that they had quit smoking did not submit samples for testing (0.5% and 1.1%, respectively), and no participants who submitted samples had positive test results.</s><s xml:id="_mcp98EY">The rate of participation in a smoking-cessation program was significantly higher in the incentive group than in the control group (15.4% vs. 5.4%, and a significantly higher percentage of incentive-group participants completed a smoking-cessation program (10.8% vs. 2.5%, P&lt;0.001).</s><s xml:id="_P5sW2zY">Members of the incentive group who participated in a smoking-cessation program had significantly higher rates of cessation than did members of the control group who participated in such a program (46.3% vs. 20.8%,</s><s xml:id="_fkU5XrA">P = 0.03).</s></p><p xml:id="_Gp8UeTx"><s xml:id="_PjsDvhp">The cotinine-confirmed cessation rate within 6 months after study enrollment was 20.9% in the incentive group, as compared with 11.8% in the control group (P&lt;0.001).</s><s xml:id="_p6ET4uD">The cessation rate at 15 or 18 months was 9.4% in the incentive group, as compared with 3.6% in the control group (P = 0.001).</s><s xml:id="_UYFuX2h">Among participants who had not stopped smoking in the first 6 months -and</s></p><p xml:id="_947ff8y"><s xml:id="_txj786t">33p9 0.01 0.1 1.0 10 100 1000 Odds Ratio for Cessation (log scale) Sex Male Female Poverty level &lt;200% of poverty level 200-500% of poverty level &gt;500% of poverty level Smoking status Nonheavy Heavy (&gt;2 packs/day) Average no. of previous attempts to quit 0-2 (bottom third) 3-4 (middle third) 5-200 (top third) Stage of change Precontemplation Contemplation Preparation Self-assessed health Poor Fair Good Very good Excellent Fagerström score for nicotine dependence &lt;6 ≥6 Odds Ratio (95% CI) no. who quit/total no.</s><s xml:id="_MhhRdsq">Control Group Incentive Group Characteristic 40/286 24/150 2/8 10/140 52/288 62/414 2/22 14/152 17/123 33/161 5/66 40/292 19/78 0/5 3/37 23/147 27/186 11/61 49/290 15/146 2.95 (1.59-5.47)</s><s xml:id="_uuvVR6e">3.40 (1.91-6.05)</s><s xml:id="_UJSkd8y">3.11 (1.10-8.81)</s><s xml:id="_mVWUaue">5.08 (1.88-13.78)</s><s xml:id="_aBGSwXg">3.53 (0.35-35.52) 2.37 (0.70-7.97) 2.96 (1.43-6.16)</s><s xml:id="_ZupqcDR">0.51 (0.02-15.06) 3.86 (1.53-9.78)</s><s xml:id="_YuRsHBE">2.75 (0.51-14.68) 3.28 (1.72-6.28)</s><s xml:id="_QR3DH9G">2.54 (1.01-6.38)</s><s xml:id="_AbCb2ZY">3.71 (1.76-7.83)</s><s xml:id="_RT4AuHX">3.35 (1.18-9.53)</s><s xml:id="_F5Whf7y">3.15 (1.89-5.23)</s><s xml:id="_bU73ngR">6.71 (0.31-147.37) 3.92 (2.15-7.15)</s><s xml:id="_uMdxcVw">1.60 (0.59-4.34) 5.77 (0.23-143.37) 4.03 (1.68-9.66)</s><s xml:id="_jmNjnaK">15/287 7/155 0/7 7/153 15/282 22/415 0/27 5/170 7/118 10/154 2/69 13/282 7/91 1/9 1/41 5/142 11/203 4/47 17/301 5/141 AUTHOR: FIGURE: JOB: 4-C H/T RETAKE SIZE ICM CASE EMail Line H/T Combo Revised AUTHOR, PLEASE NOTE: Figure has been redrawn and type has been reset.</s><s xml:id="_Ffckxak">Please check carefully.</s><s xml:id="_uNmvyy4">REG F Enon 1st 2nd 3rd Volpp 2 of 2 01-29-09 ARTIST: ts 36005 ISSUE: Stage of change refers to the smoker's readiness to quit, as defined by DiClemente et al. <ref type="bibr">16</ref> and Prochaska et al. 17</s></p><p xml:id="_SEvpjx5"><s xml:id="_wBgbWjE">The Fagerström Test for Nicotine Dependence 14 has a range of 0 to 10, with higher scores indicating greater nicotine dependence; a score of 6 or more was used to classify participants as highly dependent on nicotine. 15</s></p><p xml:id="_JESSved"><s xml:id="_Yca53uW">The New England Journal of Medicine is produced by NEJM Group, a division of the Massachusetts Medical Society.</s></p><p xml:id="_YmAhbF9"><s xml:id="_RnAbs3n">Downloaded from nejm.org on July 31, 2025.</s><s xml:id="_v7bxzMX">Copyright © 2009 Massachusetts Medical Society.</s><s xml:id="_NRXBxsX">All rights reserved, including those for text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies.</s></p><p xml:id="_jp2nhXa"><s xml:id="_6UBxNcD">thus were ineligible for financial incentivesthe cotinine-confirmed cessation rates were similar in the incentive and control groups (4.1% and 5.9%, respectively; P = 0.29).</s></p><p xml:id="_f8UatSm"><s xml:id="_VjY3SnW">The odds ratios for quitting by 9 or 12 months (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>) were significantly higher in the incentive group than in the control group in the unadjusted model (odds ratio, 3.28; 95% confidence interval [CI], 1.98 to 5.44), in a logistic-regression model that adjusted for stratification variables only (odds ratio, 3.19; 95% CI, 1.91 to 5.30), and in a model that adjusted for all the variables included in Table <ref type="table">1</ref> (odds ratio, 3.16; 95% CI, 1.88 to 5.32).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_jyb2hgT">Exploratory Subgroup Analyses</head><p xml:id="_GvH7ngk"><s xml:id="_jPzcxMA">Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref> shows 9-month or 12-month cessation rates stratified according to subgroup.</s><s xml:id="_DEBXEbP">For all subgroups, members of the incentive group had higher cessation rates than members of the control group.</s><s xml:id="_9QajGjD">None of the tests for interaction showed significant differences in this population; instead, the observed patterns showed a consistent effect of the intervention across numerous characteristics.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Dn7Xv4g">Discussion</head><p xml:id="_r3FHrQ6"><s xml:id="_uwUNwXN">In this study of employees at a large corporation, rates of prolonged abstinence from smoking after 9 or 12 months of follow-up were 14.7% in the group that was eligible for financial incentives and 5.0% in the control group.</s><s xml:id="_xeq5v5h">Rates of prolonged abstinence at 15 or 18 months in the incentive group remained significantly higher than those in the control group.</s></p><p xml:id="_c8Gp78x"><s xml:id="_JukJBpc">A 2005 Cochrane Collaboration review of financial incentives for smoking cessation in workplace settings concluded that there was insufficient evidence that these incentives are effective. 11</s><s xml:id="_sBfyanN">One reason for this finding may be that many previous studies were not designed with samples that were large enough to detect the differences we observed.</s><s xml:id="_QyDKwft">A second reason may be that the incentives used in previous studies have generally been small (as little as $10 in some of them).</s><s xml:id="_RBbsekB">Studies have shown that financial-incentive programs are associated with an increased rate of smoking cessation in the short term, but the programs reported in these studies were not designed to focus on sustaining high rates over time. <ref type="bibr">7,</ref><ref type="bibr">9</ref></s><s xml:id="_fq9pWRW">The relationships of the size and structure of incentive payments to rates of smoking cessation remain important empirical questions that need to be addressed in future research.</s><s xml:id="_geyMc9Q">It is possible that larger -or smaller -payments by employers could be more cost-effective in improving smoking-cessation rates.</s><s xml:id="_JtuVUSZ">The optimal design of incentive programs for smoking cessation is also an open question, since extension of the incentives beyond 12 months may result in higher cessation rates over a longer period.</s></p><p xml:id="_jKk3wTK"><s xml:id="_XPTrjaA">The cotinine level, which we used for biochemical verification of 7-day abstinence, is considered to be the best biomarker of smoking cessation. 12</s><s xml:id="_r2wvEbg">Consistent with the recommendations of the Society for Research on Nicotine and Tobacco, our primary measure of self-reported cessation at both 9 or 12 months and 15 or 18 months was prolonged abstinence. 12</s><s xml:id="_9tUF8bT">Although prolonged abstinence can be biochemically verified only indirectly because of the limitations of the cotinine test, it is likely that the point prevalence is highly correlated with prolonged abstinence 6 months after short-term quitting was assessed. <ref type="bibr">12</ref></s><s xml:id="_SPMsNnN">o date, financial incentives within health care settings have been directed primarily toward providers, through Pay for Performance (P4P) programs.</s><s xml:id="_EBKPCkd">However, given that up to 40% of premature deaths in the United States are due to unhealthful behaviors such as smoking, poor dietary habits, and sedentary lifestyles, 18 incentives directed toward patients rather than providers may have greater potential for changing health behaviors. <ref type="bibr">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr">[20]</ref></s><s xml:id="_53UCZsm">0]<ref type="bibr">[21]</ref> One approach to encouraging smoking cessation would be to adjust health-insurance premiums on the basis of smoking status; however, targeted payments for smoking cessation have the advantage of being unbundled from health-insurance premiums and thus may be more salient to people, thereby having a greater influence on behavior. <ref type="bibr">22</ref></s><s xml:id="_5m2ZC46">he financial benefit to employers of having their employees stop smoking is estimated to be about $3,400 per year 23 as a result of increased productivity, decreased absenteeism, and a reduced incidence of illness.</s><s xml:id="_hehFQHc">There is also strong evidence that employees prefer to work for firms that offer effective and attractive benefit programs. 24</s><s xml:id="_3kJwYS5">However, few employers offer full coverage of smoking-cessation services or cessation programs in the workplace, <ref type="bibr">8,</ref><ref type="bibr">25,</ref><ref type="bibr">26</ref> partly because a compelling "business case" for such coverage has not been made.</s><s xml:id="_zwx83bd">Notably, neither the financial-incentive intervention nor the control intervention in our study</s></p><p xml:id="_Pd2e2VJ"><s xml:id="_brm99hP">The New England Journal of Medicine is produced by NEJM Group, a division of the Massachusetts Medical Society.</s><s xml:id="_hdJxakA">The literature on smoking cessation suggests that most relapses occur within the first month of cessation, that approximately 90% of relapses occur within the first 6 months, 27 and that the likelihood of continuous abstinence over a 20-month period is about 95% for smokers who quit for 1 year or longer. 12</s><s xml:id="_UBufAaH">Our finding of relapse rates between the 9-or 12-month visit and the 15-or 18-month visit (27.3% in the control group and 35.9% in the incentive group) that appear to be higher than those reported in the literature may suggest that relapse rates differ according to whether smoking cessation occurs in the presence or absence of incentives.</s><s xml:id="_QfMdSRS">However, since the relapse rates in both the incentive and control groups differ from those in the literature, and in view of the relatively small number of participants in our study who quit smoking, we cannot be confident that the relapse rates do in fact differ from those previously reported.</s></p><p xml:id="_MzkjDyW"><s xml:id="_AJDaxas">Because approximately 90% of the enrolled population was white and the participants had relatively high education and income levels, our study may have limited generalizability to employees with lower socioeconomic status than that of the participants in our study or to members of a minority racial or ethnic group.</s><s xml:id="_YeUVYny">In addition, programs that are designed to change behavior may have unintended consequences that we could not observe in our study.</s><s xml:id="_XMU3MDd">However, we think it is unlikely that substantial numbers of people would start smoking in order to be eligible for such incentive programs.</s><s xml:id="_CW7ywrY">Studies such as this one are subject to selection bias, in that smokers who voluntarily enroll in these programs may be more likely (whether they are assigned to the incentive group or the control group) to quit smoking; it is difficult to project how effective these programs would be in a population that included all employees within a given company.</s></p><p xml:id="_X7k6pmw"><s xml:id="_ypyCvUt">In summary, this study shows that smokingcessation rates among company employees who were given both information about cessation programs and financial incentives to quit smoking were significantly higher than the rates among employees who were given program information but no financial incentives.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_Sek53b8"><s xml:id="_PE7dFgh">Figure 2. Rates of Smoking Cessation in Various Subgroups at 9 or 12 Months.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_vRDuz8z"><s xml:id="_VzrDMYb">Downloaded from nejm.org on July 31, 2025.</s><s xml:id="_ePP4ync">Copyright © 2009 Massachusetts Medical Society.</s><s xml:id="_RKaMKRE">All rights reserved, including those for text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_GgBZpGh"><s xml:id="_NCsNg5F">included the establishment of a smoking-cessation program; both interventions merely encouraged participants to use existing programs.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xml:id="_kfsThyT"><p xml:id="_Jh9WG4V"><s xml:id="_EnQJYRf">Supported by grants from the <rs type="funder">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</rs> (<rs type="grantNumber">RO1 DP000100-01</rs> and <rs type="grantNumber">RO1 DP001168-01</rs>) and from the <rs type="funder">Pennsylvania Department of Health</rs>, which specifically disclaims responsibility for any analyses, interpretations, or conclusions.</s></p><p xml:id="_tf7tTrm"><s xml:id="_rDQZ6hJ"><rs type="person">Dr. Volpp</rs> reports receiving lecture fees from <rs type="funder">Aetna</rs> and grant support from <rs type="funder">Aetna</rs> and <rs type="funder">Pfizer</rs> and owning equity in <rs type="funder">General Electric</rs>; <rs type="person">Dr. Pauly</rs>, being a board member of <rs type="institution">Independent Health</rs>, owning equity in General Electric, receiving lecture fees from <rs type="institution">America's Health Insurance Plans</rs>, and receiving grant support from <rs type="funder">Merck and MedStar</rs>; <rs type="person">Dr. Glick</rs>, owning equity in General Electric; and <rs type="person">Dr. Galvin</rs>, owning equity in General Electric.</s><s xml:id="_p8FTYcF">No other potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.</s></p><p xml:id="_AkTMx4F"><s xml:id="_YhVsRDT">We thank <rs type="person">Quincy Greene</rs> for his contributions to the analyses for this article and <rs type="person">Donna Tomlinson, M.D.</rs>, for assistance in implementing this study.</s></p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_a4f2HVq">
					<idno type="grant-number">RO1 DP000100-01</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_Ssc9nTj">
					<idno type="grant-number">RO1 DP001168-01</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_NrPzw3M">Actual causes of death in the United States, 2000</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Mokdad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Marks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Stroup</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">1</forename><surname>Gerberding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1001/jama.291.10.1238</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_vzYF6k6">JAMA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">291</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="293" to="294" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004. 2005. 298</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Errata JAMA Cigarette smoking among adults -2</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mokdad AH, Marks JS, Stroup DF, 1. Gerberding JL. Actual causes of death in the United States, 2000. JAMA 2004;291: 1238-45. [Errata, JAMA 2005;293:293-4, 298.] Cigarette smoking among adults - 2.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_tTEKaX6">Annual smoking-attributable mortal-3. ity, years of potential life lost, and productivity losses -United States, 1997-2001</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">United</forename><surname>States</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.15585/mmwr.mm6939a5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_amhEs8Q">MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1145" to="1148" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000. 2002. 2005. 2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep Tobacco use among adults -United 4. States, 2005 MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">United States, 2000. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2002;51:642-5. Annual smoking-attributable mortal- 3. ity, years of potential life lost, and pro- ductivity losses -United States, 1997- 2001. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2005;54:625-8. Tobacco use among adults -United 4. States, 2005. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2006;55:1145-8.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_3G2zGpX">Smoking cessation with and without assistance: a population-based analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Melcer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Rosbrook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">5</forename><surname>Pierce</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0749-3797(00)00124-0</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ZM6VNHY">Am J Prev Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="305" to="311" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Zhu S, Melcer T, Sun J, Rosbrook B, 5. Pierce JP. Smoking cessation with and with- out assistance: a population-based analy- sis. Am J Prev Med 2000;18:305-11.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_NJdJQsW">US Public Health Service 6. Clinical Practice Guideline: treating tobacco use and dependence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Fiore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_5Maz5pu">Respir Care</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1200" to="1262" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Fiore MC. US Public Health Service 6. Clinical Practice Guideline: treating to- bacco use and dependence. Respir Care 2000;45:1200-62.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_7x3ZBR5">A randomized controlled trial of financial incentives for smoking cessation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Volpp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gurmankin</forename><surname>Levy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Asch</forename><forename type="middle">7</forename><surname>Da</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1158/1055-9965.epi-05-0314</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_VJQZ4qw">Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Volpp KG, Gurmankin Levy A, Asch 7. DA, et al. A randomized controlled trial of financial incentives for smoking cessation. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 2006; 15:12-8.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_3FmS3YP">The SUCCESS project: the effect of program format and incentives on participation and cessation in worksite smoking cessation programs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hennrikus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Jeffery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lando</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2105/ajph.92.2.274</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_rwABmSD">Am J Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="274" to="279" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hennrikus DJ, Jeffery RW, Lando HA, 8. et al. The SUCCESS project: the effect of program format and incentives on partici- pation and cessation in worksite smoking cessation programs. Am J Public Health 2002;92:274-9.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_2TpvDAG">Randomised controlled trial using social support and financial incentives for high risk pregnant smokers: Significant Other Supporter (SOS) program</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Donatelle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Prows</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Champeau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hudson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/tc.9.suppl_3.iii67</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_P42XjYs">Tob Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">Suppl 3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="I67" to="I69" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Donatelle RJ, Prows SL, Champeau D, 9. Hudson D. Randomised controlled trial using social support and financial incen- tives for high risk pregnant smokers: Sig- nificant Other Supporter (SOS) program. Tob Control 2000;9:Suppl 3:III67-III69.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Donatelle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hudson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dobie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/14622200410001669196</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date>10</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Donatelle RJ, Hudson D, Dobie S, 10.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_h4jjAxM">Incentives in smoking cessation: status of the field and implications for research and practice with pregnant smokers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Goodall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hunsberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Oswald</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_TgAjtQB">Nicotine Tob Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">Suppl 2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="163" to="S179" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Goodall A, Hunsberger M, Oswald K. In- centives in smoking cessation: status of the field and implications for research and practice with pregnant smokers. Nic- otine Tob Res 2004;6:Suppl 2:S163-S179.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_GvBCZKj">SRNT Subcommittee on Biochemical 12. Verification. Biochemical verification of tobacco use and cessation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Perera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/14651858.cd004307.pub2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_4QdKjf2">Cochrane Database Syst Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="149" to="159" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2005. 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Competitions and in-11. centives for smoking cessation Nicotine Tob Res</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hey K, Perera R. Competitions and in- 11. centives for smoking cessation. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 2005;2:CD004307. SRNT Subcommittee on Biochemical 12. Verification. Biochemical verification of tobacco use and cessation. Nicotine Tob Res 2002;4:149-59.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_JmgdSNF">Anabasine and anatabine as biomarkers for tobacco use during nicotine replacement therapy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Jacob</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Iii</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hatsukami</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Severson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Benowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_rN7Rupz">Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1668" to="1673" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Jacob P III, Hatsukami D, Severson H, 13. Hall S, Yu L, Benowitz N. Anabasine and anatabine as biomarkers for tobacco use during nicotine replacement therapy. Can- cer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 2002;11: 1668-73.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Heatherton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Kozlowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Frecker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/t03773-000</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Heatherton TF, Kozlowski LT, Frecker 14.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_6A9YwvH">The Fagerström Test for Nicotine Dependence: a revision of the Fagerström Tolerance Questionnaire</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Fagerström</forename><surname>Rc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ko</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_u4AX4TF">Br J Addict</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1119" to="1127" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">RC, Fagerström KO. The Fagerström Test for Nicotine Dependence: a revision of the Fagerström Tolerance Questionnaire. Br J Addict 1991;86:1119-27.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Westman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Behm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Simel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/00007611-199308000-00013</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Westman EC, Behm FM, Simel DL, 15.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_NCUcx2e">Smoking behavior on the first day of a quit attempt predicts long-term abstinence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Rose</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_bCNskEA">Arch Intern Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">157</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="335" to="340" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rose JE. Smoking behavior on the first day of a quit attempt predicts long-term absti- nence. Arch Intern Med 1997;157:335-40.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Diclemente</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Prochaska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date>Fair-16</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">DiClemente CC, Prochaska JO, Fair- 16.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_EgjFU6A">The process of smoking cessation: an analysis of precontemplation, contemplation, and preparation stages of change</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Hurst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Velicer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Velasquez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rossi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_g2SXcFe">J Consult Clin Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="295" to="304" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">hurst SK, Velicer WF, Velasquez MM, Rossi JS. The process of smoking cessation: an analysis of precontemplation, contempla- tion, and preparation stages of change. J Consult Clin Psychol 1991;59:295-304.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_MK8ezfZ">Standardized, individualized, interactive, and personalized selfhelp programs for smoking cessation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Prochaska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Diclemente</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Velicer 17</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rossi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037//0278-6133.12.5.399</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_bSHQGdU">Health Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="399" to="405" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Prochaska JO, DiClemente CC, Velicer 17. WF, Rossi JS. Standardized, individual- ized, interactive, and personalized self- help programs for smoking cessation. Health Psychol 1993;12:399-405.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_TXaSUmu">Shattuck Lecture: We 18. can do better -improving the health of the American people</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Schroeder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1056/nejmsa073350</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_gDmY7kj">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">357</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1221" to="1228" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Schroeder SA. Shattuck Lecture: We 18. can do better -improving the health of the American people. N Engl J Med 2007; 357:1221-8.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_3jcXezV">Paying for performance: 19. the power of incentives over habits</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Sindelar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/hec.1350</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_s8nusdj">Health Econ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="449" to="451" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sindelar JL. Paying for performance: 19. the power of incentives over habits. Health Econ 2008;17:449-51.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_KtdSbQd">Asymmetric paternalism to improve health behaviors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Loewenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Brennan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Volpp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1001/jama.298.20.2415</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_dKPmjf8">JAMA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">298</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2415" to="2417" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>20</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Loewenstein G, Brennan T, Volpp KG. 20. Asymmetric paternalism to improve health behaviors. JAMA 2007;298:2415-7.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qeQftJj">P4P4P: an agenda for research on pay-for-performance for patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Volpp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Pauly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Loewenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bangsberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1377/hlthaff.28.1.206</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_U9EtN9H">Health Aff (Millwood)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="206" to="214" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Volpp KG, Pauly MV, Loewenstein G, 21. Bangsberg D. P4P4P: an agenda for re- search on pay-for-performance for patients. Health Aff (Millwood) 2009;28:206-14.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_GCSn5UQ">Annual smoking-attributable mortal-23. ity, years of potential life lost, and economic costs -United States, 1995-1999</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Thaler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_j52hJUJ">MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="300" to="303" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985. 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Mental accounting and 22. consumer choice Marketing Sci</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Thaler RH. Mental accounting and 22. consumer choice. Marketing Sci 1985;4: 199-214. Annual smoking-attributable mortal- 23. ity, years of potential life lost, and eco- nomic costs -United States, 1995-1999. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2002;51: 300-3.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Pauly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3998/mpub.15825</idno>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_NmKFAPa">Health benefits at work: an 24. economic and political analysis of employment-based health insurance</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Ann Arbor</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>University of Michigan Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Pauly MV. Health benefits at work: an 24. economic and political analysis of employ- ment-based health insurance. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 2002.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_CxbdzNg">Coverage of smoking cessation treatment by union health and welfare funds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Barbeau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sorenson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Con-25. Lan</forename><surname>Km</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Youngstrom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Emmons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2105/ajph.91.9.1412</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_EWHjptN">Am J Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1412" to="1415" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Barbeau EM, Li Y, Sorenson G, Con- 25. lan KM, Youngstrom R, Emmons K. Cov- erage of smoking cessation treatment by union health and welfare funds. Am J Public Health 2001;91:1412-5.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_dhPvw59">Smoking cessation services offered by health insurance plans for Wisconsin state employees</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Aakko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Piasecki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Remington</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">26</forename><surname>Fiore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mc</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_vwZNCtJ">WMJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Aakko E, Piasecki TM, Remington P, 26. Fiore MC. Smoking cessation services of- fered by health insurance plans for Wis- consin state employees. WMJ 1999;98: 14-8.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_mzWtjqC">Shape of 27. the relapse curve and long-term abstinence among untreated smokers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hughes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Keely</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Naud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1360-0443.2004.00540.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_rK6Wvpb">Addiction</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hughes JR, Keely J, Naud S. Shape of 27. the relapse curve and long-term abstinence among untreated smokers. Addiction 2004; 99:29-38.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
