<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_kJGaRFs">Remote neuro-endovascular consultation using a secure telemedicine system: A feasibility study</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
					<p type="raw">Surgical Neurology International • 2022 • 13(47) | 1 is is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial-Share Alike 4.0 License, which allows others to remix, transform, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as the author is credited and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms. ©2022 Published by Scientific Scholar on behalf of Surgical Neurology International</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2022-02-11">11 February 2022</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Toshihiro</forename><surname>Ishibashi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>1</label> Department of Neurosurgery , e Jikei University School of Medicine , Minato-Ku , Tokyo ,</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neurosurgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">e Jikei University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Minato-Ku</addrLine>
									<settlement>Tokyo</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Shogo</forename><surname>Kaku</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>2</label> Department of Neurosurgery , Higashi-Yokohama Neurosurgery Hospital , Yokohama , Kanagawa , Japan.</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neurosurgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Higashi-Yokohama Neurosurgery Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Yokohama</settlement>
									<region>Kanagawa</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Shota</forename><surname>Sonoda</surname></persName>
							<email>s.sonodas@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>2</label> Department of Neurosurgery , Higashi-Yokohama Neurosurgery Hospital , Yokohama , Kanagawa , Japan.</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neurosurgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Higashi-Yokohama Neurosurgery Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Yokohama</settlement>
									<region>Kanagawa</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yuichi</forename><surname>Murayama</surname></persName>
							<email>murayamayuichi@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>1</label> Department of Neurosurgery , e Jikei University School of Medicine , Minato-Ku , Tokyo ,</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neurosurgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">e Jikei University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Minato-Ku</addrLine>
									<settlement>Tokyo</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Nancy</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Epstein</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Department of Neurosurgery , e Jikei University School of Medicine , Minato-Ku , Tokyo , Japan.</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neurosurgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">e Jikei University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Minato-Ku</addrLine>
									<settlement>Tokyo</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Clinical Professor of Neurological Surgery , School of Medicine , State U. of NY at Stony Brook. MD Shinshu University , Matsumoto , Japan</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Clinical Professor of Neurological Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">State U. of NY at Stony Brook</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Shinshu University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Matsumoto</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_2pc9kHF">Remote neuro-endovascular consultation using a secure telemedicine system: A feasibility study</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2022-02-11">11 February 2022</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">7F69547684315023A4A032327B63CEAA</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.25259/sni_1165_2021</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received : 22 November 2021 Accepted : 19 January 2022</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T07:19+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term xml:id="_sXpdq2Y">Education</term>
					<term xml:id="_EKhspPk">Endovascular</term>
					<term xml:id="_9CDG6Sx">Remote</term>
					<term xml:id="_4whqTt9">Stroke</term>
					<term xml:id="_u8MVHqB">Telemedicine www.surgicalneurologyint.com</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_sQ8Xnt9"><p xml:id="_xQq8gq2"><s xml:id="_BMyyfQh">Background: Telemedicine has been rapidly implemented under COVID-19 conditions, to assess the ability to use an audio-visual telemedicine system for neuro-endovascular remote consultation.</s><s xml:id="_RECbRgW">Methods: e system consists of a live streaming function for angiography and an operating room (OR) camera using a smartphone application (JOIN; Allm Inc, Tokyo, Japan) in conjunction with verbal communication using the Zoom app.</s><s xml:id="_wyqy9q9">e system allows us to display multiple angiographic images in addition to streaming video from the 4K camera recording the operator's procedure and from the 4K camera showing the OR view on the monitor of any smart device.</s></p><p xml:id="_ZJqwsS4"><s xml:id="_vzmn5rv">Results: e operator was able to speak with the senior supervisor through a bone conduction headphone and to talk to assistants or radiology technicians without any hearing difficulties.</s><s xml:id="_ZYkA8Mj">e remote supervisor was able to check the streaming images, which had almost the same imaging quality as real digital subtraction angiogram (DSA) monitors, and he could advise the handling of devices and preparation through the 4K video camera systems.</s><s xml:id="_qCN7nPg">e DSA image delay was within 2 s.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_w88s8Jt">Conclusion:</head><p xml:id="_ArhU3bS"><s xml:id="_QnGGEA9">A remote consultation system with real-time audio-visual capability may play an important role in acute stroke management and maintain the quality of patient care under COVID-19 conditions.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_CDbYhP4">INTRODUCTION</head><p xml:id="_V6z8gFA"><s xml:id="_cRcWKXb">Telemedicine has been quickly applied under COVID-19 conditions.</s><s xml:id="_Djnpeuf">Several studies have shown that telemedicine is effective in the management of stroke care. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref></s><s xml:id="_mEu4S3X">,<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9]</ref> Under COVID-19 conditions, hospital regulations sometimes prohibit technical support from senior neuroendovascular specialists outside the hospital.</s><s xml:id="_C5ucvF4">In addition, the rapid expansion of acute ischemic stroke therapy imposes further work tasks on experienced neuro-endovascular specialists.</s><s xml:id="_6FuyZ7N">Young physicians who need expert opinion or supervision for complex neurovascular treatments sometimes experience difficulty analyzing the treatment strategies or selecting the optimal devices.</s><s xml:id="_9sgGPsP">erefore, a more direct "audio-visual" communication system is required for real-time consultation.</s></p><p xml:id="_utWVCfh"><s xml:id="_TX2dE2X">We recently established a telemedicine system that allows further remote support, including realtime imaging and verbal communication, for neuro-endovascular therapy.</s><s xml:id="_AbUAECA">We report our initial Ishibashi, et al.: Remote neuro-endovascular consultation Surgical Neurology International • 2022 • 13(47) | 2</s></p><p xml:id="_uH6kCVC"><s xml:id="_MSrhKgD">clinical experience in acute stroke treatment and scheduled unruptured aneurysm embolization using a remote neuroendovascular support system.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_NUnz6HT">MATERIALS AND METHODS</head><p xml:id="_PdGW684"><s xml:id="_RMUktRP">is system was developed at the university and was used for case consultation at an affiliated hospital.</s><s xml:id="_UnqsyDp">e study protocol was reviewed and approved by the ethics committee and the research review board at the affiliated hospital.</s><s xml:id="_jcgASSV">All patients were provided informed consent, and each site had obtained Institutional Review Board approval and signed consent forms.</s><s xml:id="_t2APy5k">e participants and any identifiable individuals consented to the publication of their image.</s></p><p xml:id="_txKYWDG"><s xml:id="_8gFuQS4">e system consists of 1) a live streaming function for angiography and cameras and 2) a verbal communication function [Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>].</s><s xml:id="_zYMEGVC">We use medical software, which complies with medical information guidelines (Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare "Guidelines for Safety Management of Medical Information Systems" 2021/1), for the live streaming function (JOIN; Allm Inc, Tokyo, Japan).</s><s xml:id="_Eq7Dawe">Because angiography devices and cameras in operation contain medical information, streaming from angiography is delivered to the system cloud through the encoder, a JOIN Gateway server (JGW).</s><s xml:id="_WBkk2zV">Steaming from the camera is delivered to the cloud through the JGW.</s><s xml:id="_gAXbTte">e system users can access the closed cloud system through smartphones or tablets to see live streams from angiography.</s><s xml:id="_xjZXuhj">e system has a viewing function that allows the senior supervisor to view the images he or she wants to see, with multiple images simultaneously presented side by side.</s><s xml:id="_yNE83VE">We use "Zoom" as the verbal communication program.</s><s xml:id="_nNPzP8d">We allow only the system user to access the Zoom event by linking it with the JOIN App.</s><s xml:id="_fxBsJFf">e endovascular surgeon wears a bone conduction headphone system connected with smartphones, tablets, or PCs.</s><s xml:id="_sH2KS7e">e endovascular surgeon sets up "Zoom" through "JOIN.</s><s xml:id="_KHTk3Vt">" e remote doctor sets up "Zoom" through "JOIN" with smartphones, tablets, or PCs.</s><s xml:id="_H8YM49w">en, they can start communication.</s><s xml:id="_Wrnv76J">e systems introduced in each hospital are shown in [Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>].</s></p><p xml:id="_kXhqhUr"><s xml:id="_ZVG6qr7">e system allows us to display AP, lateral view; native AP, lateral view; reference AP, lateral view; and workstation images, in addition to the 4K operator's procedure streaming video camera and the 4K operating room (OR) view video camera on the monitor of any smart devices.</s><s xml:id="_VnWreAy">A total of eight images can be displayed simultaneously on the iPad (Apple Inc., Cupertino, CA, USA) [Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>].</s><s xml:id="_heRC4sw">e remote supervisor can select one of the images on the touch screen of the iPad or smartphone to magnify the images.</s><s xml:id="_DmgvBmb">All communication between the endovascular surgeon and remote supervisor can be conducted through bone conduction headphones (endovascular surgeons).</s><s xml:id="_DXqv5nT">In this study, two independent observers checked the data transmission delay time at the angiography suite and remote supervisor's office when a scheduled unruptured aneurysm procedure was conducted.</s><s xml:id="_qvvSYEy">e speed delay was verified by the digital subtraction angiogram (DSA) and the quality of the camera image that the doctor confirmed to be clinically available.</s><s xml:id="_EvJFwwx">en, we recorded images from both DSA and camera monitoring in the hospital and that out of the hospital in parallel and measured the delay speed with a stopwatch.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_hwNuc9X">RESULTS</head><p xml:id="_eAzQNz2"><s xml:id="_U5BEfQz">e operator was able to speak with the senior supervisor through a bone conduction headphone and to talk to assistants or radiology technicians without any hearing difficulties [Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3a</ref>].</s><s xml:id="_wNx9HgP">e remote supervisor could check Ishibashi, et al.: Remote neuro-endovascular consultation Surgical Neurology International • 2022 • 13(47) | 3</s></p><p xml:id="_wydYdb5"><s xml:id="_EhZZaby">streaming images with almost the same imaging quality as real DSA monitors, and he advised the handling of devices and preparation through 4K video camera systems.</s></p><p xml:id="_UaJWbYZ"><s xml:id="_6KbY7TK">We used 4G Long Term Evolution (LTE) and internet WiFi as the network infrastructure.</s><s xml:id="_DVqfTyp">However, the hospital with the interventional specialist could not use 4G LTE because the radio waves did not reach the OR where we conducted the measurements.</s><s xml:id="_vRdUAAA">e range of delay speed was approximately 1-2 s [Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>].</s><s xml:id="_Tv7fRb5">In the affiliated hospital (Kanagawa prefecture), we could use both 4G LTE and internet WiFi.</s><s xml:id="_Wsv5dgZ">ere was no difference in delay speed between the two methods.</s><s xml:id="_7xmKzeP">e range of delay speed was also approximately 1-2 s.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_jGfc927">Illustrative case 1</head><p xml:id="_djuKzrp"><s xml:id="_aqaP2kF">A 73-year-old patient who had an unruptured intracranial IC ophthalmic aneurysm was scheduled for stent-assisted coiling at the affiliated hospital (Kanagawa Prefecture).</s><s xml:id="_VzQZ8NS">Under general anesthesia, the guiding system was advanced into the right internal carotid artery (ICA), and the microcatheter was placed in the aneurysm sac.</s><s xml:id="_Gm4WuPu">e operator and consultant, who were located at the hospital with the interventional specialist (Tokyo), discussed the treatment strategy by viewing the same 3D workstation before the procedure.</s><s xml:id="_7Ca8mWR">e distance between the 2 institutions was 30 miles.</s><s xml:id="_uZawFqe">e consultant used 2 display systems and advised placing the microcatheter tip at the center of the aneurysm, and subsequently, a low profile visualized intraluminal support stent (Microvention/Termo, Tokyo, Japan) was placed.</s><s xml:id="_vfbtrgQ">e consultant detected slight proximal stent corning before the operator realized it because of the high magnification of the image on the iPad (Apple Inc.).</s><s xml:id="_SeFCncT">All procedures were safety conducted in the same manner as those under conventional supervision.</s><s xml:id="_QjhSNsU">ere were no communication errors or image deteriorations during the procedures [Video 1].</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_pnuBQSM">Illustrative case 2</head><p xml:id="_DktcMtz"><s xml:id="_zhewPMe">An 80-year-old female who presented with hemiparesis was transferred to the affiliated hospital.</s><s xml:id="_7xMz4X3">Her NIHSS scale was 13.</s><s xml:id="_2EQUznZ">CT and imaging work-up demonstrated left ICA occlusion [Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3b</ref> and <ref type="figure">c</ref>].</s><s xml:id="_H6cBfTs">e junior staff neurosurgeon called a senior specialist who was already on-call at home for emergency procedures [Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3d</ref> and <ref type="figure">e</ref>].</s><s xml:id="_U3WTb94">Senior specialists conducted remote supervision from their homes to save time.</s><s xml:id="_ypd8D6h">During the procedure, junior staff could discuss the procedural strategy with senior staff.</s><s xml:id="_RT48nkA">Using the same setup, the clot was successfully removed from the ICA and middle cerebral artery segments without any procedural complications.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_jwgsKdB">DISCUSSION</head><p xml:id="_mKaZKUk"><s xml:id="_W5SHATZ">Telemedicine is a rapidly growing component of the global health-care system under the circumstances of COVID-19. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref></s><s xml:id="_pkxmSb6">specially in stroke medical care, the benefits of telemedicine are remarkably demonstrated because urgent treatment is required.</s><s xml:id="_kVEn8aX">At the same time, it is necessary to protect medical staff from infection.</s><s xml:id="_RPpeShb">We have developed a telemedicine network system using medical software that complies with medical information guidelines.</s><s xml:id="_tgQKvCa">JOIN <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> is a communication application for smartphones and tablet devices that operate over current high-speed networks (LTE, 4G, 5G).</s><s xml:id="_C8gvS3A">is is cloud-based remote radiology related to smart device "chat" consultation applications, first approved as a medical device by the Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare.</s><s xml:id="_BUH82gB">Medical professionals such as doctors, nurses, and radiologists can share patient medical information and still/streaming images in Digital Imaging and Communications in Medicine format on high-resolution screens of smart devices.</s><s xml:id="_MtVBDsG">e JOIN system was initially developed for interdoctor telemedicine systems in the field of neurosurgical disorders and was first approved as a commercial medical app in Japan. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref></s><s xml:id="_Dv7dBMD">We have access Internet speed (Download) Devices Speed delay Affiliated hospital (Endovascular surgeon) DSA WiFi 26 Mbps iPad 1.9 s 4G LTE 14 Mbps iPhone 1.9 s Camera WiFi 13 Mbps PC 1.2 s 4G LTE 14 Mbps iPhone 1.2 s Hospital with interventional specialist (Supervisor) DSA WiFi 33 Mbps iPhone 1.4 s 4G LTE NA iPhone Camera WiFi 33 Mbps iPhone 1.2 s 4G LTE NA iPhone s: Seconds, DSA: Digital subtraction angiogram, Mbps: Megabits per second, LTE: Long-term evolution d e c b a</s></p><p xml:id="_vq6TZ7w"><s xml:id="_xJ2a8zU">improved this system and developed a telemedicine system that enables two-way communication between audio and video in real time.</s></p><p xml:id="_E3bHes4"><s xml:id="_6fvXbgk">Because of a shortage of experienced neuroendovascular specialists, emergency stroke care for stroke intervention is limited.</s><s xml:id="_w3FF4a8">Young neurosurgeons who have just completed fellowships are sometimes dispatched from university hospitals to affiliated local hospitals to cover regional medical services.</s><s xml:id="_KXPcKRe">ey need expert supervision when complex stroke patients are transferred to their hospital.</s><s xml:id="_kApNWaq">However, since the beginning of the COVID-19 pandemic, there have been unprecedented limitations in the movement of people.</s><s xml:id="_54ZhUsx">In such situations, remote consultation systems with realtime audio-visual capability are extremely useful for safe procedures.</s><s xml:id="_wA4NjF4">In this report, we demonstrated the usefulness of a remote supervision system for young physicians.</s><s xml:id="_9qXrTqD">is system has several potentials, such as a two-way education system.</s><s xml:id="_DwA6uBm">Skilled physicians can demonstrate their technique for residents, trainees, or junior attending's for teaching purposes under restrictions of patient privacy and security.</s><s xml:id="_AUaFAfQ">Resident education or device training has also been restricted by hospital infection control.</s><s xml:id="_xAXjtTy">Using this system, trainees can learn the endovascular cutting-edge technique using their own monitoring system, such as the iPad.</s><s xml:id="_2HnZadR">A similar system was reported by Orru et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> for endovascular proctoring purposes in the United States and Canada.</s><s xml:id="_qZQqbcb">In their system, images were controlled by the operator site, not the proctor site.</s><s xml:id="_4fWzKVt">Bechstein et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref> also reported endovascular proctoring achieved by using a specialized live camera system.</s><s xml:id="_X3Xhng9">After COVID also believes that this system must be utilized.</s><s xml:id="_85U8r7B">Due to the influence of COVID, people are accustomed to teleconferencing, telemedicine, etc. is practice will continue with After COVID.</s><s xml:id="_t8Mjum8">In stroke practice, a significant strength of the system is that neuroendovascular specialists do not have to be always on standby in or near the hospital.</s><s xml:id="_GZKanY2">Excessively speaking, even if you are abroad, it is a great advantage to receive treatment advice in real-time as if you were in the operation room.</s><s xml:id="_HdSNsWx">A feature of our system is that telemedicine is possible using an iPad or iPhone, and the size can be changed with a finger while maintaining the high resolution of the image.</s></p><p xml:id="_NfhpyPa"><s xml:id="_nprMHy9">One limitation of this system is the requirement for a secure encoder system that connects the hospital DSA/streaming video network.</s><s xml:id="_ydyvmCh">e system anonymizes private patient data, such as the patient's name or ID.</s><s xml:id="_3wFkUja">Only the patient's age and case number are displayed.</s><s xml:id="_uEgCarK">is system transmits images in an unidentified HIPAA-compliant manner and complies with national guidelines. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref></s><s xml:id="_BkMTss5">spite such Japanese HIPPA compliance <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> clearing the cloud system, illegal recording should be strongly restricted for patient privacy.</s><s xml:id="_FCQxBw6">However, there are several things to note in the patient protection and legal areas when operating this system.</s><s xml:id="_gZdfEmH">At first, the patient's face, etc., may be shared in remote areas.</s><s xml:id="_HjYcMDD">By adjusting the position of the camera, the patient's privacy is protective.</s><s xml:id="_cANKks8">It is desirable to devise such as blurring the screen, but it is technically advanced and may affect the communication speed.</s><s xml:id="_wz4xGKz">e second point is the surrounding environment when viewing images in remote locations.</s><s xml:id="_t7DXDXE">If other people are in a situation where they can see the screen, it is possible for an unspecified number of people to see the image.</s><s xml:id="_8P785AA">Regarding these, it is necessary to make rules for remote surgery support.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_UBxAMBY">CONCLUSION</head><p xml:id="_rx5XCCZ"><s xml:id="_v7YZZY8">Under COVID-19 conditions, a remote consultation system with real-time audio-visual capability may play an important role in acute stroke management while maintaining the quality of patient care.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_zKQvhcZ">Ethics approval statements</head><p xml:id="_ZpZrTSz"><s xml:id="_yk7AUbP">e study protocol was reviewed and approved by the ethics committee and the research review board at the affiliated hospital.</s><s xml:id="_Hm2DYRf">All patients were provided informed consent, and each site had obtained Institutional Review Board approval and signed consent forms.</s><s xml:id="_Cz2D2M4">e participants and any identifiable individuals consented to the publication of their image.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_qJmDNaA"><s xml:id="_53GeNzn">Figure 1: System configuration.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,124.56,506.92,362.88,195.36" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_6xMzrqx"><s xml:id="_CAHHfY8">Figure 2: Live streaming display on iPad.</s><s xml:id="_BDyz7C6">Eight images can be displayed at the same time.</s><s xml:id="_wWsgrgk">By selecting the screen, images can be freely enlarged or reduced on the iPad.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,125.28,468.49,361.44,227.64" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_nDb6XG9"><s xml:id="_EQeSpRK">Figure 3: Acute ischemic stroke supervised at home.</s><s xml:id="_xA9YmNJ">Acute ischemic stroke due to the left middle cerebral artery occlusion.</s><s xml:id="_bfSp5CT">rombectomy with a stent retriever was performed by neuroendovascular trainees.</s><s xml:id="_vHNQZV2">e operator was able to speak with the senior supervisor through a bone conduction headphone and to talk to assistants or radiology technicians without any hearing difficulties (a).</s><s xml:id="_aqHg9HH">Live streaming images of split monitors on the iPad (b).</s><s xml:id="_cKHbnp8">By selecting areas on images, left ICA occlusion was made clearly visible on the screen (c).</s><s xml:id="_7AuhvNN">e supervisor at home could freely change the size of the image by pinching in and pinching out.</s><s xml:id="_yKhWHxW">e senior physician could supervise the procedure while at home (d and e).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,55.08,74.37,501.84,259.44" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_PYsaC3y"><s xml:id="_X8HP4Q2">Systems introduced in each hospital.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Hospital with</cell><cell>Affiliated hospital</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>interventional</cell><cell>(Endovascular</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>specialist</cell><cell>surgeon)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(Supervisor)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Camera</cell><cell>Sony, Tokyo, Japan</cell><cell>Axis Communication,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Lund, Sweden</cell></row><row><cell>Angiography</cell><cell>Siemens, Erlangen</cell><cell>Canon, Tokyo, Japan</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Germany</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Encoder</cell><cell>STRASSE, Tokyo,</cell><cell>Carina System, Kobe,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Japan</cell><cell>Japan</cell></row><row><cell>Bone</cell><cell>AfterShokz, Texas,</cell><cell>AfterShokz, Texas,</cell></row><row><cell>conduction</cell><cell>Austin</cell><cell>Austin</cell></row><row><cell>headphone</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_34XrW4b"><s xml:id="_srqwVnv">Speed delay between the source and devices in each hospital.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Place</cell><cell>Source Internet</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head xml:id="_RuAVcya">Acknowledgment</head><p xml:id="_98qy84Z"><s xml:id="_3eTZ7cg">All authors thank <rs type="person">Mr. Masahiro Kazama</rs> for his assistance regarding data equation.</s></p></div>
			</div>			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_XrYeSpE">Authors' contributions</head><p xml:id="_eA7Yapu"><s xml:id="_h4gQhtc">All authors have met the four criteria for authorship, as described by the journal.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_DW7eZye">Declaration of patient consent</head><p xml:id="_S372ufT"><s xml:id="_2j9ABwK">e authors certify that they have obtained all appropriate patient consent.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_FjuZ3bU">Financial support and sponsorship</head><p xml:id="_YenuyZr"><s xml:id="_zbgcSYE">Nil.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_QvpkyKn">Conflicts of interest</head><p xml:id="_mrH7cv4"><s xml:id="_sZbJk7R">ere are no conflicts of interest.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_dHcbG8z">Training and supervision of thrombectomy by remote live streaming support (RESS): Randomized comparison using simulated stroke interventions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bechstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Buhk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Frölich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Broocks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Hanning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Erler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00062-019-00870-5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_44kVWdA">Clin Neuroradiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="181" to="187" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bechstein M, Buhk JH, Frölich AM, Broocks G, Hanning U, Erler M, et al. Training and supervision of thrombectomy by remote live streaming support (RESS): Randomized comparison using simulated stroke interventions. Clin Neuroradiol 2021;31:181-7.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_zGzM7Mf">Republished: Interhospital teleproctoring of endovascular intracranial aneurysm treatment using a dedicated live-streaming technology: First experiences during the COVID-19 pandemic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bechstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Elsheikh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Wodarg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Taschner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Hanning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Buhk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/neurintsurg-2020-016722.rep</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_K3y6QHV">J Neurointerv Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bechstein M, Elsheikh S, Wodarg F, Taschner CA, Hanning U, Buhk JH, et al. Republished: Interhospital teleproctoring of endovascular intracranial aneurysm treatment using a dedicated live-streaming technology: First experiences during the COVID-19 pandemic. J Neurointerv Surg 2021;1:e1.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qEWNeDx">United States medicolegal progress and innovation in telemedicine in the age of COVID-19: A primer for neurosurgeons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cruz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Nieblas-Bedolla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Feroze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Ellenbogen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/neuros/nyab185</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_hXJ29Cu">Neurosurgery</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="364" to="371" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Cruz MJ, Nieblas-Bedolla E, Young CC, Feroze AH, Williams JR, Ellenbogen RG, et al. United States medicolegal progress and innovation in telemedicine in the age of COVID-19: A primer for neurosurgeons. Neurosurgery 2021;89:364-71.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_MaJWkzZ">rombectomy for stroke in the public health care system of Brazil</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Martins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mont' Alverne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Rebello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Abud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Silva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Lima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1056/nejmoa2000120</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_KT6wmG4">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">382</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2316" to="2326" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Martins SO, Mont&apos; Alverne F, Rebello LC, Abud DG, Silva GS, Lima FO, et al. rombectomy for stroke in the public health care system of Brazil. N Engl J Med 2020;382:2316-26.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_sHvpj5c">Validation of a smartphone application in the evaluation and treatment of acute stroke in a comprehensive stroke center</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Martins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Almeida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Brondani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Carbonera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Souza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1161/strokeaha.119.026727</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_XNggHVB">Stroke</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="240" to="246" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Martins SC, Weiss G, Almeida AG, Brondani R, Carbonera LA, Souza A, et al. Validation of a smartphone application in the evaluation and treatment of acute stroke in a comprehensive stroke center. Stroke 2020;51:240-6.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_nBtBFGP">International teleproctoring in neurointerventional surgery and its potential impact on clinical trials in the era of COVID-19: Legal and technical considerations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">'</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Orru</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Marosfoi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Patel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Coon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wald</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Repucci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/neurintsurg-2020-017053</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_PQ7k9zT">J NeuroIntervent Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="5" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Orru&apos; E, Marosfoi M, Patel NV, Coon AL, Wald C, Repucci N, et al. International teleproctoring in neurointerventional surgery and its potential impact on clinical trials in the era of COVID-19: Legal and technical considerations. J NeuroIntervent Surg 2020;13:1-5.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_EkZGtaK">Safety Management Guidelines for Information System and Service Providers that Handle Medical Information</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-1-4939-3594-9_21</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.meti.go.jp/policy/mono_info_service/healthcare/01gl.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_T2TJu4t">Website of the Ministry of Economy, Trade and Industry of Japan</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021-11-22">2021 Nov 22</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Safety Management Guidelines for Information System and Service Providers that Handle Medical Information. Website of the Ministry of Economy, Trade and Industry of Japan. Available from: https://www.meti.go.jp/policy/mono_info_ service/healthcare/01gl.pdf. [Last accessed on 2021 Nov 22].</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_tMGpUDe">Communication-type smartphone application can contribute to reducing elapsed time to reperfusion therapy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sakai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Sato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Komatsu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Mitsumura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Iguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ishibashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10072-021-05132-2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_99ghbHs">Neurol Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sakai K, Sato T, Komatsu T, Mitsumura H, Iguchi Y, Ishibashi T, et al. Communication-type smartphone application can contribute to reducing elapsed time to reperfusion therapy. Neurol Sci 2021;26:1-6.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_vrTXK7x">A new support system using a mobile device (smartphone) for diagnostic image display and treatment of stroke</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Takao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Murayama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ishibashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Karagiozov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Abe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1161/strokeaha.111.627943</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_WDmCBRt">Stroke</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="236" to="239" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Takao H, Murayama Y, Ishibashi T, Karagiozov KL, Abe T. A new support system using a mobile device (smartphone) for diagnostic image display and treatment of stroke. Stroke 2012;43:236-9.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_HqN7JQs">A smartphone application as a telemedicine tool for stroke care management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Takao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sakai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Mitsumura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Komatsu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Yuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Takeshita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2176/nmc.oa.2020-0302</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_2G7fUDN">Neurol Med Chir</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="260" to="267" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<pubPlace>Tokyo</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Takao H, Sakai K, Mitsumura H, Komatsu T, Yuki I, Takeshita K, et al. A smartphone application as a telemedicine tool for stroke care management. Neurol Med Chir (Tokyo) 2021;61:260-7.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_EQd3ZXu">Telehealth transformation: COVID-19 and the rise of virtual care</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wosik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fudim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Cameron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Gellad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Phinney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/jamia/ocaa067</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_BzEeXFg">J Am Med Inform Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="957" to="962" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Wosik J, Fudim M, Cameron B, Gellad ZF, Cho A, Phinney D, et al. Telehealth transformation: COVID-19 and the rise of virtual care. J Am Med Inform Assoc 2020;27:957-62.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
