<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_mWp73U4">Pyridine Nucleotide-Linked Oxidation of Methanol in Methanol-Assimilating Yeasts</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mehtai</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Science Institute , Ahmedabad , Gujarat , India</note>
								<orgName type="institution">Science Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Ahmedabad</settlement>
									<region>Gujarat</region>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_wb2FnP3">Pyridine Nucleotide-Linked Oxidation of Methanol in Methanol-Assimilating Yeasts</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">F6202232C3419F708139DA84B67C0265</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received for publication 25 July 1975</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T07:32+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_hTYnpvA"><p xml:id="_eKVG6nu"><s xml:id="_VCgJynu">An alcohol dehydrogenase linked to nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide and requiring glutathione has been isolated and partially purified from two meth- anol-assimilating yeasts.</s><s xml:id="_tAagFzs">It differs from previously described methanol-oxidiz- ing enzymes in pH optima, electron acceptor specificity, substrate specificity, inhibition pattern, and stability.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="486.48" lry="714.72"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="486.48" lry="714.72"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="486.48" lry="714.72"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_YH9YzRM"><p xml:id="_zEKf5ZW"><s xml:id="_gKtHwTq">Several workers have investigated methanol oxidation in bacteria and none has reported evidence of a pyridine nucleotide-linked me- thanol-oxidizing enzyme (1-3).</s><s xml:id="_PUERtpk">Tani et al. (6)  described methanol oxidation in yeast that occurs via an oxidase.</s><s xml:id="_PDD4wdc">The data suggest that a flavine nucleotide was involved.</s></p><p xml:id="_WGrBGat"><s xml:id="_9Ws9PFx">This paper describes the nicotinamide ade- nine dinucleotide (NAD)-linked methanol-oxi- dizing enzyme in methanol-assimilating yeasts, Pichia pinus and Candida boidianii.</s></p><p xml:id="_kJzdeg5"><s xml:id="_mpwnYyS">A previous study showed that this enzyme is present in P. pinus and Kloeckera sp.</s><s xml:id="_jbtycA2">2201 (4).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_3Uczu3N">MATERIALS AND METHODS</head><p xml:id="_K24v5Mc"><s xml:id="_f399NCv">Organisms.</s><s xml:id="_kt9BQrP">P. pinus NRRL YB-4025 and C. boi- dianii NRRL Y-2332 were obtained from the Northern Regional Laboratory, Peoria, Ill.</s><s xml:id="_tqWE4rj">Cultures were main- tained as described previously (4).</s></p><p xml:id="_aEVYH9f"><s xml:id="_cE9gbqQ">Growth conditions.</s><s xml:id="_3NJ24PR">Both cultures were grown as described previously (4) in a synthetic medium con- sisting of: NH4NO, 0.5%; K2HPO 0.2%; MgSO4.</s><s xml:id="_7Sdg84V">7H3O, 0.05%; yeast extracts, 0.2%; and methanol, 2%.</s></p><p xml:id="_Z2CHme9"><s xml:id="_WJKqaJ5">Chemicals: Methanol was purchased from Fisher Scientific Co., Fairlane, N.J.</s><s xml:id="_b7A85F8">NAD and its phosphate form (NADP), dichlorophenol indophenol, and gluta- thione (GSH) were from Sigma Chemical Co., St. Louis, Mo.</s></p><p xml:id="_Xcu4tKX"><s xml:id="_v8ZaqDF">Preparation of cell extracts.</s><s xml:id="_tREK54n">The cultures were centrifuged at 27,000 x g at 4 C and washed twice with deionized water.</s><s xml:id="_bt8pDgq">The washed cells (5 g, wet weight) were suspended in 30 ml of 0.001 M potassium phosphate buffer (pH 7.0) with 5 g of washed, superfine glass beads (Superbrite type 110, 3M Com- pany, St. Paul, Minn.).</s><s xml:id="_ZBHAWNM">The suspension, contained in a 100-ml beaker placed in dry ice, was treated in an ultrasonic disintegrator (Branson Sonifier, Stamford, Conn.) fitted with a 2.5-cm probe for 5 min at 1 C and then centrifuged at 27,000 x g for 30 min at 4 C.</s><s xml:id="_8EA6Csb">The clear supernatant was then assayed for the enzyme.</s></p><p xml:id="_6mdPJ27"><s xml:id="_WkyesMS">'Present address: Department of Microbiology, Smith Kline &amp; French Laboratories, Philadelphia, <ref type="bibr">Pa. 19101.</ref></s><s xml:id="_V5Xs47h">Methanol dehydrogenase was assayed, as described previously (4), in a 1-ml system containing: potas- sium phosphate buffer, 100 gmol; NAD, 1 Amol; GSH, 1 umol; and enzyme protein, 10 to 20 ug.</s><s xml:id="_MjVDnAe">To start the reaction, 20 Amol of methanol was added.</s><s xml:id="_R6VAumT">Protein was measured by the method of Warburg and Christian (7).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_dM3nEVK">RESULTS</head><p xml:id="_AEwq9aX"><s xml:id="_X4Uek6K">Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> shows amount of methanol dehydrogenase activity in both yeasts at different pH values; pH <ref type="bibr">7.5</ref> is optimum for both.</s></p><p xml:id="_u49jyzj"><s xml:id="_rfWUcy2">Cofactors required to oxidize methanol in a cell-free system.</s><s xml:id="_Fu7ZRsJ">The results in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> indicate that different cofactors affect methanol oxidation in a cell-free system.</s><s xml:id="_mg89pNu">GSH stimulated the activity; this oxidation requires NAD (NADP cannot replace it).</s></p><p xml:id="_Yp5XsxV"><s xml:id="_RZEbftx">Replacement of GSH by other thiol com- pounds.</s><s xml:id="_pMgpwGZ">Several thiol compounds were tested for their ability to replace GSH.</s><s xml:id="_ZjbkE2A">It was found that methanol oxidation in both yeasts depends strongly on GSH; dithiothreitol, cysteine, and sodium dithionite cannot replace it.</s></p><p xml:id="_FVdxKU5"><s xml:id="_5vDyFSY">Partial purification of enzyme from P. pinus.</s><s xml:id="_k7YYyuu">A crude extract (40 ml) was applied to a column (95 by 2.5 cm) of diethylaminoethyl-cellulose that had been equilibrated with 0.01 M phosphate buffer.</s><s xml:id="_vsmHa5D">The charged column was treated with 300 ml of 0.01 M buffer, 200 ml of 0.1 M buffer, and 500 ml of 0.3 M buffer, each containing 0.001 M GSH.</s><s xml:id="_hN3ZMqr">The enzyme was eluted when the column was washed with 0.3 M phosphate buffer.</s><s xml:id="_rUdz2Sf">By this method, the enzyme was purified fourfold (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_WN9ZnCT">When purified further by ammonium sulfate fractionation or Sephadex G-200 column chromatography, it became inactive.</s><s xml:id="_zFUrJ8G">By an alternate method <ref type="bibr">(Table 3,</ref><ref type="bibr">no.</ref></s><s xml:id="_K567smd">2) using ammonium sulfate frac- tionation, about fourfold purification was ob- tained.</s><s xml:id="_ykesXxD">Minus cell-free extract 0 0 Minus NAD plus NAI)P 0 0 a The complete system contained (in a total volume of 1 ml): potassium phosphate buf'fer (pH 7.0), 200 Amol; NAD, 1 ,umol; GSH, 1 gmol; and enzyme protein, 10 to 20 Ag.</s><s xml:id="_KAr8P8U">Reaction was initiated with 20 jlmol of methanol.</s><s xml:id="_mngZeJe">" Nanomoles of NADH f'ormed per minute per milligram of' protein.</s></p><p xml:id="_FwMMGHV"><s xml:id="_DMJVF73">TABLE :3.</s><s xml:id="_GckMNvg">Partial purification of the methanol dehy'drogenase of P. pinus TVl Total aTotal sp Puriifi- Method Step (m l)IproeI activity acta cation Stability.</s><s xml:id="_Zuz7d4u">At 4 C the enzyme lost all ability to oxidize methanol within 24 h after fourfold purification by ammonium sulfate fractionation or diethylaminoethyl-cellulose chromatogra- phy; at 50 C it lost its activity within <ref type="bibr">5 min.</ref></s><s xml:id="_pcPGbA4">Methanol-oxidizing activity did not stabilize when dithiothreitol, GSH, substrate, or a com- bination of GSH and substrate was added during purification, possibly because protecting proteins were removed and sulfhydryl groups oxidized rapidly at the active sites.</s><s xml:id="_EjFbtpK">An inhibition study supported this observation.</s></p><p xml:id="_bhgurKT"><s xml:id="_xvTpNaC">Inhibitor studies.</s><s xml:id="_bPrbxrX">Para-chloromercuric ben- zoate or iodoacetamide at a concentration of 10-6 M inhibited methanol-oxidizing activity from both yeasts after the enzyme was preincubated for 15 min.</s><s xml:id="_gwPY4C2">Substrate specificity of a partially purified enzyme from P. pinus.</s><s xml:id="_w5SYWSS">The partially purified enzyme showed broader substrate specificity for various primary and secondary alcohols (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">4</ref>).</s></p><p xml:id="_kjP5jUH"><s xml:id="_4ed7w5G">Electron acceptor specificity.</s><s xml:id="_J8FfuQd">Methanol de- hydrogenase activity from the partially purified enzyme is specific for NAD and GSH but not for NADP, potassium ferricyanide, dichlorophenol indophenol, and phenazine methosulfate.</s></p><p xml:id="_zVWxQmn"><s xml:id="_brDjvBN">Effect of metal ions.</s><s xml:id="_N9NYZgp">The effect of various metal ions on the oxidation of methanol by the enzyme is shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">5</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_QGEKfuS">None of the metal ions tested stimulated the activity, and it was completely inhibited by Cu and Hg at a concen- tration of 10-4 M. Zn gave 50%c inhibition at this concentration.</s><s xml:id="_tzbEjxp">ZnSO47* H,0 50 CuSO4,5H20 ( MnC12 4H20 102 HgCl20 CaCl22H20 85 aThe enzyme was preincubated at a concentration of 10-' M for 1 h at room temperature and then as- sayed for activity.</s></p><p xml:id="_TJ6HGQs"><s xml:id="_u8Fsm2z">I DISCUSSION The results of this study demonstrate that the methanol-assimilating yeasts P. pinus and C. boidienii contain NAD-specific and GSH- requiring alcohol dehydrogenases that oxidize methanol.</s></p><p xml:id="_DZp8nuH"><s xml:id="_UMenpe8">In contrast, methanol dehydrogenases of Pseudomonas strains M27, AM1, and RJ1 were shown to be independent of pyridine nucleo- tides, and required phenazine methosulfate and dichlorophenol indophenol <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_7t6WCKH">An oxidase enzyme that utilizes molecular oxygen has been described for Kloeckera sp.</s><s xml:id="_ERDbSPG">2201 and C. boidianii (5, 6).</s><s xml:id="_EmKT6fW">The pH optima are 8.5 to 9.0 for the methanol dehydrogenase enzyme in bacteria (2, 3), 7.5 to 9.5 for the methanol oxidase in yeasts, and 7.5 for the enzyme described here.</s></p><p xml:id="_kqPvQqg"><s xml:id="_9h2NT8V">The methanol-oxidizing enzyme in bacteria (1, 2) and yeast <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6)</ref> is quite stable, but the partially purified Pichia methanol-oxidizing enzyme is very unstable.</s></p><p xml:id="_8a54MDn"><s xml:id="_Ys7nbAD">Methanol dehydrogenases reported in the literature have broad specificity toward primary alcohols; the enzyme described here also ex- hibits similar broad specificity.</s></p><p xml:id="_5zp7BYT"><s xml:id="_c7bzFW7">An unusual affinity was observed with the Pichia enzyme in that isopropanol was oxidized very rapidly.</s><s xml:id="_Hbpvfb5">This reaction has not been ob- served with other alcohol dehydrogenases.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>a</head><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_nxwG7nA"><s xml:id="_BXdMdtG">Nanomoles of NADH formed per minute per milligram of protein.</s><s xml:id="_CcHNtt7">°DEAE, Diethylaminoethyl.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLE 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_fBJXSc6"><s xml:id="_jzsDFfq">Specific activities of methanol dehydrogenase in methanol-assimilating yeasts</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Act ivityv</cell></row><row><cell>System (pH)</cell><cell>P. pinus</cell><cell>C. boidianjii</cell></row><row><cell>5.5</cell><cell>10.8</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>6.0</cell><cell>42.9</cell><cell>2.0</cell></row><row><cell>6.5</cell><cell>48.2</cell><cell>4.0</cell></row><row><cell>7.0</cell><cell>53.6</cell><cell>118.0</cell></row><row><cell>7.5</cell><cell>90.8</cell><cell>279.0</cell></row><row><cell>8.0</cell><cell>64.3</cell><cell>268.0</cell></row><row><cell>8.5</cell><cell>21.4</cell><cell>247.0</cell></row><row><cell>9.0</cell><cell>27.0</cell><cell>107.0</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">a Nanomoles of NADH f'ormed per minute per</cell></row><row><cell>milligram of protein.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>TABLE 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_fxQjtsm"><s xml:id="_YfkA9Df">Cofactor requirement for oxidation of methanol by a cell-free system of methanol-assimilating yeastsa</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Activitv V</cell></row><row><cell>Svstem</cell><cell>P. pinus</cell><cell>C. boidianii</cell></row><row><cell>Complete</cell><cell>90.8</cell><cell>279.0</cell></row><row><cell>Minus GSH</cell><cell>:32.0</cell><cell>30.0</cell></row><row><cell>Minus NAD</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Minus methanol</cell><cell>10.0</cell><cell>15.0</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>TABLE 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_sm6geYP"><s xml:id="_qNTc9y6">Oxidation of various alcohols by the partially purified enzyme of P. pinus</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Substrate</cell><cell>Relative rate(</cell></row><row><cell>Met hanol Ethanol</cell><cell>100 27I7i</cell></row><row><cell>n-Propanol n-Butanol</cell><cell>144 50(</cell></row><row><cell>n-Pentanol Isopropanol Isobutanol</cell><cell>6 6:3:3 6</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>TABLE 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_vXurmpd"><s xml:id="_5q64nB5">Effect of metal ions on enzyme activity of P. piauS</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Metal ion</cell><cell>Relat ive act ivit! (v</cell></row><row><cell>None MgCl2</cell><cell>10() 90</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xml:id="_xpW6AtM"><p xml:id="_supjgxr"><s xml:id="_xtDkQPc">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS I thank <rs type="person">J. J. Trivedi</rs> for his interest and encouragement during this work, and also <rs type="person">L. Fare</rs> and <rs type="person">R. S. Burger</rs> for their help in reviewing this manuscript.</s></p></div>
			</div>			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_tvb87qN">The microbial oxidation of methanol. The alcohol dehydrogenase of Pseudomornas sp</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Anthony</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Zatman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1042/bj0960808</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_k3dG4j3">Biochem. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">96</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="808" to="812" />
			<date type="published" when="1965">1965</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>M27</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Anthony, C., and L. J. Zatman. 1965. The microbial oxidation of methanol. The alcohol dehydrogenase of Pseudomornas sp. M27. Biochem. J. 96:808-812.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_N5jU65t">Microbial growth on C, compounds. 6. Oxidation of methanol, formaldehyde and formate by methanol-grown Pseudomonrs AML</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Quale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1042/bj0930281</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_apadEQF">Biochem. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="281" to="290" />
			<date type="published" when="1964">1964</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Johnson, P. A., and J. R. Quale. 1964. Microbial growth on C, compounds. 6. Oxidation of methanol, form- aldehyde and formate by methanol-grown Pseudomonrs AML. Biochem. J. 93:281-290.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_fErFAYb">Studies on methanol-oxidizing bacteria. II. Purification and properties of methanol dehydrogenase from Pseudomonas RJ1. Antonie van Leeuwenhoek</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mehta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/bf02578862</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_nRZdByp">J. Microbiol. Serol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="295" to="312" />
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mehta, R. J. 1973. Studies on methanol-oxidizing bacteria. II. Purification and properties of methanol dehydro- genase from Pseudomonas RJ1. Antonie van Leeuwen- hoek J. Microbiol. Serol. 39:295-312.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_6CBCqMS">Demonstration of methanol dehydrogenase in methanol assimilating yeasts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mehta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/bf02026344</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_a2kxW8w">Experientia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="407" to="408" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mehta, R. J. 1975. Demonstration of methanol dehy- drogenase in methanol assimilating yeasts. Experientia 31:407-408.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_K5pfNsP">Microbial assimilation of methanol. The ethanol and methanol oxidizing enzymes of yeast Candida boidianii</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sahm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Wagner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1432-1033.1973.tb02907.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_FVfjpBf">Eur. J. Biochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="250" to="256" />
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sahm, H., and F. Wagner. 1973. Microbial assimilation of methanol. The ethanol and methanol oxidizing en- zymes of yeast Candida boidianii. Eur. J. Biochem. 36: 250-256.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_nJsa4Fs">The microbial metabolism of methanol. I. Formation and crystallization of methanol oxidizing enzyme in methanol utilizing yeast, Kloeckera sp</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Miya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Nishikawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ogata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/00021369.1972.10860215</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_dkfjZcE">Agric. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="68" to="75" />
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972. 2201</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Tani, Y., T. Miya, H. Nishikawa, and K. Ogata. 1972. The microbial metabolism of methanol. I. Formation and crystallization of methanol oxidizing enzyme in methanol utilizing yeast, Kloeckera sp. 2201 Agric. Biol. Chem. 36:68-75.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_7wjkaBJ">Isolierung und Kristallisation des Garungsferments Enolase</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Warburg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Christian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/bf01482279</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_jTrjKwr">Biochem. Z</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">310</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="384" to="421" />
			<date type="published" when="1942">1942</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Warburg, O., and W. Christian. 1942. Isolierung und Kristallisation des Garungsferments Enolase. Biochem. Z. 310:384-421.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
