<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_wRbt7eZ">SROI in the art gallery; valuing social impact</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><surname>Jackson</surname></persName>
							<email>andrew.jackson@canterbury.ac.uk</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Richard</forename><surname>Mcmanus</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Christ Church Business School , Canterbury Christ Church University , Canterbury , UK</note>
								<orgName type="department">Christ Church Business School</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Canterbury Christ Church University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Canterbury</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Canterbury Christ Church University , North Holmes Road , Canterbury , Kent CT1 1QU , UK</note>
								<orgName type="institution">Canterbury Christ Church University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>North Holmes Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>CT1 1QU</postCode>
									<settlement>Canterbury</settlement>
									<region>Kent</region>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ubG8mCs">SROI in the art gallery; valuing social impact</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">EB474B5EA5559767A8D90E23A4C5420E</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1080/09548963.2019.1617937</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T07:34+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term xml:id="_fm9ZBy2">SROI</term>
					<term xml:id="_SSAHY38">evaluation</term>
					<term xml:id="_nGjayaq">social impact</term>
					<term xml:id="_pDn8dcG">Turner Contemporary</term>
					<term xml:id="_fHsBpnx">Margate</term>
					<term xml:id="_pdFDzCK">art galleries</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_Bu9dxCB"><p xml:id="_uBrnDaU"><s xml:id="_WefXWBN">This article considers a project that used the Social Return on Investment (SROI) methodology to describe and measure the social impact of Turner Contemporary art gallery in Margate, a coastal town in the South East of England.</s><s xml:id="_KhZdJCJ">The article details the reasons why the methodology was chosen by the gallery, setting this in the context of the wider debate around evaluation and social impact reporting.</s><s xml:id="_VpgYZUH">A section of the research and analysis, which was carried out by COaST, a consultancy and research centre based within Canterbury Christ Church University, is described in detail, allowing the reader to understand the processes involved in this type of project and the kinds of outcomes that can be delivered using this method.</s><s xml:id="_7665vSd">Finally, an account is given of the impact the work had on the management of the gallery, and the ways in which the final report was used.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="493.228" lry="702.992"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="493.228" lry="702.992"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="493.228" lry="702.992"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="493.228" lry="702.992"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="493.228" lry="702.992"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="493.228" lry="702.992"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="493.228" lry="702.992"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="493.228" lry="702.992"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="493.228" lry="702.992"/>
		<surface n="10" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="493.228" lry="702.992"/>
		<surface n="11" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="493.228" lry="702.992"/>
		<surface n="12" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="493.228" lry="702.992"/>
		<surface n="13" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="493.228" lry="702.992"/>
		<surface n="14" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="493.228" lry="702.992"/>
		<surface n="15" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_9asGXSP">Introduction</head><p xml:id="_vS6nXVx"><s xml:id="_xRe7g2s">Turner Contemporary art gallery was established in 2001, with the current high-profile building opening in 2011. 1 It receives most of its revenue funding from Arts Council England and Kent County Council, supplemented by income from independent fundraising activities.</s><s xml:id="_XeDkg4E">Entrance to the gallery is free of charge, and in its first five years Turner Contemporary achieved more than 2 million visits. 2 As well as hosting exhibitions by internationally significant artists, the gallery also delivers a programme of workshops and activities.</s></p><p xml:id="_KaTkGVD"><s xml:id="_QecmZfM">The establishment of Turner Contemporary is a prime example of what has become known as arts-led regeneration <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Cameron &amp; Coaffee, 2005)</ref>, with one of its stated aims being "to be a catalyst for the regeneration of Thanet" (Eslea, 2018, November 9, Personal interview; Turner Contemporary, 2012). 3</s><s xml:id="_MjUyz2z">Until the 1970s Margate had benefitted from a thriving seaside tourist industry; however, with the advent of cheap package holidays to warmer climes, the town's tourist industry began to decline.</s><s xml:id="_zBV4FMa">The combined effects of deprivation, unemployment and a lack of resources and opportunities, have led to negative effects across the population of the town <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Ewbank et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Kennell, 2011)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_u9JUPgK">Responding to this economic and social decline, the gallery's key strategic aims included, "to change people and communities" and to "to build a larger, more diverse and more engaged audience for visual art" <ref type="bibr">(Turner Contemporary, 2012)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_7RMSajE"><s xml:id="_uhKxRxU">In 2015-16, the period under review, there were 415,000 visits to the gallery, attracting net additional visitor-related expenditure estimated at £7.8 million; 4 however, discussing why the gallery decided in 2014 to commission a social impact evaluation, Karen Eslea, one of the founding members of staff at the gallery and now the visitor experience manager, stated:</s></p><p xml:id="_SgC8DeB"><s xml:id="_9c2nQXm">Our economic impact is amazing, but it's about so much more than that.</s><s xml:id="_7whrzwQ">There is lots of important stuff going on, but how do you capture that, how do you go beyond that?</s><s xml:id="_6NggFkT"><ref type="bibr">(Eslea, 2018, November 9, Personal interview)</ref> The need for the gallery to justify its funding and demonstrate to its backers that that they were getting value for money, that they were "making a difference", was clear.</s><s xml:id="_pEyXN3Q">In addition, the team also sought to improve their understanding of their audiences, thus better informing their exhibitions and programming.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_EBCN2kn">The arts evaluation landscape</head><p xml:id="_up69VcY"><s xml:id="_8NqRTy9">Within the field of publicly subsidised arts and culture in the UK, there is an increasing emphasis on accountabilitymeasuring and valuing the impact and value of institutions and projects.</s><s xml:id="_yqEHpnf">Since the formation of the Arts Council of Great Britain in 1946, efforts to democratise culture have resulted in a significant sector of the arts becoming dependent on subsidy.</s><s xml:id="_wuypvtr">In its plans for 2018-2022, Arts Council England announced that it would be investing £409 million per year in 830 arts organisations, museums and libraries in its National Portfolio of Organisations <ref type="bibr">(Arts Council England, 2018)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_jvN3JGf">Organisations that receive most of their funding from the government or non-departmental public bodies are frequently required to guarantee future subsidy by producing evaluations of past performance, adhering to funding agreements and meeting targets.</s><s xml:id="_yVp4psH">This trend has led to the emergence of an arts evaluation industry, a specialised sector within the larger market research industry (examples in the UK include the marketing consultants Morris Hargreaves Macintyre and BOP Consulting), and the development and popularisation of "evaluation toolkits" that are made available to recipients of arts funding.</s><s xml:id="_9bMgG3c">Additionally (like the project described in this article) a significant amount of evaluation is also carried out in partnership with universities <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Oman &amp; Taylor, 2018)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_vr9NhZ8"><s xml:id="_mTuGham">There is an emerging view that organisations in the cultural sector need to establish their legitimacy by using the tools and concepts of economics to fully state the benefits they offer wider society, and that failure to embrace these methods will lead to arts organisations losing the subsidy they currently enjoy <ref type="bibr">(O'Brien, 2010, p. 4)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_Rk74AMD">Whilst economic valuation techniques are widely used across government to calculate the costs and benefits of competing demands on public funding, the cultural sector is lagging behind in its methods, largely because of the complexity of placing a monetary value on the benefits of culture to individuals or groups of people <ref type="bibr">(Donovan, 2013, p. 4)</ref>; however, this pressure to evaluate using quantitative methods creates anxiety, both amongst academics and researchers, and within arts organisations themselves <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(MacDowall, Badham, Blomkamp, &amp; Dunphy, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Mirza, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Phiddian, Meyrick, Barnett, &amp; Maltby, 2017)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_4Rywwyf"><s xml:id="_VwwVbJ5">As Belfiore and Bennett highlight:</s></p><p xml:id="_TA6sKEr"><s xml:id="_QARgbnM">… a 'toolkit approach' to arts impact assessment […] demands excessive simplifications, and its popularity is linked to its perceived advocacy potential rather than to any demonstrable contribution it may make to a genuine understanding of the nature and potential effects of artistic engagement.</s><s xml:id="_RAatB2a"><ref type="bibr">(Belfiore &amp; Bennett, 2010, p. 121)</ref> This brings to the fore a tension between two kinds of researchso-called "legitimate" research carried out for academic ends, and "advocacy driven" research that is characterised as being subservient to the needs and priorities of organisations who need to justify their impact and funding <ref type="bibr">(Belfiore, 2016, p. 205)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_vaew4x6">Bennett has described this as the "torn halves of cultural policy research"in other words "critical" versus "instrumental" approaches (2004).</s></p><p xml:id="_NWQxbcV"><s xml:id="_PfDaqmj">Concerns have been expressed that governments are only interested in instrumental value and its social and economic impact.</s><s xml:id="_7ACqmea">Consequently, data collection to inform policy and funding decisions not only overlooks capturing intrinsic value, but the methods employed have difficulty grasping the essence of subjective experiences <ref type="bibr">(Holden, 2006, p. 3)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_zM8c2CZ"><s xml:id="_WWKcmNz">Given the policy environment outlined above, it is hard to argue against the pragmatism of arts organisations who are required to evidence their impact in ways that are both convincing and communicable.</s><s xml:id="_GK6JwSP">Arts managers seek to maximise the value of their activity reporting, not only to account to stakeholders, but also to arrive at understandings of their effectiveness that can lead to better strategy and, in turn, a more efficient use of resources.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_PneDmw7">Social return on investment</head><p xml:id="_3y6aYMG"><s xml:id="_CssMcjJ">The problem for Turner Contemporary was how to find robust evidence of their social impact.</s><s xml:id="_24dUSJa">At one level this was an exercise in advocacy, but at another there was clearly a genuine curiosity amongst the management team to find ways to describe and understand the difference they were making.</s><s xml:id="_wrJkE4r">The gallery had not been without its critics amongst the local population and in the press <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Batty, 2016)</ref> and in academic work that had been openly hostile to the idea of arts-led regeneration in Margate <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Hubbard, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Lees &amp; McKiernan, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Ward, 2018)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_f39VW9u">When the report was commissioned there was a sense that the gallery needed to develop a stronger evidence base in order to communicate its benefits more effectively.</s></p><p xml:id="_GJCuspn"><s xml:id="_SU95Rpk">Against this backdrop, in 2014 the gallery commissioned a report on its social impact from the COaST research centre at Canterbury Christ Church University.</s><s xml:id="_2x5wgmn">The team at COaST proposed the use of the relatively newly developed Social Return on Investment (SROI) methodology <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Nicholls, Lawlor, Neitzert, &amp; Godspeed, 2012)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_99B6TY7">The current guardians and advocates of the process are an organisation called Social Value UK, who aim to ensure the method is used consistently and adheres to a set of published principles.</s><s xml:id="_3wQUj99">Social Value UK describe SROI to potential users as:</s></p><p xml:id="_3WPAx2p"><s xml:id="_6Gx6TKW">It surprised us all how large the amount of work was, and how it took longer than expected.</s><s xml:id="_Tr9wnwb">I don't think I had really factored in enough of my own time.</s><s xml:id="_xzB5bdE"><ref type="bibr">(Eslea, 2018, November 9, Personal interview)</ref> The investment and expertise required to undertake an SROI analysis is considerable, and this has been one of the key criticisms of the method.</s><s xml:id="_YrMf7t5">In their review of SROI, Yates and Marra conclude not only that more training might be needed to produce "better, more uniform and more informative SROIs", but SROI should itself be subject to a metaevaluation to ascertain in each case whether the cost of the method justified the benefits accrued <ref type="bibr">(2017, p. 137)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_bP79CTC"><s xml:id="_uHcBzzn">Due to the scale of the Turner Contemporary SROI evaluation, the constraints of a journal article do not allow us to describe every part of the process, nor discuss all the data in detail. 5</s><s xml:id="_325XR42">Instead, we aim to articulate the key parts of the methodology, offering some of the findings as illustrations of how the research was carried out, and how the data was analysed.</s></p><p xml:id="_4Syvqxm"><s xml:id="_sDCeV9W">Originating in San Francisco in the late 1990s, forms of the SROI methodology have been in use in the UK since the early 2000s and the method was endorsed by the UK government in 2009 <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Nicholls, 2017)</ref>. 6</s><s xml:id="_erGvRvG">The method relies on its users strictly following a set of principles that are published online in a comprehensive guidance document, and which can also be understood by attending a two-day training course run by Social Value UK.</s><s xml:id="_EczqMWf">The stated intention is that international standardisation will increase and improve practice and allow findings from SROI studies to be compared and understood; however, as Nicholls acknowledges, SROI continues to be interpreted in different ways <ref type="bibr">(2017, p. 128)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_VMJCyJh">For instance, although in their discussion of cultural advocacy and evidence based policy making Oman and Taylor explicitly refer to organisations in the cultural sector enthusiastically "evidencing their value through social return on investment" (2018, p. 226), they subsequently critique a published analysis by <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Fujiwara (2013)</ref> that bears no resemblance to the method endorsed by Social Value UK.</s><s xml:id="_c9NfccN">Where Fujiwara's work uses large publicly available datasets to carry out purely quantitative analysis, the widely adopted SROI method endorsed by Social Value International uses a very different approach.</s><s xml:id="_KZVy3JV">Although based on accounting methods, and frequently associated with the production of a number, or ratio, that represents a return on investment, the method actually uses qualitative, rich description, in combination with quantitative outcomes.</s><s xml:id="_mRjC8VE">This, as we discuss below, leads to range of insights that extend much further than a set of numbers.</s><s xml:id="_a7ZNCB7">As SROI practitioners point out:</s></p><p xml:id="_hgm6r2S"><s xml:id="_Epzpa5F">… SROI is much more than just a number.</s><s xml:id="_Hngjyny">It is a story about change, on which to base decisions, that includes case studies and qualitative, quantitative and financial information.</s><s xml:id="_HXregRf"><ref type="bibr">(Nicholls et al., 2012, p. 8)</ref> The association with numerical outputs has however, resulted in some suspicion about the process, particularly in the arts sector.</s><s xml:id="_M4J87zx">After the report was complete, Eslea told us: "At the time, when it was relatively new, there were a few external comments saying that using a financial figure is not the best way to go … " (Eslea, 2018, November 9, Personal interview).</s></p><p xml:id="_HX9urkM"><s xml:id="_szTXhz2">When Woodley et.</s><s xml:id="_uCvSdAQ">al. carried out a survey on behalf of Arts Council England that investigated the meaning of resilience to arts practitioners, they found that management theory and practice informed by business seldom appealed or seemed relevant to arts and cultural sector workers.</s><s xml:id="_mQf92Sp">They noted that " … this can in part be a language barrier -with 'profit', 'return' and other concepts from the business and start-up world being seen as alien to the sector" <ref type="bibr">(Woodley, Towell, Turpin, Thelwall, &amp; Schneider, 2018, p. 58)</ref>; however, the SROI method is relevant for the cultural sector because it not only involves a detailed consideration of the investment that must take place in order to achieve an outcome (in other words a "cost/benefit analysis"), but it requires the evaluator to directly engage with the audiences and users of the provision.</s><s xml:id="_bc9PghH">This process offers rich insights about what matters to them, requiring them to describe in their own language the impacts (both positive and negative) that they feel as result of taking part in the activity.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_HkaJhBp">SROI principles</head><p xml:id="_8q4vWbV"><s xml:id="_t2zecwk">There are six principles that SROI practitioners follow as outlined in the guides published both by Social Value UK and others (APM Specific Interest Group white paper, 2016; <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Nicholls, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Nicholls et al., 2012)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_kmfKNjz">The principles or, more accurately, steps, are:</s></p><p xml:id="_Mu4nZAE"><s xml:id="_RQX8ppW">(1) Establish the scope and outline those affected by the intervention (2) Determine a story of change (3) Collect evidence (4) Establish impact and causality (5) Calculate a value for SROI (6) Use and implement what has been learnt</s></p><p xml:id="_v4xYXXG"><s xml:id="_8qCZnkJ">In this project data was collected using a range of methods including interviews, focus groups, workshops, observation, surveys and desk research.</s><s xml:id="_R6tTEuM">In the following sections we illustrate our approach by outlining a specific sub-section of the research.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_atvezam">Scope</head><p xml:id="_jer7F9E"><s xml:id="_mvTaws5">The scope is established by delineating the research, both in its breadth and by the time period that is being reported.</s><s xml:id="_m5hzaQr">As the outcome will be a return on investment, the period of an SROI report normally coincides with an accounting period, or a financial year.</s><s xml:id="_9RvwG2B">In this case we measured the social return on investment in the gallery's 2015-16 financial year and we were able to use accounting information from that period to record the quantity of (monetary) resources expended to deliver the activities.</s></p><p xml:id="_pH6Arjv"><s xml:id="_h39HDct">Establishing the breadth of the research was more challenging.</s><s xml:id="_hTFu9MR">Initially the ambition had been to carry out an SROI report on the activities and impact of the entire organisation; however, it transpired this underestimated the time and resources necessary to produce a report of this scale.</s><s xml:id="_mkaT5WD">To date, most SROI reports have been designed to account for just one strand of an organisation's activityperhaps associated with a distinct project or initiative.</s><s xml:id="_QVkERN6">Our solution was to identify and categorise three distinct types of activity delivered by the gallerythe exhibition programme; the work with schools and colleges; and the evening classes, workshops and drop-in arts education events.</s></p><p xml:id="_Avjp9B7"><s xml:id="_KMeufZB">We identified and aggregated the gallery's stakeholdersdefined in SROI as people who experience "material change" as a result of an organisation's outputsinto six overarching groups.</s><s xml:id="_Cmyxsjd">We classified the most significant of these as primary stakeholders; these were visitors to exhibitions, participants in formal education and participants in lifelong learning.</s><s xml:id="_epZzwtQ">We classified the remaining three groups as secondary; they experience change even though they may not be directly involved in the activities of the gallery.</s><s xml:id="_2Zpqz4d">These secondary stakeholder groups were local retailers, non-visiting local residents and local artists.</s><s xml:id="_waUwa5f">Our research found that these three groups benefit from increased footfall in the retail areas of the town, increases in tourism, a changed visitor demographic, the growth of a creative and cultural industry infra-structure and increased levels of social capital.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_2CzmpRu">Story of change, collecting evidence and establishing impact</head><p xml:id="_HqQjePk"><s xml:id="_QUFBT4j">We dealt with the problem of complexity and scale by producing a discrete SROI report for each of the activities considered, producing a separate return on investment ratio, and combining these to make a final overall report.</s><s xml:id="_PGx3V3W">For brevity, we will give an account of the way we established the SROI for one of these activities, the lifelong learner provision.</s><s xml:id="_5HhSxxU">We used the term lifelong learning to describe educational activities that are not undertaken as part of a formal programme of education.</s><s xml:id="_sQd4Pyc">Typically, participants will attend weekly sessions at the gallery where they engage in arts activities, produce their own artwork and, in some cases, commission professional artists to collaborate in the production of installations and exhibitions.</s><s xml:id="_DgaA2d4">Others attend occasional drop-in sessions with their families on Sundays or during school holidays where they undertake arts and craft projects.</s><s xml:id="_PQef5MA">To give an idea of the scale of the programme, 8,586 participants took part in activities, projects and workshops identified as lifelong learning, either on a regular basis throughout the period under consideration, or at a one-off.</s></p><p xml:id="_9AxhE3z"><s xml:id="_sC68u2K">As discussed above, the central tenet of SROI methodology is that the outcomes are identified by the stakeholders themselves, typically using interviews, focus groups and workshops, with analysis being undertaken to identify dominant themes and patterns in the dataessentially a qualitative methodology that is repeated until saturation is achieved.</s><s xml:id="_agzRpjh">At this stage the SROI method strongly resembles a grounded theory methodology where themes are drawn inductively from qualitative data <ref type="bibr">(Glaser &amp; Strauss, 1967)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_dP2Y79e">Time spent talking with stakeholders is not only the most time-consuming aspect of an SROI analysis, but also has the biggest impact on the quality of the reporting.</s></p><p xml:id="_aWJfaDT"><s xml:id="_AWhQTgc">A three-stage approach was taken to identify stories of change: first, discussions were had with both the Gallery and practitioners to derive a baseline understanding; second, a focus group was performed with six lifelong learners to establish outcomes as a result of the activities; finally, a series of surveys were designed using the results from the focus group.</s><s xml:id="_DjybFaN">These surveys extended the sample of those stakeholders considered in the analysis in order to obtain more comfort that these changes were true of those participants not part of the focus group.</s><s xml:id="_8FG6pDw">Each outcome is discussed below with a selection of the material gathered as part of our interviews and focus groups.</s></p><p xml:id="_rfRKnw6"><s xml:id="_VTCfYYm">Outcome 1they became more open-minded and confident Participants feel empowered, increasing their self-belief, creating a stronger sense of selfefficacy and leading them to become more pro-active members of the community.</s></p><p xml:id="_P72BSwC"><s xml:id="_hV82qJr">There is something that everyone's good at.</s><s xml:id="_MmVHVtw">The workshops increase participants' confidence, allowing them to find their strengths, tackle their weaknesses and as a result believe in themselves.</s><s xml:id="_cuxtxg3">They find it easier to sustain their efforts even after failures or setbacks.</s><s xml:id="_Vpr7FMZ">They feel more in control over the situations they encounter.</s></p><p xml:id="_kbrb9wS"><s xml:id="_8UFDkVX">Outcome 2they strengthened their social networks Participants improve their ability to form better and stronger relationships and therefore feel less lonely and experience a sense of belonging to the community.</s></p><p xml:id="_5vwwJfC"><s xml:id="_rkXTD2Z">It really changed a lot of things for memy outlook on things (…) and just generally my ability for getting back out and about.</s></p><p xml:id="_HM3hmCC"><s xml:id="_89hdV6B">… you make friends with different people with different interests.</s></p><p xml:id="_bC8Bq4j"><s xml:id="_XupyxqS">Through interacting at Turner Contemporary, the participants improve their social skills, finding it easier to socialise outside of the organisation, enabling them to enjoy a sense of belonging to the community.</s></p><p xml:id="_8TkUhjq"><s xml:id="_ZajE3k6">Outcome 3they enhanced their knowledge and skills Lifelong Learners report developing new skills and improving existing ones, which boosts their confidence and increases an appetite for more.</s><s xml:id="_BKmw6b2">A combination of confidence, inspiration, and new competencies influences the next steps in their lives, such as choosing to enter higher or further education, working in arts related environment, or holding an exhibition of their own work.</s></p><p xml:id="_JwbQHXu"><s xml:id="_KN9WJ4p">I am now planning to get an art degree at university.</s><s xml:id="_eV6rZP9">As a result of the experience I am now thinking about pursuing a career in journalism.</s></p><p xml:id="_wd2rP2p"><s xml:id="_BXWJYnH">I have just had my own exhibition which I would never have imagined doing before.</s><s xml:id="_edKVMWn">SROI practitioners are encouraged to consider the longer-term social impact of interventions and projects, describing this as a causality chain.</s><s xml:id="_jhmknkj">Typically, a causality chain will move from the specific and direct outcomes experienced by stakeholders to the wider reaching, longer-term effects.</s><s xml:id="_bUUnFUt">The causality chain developed for this group of stakeholders is shown in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_q7CpaCm"><s xml:id="_4Wn5xA9">Although the SROI method explicitly advises researchers to consider negative as well as positive outcomes (in SROI terms, social value can be destroyed as well as created by an activity), the voluntary nature of the lifelong learning activities we considered means that participants tended to feel consistently positive about their experience; that is, those who were receiving negative value would voluntarily no longer attend.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_fZrR8Jv">Calculate a value for SROI</head><p xml:id="_N5qgwNJ"><s xml:id="_h7KsEE5">Having identified what outcomes the stakeholders experience, we conducted further consultation to understand how much had changed for each stakeholder group.</s><s xml:id="_5hn6JpE">We observed sessions, spoke to participants and carried out a series of surveys at a selection of the Lifelong Learning sessions.</s><s xml:id="_hU2Tyad">The analysis of survey responses from our stakeholder groups enabled us to quantify the outcomes experienced.</s><s xml:id="_HWUS2Gc">This provided us with overall percentages of occurrence for each of the identified outcomes for each activity and across the whole of the Lifelong Learning programme.</s><s xml:id="_gu5A546">We used objective indicators such as asking them how many new people they had met whilst at the gallery, and we used subjective indicators, such as asking them if they felt open to new things.</s><s xml:id="_etzcFkn">We also asked them how much of this change they attributed to taking part in activities at the gallery, allowing us to assess how much of this change was because of Turner Contemporary.</s></p><p xml:id="_khVKGVC"><s xml:id="_GAnaveZ">Not every participant attributed all of their positive change to Turner Contemporaryand some either did not feel these outcomes at all or did not attribute them entirely to their involvement with the gallery.</s><s xml:id="_t9HC8UK">The SROI deals with this when the final social return is calculated by considering and discounting for attribution factors, and the results from surveys dictated the values we applied to attribution.</s></p><p xml:id="_KhJkcRH"><s xml:id="_38qjQRZ">Conventional approaches to evaluating an investment measure monetary transactionin other words, the benefit (or financial return) of an investment is divided by the cost of the investment.</s><s xml:id="_EtFacRr">However, the SROI methodology differs from this because it recognises that using monetary transactions alone does not capture the whole "value" that is created.</s><s xml:id="_GXUtt63">Where there is no market price for a series of outcomes, the SROI method translates them into a monetary value by assigning a proxy, thus representing the outcome using the same currency as the initial investment.</s><s xml:id="_4ea695s">A proxy acts as an estimate of value that can determine the relative importance across a range of different outcomes.</s><s xml:id="_k5brsAh">Different people will have different views on this value, but by using a range of financial proxies we are able to arrive at an estimate of value.</s></p><p xml:id="_YJpudsb"><s xml:id="_2894skK">It is important to note that SROI methodology already treats financial investment (in the form of wages paid to both permanent employees and freelance practitioners) as a proxy for the social cultural and emotional capital contributed by those delivering the project.</s><s xml:id="_RWqEeUn">Voluntary labour would need to be valued in some other way (though, in order to work in the SROI methodology, ultimately it must always be represented as financial proxy).</s><s xml:id="_WjhQCvh">However, in the case of the delivery of Lifelong Learning at Turner Contemporary, no voluntary labour was used, and all members of staff responsible for delivery were salaried or hourly paid.</s><s xml:id="_N3kFjmT">Their input is thus fairly represented in the calculation.</s></p><p xml:id="_9kXvh3c"><s xml:id="_dTSaqua">We used two recognised SROI methodologies to calculate the value of the outcomes experienced by lifelong learning participants: a valuation workshop (meeting directly with a range of participants in a focus group situation) and a desk-based review.</s><s xml:id="_vAF2e4R">In the Table <ref type="table">1</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_Eh5D5tg">Causality chain of outcomes for lifelong learners.</s></p><p xml:id="_SQNfpqY"><s xml:id="_a237h7h">Participants take part in sessions with visiting artists and tutors.</s></p><p xml:id="_sBG5cAk"><s xml:id="_YvdzX2f">They are encouraged to take risks, try new things, and to explore their capabilities in unusual ways.</s></p><p xml:id="_GxHDC9W"><s xml:id="_AS9V6nZ">They become more openminded and confident.</s><s xml:id="_WMYAXDD">Their willingness to take new opportunities is enhanced.</s></p><p xml:id="_xpHd9Kk"><s xml:id="_J2Ah9tD">Participants feel empowered, which increases their selfbelief and leads them to be more pro-active members of the community.</s><s xml:id="_PyxDdwt">Participants take part in sessions with people they have never met before in a supportive environment.</s></p><p xml:id="_mtYgh3Q"><s xml:id="_XaTdNCQ">Group activities and opportunities to share their work and experiences allows them to form new friendships Participants strengthen their social networks and improve their ability to form better and stronger relationships.</s></p><p xml:id="_45ZBEnm"><s xml:id="_kbEVuYG">They experience a stronger sense of belonging to the community.</s></p><p xml:id="_RZBpj6D"><s xml:id="_6X9m4ED">Participants work in a sophisticated gallery setting and can directly experience art.</s></p><p xml:id="_Qm4XeKE"><s xml:id="_zJbTqgu">Activities built around the exhibitions in the gallery and philosophical enquiry structured by the tutor builds their knowledge base.</s></p><p xml:id="_hT6jZG6"><s xml:id="_8kUQsRw">Participants have enhanced knowledge and skills and feel more connected to culture.</s></p><p xml:id="_mdrvfGa"><s xml:id="_WjECgga">Participants become more competent and accomplished which makes more education and professional opportunities available to them.</s></p><p xml:id="_5ZasGsq"><s xml:id="_yFkeac8">workshop we used a "revealed preference" valuation game, asking participants to rate the value of related market traded goods, and then rank the importance of these in relation to the outcomes they accrued as a result of taking part in their art workshops <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Fujiwara &amp; Campbell, 2011)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_43HkFAA">Working collectively, participants valued the essentials of accommodation, heating and food above those of the three main outcomes from lifelong learning; however, other items such as a car, a cruise for two and a television were deemed to be of lower value.</s><s xml:id="_ny8Fhsg">Valuing the outcomes against items with known financial values, they generated a financial proxy for a full year of participation in Lifelong Learning activity of £4,500.</s><s xml:id="_gRyKTK6">We triangulated our primary research by carrying out a desk review of the literature in the area.</s><s xml:id="_ZTPK2TE"><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Fujiwara and Campbell (2011)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Fujiwara (2012)</ref> found that adult education improved outcomes for participants through health, social relationships, employment and volunteering; using well-being valuation approach and responses form the British Household Panel Survey they estimated the monetary value of these to collectively equal £2,320. 7</s><s xml:id="_bT4Fezn">Matrix Knowledge Group (2009), using an approach more in line with our SROI discussing outcomes with stakeholders, estimated the annual value of part-time learning to be between £4,066 and £4,740.</s><s xml:id="_wTCQW9K">Taking an average of these two approaches, would value intensive participation in Lifelong Learning at Turner Contemporary at £3,000 per year per participant, and we applied this lower number for prudence.</s></p><p xml:id="_wZ2SKNF"><s xml:id="_T53tAeS">The engagement of those participating in drop-in lifelong learning sessions, is less frequent and intensive and therefore is estimated to have a lower impact.</s><s xml:id="_WUkYsuc">To value this we used the price of a similarly run local art class (£15) plus an additional amount for the ambience provided by having the classes at Turner Contemporary (£10).</s><s xml:id="_bHxy85N">Moreover, the venue was used for a local singing group, who gains from this ambience, although as this is for singing, we value the benefit here at £2 per hour as a prudent estimate.</s><s xml:id="_Nc7SpFH">This lower figure represents a more transactional relationship with the gallery.</s></p><p xml:id="_xSGQ2c9"><s xml:id="_ktBktqR">By multiplying the proxy values by the number of participants (taking into account the type of activity they were involved in and the amount of time they spent taking part) we were able to arrive at a total value for the outcomes of all lifelong learners who participated in the 2015/16 financial year of £1,185,570. 8</s><s xml:id="_T5pag2D">This step is important from a return on investment perspective because it precisely accounts for the numbers of participants over the course of a year and it details the level of engagement of each participant.</s><s xml:id="_Yq89Wca">This was made easier by Turner Contemporary's rigorous approach to recording participant numbers at each of their events and activities, allowing us to accurately estimate the level of return experienced by the totality of stakeholders in relation to the investment made by the gallery.</s></p><p xml:id="_awh952K"><s xml:id="_VHWBeWe">Finally, we used data to calculate:</s></p><p xml:id="_QGuRdrb"><s xml:id="_JchxQVy">. deadweight (a measure of the amount of outcome that would have happened even if the activity had not taken place) .</s><s xml:id="_cwUeFTB">displacement (how much of the outcome displaced other outcomes) .</s><s xml:id="_EUaeSCP">attribution (how much of the outcome was caused by the contribution of other organisations or people).</s></p><p xml:id="_DFuCnKp"><s xml:id="_JGRdWfT">We accounted for these through directly surveying lifelong learners, to expand the number of stakeholders involved in the process beyond those in the focus group.</s><s xml:id="_2s27Rvf">The survey was completed by 46 of the learners during the year.</s><s xml:id="_P7dw9bU">Participants were asked for each of the three outcomes to state: one, to what extent they agreed the outcome applied to them; two, to what extent they felt this was attributable to Turner Contemporary; and three, if their participation in lifelong learning stopped them doing something else.</s><s xml:id="_Zx6yWpf">Respondents that gave a neutral or negative appraisal to the first two questions for any of the three outcomes were used for our calculation of deadweight and attribution (17.5% and 36.2%);</s><s xml:id="_DaAAgKM">those who answered "yes" to the third question provided the value for displacement (8.7%).</s><s xml:id="_myF4at4">This provided a social return from lifelong learning of £569,074 (which is 1, 185, 570 × (1 -17.5%) × (1 -36.2%) × (1 -8.7%)).</s></p><p xml:id="_QTMcv9n"><s xml:id="_jm2sVXA">In consultation with the gallery's senior management and finance team, we apportioned 2% of the overheads of running the gallery (indirect costs) to the programme and considered any income generated by the activity.</s><s xml:id="_THZec4G">We found that the total investment in the Lifelong Learning programme was £111,825.</s><s xml:id="_JKwTYC2">The analysis then shows that the net SROI ratio for Turner Contemporary's lifelong learning programme was 4.09 to 1 ((£569,074 -£111,825)/£111,825).</s><s xml:id="_cvAzFgS">This means that in one year, for every £1 invested by Turner Contemporary, £4.09 of net social value is created for participants in lifelong learning activities.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_q8TnP3c">Sensitivity testing</head><p xml:id="_Nh8Fu8u"><s xml:id="_sZTGRV2">The analysis uses estimations for the valuation of outcomes and proportions for deadweight, displacement and attribution, for which there is uncertainty.</s><s xml:id="_6q47NSF">Social Value UK proposes sensitivity analysis consider each estimate at a time, and calculate the value at which SROI is 1:1 (that is, no excess return); for this analysis Social Value UK provide a spreadsheet for which all calculations and analysis can be performed.</s><s xml:id="_yNpgWNG">A more formal approach would apply probability distributions for each estimated parameter and bootstrap the uncertainty in the valuation of returns; however, given that this is not done as standard practice, providing appropriate probability distributions is hard.</s><s xml:id="_39EQhBq">Applying a similar intuition as proposed by Social Value UK, attributing uniform distributions to the value of outcomes, and using binomial distribution randomisation from our survey results to provide values for deadweight, displacement and attribution, we estimate an 80% confidence band for the social returns from lifelong learning between £411,180 and £760,980 (leading to a confidence band in the SROI ratio of between £2.67 to £5.08).</s><s xml:id="_vFu237v">Note that the headline estimate of £569,074 is towards the lower end of this band due to the fact that we applied prudency, partially because of the uncertainty in the numbers.</s><s xml:id="_NPzwgvp">Also note that the confidence band would have been wider had the numbers of those participating in each activity been unknown (and therefore estimated).</s><s xml:id="_CuU9EyW">Turner Contemporary had diligent records of this, which might not necessarily be the case of all arts organisations.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_VG4KpNK">Conclusions</head><p xml:id="_ZxHRsRn"><s xml:id="_2KTnMvw">The gallery commissioned this report as an adjunct to its existing research which focussed on economic impact, visitor numbers, visit motivation and visitor satisfaction.</s><s xml:id="_Yt6B6Du">The management team felt confident they were having an influence that went beyond high visitor numbers and spend, but were unsure about how this could be measured.</s><s xml:id="_4FdgsZe">Their marketing director had stated early in the commissioning process that the SROI method appealed because it "produced a number rather than a narrative", and it was felt that this would advocate more powerfully for the gallery.</s></p><p xml:id="_NUK9zA3"><s xml:id="_Msh3zwe">Although SROI is offered as a highly regulated and systematic method that appears to offer high levels of precision in the way it represents social returns as a precise figure, this representation tends to conceal the subjective nature of the judgments being made, both by the stakeholders and the researchers.</s><s xml:id="_R2c4d9c">As discussed above, there may be uncertainty around the final estimate in an SROI report, but this uncertainty is rarely discussed, nor fully modelled.</s><s xml:id="_MuGjN3v">Although in this research we have made clear how data was gathered, where necessary estimates have been made, and have expressed confidence levels, there has still been a tendency to focus strongly on the SROI ratio at the expense of the wider findings.</s><s xml:id="_XpkcWfW">In some cases the numbers have even been significantly misrecognised.</s><s xml:id="_hANtWxR">Unsurprisingly, given the complexity of the method, when the results of this study were published they were almost immediately misinterpreted by a well-meaning local journalist, who wrote:</s></p><p xml:id="_WT2RWf6"><s xml:id="_ehtRdqY">Using a method called social return on investment, researchers led by Dr Andrew Jackson found that for every pound spent by visitors to the gallery £2.88 was generated, for every pound spent by the gallery on life-long learning £4.09 was created, and for every pound spent on formal education programmes there was a £5.15 return <ref type="bibr">[sic]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_JgNgVCg"><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Whitlock, 2016, November 2)</ref> This short piece typifies the problems with understanding SROI research (and indeed using it as an advocacy tool)the misrecognition of the proxy values attached to nonmarket outcomes as financial returns.</s><s xml:id="_JERC44E">Yates and Marra highlight this as one of the dangers of SROIthat because the use of monetary units implies more reliability and validity than might be due, important (and perhaps damaging) funding decisions might be made based on numbers that tell only a small part of the story <ref type="bibr">(2017, p. 139)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_KqjWYrq"><s xml:id="_2EvNfmR">Although, as discussed earlier in this paper, Social Value International goes to great lengths to stress that SROI is much more than just a numberemphasising that it is fundamentally a story about change that includes case studies and qualitative information as well as quantitative and financial informationthe temptation to challenge the numbers is frequently so great that the value of the wider findings can be ignored.</s><s xml:id="_N8aqVmm">Clearly, regardless of the rigour that is applied to an SROI analysis by researchers, the doubts about the method thrown up by these critiques may undermine the credibility of the method, and ultimately challenge its utility as an advocacy tool.</s></p><p xml:id="_v7squ7P"><s xml:id="_PwftN3G">This criticism notwithstanding, our experience has been that funding decisions for organisations such as Turner Contemporary are based not upon single advocacy documents, but upon a myriad of complex and interacting factors.</s><s xml:id="_jxspB2f">As <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Belfiore (2016)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Belfiore and Bennett (2010)</ref> have observed, funding decisions in the arts rarely adhere to a rational process of evidence-based policy making.</s><s xml:id="_WMgu28v">Furthermore, as the final report for the AHRC Cultural Value Project made clear, relying on one single method of enquiry to evaluate the complexity of cultural experience is rarely successful:</s></p><p xml:id="_fZEJctp"><s xml:id="_hBeCW75">Accounting for human experiences of art and culture calls for multi-criteria analyses and a range of approaches, in order to span the depth and the breadth of research.</s><s xml:id="_Y5w69sp">Such evaluation is often not suited to accountability, which often needs headline results, single measures and weighted aggregates.</s><s xml:id="_keRwgAt"><ref type="bibr">(Crossick &amp; Kaszynska, 2016, p. 10)</ref> Although at the beginning of this article we discussed the perceived need for cultural institutions to use the tools and concepts of economics to fully state the benefits they offer wider society, for Turner Contemporary the value of this exercise eventually came not from a set of numbers, but from the method itself.</s><s xml:id="_CjwHNRV">Reflecting on the process, this had an impact on the way the gallery team thought about their role, and it prompted them to ask questions that had never been asked before.</s><s xml:id="_BGDaJF4">Above all it was a learning experience for the management team who are required by the process to look carefully at how they invest resources, the kinds of returns this gives, and where they can usefully focus their activities.</s><s xml:id="_JRzsTRN">It also gives them deeper insight into the personal experiences and outcomes of individual users.</s><s xml:id="_DzsGtSd">This is frequently cited by SROI practitioners as one of the key benefits of the methodologyit obliges the client organisation to reflect much more carefully not only on how they create value, but also on the resources expended in order to achieve that value.</s></p><p xml:id="_aJ9Rtuc"><s xml:id="_kxQqNeq">An epiphany for Eslea had been the realisation that the impact felt by participants in lifelong learning programmes was very large in the first year of their attendancethey quickly met new people, learnt new skills and become more open minded.</s><s xml:id="_jUjgC3u">However, whilst these benefits are accrued quite rapidly in the first year, they were likely to drop off as their attendance continued over longer periods of two or more years, the initial gains having been attained and consolidated by the participants.</s><s xml:id="_KJp6Kgf">The high return generated for the gallery by its lifelong learning programme can only be sustained if they are able to continuously introduce new people to their programmes of activity thus refreshing the cohorts.</s><s xml:id="_7PArhvh">Some participants exhibited signs of becoming dependent on the gallery and commented that they would feel "a sense of bereavement" if they were no longer able to attend their evening workshops.</s><s xml:id="_NpNHrdW">This poses a problem for the gallery when projects are often reliant on short-term funding and the gallery has no choice but to end the project once the funding comes to an end.</s></p><p xml:id="_ebeuAWv"><s xml:id="_dgfzF48">In terms of advocacy, the role that the gallery had expected the numbers to play proved to be less useful than first imaginedthe descriptive outcomes were more powerful in telling the story of the gallery.</s><s xml:id="_2EeMj4G">It would be fair to ask whether qualitative study would have achieved the same results with less complexity and less resource; however, the strength of SROI is that it offers a replicable method of study that could conceivably be repeated over subsequent years, allowing comparison with previous activity and accounting for change, both positive and negative.</s><s xml:id="_B7THnrw">In theory this could contribute to strategic planning decisions, and be used as a measure of performance.</s><s xml:id="_EAVjrxN">In practice, as noted earlier in this article, the relative complexity and time-consuming nature of SROI as a method means that for most arts institutions this is likely to be luxury that they are unlikely to be able to afford.</s><s xml:id="_FxhKKVX">Notes 1.</s><s xml:id="_Hmukpm6">The building was design by internationally known David Chipperfield Architects and received wide press coverage when it opened: <ref type="url" target="https://www.turnercontemporary.org">https://www.turnercontemporary.org</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_trvEVRu">2. Visit numbers are recorded by the gallery using an electronic door register.</s><s xml:id="_XJBh67u">3. Thanet is the geographical area in the north east of Kent. 4. Economic impact reporting carried out by Christ Church Business School. 5.</s><s xml:id="_SkRUpxK">The full 79 page report is available for download here: <ref type="url" target="https://www.turnercontemporary.org/media/documents/COaST%20Turner%20SROI%202015-2016%20FINAL%202.pdf">https://www.turnercontemporary.org/  media/documents/COaST%20Turner%20SROI%202015-2016%20FINAL%202.pdf</ref> 6.</s><s xml:id="_eKfztbf">The UK government's Office of the Third Sector and the Scottish Government commissioned a project beginning in 2007 that continues to develop guidelines that allow social businesses seeking government grants to account for their impact using a consistent, verifiable method.</s><s xml:id="_wKF4X2D">This resulted in another formal revision to the method, produced by a consortium led by the SROI Network, published in the Guide to SROI <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Nicholls et al., 2012)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_FEvUArE">7. The well-being valuation approach looks at calculating the monetary value one would need to be compensated were they not to have certain factors.</s><s xml:id="_K9PKQUm">This done by looking at stated wellbeing of respondents compared against their income.</s><s xml:id="_FSeVCaZ">8. Calculated by taking the estimated value from annual intensive lifelong learning and multiplying by the number of participants (£885,300), and adding the hourly value of participation in drop-in sessions and use of the facilities and multiplying by the number of hours of participation in each of these (resulting in values of £283,950 and £16,320 respectively).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_MFVqHKp">Notes on the contributors</head><p xml:id="_G89PgQ7"><s xml:id="_qMmH7cv">Andrew Jackson is Senior Lecturer at Canterbury Christ Church University, where he is Director of the COaST arts evaluation and research group.</s><s xml:id="_DexGxwk">His research interests are centred around cultural consumption and participation, with a focus on cultural value and arts evaluation, particularly in relation to place and regeneration.</s><s xml:id="_zgAMBbD">Richard McManus is Senior Lecturer at Canterbury Christ Church University, whose research includes the aggregate and distributional consequences of government spending and taxation policy.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_FaVrZ2w"><s xml:id="_BZeCt7j">That just gave me such confidence, I felt wonderful (…) I felt like I could do anything after that … I think what it made me do is just open my eyes to everything I look at.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p xml:id="_Y5dt62y"><s xml:id="_4ewek7d">… a framework for measuring, managing, reporting and accounting for social value that engages with stakeholders and analyses your activities through their eyes.(Social</s><s xml:id="_qCVqYhu">Value International, 2015)    One of the characteristics of SROI is its relative complexity as a method<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Yates &amp; Marra, 2017)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_eg2zFue">Applied to the operations of a reasonably large and multifaceted arts institution, the resulting evaluation was significantly more extensive and complicated than first envisaged.</s><s xml:id="_RPUwppw">The gallery team took a chance with commissioning the report because, as Eslea subsequently admitted, nobody on the team really knew what the process would entail or what the result would look like.</s><s xml:id="_VSQY4Nn">134A.</s><s xml:id="_x9YrrJF">JACKSON AND R. MCMANUS</s></p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_5esDu8y"><p xml:id="_rfMAXS3"><s xml:id="_PHPBr6f">Copyright of Cultural Trends is the property of Routledge and its content may not be copied or emailed to multiple sites or posted to a listserv without the copyright holder's express written permission.</s><s xml:id="_N3xMG4D">However, users may print, download, or email articles for individual use.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/09540962.2019.1537706</idno>
		<ptr target="http://www.artscouncil.org.uk/about-us/how-and-where-we-invest-public-money" />
		<title level="m" xml:id="_QA9QVjm">Social return on investment (SROI): A powerful tool for the realisation of benefits</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Arts Council England</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>How we invest public money</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Specific Interest Group White Paper. (2016). Social return on investment (SROI): A powerful tool for the realisation of benefits. Arts Council England. (2018). How we invest public money. Retrieved from http://www.artscouncil. org.uk/about-us/how-and-where-we-invest-public-money</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_VgWQrNt">Coastal towns get trendy but will it help the locals? The Guardian</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Batty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://search.proquest.com/docview/1812065714" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016-08-17">2016, August 17</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Batty, D. (2016, August 17). Coastal towns get trendy but will it help the locals? The Guardian, Retrieved from https://search.proquest.com/docview/1812065714</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_bBYGTHR">Cultural policy research in the real world: Curating &quot;impact&quot;, facilitating &quot;enlightenment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Belfiore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/09548963.2016.1204050</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_hu9s7FM">Cultural Trends</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="205" to="216" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Belfiore, E. (2016). Cultural policy research in the real world: Curating &quot;impact&quot;, facilitating &quot;enlight- enment&quot;. Cultural Trends, 25(3), 205-216. doi:10.1080/09548963.2016.1204050</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_FDHHW3K">Beyond the &quot;toolkit approach&quot;: Arts impact evaluation research and the realities of cultural policy-making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Belfiore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Bennett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/14797580903481280</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_fKTZadF">Journal for Cultural Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="142" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Belfiore, E., &amp; Bennett, O. (2010). Beyond the &quot;toolkit approach&quot;: Arts impact evaluation research and the realities of cultural policy-making. Journal for Cultural Research, 14(2), 121-142. doi:10.1080/ 14797580903481280</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_sYQ3hZH">The torn halves of cultural policy research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Bennett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/1028663042000255844</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_77kecZW">International Journal of Cultural Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="237" to="248" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bennett, O. (2004). The torn halves of cultural policy research. International Journal of Cultural Policy, 10(2), 237-248. doi:10.1080/1028663042000255844</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_FSyAUEC">Art, gentrification and regenerationfrom artist as pioneer to public arts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cameron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Coaffee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/14616710500055687</idno>
		<ptr target="http://econpapers.repec.org/article/tafintjhp/v_3a5_3ay_3a2005_3ai_3a1_3ap_3" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_nVeVG6D">European Journal of Housing Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="58" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005. a39-58</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Cameron, S., &amp; Coaffee, J. (2005). Art, gentrification and regeneration -from artist as pioneer to public arts. European Journal of Housing Policy, 5(1), 39-58. Retrieved from http://econpapers.repec.org/ article/tafintjhp/v_3a5_3ay_3a2005_3ai_3a1_3ap_3a39-58.htm</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Crossick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kaszynska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://ahrc.ukri.org/documents/publications/cultural-value-project-final-report/" />
		<title level="m" xml:id="_epEJbAZ">Understanding the value of arts &amp; culture, The AHRC Cultural Value Project</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Crossick, G., &amp; Kaszynska, P. (2016). Understanding the value of arts &amp; culture, The AHRC Cultural Value Project. Retrieved from https://ahrc.ukri.org/documents/publications/cultural-value-project-final- report/</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Donovan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ww/9780199540884.013.2000264</idno>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_cGR249E">A Holistic Approach to Valuing Our Culture: A Report to the Department for Culture, Media and Sport</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Brunel University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Donovan, C. (2013). A Holistic Approach to Valuing Our Culture: A Report to the Department for Culture, Media and Sport. London: Brunel University.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ewbank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Vella-Burrows</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mills</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Shipton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Clift</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Fred</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.canterbury.ac.uk/health-and-wellbeing/sidney-de-haan-research-centre/documents/report-cultural-value-and-social-capital.pdf" />
		<title level="m" xml:id="_SH9JgJw">Cultural Value and Social Capital: Investigating Social, Health and Wellbeing Impacts in Three Coastal Towns Undergoing Culture-led Regeneration</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Canterbury</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Sidney De Haan Research Centre for Arts and Health</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ewbank, N., Vella-Burrows, T., Mills, S., Shipton, M., Clift, S., &amp; Fred, G. (2014). Cultural Value and Social Capital: Investigating Social, Health and Wellbeing Impacts in Three Coastal Towns Undergoing Culture-led Regeneration. Canterbury: Sidney De Haan Research Centre for Arts and Health. Retrieved from https://www.canterbury.ac.uk/health-and-wellbeing/sidney-de-haan-research- centre/documents/report-cultural-value-and-social-capital.pdf</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_WGedFdX">Valuing the Impact of Adult Learning: An Analysis of the Effect of Adult Learning on Different Domains in Life</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fujiwara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>NIACE</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Leicester</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Fujiwara, D. (2012). Valuing the Impact of Adult Learning: An Analysis of the Effect of Adult Learning on Different Domains in Life. Leicester: NIACE.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_3TkAmTe">Museums and Happiness: The Value of Participating in Museums and the Arts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fujiwara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Arts Council England</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Fujiwara, D. (2013). Museums and Happiness: The Value of Participating in Museums and the Arts. London: Arts Council England.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fujiwara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4337/9781781009727.00017</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/valuation-techniques-for-social-cost" />
		<title level="m" xml:id="_6GAuEzn">Valuation techniques for social Cost-Benefit analysis: Stated preference, revealed preference and subjective well-being approaches HM Treasury</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Glaser</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Strauss</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Chicago</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Aldine</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1967">2011. 1967</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The Discovery of Grounded Theory</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Fujiwara, D., &amp; Campbell, R. (2011). Valuation techniques for social Cost-Benefit analysis: Stated prefer- ence, revealed preference and subjective well-being approaches HM Treasury. Retrieved from https:// www.gov.uk/government/publications/valuation-techniques-for-social-cost-benefit-analysis Glaser, B., &amp; Strauss, A. (1967). The Discovery of Grounded Theory. Chicago: Aldine.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Holden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.demos.co.uk/files/Culturalvalueweb.pdf" />
		<title level="m" xml:id="_z2tDQAJ">Cultural Value and the Crisis of Legitimacy: Why Culture Needs a Democratic Mandate</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Demos</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Holden, J. (2006). Cultural Value and the Crisis of Legitimacy: Why Culture Needs a Democratic Mandate. London: Demos. Retrieved from https://www.demos.co.uk/files/Culturalvalueweb.pdf</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_aVzgWv2">The Battle for the High Street: Retail Gentrification, Class and Disgust</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hubbard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1057/978-1-137-52153-8</idno>
		<ptr target="https://ebookcentral.proquest.com/lib/[SITE_ID]/detail.action?docID=4797380" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<publisher>Palgrave Macmillan Limited</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hubbard, P. (2017). The Battle for the High Street: Retail Gentrification, Class and Disgust. London: Palgrave Macmillan Limited. doi:10.1057/978-1-137-52153-8. Retrieved from https://ebookcentral. proquest.com/lib/[SITE_ID]/detail.action?docID = 4797380</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_fNYVnkA">Rediscovering cultural tourism: Cultural regeneration in seaside towns</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kennell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/09548963.2013.819662</idno>
		<ptr target="http://gala.gre.ac.uk/id/eprint/10656" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_kjeusrE">Journal of Town and City Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="364" to="380" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kennell, J. (2011). Rediscovering cultural tourism: Cultural regeneration in seaside towns. Journal of Town and City Management, 1(4), 364-380. Retrieved from http://gala.gre.ac.uk/id/eprint/10656</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_KcAE7Tp">Art-led regeneration in Margate: Learning from Moonbow Jakes Café and Lido Nightclub intervention</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lees</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mckiernan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1386/aps.2.1-3.17_1</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_VxAKMRH">Art &amp; the Public Sphere</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">17</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lees, L., &amp; McKiernan, J. (2014). Art-led regeneration in Margate: Learning from Moonbow Jakes Café and Lido Nightclub intervention. Art &amp; the Public Sphere, 2(1, 2 &amp; 3), 17.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_EZCZv9V">Making Culture Count : The Politics of Cultural Measurement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Macdowall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Badham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Blomkamp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Dunphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-1-137-46458-3</idno>
		<ptr target="http://replace-me/ebraryid=11102121" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<publisher>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">MacDowall, L., Badham, M., Blomkamp, E., &amp; Dunphy, K. (2015). Making Culture Count : The Politics of Cultural Measurement. London: Palgrave Macmillan. doi:10.1007/978-1-137-46458-3. Retrieved from http://replace-me/ebraryid = 11102121</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<idno type="DOI">10.14267/phd.2023070</idno>
		<ptr target="http://shop.niace.org.uk/media/catalog/product/f/i/file_1_50.pdf" />
		<title level="m" xml:id="_VrGe9NJ">Lifelong learning and well-being: An analysis of the relationship between adult learning and subjective well-being</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Leicester</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Matrix Knowledge Group</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Matrix Knowledge Group. (2009). Lifelong learning and well-being: An analysis of the relationship between adult learning and subjective well-being. Leicester. Retrieved from http://shop.niace.org. uk/media/catalog/product/f/i/file_1_50.pdf</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_VdGRRXq">Culture Vultures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mirza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.47688/rba_archives_2006/26373</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<publisher>Policy Exchange</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mirza, M. (Ed.). (2006). Culture Vultures. London: Policy Exchange.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_kpWKDzR">Social return on investment-development and convergence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nicholls</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.evalprogplan.2016.11.011</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/27919435" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_qcyNXv6">Evaluation and Program Planning</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="135" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nicholls, J. (2017). Social return on investment-development and convergence. Evaluation and Program Planning, 64, 127-135. Retrieved from https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/27919435</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nicholls</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Lawlor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Neitzert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Godspeed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.socialvalueuk.org/resources/sroi-guide/" />
		<title level="m" xml:id="_T3kNydY">A Guide to Social Return on Investment</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The SROI Network</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nicholls, J., Lawlor, E., Neitzert, E., &amp; Godspeed, T. (2012). A Guide to Social Return on Investment. The SROI Network. Retrieved from http://www.socialvalueuk.org/resources/sroi-guide/</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_Bu56fJ9">Measuring the Value of Culture: A Report to the Department for Culture Media and Sport</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>O'brien</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ww/9780199540884.013.u284691</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<publisher>Department for Culture, Media and Sport</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">O&apos;Brien, D. (2010). Measuring the Value of Culture: A Report to the Department for Culture Media and Sport. London: Department for Culture, Media and Sport.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_b7wEGwM">Subjective well-being in cultural advocacy: A politics of research between the market and the academy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Oman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/17530350.2018.1435422</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_6CVzUea">Journal of Cultural Economy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="225" to="243" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Oman, S., &amp; Taylor, M. (2018). Subjective well-being in cultural advocacy: A politics of research between the market and the academy. Journal of Cultural Economy, 11(3), 225-243. doi:10. 1080/17530350.2018.1435422</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_XfhtgEm">Counting Culture to Death: An Australian Perspective on Culture Counts and Quality Metrics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Phiddian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Meyrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Barnett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Maltby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/09548963.2017.1324014</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Phiddian, R., Meyrick, J., Barnett, T., &amp; Maltby, R. (2017). Counting Culture to Death: An Australian Perspective on Culture Counts and Quality Metrics. Routledge. doi:10.1080/09548963.2017.1324014</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1201/9781003024910-18</idno>
		<ptr target="http://www.socialvalueuk.org/resource/principles-of-social-value/TurnerContemporary" />
		<title level="m" xml:id="_eJrpdQj">The seven principles of social value</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Social Value International</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2015. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Turner Contemporary business plan</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Social Value International. (2015). The seven principles of social value. Retrieved from http://www. socialvalueuk.org/resource/principles-of-social-value/ Turner Contemporary. (2012). Turner Contemporary business plan.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_b5KpH4z">Down by the sea: Visual arts, artists and coastal regeneration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/10286632.2016.1153080</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_UjSRA2c">International Journal of Cultural Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="138" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ward, J. (2018). Down by the sea: Visual arts, artists and coastal regeneration. International Journal of Cultural Policy, 24(1), 121-138. doi:10.1080/10286632.2016.1153080</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Whitlock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.19043/ipdj.71.012</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.kentonline.co.uk/thanet/news/millions-generated-by-gallerys-visitors-115057/" />
		<title level="m" xml:id="_mpP8Z58">Value of the Turner Contemporary, Margate, researched by students at Canterbury Christ Church University</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Kent Online</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2016-11-02">2016, November 2</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Whitlock, L. (2016, November 2). Value of the Turner Contemporary, Margate, researched by students at Canterbury Christ Church University. Kent Online. Retrieved from https://www.kentonline.co.uk/ thanet/news/millions-generated-by-gallerys-visitors-115057/</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_rbDgbyC">What is Resilience Anyway? A Review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Woodley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Towell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Turpin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Thelwall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ww/9780199540884.013.43198</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>Arts Council England</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Woodley, S., Towell, P., Turpin, R., Thelwall, S., &amp; Schneider, P. (2018). What is Resilience Anyway? A Review. London: Arts Council England.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_cD5Ujbt">Social return on investment (SROI): Problems, solutions … and is SROI a good investment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Yates</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Marra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.evalprogplan.2016.11.009</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_RtsnhYK">Evaluation and Program Planning</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="136" to="144" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Yates, B., &amp; Marra, M. (2017). Social return on investment (SROI): Problems, solutions … and is SROI a good investment? Evaluation and Program Planning, 64, 136-144. doi:10.1016/j.evalprogplan. 2016.11.009</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
