<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_TTwAh6E">Solutions toCybersecurity Challenges in Secure Vehicle-to-Vehicle Communications: A Multivocal Literature Review</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
					<p type="raw">© 2024 Elsevier B.V. All rights are reserved, including those for text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies.</p>
				</availability>
				<date>28 November 2024 0950</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Naeem</forename><surname>Ullah</surname></persName>
							<email>naeemullah72@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>a</label> Software Engineering Research Group (SERG-UOM) , Department of Computer Science &amp; Information Technology , University of Malakand , Pakistan</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science &amp; Information Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Software Engineering Research Group (SERG-UOM)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Malakand</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="PK">Pakistan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Siffat</forename><surname>Ullah Khan</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>a</label> Software Engineering Research Group (SERG-UOM) , Department of Computer Science &amp; Information Technology , University of Malakand , Pakistan</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science &amp; Information Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Software Engineering Research Group (SERG-UOM)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Malakand</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="PK">Pakistan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mahmood</forename><surname>Niazi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>b</label> Information and Computer Science Department , IRC for Intelligent Secure Systems , King Fahd University of Petroleum and Minerals , Dhahran 31261 , Saudi Arabia</note>
								<orgName type="department">Information and Computer Science Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">IRC for Intelligent Secure Systems</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">King Fahd University of Petroleum and Minerals</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>31261</postCode>
									<settlement>Dhahran</settlement>
									<country key="SA">Saudi Arabia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Matteo</forename><surname>Esposito</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>c</label> University of Oulu , Oulu , Finland</note>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Oulu</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Oulu</settlement>
									<country key="FI">Finland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>d</label> University of Rome &quot;Tor Vergata&quot; , Rome , Italy</note>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Rome &quot;Tor Vergata&quot;</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Rome</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ali</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>e</label> M3S Research Unit , University of Oulu , Finland</note>
								<orgName type="laboratory">M3S Research Unit</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Oulu</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="FI">Finland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jamal</forename><forename type="middle">Abdul</forename><surname>Nasir</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>f</label> ICIT , Gomal University D . I Khan , Pakistan Software Engineering Research Group (SERG-UOM) ,</note>
								<orgName type="department">ICIT</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Software Engineering Research Group (SERG-UOM)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Gomal University D</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>I Khan</settlement>
									<country key="PK">Pakistan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Department of Computer Science &amp; Information Technology , University of Malakand , Pakistan</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science &amp; Information Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Malakand</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="PK">Pakistan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_G6MqyHp">Solutions toCybersecurity Challenges in Secure Vehicle-to-Vehicle Communications: A Multivocal Literature Review</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published">28 November 2024 0950</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">FE55BA3C11A51071926C696683017A2E</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.infsof.2024.107639</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 26 June 2024; Received in revised form 19 November 2024; Accepted 26 November 2024</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T07:41+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords xml:id="_dPdNwGY">vehicle communication Cybersecurity challenges Automotive vehicles Multivocal</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_wZP7e2m"><p xml:id="_HNX9j5w"><s xml:id="_jruSGmJ">Context: Vehicle-to-Vehicle (V2V) technology is evolving rapidly, meeting modern transportation needs and driving economic and technological progress.</s><s xml:id="_efd44hT">V2V brings numerous benefits, enabling vehicles to communicate with each other and with infrastructure like Roadside Units (RSUs), which helps minimize collisions, reduce fatalities, and boost road safety for passengers, drivers, and pedestrians alike.</s><s xml:id="_GEK88rP">Beyond safety, V2V improves traffic management and optimizes routes.</s><s xml:id="_PmxJKfH">However, these advancements also introduce new challenges.</s><s xml:id="_aWQMbGG">Greater reliance on IT makes vehicles more vulnerable to cyber-attacks and increases costs related to system installation and maintenance.</s><s xml:id="_YYBuMsN">This highlights a pressing need to advance V2V technology to enhance overall safety.</s></p><p xml:id="_YgYPNJD"><s xml:id="_k6zjD4P">Objective: This research focuses on identifying the primary challenges and effective practices within Vehicle-to-Vehicle (V2V) communication.</s><s xml:id="_jyq2QXr">Method: We conducted a Multivocal Literature Review (MLR) using tailored search strings derived from our research questions.</s><s xml:id="_uWbZzgH">This process adhered to all standard MLR steps, including protocol development, initial and final selection, quality assessment, data extraction, and synthesis.</s><s xml:id="_5qYcGJJ">Results: We have identified a list of 18 challenges in the context of V2V communication. 10 of these challenges were marked as critical challenges based on the criterion of ≥20 % occurrences in both formal and grey literature.</s><s xml:id="_FtV8pEZ">We also identified related practices for the identified critical challenges.</s><s xml:id="_jdaamH6">The identified challenges were further analyzed based on different variables such as publication periods and study strategies.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_XBFq9qq">Conclusion:</head><p xml:id="_39en8y2"><s xml:id="_qDrNKQW">We recommend that automotive industries should prioritize addressing these challenges to enhance their readiness for secure V2V communication.</s><s xml:id="_vaNPZzh">Our overarching goal is to develop a Cybersecurity Challenges Mitigation Model (CCMM) based on MLR findings and industrial survey outcomes, assisting companies in the automobile sector to assess their readiness for secure V2V communication development.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="793.701" lry="595.276"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="10" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="11" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="12" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="13" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="14" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1." xml:id="_nWdtXQs">Introduction</head><p xml:id="_A9WdbuC"><s xml:id="_5pN6Y4Q">Vehicular Ad-hoc Network (VANET) is used for inter-vehicular communication, employing wireless mode for vehicle connections <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_67MWaPv">VANET primarily utilizes two types of communication: Vehicle-to-Vehicle (V2V) and Vehicle-to-Infrastructure (V2I) communication.</s><s xml:id="_tSgHgwz">Through V2V communication, a vehicle interacts with others in the network to send, receive, or exchange valuable traffic-related information, including speed, direction, road conditions, traffic jams, and accidents <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_ZqhbkAv">For connecting to external networks like the internet, a vehicle connects with stationary equipment known as Roadside Units (RSU) (or Roadside Infrastructure), referred to as V2I communication <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_wZy8ZtV">Sensors collect data on vehicles and share it with others through Vehicle-to-Vehicle (V2V) messaging and cloud infrastructure via Vehicle-to-Infrastructure (V2I) <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_sQymBZh">V2V and V2I communication models are used to connect VANET.</s><s xml:id="_5Y5HRqz">The area of V2V technology is rapidly developing, meeting the transportation needs of citizens and contributing to economic growth and technological advancement.</s><s xml:id="_KAyj7p7">The growth of cities and global mobility has significantly increased the number of vehicles on the roads <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_NwGQntj"><s xml:id="_mJ7YV7K">Integrating information technologies and telecommunication into transportation systems is known as Intelligent Transportation Systems (ITS) <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_dYTv7FR">These technologies aim to address crucial issues like traffic congestion and passenger safety.</s><s xml:id="_49Hdqcj">The VANET components of mobile vehicles are connected wirelessly, allowing them to form a network spontaneously while driving.</s><s xml:id="_hT5SXzG">VANET offers decentralized settings for traffic data distribution without needing fixed infrastructures <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_SPbynCp">The V2V and V2I use the Dedicated Short-Range Communication (DSRC) protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_AcjJP5F">Using the assistance of another vehicle within range, a vehicle transmits safety signals to remote vehicles.</s><s xml:id="_Pd6pktT">The sender can still use other active vehicles if the vehicle in range cannot forward the message.</s></p><p xml:id="_ZZ6VZ3e"><s xml:id="_ZvG4wNE">Consequently, VANET equips all vehicles with enough storage and power to transmit information about accidents, traffic congestion, and emergencies to nearby members <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_Q6p6QQT">However, when information is sent over an unrestricted wireless channel, attackers can eavesdrop, alter, duplicate, or delete it.</s><s xml:id="_nwWBK8g">For example, attackers could alter safety-related alerts to cause accidents or fabricate fake traffic jams to disrupt normal operations <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_tJjMsEC">Effective communication between vehicles in the network is crucial in information distribution for increased traffic safety and travel comfort <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_6TCdhsZ">While V2V has many advantages, however, it poses several cybersecurity challenges and exposed to cyber attacks <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_72pkBHQ"><s xml:id="_6UGutGy">V2V technology enables direct vehicle communication, making it possible without relying on any established infrastructure.</s><s xml:id="_YvDRQK7">V2V technology communication applies to safety and emergencies <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_CfGF33U">Information exchanged over wireless channels requires a protected environment to prevent threats on the V2V networks, such as: i. Bogus messages with fake information intended to cause accidents.</s><s xml:id="_wNA7GbA">ii.</s><s xml:id="_Ve2Bp7X">Leak of the geographical position and identity of other vehicles.</s><s xml:id="_nrgBuzs">iii.</s><s xml:id="_nhRtKAX">Unauthorized access occurs when malicious entities use network services without authorization or privileges.</s><s xml:id="_bP6st75">iv.</s><s xml:id="_ZDExMGc">Impersonation or spoofing, when an attacker attempts to pass as another node to receive messages or use privileges not meant for them.</s><s xml:id="_YzAJYjJ">v. Denial of service, rendering resources and services inaccessible to network users through jamming or sleep deprivation <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_URaXcSc"><s xml:id="_R4RazC8">V2V technology is gaining popularity and may be used by every vehicle soon <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_kxDpSSH">This innovation can increase traffic safety and reduce delays or gridlock.</s><s xml:id="_dHqshhx">Although this technology has several advantages for consumers, cybersecurity challenges in V2V communication should be considered to protect against cyber-attacks.</s></p><p xml:id="_5zSbm3T"><s xml:id="_QcS9swf">V2V communication enables the exchange of vital traffic information, such as speed, direction, traffic conditions, accidents and other safety critical data, to enhance road safety and efficiency <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_XbcuTje">Many cybersecurity challenges have been reported in the V2V communication technology <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_ATNtZ2D">Despite the importance of V2V technology, there is a knowledge gap in Multivocal Literature Review (MLR) studies to address practices of the challenges in general and particularly, the identification and analysis of cybersecurity challenges in this domain.</s></p><p xml:id="_tjmgsYT"><s xml:id="_aJ2Jf9J">This research aims to identify cybersecurity challenges and their corresponding practices through MLR for the automotive industry related to V2V communication.</s><s xml:id="_5V2StyD">It intends to assist various organizations in addressing potential attacks involved in V2V communication, achieving a higher level of cybersecurity while dealing with cyber threats.</s><s xml:id="_PvWxyYj">The primary goal of this MLR is to identify cybersecurity challenges and their practices in V2V communication using a pre-defined protocol, reviewing both grey literature and formal literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_mJBQhzk"><s xml:id="_PbGvx9h">MLR is widely used in the field of software engineering <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_bAq7FXC">The identified results in the study will serve as a foundation for other researchers to explore these challenges and practices to address the problems faced in V2V communication.</s></p><p xml:id="_s8gSbZR"><s xml:id="_Nww5Nb4">To the best of our knowledge, and based on the literature survey and available resources, the research presented in this paper is novel due to the clear research questions and MLR methodology.</s><s xml:id="_bS7P7wD">We have formulated the following research questions:</s></p><p xml:id="_5nUPKgr"><s xml:id="_wfGtgrK">RQ1: What are the cybersecurity challenges in V2V Communication from a Software Engineering perspective?</s></p><p xml:id="_yEDSBVJ"><s xml:id="_fa7JpBb">This question aims to identify a list of cybersecurity challenges and analyze each challenge to be addressed.</s></p><p xml:id="_EEpSMc9"><s xml:id="_43DnnSM">RQ2: What are the practices/solutions that can be implemented to address the cybersecurity challenges?</s><s xml:id="_P2vQn2a">This question aims to identify the best possible practices for addressing cybersecurity challenges.</s></p><p xml:id="_G5PNxMZ"><s xml:id="_89VqB2B">These questions are designed to identify cybersecurity challenges and associated best practices from different perspectives.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2." xml:id="_sWFeFnC">Background</head><p xml:id="_2J2vNbG"><s xml:id="_wxETvYV">Cybersecurity is the protection of various information systems, the data within them, and the services they provide against abuse, dangerous elements, and illegal access, encompassing related infrastructure, software, and hardware <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_yXeUPMs">Automotive Vehicles (AVs) rely on sensing, communication, and artificial intelligence, making them vulnerable to cyber-attacks <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_4DnHS4T">As vehicular systems have advanced rapidly due to the swift progress in technology, the potential for cyber threats on these systems continues to grow.</s><s xml:id="_D6b8nad">Therefore, to enhance the safety of automotive vehicles, the industry must apply cybersecurity principles at different stages to govern security, safety, and protection from various forms of damage, including illegitimate access, malicious attacks, and any kind of cyber threats <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1." xml:id="_FNZbe2b">Vehicular adhoc network (VANET)</head><p xml:id="_6W6jWFz"><s xml:id="_Tk3sADf">Ghassan Samara et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>, defined VANET as a subset of Mobile Adhoc Networks (MANETs) used to establish communications between vehicles and surrounding fixed infrastructure.</s><s xml:id="_vJTCHe6">VANET technology employs moving vehicles as network nodes to construct a mobile network.</s><s xml:id="_FTYQs7D">Upon joining the VANET, each vehicle transforms into a wireless router or node, facilitating connections between vehicles up to 300 m apart and resulting in a network with a broad coverage area <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_qCBjKjH">Mobile internet is generated as vehicles connect to the network when entering its signal range and cease connection when leaving.</s><s xml:id="_4ABq7Em">VANETs utilize various wireless technologies, including WiFi, such as DSRC.</s><s xml:id="_UfY75xX">There are two types of VANET communication <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.1." xml:id="_4A5U9Ta">Vehicle-to-Vehicle (V2V) communication</head><p xml:id="_ZNw947Y"><s xml:id="_YBuHgK6">A vehicle can communicate with others in the network through vehicle-to-vehicle (V2V) communication, enabling the transmission, reception, or sharing of crucial traffic-related data, including speed, direction, road conditions, traffic jams, and accidents on the road <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.2." xml:id="_zcD5wbV">Vehicle-to-Infrastructure (V2I) communication</head><p xml:id="_HRzxDVY"><s xml:id="_UUSGa59">To communicate and establish connections with external networks, such as the Internet, a vehicle establishes a link with stationary equipment known as Road Side Units (RSU) or Road Side Infrastructure <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2." xml:id="_hVUKjdN">Overview of vehicle-to-vehicle (V2V)</head><p xml:id="_ZzBTBHb"><s xml:id="_XUDcxy7">The objective of V2V is to share critical essential details with drivers and warn them about incidents in realtime.</s><s xml:id="_c3ZcJm2">Utilizing Dedicated Short Range Communication (DSRC) technology <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>, vehicles interact with each other, broadcasting electronic data, including the speed of the vehicles, GPS location, route, track history, vehicle control information, steering wheel angle, brake status, and transmission state.</s><s xml:id="_ezgkcvc">According to the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration (NHTSA), V2V communication messages serve as essentialsafety messages (BSMs), transmitting dynamic information between vehicles, such as speed, location, and headings <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_khx8Hpd">Vehicles in the Internet of Vehicles (IoV) exchange important messages, enabling applications like changing traffic routes, crash avoidance, traffic data, content caching, and entertainment, among others <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_4RC3R6h">V2V communication serves several purpose, including traffic management, driver assistance apps, safety, and direction optimization.</s><s xml:id="_UefycmK">With road traffic collisions causing nearly 1.35 million fatalities annually worldwide <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, various applications can contribute to enhancing traffic safety using DSRC technology <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_S5N7GKn">DSRC enables vehicles to detect obstacles, avoid traffic accidents <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>, identify sharp bends, and alert other drivers <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_JjV9TJD">Vehicles can warn each other if a collision is imminent, and a traffic control system for safe overtaking, highway fleet management, can be established using DSRC, which allows vehicles to safely pass/overtake each other, maintaining the necessary distance during lane changes <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_XuUbTHg">A specific vehicle signals others for a lane change when needed, enabling effective traffic management using DSRC communications.</s><s xml:id="_ZW9urVB">To ensure reliable V2I and V2V communication among unrelated moving entities, a PKI-based security infrastructure system proposed by the United States Department of Transportation (USDT) named the Security Credential Management System (SCMS) is implemented <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_mgpNn3a">Attaching certificates to each message protects the communication's security, integrity, and privacy, along with the verification and authentication of basic safety messages.</s><s xml:id="_h2BHCgw">Digital certificates created by SCMS are utilized by approved participating automobiles to authenticate BSMs.</s><s xml:id="_PDSctNF">Although the use of SCMS is recommended for the current peer-to-peer V2V and V2I communication to enable secure and trusted essential safety message exchange across entities, user privacy and security issues arising from the extensive and intricate complexity of this PKI-based system must be resolved before implementation <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3." xml:id="_AQzxMZY">Related work</head><p xml:id="_MxneV8U"><s xml:id="_MbKbcnv">One major risk in V2V communication is the potential for communications to be intercepted and altered before reaching the intended recipient or for tracking drivers' activities.</s><s xml:id="_wDFRswV">This poses a threat to driver privacy and can compromise the security of the vehicle.</s><s xml:id="_tSqDM25">In a VANET <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>, where the wireless communication environment exposes essential data to external users or hackers, safeguarding against improper use is crucial.</s><s xml:id="_4bqaaXE">The dynamic changes in network topology and the high mobility of vehicles make securing information sharing more challenging.</s><s xml:id="_V47hVzn">Security requirements for VANET encompass assuring data integrity, authenticating users, securing data, maintaining privacy and secrecy, scalability, non-repudiation, and addressing mobility concerns.</s><s xml:id="_ZcWaDTD">This section delves into the research conducted on security issues in VANET and V2V communication.</s><s xml:id="_RcfXJmc">Numerous researchers have explored security challenges in these domains, their findings and limitations are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_vQk37UT"><s xml:id="_6txNJ2A">Upon analyzing Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>, it is evident that none of the individual or studies employed a systemtic process, such as Multivocal Literature Review (MLR), to identify cybersecurity challenges and their corresponding practices/solutions.</s></p><p xml:id="_C2SCpFQ"><s xml:id="_DmHbZ4s">The research presented in this paper aims to identify, through Multivocal literature review, cybersecurity challenges in V2V communication and their related best practices/solutions.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3." xml:id="_R9yfMha">Research methodology</head><p xml:id="_CTYXQsD"><s xml:id="_4QkBjup">We perform a Multivocal literature review.</s><s xml:id="_XXp7GTc">The Multivocal literature review is a research methodology designed to systematically review formal and grey literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_NypXx4W">The term 'grey literature' refers to a broad range of informal publications, such as technical reports, blogs, white papers, etc.</s><s xml:id="_n6x2zBv">Through MLR, we aim to gather sufficient data to bridge the knowledge gap between academics and industry practitioners.</s><s xml:id="_SATvb4n">In this research, we conducted MLR following the guidelines proposed by Garousi et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_4pgA89V">MLR has been widely used in the software engineering <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_7mWwYRd">MLR comprises three phases.</s><s xml:id="_P3YGtJK">The first phase involves protocol development, encompassing the planning phase of MLR.</s><s xml:id="_WJC45Vq">This phase includes settling research objectives, formulating research questions, determining source selection, outlining the search method, establishing inclusion and exclusion criteria for publications, and defining standards for quality evaluation, data extraction, and synthesis.</s><s xml:id="_yyPNC2N">We designed the MLR protocol first that wasinitially reviewed by fellow researchers of the Software Engineering Research Group at the University of Malakand (SERG-UOM).</s><s xml:id="_aRpQgbe">Suggestions from the reviewers were incorporated, and the final protocol was presented at the 2nd Annual International Workshop on Software Engineering (WSE-2022), themed 'Cybersecurity Culture' at University of Malakand.</s><s xml:id="_dTPAZTb">The second phase of MLR involves the implementation of the protocol, while the final phase focuses on reporting findings.</s><s xml:id="_tRhvgXd">This study integrates primary and secondary research to provide a comprehensive understanding of cybersecurity challenges and their corresponding practices related to V2V communication.</s><s xml:id="_xMCNwtt">To provide a comprehensive overview, we systematically integrated primary research with relevant ssecondary studies, selected through rigorous process, to reveal broader trends and patterns across the research domain.</s><s xml:id="_tjDyF7n">Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> presents the MLR workflow.</s></p><p xml:id="_VUJktzu"><s xml:id="_vkcSCgx">Furthermore, we have formulated the following research questions to investigate variations in outcomes based on study strategies and publication periods.</s></p><p xml:id="_TTe6syk"><s xml:id="_9kFTHYC">RQ3: Do the identified cybersecurity challenges in V2V Communication vary based on the study strategies?</s><s xml:id="_eRT2ynn">RQ4: Do the identified cybersecurity challenges in V2V Communication vary based on publication periods?</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1." xml:id="_5az55nz">Search strategy</head><p xml:id="_pbG5umc"><s xml:id="_dThz3Fx">Search strategy is used to select and retrieve the related sources for review.</s><s xml:id="_fUgub9U">To define the search strategy for the MLR is plan to:</s></p><p xml:id="_QmbvF3X"><s xml:id="_Uux6hrm">• Construct search terms for the identification of population, intervention and outcome.</s><s xml:id="_rzwMxkc">• Identifying the related synonyms and spellings.</s></p><p xml:id="_rWSS93x"><s xml:id="_QVtanPv">• Keywords verification in the related paper.</s></p><p xml:id="_42KWT5x"><s xml:id="_4VhuF4Q">• Usage of Boolean Operators.</s></p><p xml:id="_Z7ZY5Zf"><s xml:id="_qqk57K7">It is essential to outline the criteria for source inclusion/exclusion and the quality assessment checklist.</s><s xml:id="_5NrRkHq">We have adopted the PICO criteria from the literature as the initial step in creating the search string <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref> as <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Kitchenham (2007)</ref> suggested <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_se8nsfK">Other researchers also used the similar approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_eJ3fFKY">The PICO criteria involve identifying Population, Intervention, and relevant Outcomes as shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_acKtgRW"><s xml:id="_c2WSY8P">Research question is formulated as below: N. Ullah et al.</s><s xml:id="_Z8hNhvt">Information and Software Technology 179 (2025) 107639</s></p><p xml:id="_ghv3KJV"><s xml:id="_2hRSZDy">Using these PICO criteria, we derived search terms and created search strings based on the research questions.</s><s xml:id="_C5QYmUt">These search terms were applied to academic databases and the Google search engine, and we identified synonyms from the obtained papers as shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_FQgJXXV">As illustrated in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">4</ref> these synonyms are connected using Boolean operators.</s><s xml:id="_25s9w7q">Ultimately, we formulated the following search string to identify cybersecurity risks, challenges, and threats in V2V communication:</s></p><p xml:id="_cvspp9Q"><s xml:id="_4cpcSVb">("Cybersecurity in V2V communication" OR "V2V communication" OR "Information security in V2V communication") AND ("Cybersecurity risks" OR "Cybersecurity challenges" OR "Cybersecurity issues" OR Practices OR Solutions OR Guidelines).</s></p><p xml:id="_ae3uQE6"><s xml:id="_dqpfEZu">The MLR search result and review timetable are shown in Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">4</ref> and <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">5</ref> respectively.</s></p><p xml:id="_bmED6fr"><s xml:id="_Jsxavhv">Each phase of the search strategy and publication selection was thoroughly reviewed by the research supervisor (the secondary author) during the research meetings.</s><s xml:id="_5ExRjVp">No major issue was found during the review meetings.</s></p><p xml:id="_YBZGvqx"><s xml:id="_GC4MQnQ">The search string was used in the following digital libraries for searching relevant literature:</s></p><p xml:id="_RBjuY59"><s xml:id="_n92kpaE">• IEEE Xplore (<ref type="url" target="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org">http://ieeexplore.ieee.org</ref>)</s><s xml:id="_uZjUVxc">• ACM digital library (<ref type="url" target="http://dl.acm.org">http://dl.acm.org</ref>)</s><s xml:id="_uhEqQ66">• ScienceDirect (<ref type="url" target="http://www.sciencedirect.com">http://www.sciencedirect.com</ref>)</s><s xml:id="_EKmFhCr">• Springer Link (<ref type="url" target="http://link.springer.com">http://link.springer.com</ref>)</s><s xml:id="_b2f98RK">• Google Scholar (<ref type="url" target="https://scholar.google.com">https://scholar.google.com</ref>),</s><s xml:id="_vKKPqdj">engine • Google (<ref type="url" target="http://www.google.com">http://www.google.com</ref>),</s><s xml:id="_fX4yS2Y">engine</s></p><p xml:id="_Qkq9bNZ"><s xml:id="_pk3bcRX">We used a snowballing approach as a post-search technique to include potential literature in the study that may have been missed out by the search engine during the initial search phase.</s><s xml:id="_mXGcvFV">This involved examining the reference sections of relevant publications (backward snowballing) and citing the studies chosen in the literature (forward snowballing).</s><s xml:id="_3cQUjhJ">This approach led to an enhanced sample size as it explored more citations and references <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_fMWrXk3">Other researchers also used the similar technique <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[54,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_6r5Zb96"><s xml:id="_rxNnbaX">In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>, the X-axis of the graph represents both formal literature (papers published in conference proceedings and journals) and grey literature (white papers, technical reports, blogs, etc.) of the finally selected articles.</s><s xml:id="_835TkPx">The Y-axis of the graph represents the frequencies of each category.</s><s xml:id="_ZxDnJty">It is evident that more attention has been given to cybersecurity challenges in V2V communication in the formal literature, while the grey literature comprising technical reports, white papers, blogs, etc. has lower frequencies.</s></p><p xml:id="_nVfc6g5"><s xml:id="_ZKpdjQf">In</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2." xml:id="_dC2R63c">Inclusion/Exclusion criteria</head><p xml:id="_zvYm9j5"><s xml:id="_6Pt95Pv">The inclusion and exclusion criteria were specified to ensure the selection of only relevant articles for the final sample, facilitating data extraction and further investigation.</s><s xml:id="_ah78VUT">Inclusion criteria were based on the following standards:</s></p><p xml:id="_CqbzSCZ"><s xml:id="_sSY69eX">• Articles that specifically focus on cybersecurity V2V communication.</s></p><p xml:id="_VwemccT"><s xml:id="_3wbdBPu">• Articles written in the English language.</s></p><p xml:id="_GdSFfZq"><s xml:id="_ccJ6CMq">• Studies describing challenges, threats, risks, or practices related to cybersecurity in V2V communication.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_QRpmNwj">• Studies outlining solutions to cybersecurity challenges in V2V</head><p xml:id="_y6Cst9s"><s xml:id="_4AzsZ3Z">communication.</s></p><p xml:id="_NkrRbAE"><s xml:id="_d66JrpD">• Grey literature, including online reports, white papers from various organizations, or blogs from industry practitioners addressing the aforementioned agenda.</s></p><p xml:id="_dvuuRRV"><s xml:id="_WFef2Jt">The following criteria were applied to exclude sources from the final sample of publications.</s></p><p xml:id="_VQU3Sjj"><s xml:id="_Xq5Wtaw">• Studies not relevant to the research questions.</s></p><p xml:id="_WcRUJdf"><s xml:id="_HEcFcBq">• Studies that do not describe challenges, issues, or practices for cybersecurity in V2V communication.</s><s xml:id="_956sFEN">• Studies not entirely accessible online or written in languages other than English.</s><s xml:id="_D65rqmp">• In the case of identical studies, the most current one will be chosen.</s></p><p xml:id="_sRmwXzk"><s xml:id="_zpC8ka9">• Studies not meeting the aforementioned inclusion criteria.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3." xml:id="_BAzVwyF">Quality assessment criteria</head><p xml:id="_h8DgpH9"><s xml:id="_gSUsCEW">To assess the quality of the selected primary studies and minimize bias, we established assessment criteria that evaluate the importance and comprehensiveness of each chosen primary study <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[56,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">57]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_zqS45m6"><s xml:id="_ycjm2rW">We followed the checklist developed by Kitchenham and Charters <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[56,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">58]</ref> for Quality Assessment (QA) criteria, guiding the design of QA questions (QA1-QA8) for formal papers and design QA questions (QA1-QA5) for non-formal papers.We used quality assessment criteria to analyze each chosen primary study.</s><s xml:id="_cfGKjd9">These criteria were applied to analyze each chosen primary study, encompassing formal and non-formal literature sources.</s><s xml:id="_CaB7gwA">To evaluate the quality of grey literature, we utilized criteria based on the checklist developed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">58]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_vuQtmpk">The QA questions for formal and non-formal papers are shown in Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">6</ref> &amp; <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">7</ref> respectively.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4." xml:id="_FQqzCDV">Papers selection</head><p xml:id="_Ebu2tKV"><s xml:id="_3f8he8z">Sources and papers were selected for data extraction by applying the criteria outlined in the previous sections.</s><s xml:id="_e2B2KqJ">An initial selection of relevant sources was made by reviewing titles and abstracts in the search results.</s><s xml:id="_rhufX8N">In the second stage, the final selection was made by thoroughly reading all the texts from the initially chosen sources.</s><s xml:id="_cvxFXCC">The chosen sources for data extraction meet both the inclusion/exclusion and quality assessment criteria.</s><s xml:id="_4n4t2MZ">The final list of publications, totaling 84, selected for data extraction from formal literature, is provided in Appendix -A.</s><s xml:id="_xg8GygP">Additionally, the papers from grey literature, numbering 17, are listed in Appendix -B.</s><s xml:id="_r6CTYDu">The final sample of publications from formal and grey literature is 101.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5." xml:id="_dNGYKUM">Data extraction and synthesis</head><p xml:id="_jBYv3hU"><s xml:id="_p65frjA">The analysis of original studies in the final selection process enabled   The primary reviewer conducted the data synthesis and subsequently reviewed by the secondary reviewers.</s><s xml:id="_D5ScGJC">Thes secondary reviewer randomly choosed 16 publications amongst the list of publications already selected by the first reviewer.</s><s xml:id="_yVnZg5q">The secondary reviewer extracted the data independtly from the 16 publications randomly choosen papers.</s><s xml:id="_TWfFbWE">The results were compared with the identified results of the first reviwer and found no major differences.</s><s xml:id="_dzYhYXM">From each paper a list of quotes were extracted, where each quote represent a list of cybersecurity challenges that are facing by V2V communications.</s><s xml:id="_WwKs6x8">Initially, the primary reviewer identified a list of 24 cybersecurity challenges, the secondary reviewer carefully reviewed the identified cybersecurity challenges, some of the related challenges were merged.</s><s xml:id="_wr6MSRS">This process yields a final list of 18 cybersecurity challenges as depicted in Table <ref type="table">8</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_NJhzeDT"><s xml:id="_mz5ZYgV">For quality assessment criteria, each question of the reviewed studies was graded on a three-tier scale: Yes, Partially, or No.</s><s xml:id="_yk82zpz">We assigned the values as follows: 1 → Yes, 0.5 → Partially, and 0 → No, for both formal and grey literature articles.</s><s xml:id="_48QF2zC">Based on the data, almost 91 percent formal primary studies obtained a score of &gt;50 percent on the QA questions and 82 percent grey literature primary studies obtained a score of &gt;60 percent on the QA questions, implying that the both selected formal and grey primary sources are relevant to the study research questions.</s><s xml:id="_E2PZ3PS">Studies with publication scores having predetermined thresholds (less than 3/8 for formal literature and less than 2/5 for grey literature) are excluded from further analysis to ensure the inclusion of only highquality evidence.</s><s xml:id="_yBRxGHP">Upon this process based on quality scores led to the removal of two formal literature articles and two grey literature articesl, yielding a refined dataset for further analysis.</s><s xml:id="_Dz6sf3P">Details regarding publications score are based on the aforementioned quality evaluation criteria for the finalized formal and grey literature are shown in Appendix-A and Appendix-B respectively.</s><s xml:id="_KFUzheq">Quality evaluation aims to exclude articles with low quality and increase the reliability of the extracted data from these papers <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">[59,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">60]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4." xml:id="_4EyFEKC">Results and analysis</head><p xml:id="_FPpqyhY"><s xml:id="_Dw962y3">To address the research question, Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">6</ref> presents the list of cybersecurity challenges identified using MLR.</s><s xml:id="_dEYcJXz">The most reported challenges in our study are "Spoofing attacks" (51 %) and "Denial of service attacks" (49 %).</s><s xml:id="_Ktf3Wmp">In total, 84 papers from the formal literature and 17 papers from the grey literature were considered, leading to a sample of 101 papers.</s></p><p xml:id="_8juKRzB"><s xml:id="_sW4qUAK">After the data extraction and synthesis, a list of 18 cybersecurity challenges emerged.</s><s xml:id="_BRb2eRw">During the data synthesis phase, initially, a list of 24 challenges was identified, which was subsequently reviewed and some categories were merged.</s><s xml:id="_Rbczj6H">This process resulted in the final list of 18 cybersecurity challenges presented in Table <ref type="table">8</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1." xml:id="_MXzEzGM">Cybersecurity challenges faced during V2V communication</head><p xml:id="_ZTPuwqP"><s xml:id="_3uhNUUF">To answer RQ1, this study identified a list of eighteen cybersecurity challenges in V2V communication as depicted in Table <ref type="table">8</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_xyuSxyv"><s xml:id="_4jrGZ2Q">Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">9</ref> presented the list of identified ten critical cybersecurity challenges.</s></p><p xml:id="_9EtzbS3"><s xml:id="_gjZzDvK">To address RQ 2, this study identified associated best practices for the ten critical cybersecurity challenges, as presented in <ref type="bibr">Tables 10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_CWzCC9p">Each critical cybersecurity challenge with identified practicesare discussed below.</s></p><p xml:id="_KN67Dd4"><s xml:id="_5njuUJk">CCC1: Denial of Service (DoS) attack:</s></p><p xml:id="_X4cWNYh"><s xml:id="_mwGjXjB">The most familiar attack in VANET attacks is DoS.</s><s xml:id="_jYFDmXm">A hacker who conducts a denial of service attack disrupts communication between vehicles.</s><s xml:id="_FGybwwR">It tries to stop the node from connecting to the network.</s><s xml:id="_PDr6QR7">Attackers also attempt to block all services offered to users, resulting in packet loss or communication delays <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">[61]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_GHcNHP2"><s xml:id="_d49zc3V">CCC2: Spoofing attacks: Spoofing is the most complicated type of attack, in which the valid signal is replaced by a bogus signal, resulting in incorrect position information for a connected vehicle.</s><s xml:id="_3BCzqKB">Tampering with the GPS signal can create turn-by-turn faked data, leading a linked vehicle to an incorrect location.</s><s xml:id="_TmYkb7R">Ultimately, this could compromise the consistency of cloud services for sustaining connected vehicle applications.</s><s xml:id="_bJsaBnq">The reliability of the location information is compromised, and personal information is revealed.</s><s xml:id="_xJ59PnW">Further, the validation of the connected vehicle also needs to be re-examined once an attack is detected <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[62]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_bNJQCvR"><s xml:id="_vd5QW3g">CCC3: Bogus warning messages:</s></p><p xml:id="_zzH6Dx5"><s xml:id="_zS3Cdqv">In bogus warning messages, the aim is to broadcast false or bogus information in the network to create confusion, which may lead to a misinterpretation of the actual incident.</s><s xml:id="_JvHh8RG">Attackers send false information to vehicles for selfish reasons.</s><s xml:id="_J2WZwbZ">For example, an attacker might disseminate bogus information related to roadblocks, congestion, and accidents to clear the road for its easy movement <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">[63]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_bXQdxq6"><s xml:id="_jMh2mSm">CCC4: Sybil and man-in-the-middle attacks: In a Sybil attack, an attacker creates several fake identities with the aim of broadcasting multiple messages using these bogus identities to disrupt or disconnect the regular operation of VANETs.</s><s xml:id="_heAHBFs">For instance, a single vehicle can broadcast messages about multiple identities simultaneously, creating theimpression that the messages are coming from numerous vehicles.</s><s xml:id="_S5XS3dV">This could be done to trick other vehicles into thinking there is traffic congestion and forcing them to alter their paths, clearing the road <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[64]</ref>.In a "man-in-the-middle attack," the attacker closely monitors communication, modifies messages, and may gain access to control the entire V2V communication, while the nodes in V2V communication believe they are communicating with each other privately <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[64]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_YUT7ugX"><s xml:id="_7PGRGJq">CCC5: Spamming and replay attacks: Ads and other spam communications pose an increased risk of transmission latency, which could lead to accidents.</s><s xml:id="_j7RzpVw">Like advertisements, these messages are useless to users.</s><s xml:id="_gDNB3fZ">Dealing with spam is challenging due to the lack of centralized administration and infrastructure <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">65]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_svzaeYw">Replay attacks have the unique ability to be carried out by illegitimate nodes.</s><s xml:id="_CB4JVw9">They involve the attacker broadcasting messages that have previously been forwarded to entities repeatedly to trick other network nodes into removing priority messages from the waiting list.</s><s xml:id="_QvWBUBZ">Repeated replays can impact the system's performance and increase bandwidth costs.</s><s xml:id="_HfAakHm">The adversary replicates the original message transmitted earlier to delay traffic.</s><s xml:id="_cvxRQx7">The procedure of a replay attack involves broadcasting an earlier message to achieve the current message's objective, such as tampering with the entity and location routing tables.</s><s xml:id="_S4rzTjd">This creates confusion for the government and prevents the recipient from discovering the sender's identity <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">[66]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_URN9YT2"><s xml:id="_zfPPKDN">CCC6: Real-time adversaries:</s></p><p xml:id="_5zXHaEZ"><s xml:id="_SkYcwnB">In VANET, transmitting security messages at the exact time is one of the basic requirements.</s><s xml:id="_YBfyJ3b">When an emergency message is received by a malicious vehicle, it may delay the forwarding/broadcast of the message.</s><s xml:id="_5ZNgJZT">Thus, the intended/neighbor vehicle doesn't receive the message at the right time to avoid an accidental situation <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_BDx7C2a">For V2V communications in VANET, Road Side Units (RSUs) are important nodes.</s><s xml:id="_qn8eZ7c">Due to vehicle mobility and dynamic topology, the attacker adds  an interruption to the authenticating demand packet issued by the vehicle.</s><s xml:id="_Wugj5cw">As a consequence, a vehicle in need of authentication may have already shifted to another RSU for service <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[67]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_SaqfY6C">CCC7: Black hole, Grey hole, and Wormhole attacks (BGW):</s></p><p xml:id="_mD2vZ3N"><s xml:id="_bck6MB4">In a black hole attack, the vehicle denies participating in communication or drops packets in between, creating a black hole.</s><s xml:id="_cACmuAc">All traffic is sent to the node that does not openly exist within this zone.</s><s xml:id="_56423Y8">The routing protocol is tricked by an attacker who assumes the identity of a node that has the straight path to the destination node.</s><s xml:id="_xXnjkgP">This causes all nodes to start believing the fake direction instead of the route discovery process, resulting in malicious nodes intercepting data packets instead of forwarding them <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[64]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_4nuuCMK">The grey hole attack utilizes the concept of selective forwarding and is reversible from the black hole attack.</s><s xml:id="_ASvz7Rx">Malicious nodes will select which packets to drop and forward, perhaps lowering the network's packet delivery ratio rather than reducing all of the data-containing packets <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[64]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_jN6WXnh">Actually, a wormhole is a private tunnel created by two participating malicious nodes in a network that can forward data from one node to another.</s><s xml:id="_buWpXbE">It hides the real paths between them and compels other nodes to route across the established tunnel <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[64,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">68]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_g6R9Een">CCC8: Eavesdropping attacks:</s></p><p xml:id="_XbSvFx3"><s xml:id="_gwwpBHU">The objective of an eavesdropping attack is to obtain private information from secure data.</s><s xml:id="_BHG2YHe">Therefore, hidden details can be exposed to non-registered users, and the leaked data may include the location of the vehicle and user identity, which are further used to track the vehicles <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[64]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_kUZk3Ww"><s xml:id="_ZksyuXW">CCC9: Location falsifications: Vehicular location privacy is more beneficial in the VANET environment, as a hacker or attacker can misuse the privacy of passengers or drivers, such as the place/location most visited by a particular passenger or driver.</s><s xml:id="_PxDKeCw">Location authentication systems are essentialand are usually applied in Intelligent Transportation Systems (ITS) applications.</s><s xml:id="_fyQBEJQ">To prevent any mishaps and ensure the safety of passengers, the authentication of location information provided by the vehicles is important <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[67]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_J3gHb57"><s xml:id="_KhPBSMN">CCC10: Authentication and authorization issues: Authenticity is the basic requirement in Autonomous Vehicle (AV) networking to ensure the network nodes' safety against malicious attacks.</s><s xml:id="_hu6WATE">Illegal actors may access sensitive data without the necessary authentication, compromising other cybersecurity criteria like confidentiality, integrity, and availability.</s><s xml:id="_n3Wax2x">Any authentication or identification process flaw may have severe consequences for the whole network <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[62]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2." xml:id="_C8wPsPZ">Analysis of cybersecurity challenges based on study strategies</head><p xml:id="_cU3WaPM"><s xml:id="_rRQS39t">To answer RQ3, the finally selected papers are classified into four categories based on the study strategies used, as shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_13">20</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_MYhPYA4">These study strategies are experiments, literature review, survey, and others.</s><s xml:id="_XTYNaDc">The 'others' category means mixed methods, formal methods, focus group sessions, etc.</s><s xml:id="_UNmVjfn">We identified different cybersecurity challenges based on the distribution of papers across these four study strategies.</s><s xml:id="_NadQuU4">Our results show that in the literature we identified a list of 18 cybersecurity challenges.</s></p><p xml:id="_WgW7Kmm"><s xml:id="_DadhrS7">Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_13">20</ref> shows that each study strategy identified 18 cybersecurity challenges except 'others'.</s><s xml:id="_TdHSAnf">The 'others' category has identified 16 challenges and has missed the two challenges CC7: fuzzy injection attacks and CC13: session hijacking.</s><s xml:id="_KEJHkFx">We have categorized these challenges into critical ones based on the criterion of occurrences of ≥50 % of the articles.</s><s xml:id="_na587AV">Other researchers in the literature have used a similar criterion for the criticality of challenges <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">[69]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_7NyRrnN">However, practitioners, based on their requirements, can define their own criteria.</s><s xml:id="_MgAcYUK">Based on the criterion of ≥50 % occurrences for critical challenges, by examining the data in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_13">20</ref> regarding the literature review, we identified 4, 6 and 1 critical challenges in the categories of Literature Review, survey, and 'others' category respectively.</s></p><p xml:id="_CnAt3f6"><s xml:id="_e4h3NQp">Similarly, the most-cited critical challenge in each study strategy in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">18</ref> is 'Denial of service attacks,' and 'Repudiation attacks' are cited (27 %) critical challenges in the experiment.</s><s xml:id="_EBdftj4">'Spoofing attacks' is the most often cited (70 %) critical challenge in the literature review.</s><s xml:id="_HWWpNzz">'Denial of service attacks' is the most often cited (78 %) critical challenge in the survey, and 'Denial of service attacks' is cited (53 %) critical challenge in the 'others' category.</s></p><p xml:id="_5WUFVev"><s xml:id="_exfTFG4">Since the data were ordinal, we used the linear-by-linear chi-square test to identify any statistically significant difference between the identified cybersecurity challenges based on study strategies.</s><s xml:id="_9fBfexa">Because it is more effective than the Pearson chi-square test, the linear-by-linear association test is chosen when determining whether there is a statistically significant difference between ordinal variables <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">[70]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_8Dd9wCg">Other researchers also used the similar approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">[69]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_QKmmR7D">The linear-by-linear chi-square test is used to identify significant differences among the challenges across different study strategies.</s><s xml:id="_6Req6Mb">We identified four significant differences for the challenges 'Denial of service attacks,' 'Information and hardware tampering,' 'Spamming and replay attacks,' and 'Spoofing attacks.'</s><s xml:id="_6SrZfQT">These results suggest that the challenges identified across different strategies share more similarities than differences.</s><s xml:id="_pK7sA7E">The four cybersecurity challenges were cited more frequently in surveys compared to other strategies.</s><s xml:id="_hAwa7gc">This is likely due to surveys typically having larger sample sizes than experiments or literature reviews.</s><s xml:id="_r2pgVFr">Additionally, survey respondents are often experts who encounter these cybersecurity challenges regularly in their work.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3." xml:id="_RxyAgxh">Analysis of cybersecurity challenges based on publication periods</head><p xml:id="_zNAc38R"><s xml:id="_tkdNJmA">To answer RQ4, the finally selected papers are classified into two periods, i.e., 2009-2015 and 2016-2021, as shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_14">21</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_gK2TB4A">No date bounds were included in the MLR search phase.</s><s xml:id="_cMa5TtN">However, papers from 2009 till the end of 2021 (End 2021 is the finalization of the search phase in our MLR process) were retrieved and finally selected based on our pre-defined inclusion/exclusion criteria.</s><s xml:id="_7Pf52xn">By examining the data in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_14">21</ref>, we found that 14 cybersecurity challenges have been cited in the literature in the first period.</s><s xml:id="_3xRWbHD">We have used the criterion of ≥50 % occurrences in the literature to identify the critical challenges amongst the list of identified challenges.</s><s xml:id="_2pFtwew">Based on this criterion, there is no critical challenge in the first period, 2009-2015.</s><s xml:id="_q9YRyyE">However, by relaxing the criteria, we hardly found one critical challenge.</s><s xml:id="_SRyYMhJ">This most cited challenge is 'real-time adversaries' (48 %), i. e., almost 50 %.Between the periods 2009-2015, the real-time adversaries have the highest number (48 %), which means that real-time adversaries were the obstacle for automotive industries.</s><s xml:id="_vcURt2u">However, over time, this inclination has significantly changed because we find a downturn in the frequency of real-time adversaries, which has reduced to 29 % in the second period 2016-2021.</s><s xml:id="_ExrQMmF">In the second period, 18 cybersecurity challenges, in total, have been cited in the literature.</s><s xml:id="_4MWN33X">Throughout these 18 challenges, only two critical challenges have been reported in ≥50 % of the articles.</s><s xml:id="_XRJsFgh">These critical challenges are 'Denial of service attacks' (61 %) and 'Spoofing attacks' (55 %).</s></p><p xml:id="_GdtZxFN"><s xml:id="_FgyDu5Z">The Linear-by-Linear chi-square test is employed to identify any statistically significant differences among the identified cybersecurity challenges based on publication periods.</s><s xml:id="_gMf4pPT">This test is chosen because it is more effective than the Pearson chi-square test, especially when determining whether there is a statistically significant difference between ordinal variables <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">[70]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_zj99DAk">Other researchers have used similar approaches <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">[69]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_Ghknfhj">The Linear-by-Linear Chi-square test is used to identify significant differences among the different challenges across publication periods.</s><s xml:id="_7xEjzUH">Six significant differences have identified for the challenges 'Authentication and authorization issues,' 'Denial of service attacks,' 'Information and hardware tampering,' 'Spamming and replay attacks,' 'Spoofing attacks,' and 'Sybil and man-in-the-middle attacks'.</s><s xml:id="_MUFCXba">These results suggest that the challenges identified across different periods share more similarities than differences.</s><s xml:id="_gDYF7aW">The six cybersecurity challenges were cited more frequently in 2016-2021 period compared to 2009-2015 period.</s><s xml:id="_P5SkS92">This is likely due to the facts that countries have been enhancing their infrastructures by adopting vehicle-to-vehicle communications technologies, which may have introduced new and more cybersecurity challenges.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5." xml:id="_qWrsyeH">Threats to validity</head><p xml:id="_2ZMuUhR"><s xml:id="_a9jhv5n">To enhance confidence in the results, this section highlights the threats to validity and how they are overcome.</s><s xml:id="_jrQh4HE">According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref> the threats are classified into validity threats, namely construct, internal, external, and conclusion.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_J8Exg88">1) Construct validity</head><p xml:id="_9MybrsA"><s xml:id="_URRCvyQ">We employed a Multivocal Literature Review (MLR) as our research strategy, following a pre-defined MLR protocol for searching relevant literature.</s><s xml:id="_NyAWR8Y">The MLR guidelines were strictly adhered to, covering both formal and grey literature.</s><s xml:id="_gUGcyNt">While acknowledging the potential threat that our search string might have missed some relevant literature, we implemented rigorous measures to address this concern.</s><s xml:id="_qzpXv3u">The search string, designed following MLR guidelines, underwent thorough testing across various search venues before the actual search phase.</s><s xml:id="_yVBx2an">To enhance construct validity, we conducted our research using prominent digital libraries in the computing discipline, as outlined in section 2. Our search encompassed four digital libraries two search engines, and employed the snowballing technique.</s><s xml:id="_t2GAdcu">As a result, we achieved comprehensive coverage of relevant sources, providing sufficient evidence of our identification of most cybersecurity challenges and practices in V2V communication.</s></p><p xml:id="_cHsJbaE"><s xml:id="_Tw4ZXbM">2) Internal validity The cybersecurity challenges and related practices obtained through the MLR process represent the latestdepiction of the existing challenges and practices in secure V2V communication.</s><s xml:id="_2h4qpuE">However, in the MLR process, sources selection and data extraction process may be subject to bias.</s><s xml:id="_fDcBYSG">To mitigate this threat, we thoroughly screened the articles, retrieved through the search phase, based on the pre-defined inclusion/exclusion criteria and selected the sources based on a set of quality assessment criteria.</s><s xml:id="_Xc8AmmE">Please refer to Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">6</ref> and <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">7</ref> for the quality assessment criteria for both formal and grey literaturerespectively.</s><s xml:id="_VDFeVW5">In order to ensure internal validity, we have provided a list of the finally selected publications from formal literature in Appendix -A, and the list of papers from the grey literature in Appendix -B, from which we extracted the data.</s><s xml:id="_geBTD7p">Each phase of the MLR underwent validation through a systematic process and periodic assessments by the primary and secondary authors, reducing the risk of biasedness in the process of publication selection and data extraction.</s><s xml:id="_P5zZT6Z">Inter-rater reliability tests were conducted to minimize researcher's bias during the selection and data extraction process of primary studies.</s><s xml:id="_WPH3UFH">A small random sample of publications was selected by the secondary reviewer, and data were independently extracted according to the data extraction form.</s><s xml:id="_jWfYK82">While it was not feasible for the secondary reviewer to check each and every paper, the results of data extraction were compared with those generated by the primary reviewer, revealing no major differences, implying that the identified results are reliable and relevant to the research questions.</s><s xml:id="_rhBn8TX">Furhter, we plan to validate the MLR findings and to find additional cybersecurity challenges, if any, and their related practices through a questionnaire survey in the industry at the next stage of our study.</s><s xml:id="_rqf8gEQ">A similar approach has been used by other researchers <ref type="bibr" target="#b71">[72]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b72">[73]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b73">[74]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_W5cztdA"><s xml:id="_22UYDc5">3) External validity Generalizing the study outcomes poses another potential threat.</s><s xml:id="_URJhdgy">To address this concern, we have identified the cybersecurity challenges and relevant cybersecurity practices from a substantial sample of relevant sources that were selected based on a pre-defined and validated MLR protocol.</s><s xml:id="_pccgNwM">Further, we have not put any date boundaries or specific country while searching the literature.</s><s xml:id="_WkJkQrG">This may give a substantial evidence for generalization of our findings.</s></p><p xml:id="_mBnbXYJ"><s xml:id="_9bAaJjY">4) Conclusion validity Through the implementation of MLR, we have compiled sufficient evidence to support our conclusions regarding the existing cybersecurity challenges and practices of secure V2V communications.</s><s xml:id="_MGMET39">We reviewed the literature in a systematic way using MLR guidelines and evaluated sources based on quality assessment criteria, thereby enhancing confidence in the identification of cybersecurity challenges and practices and mitigating threats to conclusion validity.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6." xml:id="_fJYameB">Conclusion and future work</head><p xml:id="_MQ8JXEQ"><s xml:id="_tWB2XcV">The study comprehensively reviews vehicular communication, particularly Vehicle-to-Vehicle (V2V) communication.</s><s xml:id="_hBjDgDn">Through a Multivocal Literature Review (MLR), we identified a list of 18 cybersecurity challenges and associated best practices for addressing the critical challengesin V2V communication, as outlined in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">5</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_5YsGRE4">Among these identified 18 challenges in total, we identified10 challenges as critical challenges based on the criteria of ≥20 % citations in both formal and grey literature.</s><s xml:id="_6xEsDvg">The most cited critical cybersecurity challenges are "Bogus warning messages," "Denial of service attacks," "Spamming and replay attacks," "Spoofing attacks," and "Sybil and man-in-the-middle attacks."The</s><s xml:id="_YxWg95f">identified cybersecurity challenges were further analyzed based on different variables such as study strategy and time.</s><s xml:id="_28smFsX">The analysis of the identified challenges based on study strategy, we found significant differences for four critical challenges: 'Denial of service attacks,' 'Information and hardware tampering,' 'Spamming and replay attacks,' and 'Spoofing attacks.'</s><s xml:id="_du8WTfj">Additionally, we conducted an analysis based on publication periods (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">18</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_Y8bXSbk">We identified significant differences for six critical challenges: 'Authentication and authorization issues,' 'Denial of service attacks,' 'Information and hardware tampering,' 'Spamming and replay attacks,' 'Spoofing attacks,' and 'Sybil and man-in-the-middle attacks.'We</s><s xml:id="_xZvxwQs">recommend that automotive industries prioritize addressing these cybersecurity challenges to enhance their readiness for secure V2V communication.</s><s xml:id="_cd6KtkG">Our next goal of the research is to empirically validate the MLR outcomes through a questionnaire survey in the industry, exploring differences and similarities between MLR findings and industrial perspectives.</s><s xml:id="_2zB4v63">Our overarching goal is to develop a Cybersecurity Challenges Mitigation Model (CCMM) based on MLR findings and industrial survey outcomes, assisting companies in theautomobile sector to assess their readiness for secure V2V communication development.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_MukF8Z7">CRediT authorship contribution statement</head><note type="other" xml:id="_UJtKDau">Naeem</note></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_aEXUPKJ">Declaration of competing interest</head><p xml:id="_Qqssdnm"><s xml:id="_XzQ3XqA">I have no personal or financial relationships with other people or organizations that could inappropriately influence my work.</s></p><p xml:id="_PWuHrg7"><s xml:id="_hBdyzkT">I have disclosed all related information and followed the journal guidelines for declaring the conflicts of interest.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>[Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_vxAahw3"><s xml:id="_cXDY4tA">Fig. 1.</s><s xml:id="_ahnhAnT">MLR for the derivation of cybersecurity challenges and practices.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,69.62,489.69,456.00,236.55" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_k6KwZ7H"><s xml:id="_Y5Edrx8">the X-axis represents the publication year of the selected articles whereas the Y-axis represents the frequency.</s><s xml:id="_XGvcTZm">Cybersecurity challenges and its related best practices are identified from the final sample of 101 papers that contains 84 formal and 17 grey literature papers, with the earliest article published in 2009 and the latest articles are published in 2021, as our search results are completed in the first months of 2022.</s><s xml:id="_AMvwjz3">Number of identified 101 papers are spread among the years 2009-2021 as shown in Fig. 3.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_UPkuw4S"><s xml:id="_p334fPh">Fig. 2. MLR sources.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_9tAhnJq"><s xml:id="_WQfgv6c">Fig. 3. Number of sources based on publication year.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_X27gCPp"><s xml:id="_948JcB8">Ullah: Writingoriginal draft, Methodology, Formal analysis.</s><s xml:id="_XzjWMY7">Siffat Ullah Khan: Writingreview &amp; editing, Validation, Supervision.</s><s xml:id="_gup8QHC">Mahmood Niazi: Writingreview &amp; editing.</s><s xml:id="_p3j8JPV">Matteo Esposito: Writingreview &amp; editing.</s><s xml:id="_vJrQ8gu">Arif Ali Khan: Writingreview &amp; editing.</s><s xml:id="_RdMbYzT">Jamal Abdul Nasir: Writingreview &amp; editing.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_X8QdB6F"><s xml:id="_s3ZJqwS">Overview of existing work in V2V communications.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>N. Ullah et al.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Information and Software Technology 179 (2025) 107639</cell></row><row><cell>References</cell><cell>Year</cell><cell>Journal/Conference</cell><cell>Nature of</cell><cell>Contributions</cell><cell>Limitations</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>the study</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Baraa T. Sharef et al.</cell><cell>2013</cell><cell>in Proceedings of the 7th</cell><cell>Secondary</cell><cell>Conducts a literature review analyzing VANET</cell><cell>Provides general overview by</cell></row><row><cell>[39]</cell><cell></cell><cell>International Conference on</cell><cell></cell><cell>routing protocols based on the communication</cell><cell>analyzing routing protocols for VANET</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Ubiquitous Information Management</cell><cell></cell><cell>environment. The research contrasts and</cell><cell>on the basis of communication</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>and Communication.</cell><cell></cell><cell>enumerates improvements made to the VANET</cell><cell>envoirnment.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>protocol.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Ketut BayuYogha</cell><cell>2021</cell><cell>Journal Informatika dan sains</cell><cell>Secondary</cell><cell>Presents a brief description of the latest trends</cell><cell>Identifying challenges are not enough</cell></row><row><cell>[40]</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>in literature regarding V2V communication,</cell><cell>in number, whereas the related</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>identifying challenges, characteristics, future</cell><cell>practices are not presented.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>research trends, and providing a general</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>overview of VANET.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>S. Zeadally et al.</cell><cell>2020</cell><cell>Telecommunication Systems</cell><cell>Secondary</cell><cell>Explores current trends and recent research</cell><cell>Lacks description regarding security</cell></row><row><cell>[13]</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>developments in V2V communication. They</cell><cell>issues and approaches for V2V</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>discussed wireless technologies supporting</cell><cell>communication.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>V2V, architectural problems, and the latest</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>security approaches for V2V communication</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Abdullahi</cell><cell>2021</cell><cell>IEEE Access</cell><cell>Primary</cell><cell>Describes potential mitigation measures by</cell><cell>Focuses merely on mitigation</cell></row><row><cell>Chowdhury et al.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>manufacturers and the government. The study</cell><cell>procedures.</cell></row><row><cell>[41]</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>explores how a self-driving vehicle can</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>maintain reliable performance despite</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>continual cyber attacks.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Michael Stepzinski</cell><cell>2020</cell><cell>11th IEEE Annual Ubiquitous</cell><cell>Secondary</cell><cell>Outline vehicular networks and Dedicated</cell><cell>Provides general overview about DSRC,</cell></row><row><cell>and Shamik</cell><cell></cell><cell>Computing, Electronics &amp; Mobile</cell><cell></cell><cell>Short Range Communication (DSRC),</cell><cell>and identified threats that are affecting</cell></row><row><cell>Sengupta [42]</cell><cell></cell><cell>Communication Conference</cell><cell></cell><cell>examining threats and cybersecurity-related</cell><cell>DSRC and their related solutions.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(UEMCON)</cell><cell></cell><cell>potential solutions that DSRC must deal with.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Gayathri M et al.</cell><cell>2021</cell><cell>J Crit Rev</cell><cell>Primary</cell><cell>Focuses on VANET security mechanisms,</cell><cell>The identified challenges are not</cell></row><row><cell>[14]</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>architecture, different types of attacks, and</cell><cell>specific for V2V communications,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>challenges faced during communication. Based</cell><cell>secondly, the related practices for these</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>on a survey, their findings provide a detailed</cell><cell>challenges are not identified.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>explanation of different security challenges and</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>cyber attacks.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Priyankkumar</cell><cell>2022</cell><cell>arXiv preprint arXiv:2212.08754</cell><cell>Secondary</cell><cell>Describes the security of smart automobiles,</cell><cell>The attacks and solutions are not</cell></row><row><cell>Sharma et al. [43]</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>including attacks and solutions.</cell><cell>suffient in number as compared to the</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>latest cybersecurity challenges.</cell></row><row><cell>Mohamed El</cell><cell>2020</cell><cell>The Open Transportation Journal</cell><cell>Secondary</cell><cell>Explores existing models and directions of V2V</cell><cell>Mostly focus on existing models</cell></row><row><cell>Zorkany et al.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>research and the benefits and difficulties of</cell><cell>regarding V2V technology.</cell></row><row><cell>[44]</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>applying V2V.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Hussein Ali Ameen</cell><cell>2020</cell><cell>Indonesian Journal of Electrical</cell><cell>Secondary</cell><cell>Focuses on the examination of key elements in</cell><cell>Mainly describes the general overview</cell></row><row><cell>et al. [45]</cell><cell></cell><cell>Engineering and Computer Science</cell><cell></cell><cell>ITS and provided an overview of the key V2V</cell><cell>of current advancements for V2V based</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>benefits of driver safety by primarily</cell><cell>systems</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>concentrating on the most current</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>advancements of these systems.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Ahmed Shoeb Al</cell><cell>2016</cell><cell>international conference on advances</cell><cell>Secondary</cell><cell>Identifies many security obstacles for VANET</cell><cell>Generaly identifies the security issues</cell></row><row><cell>Hasan et al. [46]</cell><cell></cell><cell>in computing, communications and</cell><cell></cell><cell>and discussed critical barriers to overcoming</cell><cell>and critical barriers for VANET.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>informatics (ICACCI). IEEE.</cell><cell></cell><cell>these problems. The defense strategies were</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>then divided into broad groups and critically</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>examined in light of several performance</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>metrics.</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_yHMBQwt"><s xml:id="_VnqAjgp">PICO criteria.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>PICO</cell><cell>Results</cell></row><row><cell>Populations</cell><cell>Cybersecurity, Automotive cybersecurity, V2V communication</cell></row><row><cell>Intervention</cell><cell>Cybersecurity challenges/issues/risks and solutions/practices</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>in Vehicle-to-Vehicle communication</cell></row><row><cell>Experimental</cell><cell>Multivocal Literature Review (MLR)</cell></row><row><cell>design</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Relevance</cell><cell>List of cybersecurity challenges and their related best practices</cell></row><row><cell>outcomes</cell><cell>in V2Vcommunication</cell></row><row><cell>Comparison</cell><cell>We don't perform any comparison in this study.</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_N5mFQb6"><s xml:id="_VrraKHh">Keywords synonyms.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Keyword</cell><cell>Synonyms</cell></row><row><cell>"Cybersecurity challenges"</cell><cell>" Cybersecurity challenges" OR</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>"Cybersecurity risks" OR</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>" Cybersecurity issues" OR</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Practices OR</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Solutions OR</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Guidelines)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_djUDZyb"><s xml:id="_zXmaFsa">MLR search results in the academic literature.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Search string</cell><cell>Digital</cell><cell>Total</cell><cell>Initial</cell><cell>Final</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>libraries</cell><cell>results</cell><cell>selection</cell><cell>selection</cell></row><row><cell>("Cybersecurity in V2V</cell><cell>Science Direct</cell><cell>880</cell><cell>82</cell><cell>21</cell></row><row><cell>communication" OR</cell><cell>Springer Link</cell><cell>280</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>05</cell></row><row><cell>"V2V communication"</cell><cell>ACM</cell><cell>245</cell><cell>61</cell><cell>24</cell></row><row><cell>OR "Information security</cell><cell>IEEE Xplore</cell><cell>534</cell><cell>102</cell><cell>17</cell></row><row><cell>in V2V communication")</cell><cell>Google</cell><cell>127</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>11</cell></row><row><cell>AND ("Cybersecurity</cell><cell>Scholar</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>risks" OR "Cybersecurity</cell><cell>(Search</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>challenges" OR</cell><cell>engine)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>"Cybersecurity issues").</cell><cell>Google</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>23</cell><cell>17</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(Search</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>engine)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Snowballing</cell><cell>78</cell><cell>29</cell><cell>06</cell></row><row><cell>Total</cell><cell></cell><cell>2169</cell><cell>350</cell><cell>101</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_YP3ZJVK"><s xml:id="_kGkG248">MLR review timetable.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Task</cell><cell>Date</cell></row><row><cell>Start of the protocol</cell><cell>05-February-2022</cell></row><row><cell>Completion of search</cell><cell>12/April/2022</cell></row><row><cell>Submission of the protocol for review</cell><cell>12-August-2022</cell></row><row><cell>Completion of the protocol</cell><cell>30/November/2022</cell></row><row><cell>Completion of primary study selection</cell><cell>5/January/2023</cell></row><row><cell>Completion of data extraction</cell><cell>14/March/2023</cell></row><row><cell>Completion of data synthesis</cell><cell>10/August/2023</cell></row><row><cell>Completion of review report</cell><cell>15/December/2023</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 6</head><label>6</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_WpVstFt"><s xml:id="_qe7Pn2x">Quality evaluation criteria for the formal literature.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>No</cell><cell>Quality assessment criteria</cell><cell>Answer</cell></row><row><cell>QA-</cell><cell>Does the chosen research paper address the research issue?</cell><cell>Yes/no/</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell>partially</cell></row><row><cell>QA-</cell><cell>Does the study have defined research goals?</cell><cell>Yes/no/</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell></cell><cell>partially</cell></row><row><cell>QA-</cell><cell>Does the study specifically present the proposed research</cell><cell>Yes/no/</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>method?</cell><cell>partially</cell></row><row><cell>QA-</cell><cell>Are the study results reported?</cell><cell>Yes/no/</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell></cell><cell>partially</cell></row><row><cell>QA-</cell><cell>Does the research discuss the real-world implications of the</cell><cell>Yes/no/</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell>research?</cell><cell>partially</cell></row><row><cell>QA-</cell><cell>Is it clear how the challenges in cybersecurity V2V</cell><cell>Yes/no/</cell></row><row><cell>6</cell><cell>communication at the industry level were identified,</cell><cell>partially</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>measured, or evaluated? (i.e., whether the mentioned</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>challenges in the paper are based on a sound methodology</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>or not)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>QA-</cell><cell>Is the paper published in the conference proceeding?</cell><cell>Yes/no/</cell></row><row><cell>7</cell><cell></cell><cell>partially</cell></row><row><cell>QA-</cell><cell>Is the paper published in a journal?</cell><cell>Yes/no/</cell></row><row><cell>8</cell><cell></cell><cell>partially</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table 7</head><label>7</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_nXwxARM"><s xml:id="_peyWYjZ">Quality assessment criteria for the grey literature.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>No</cell><cell>Criteria</cell><cell>Answer</cell></row><row><cell>GL-1</cell><cell>Has organization published the study/report?</cell><cell>Yes/no/partially</cell></row><row><cell>GL-2</cell><cell>Does the study have a clear objective?</cell><cell>Yes/no/partially</cell></row><row><cell>GL-3</cell><cell>Does the study use a clear methodology?</cell><cell>Yes/no/partially</cell></row><row><cell>GL-4</cell><cell>Does the study have a unique contribution?</cell><cell>Yes/no/partially</cell></row><row><cell>GL-5</cell><cell>Are the cybersecurity challenges presented clearly?</cell><cell>Yes/no/partially</cell></row></table><note xml:id="_9RYcc45"><p><s xml:id="_mvdcGbd">Information and Software Technology 179 (2025) 107639</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>Table 9</head><label>9</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_bU2BWJN"><s xml:id="_KnndwkS">List of critical cybersecurity challenges.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Table 12</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Practices for addressing bogus warning messages.</cell></row><row><cell>S.No</cell><cell>Critical cybersecurity challenges</cell><cell cols="2">Frequency of occurrences in both</cell><cell cols="2">CCC3: Bogus warning messages</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(CCCs)</cell><cell>formal and informal literature</cell><cell></cell><cell>S.No</cell><cell>Practices</cell><cell>Freq</cell></row><row><cell>CCC1 CCC2 CCC3 CCC4 CCC5 CCC6 CCC7 CCC8 CCC9 CCC10</cell><cell>Denial of service attacks Spoofing attacks Bogus warning messages Sybil and the man in the middle attacks Spamming and replay attacks Real-time adversaries Black hole, Grey hole, and Worm hole(BGW) attacks Eavesdropping attacks Location falsification Authentication and authorization issues</cell><cell>56 50 39 37 35 34 26 25 23 21</cell><cell></cell><cell>P#3.1 P#3.2 P#3.3 P#3.4 P#3.5</cell><cell>Adopt one or more of the available protocols, including Message Authentication Acceleration (MAAC) protocol, Distance Vector Routing protocol and Loss Differentiation Rate Adaptation (LDRA) protocol. Implement Vehicular Public Key Infrastructure (V-PKI) and Security Credential Management System (SCMS). For message authentication, employ the RSU-Aided Message Authentication Scheme (RAISE) and digital signatures for software and sensors. Utilize 'whitelisting' trusted data sources. message, registering vehicles with the Group Registration Manager requires to contact a trusted third party each time to verify each Adopt one or more of the available strategies, such as vehicles</cell><cell>19 7 6 5 3</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(GRM) to allow them to sign messages on the group's behalf,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>assigning IPs to vehicles while dropping duplicate IPs during</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Table 10 Practices for addressing denial of service attacks.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>message transfer, implement encrypted and strong passwords for message communication and employ an event-based reputation model.</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">CCC1: Denial of service attacks</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>S.No</cell><cell>Practices</cell><cell></cell><cell>Freq</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#1.1</cell><cell cols="2">Adopt one or more of the available cryptographic techniques,</cell><cell>17</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">including Message Authentication Code (MAC), symmetric</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">encryption, asymmetric encryption, attribute-based encryption,</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>and digital signatures.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#1.2</cell><cell cols="2">Implement an Intrusion Detection System (IDS) utilizing the Naive</cell><cell>10</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Bayes algorithm, Security Automotive Risk Analysis Method</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(SARA) and a contingency plan.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#1.3</cell><cell cols="2">Implement one or more of the available algorithms, including a</cell><cell>10</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">hybrid machine learning model for intrusion detection, Request</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Response Detection Algorithm (RRDA), Secure and Efficient Ad-</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">hoc Distance Vector (SEAD) and Attacked Packet Detection</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Algorithm (APDA).</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#1.4</cell><cell cols="2">Follow Redundancy Elimination Mechanism and deploying an</cell><cell>9</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Intrusion Detection System (IDS) using car hacking datasets.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#1.5</cell><cell cols="2">Employsignature-based detection, anomaly-based detection and</cell><cell>8</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>software testing.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Table 11</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Practices for addressing spoofing attacks.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">CCC2: Spoofing attacks</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>S.No</cell><cell>Practices</cell><cell></cell><cell>Freq</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#2.1</cell><cell cols="2">Implement various techniques, including Cryptographic</cell><cell>14</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">certificates via Authenticated Routing for Ad-hoc network (ARAN),</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Elliptic Curve Digital Signature Algorithm (ECDSA), Security</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Engineering Cluster Analysis (SECA), Distance Bounding Protocols</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">based on cryptographic techniques, and Probabilistic cross-layer</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Intrusion Detection System (IDS) based on machine learning</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>techniques, etc.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#2.2</cell><cell cols="2">Attach multiple digital signatures to a message.</cell><cell>7</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#2.3</cell><cell cols="2">Employ digital signatures without certificates and incorporate</cell><cell>7</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">signatures with a positioning system to accept only authentic</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>location data.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#2.4</cell><cell cols="2">Establish an Intrusion Detection System (IDS) model to counter</cell><cell>4</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">spoofing attacks in connected vehicles.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#2.5</cell><cell cols="2">Utilize a blocking antenna to safeguard against interference and</cell><cell>2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">jamming, thereby reducing the impact of spoofing signals.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#2.6</cell><cell cols="2">Implement differential monitoring on the Global Navigation</cell><cell>2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Satellite System (GNSS) to detect unusual changes in position and</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Direction-Of-Arrival (DOA) measurements.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#2.7</cell><cell cols="2">Develop a system that can provide warning signals to drivers before</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">a collision occurs by incorporating an Early Collision Warning</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Algorithm (ECWA) and Global Positioning System (GPS).</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>Table 13</head><label>13</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_UXTWsaj"><s xml:id="_X4CSuM7">Practices for addressing Sybil and man-in-the-middle attacks.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">CCC4: Sybil and man-in-the-middle attacks</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>S.No</cell><cell>Practices</cell><cell>Freq</cell></row><row><cell>P#4.1</cell><cell>Employ trusted certificates, public key cryptography, a central</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Validation Authority (VA), and encryption techniques utilizing</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>public keys.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#4.2</cell><cell>Incorporate cybersecurity protections at various vehicle layers,</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>such as the electronic control unit level and the in-vehicle network</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>level, to create multiple obstacles for cyber attackers and mitigate</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>the impact of a cyber breach. Include a non-cryptographic</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>checksum for each message, along with position verification and a</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Tamper Resistant Model (TRM).</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#4.3</cell><cell>Adopt various schemes, including the received signal strength</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(RSS)-based position verification scheme, acceptance range</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>thresholds for speed deviation, position verification through signal</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>strength analysis, radio resource testing, and Robust Sybil Attack</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Detection (RSAD).</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#4.4</cell><cell>Implement a Sybil attack detection scheme utilizing Advanced</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Driving Assistant System (ADAS) sensors installed on modern</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>passenger vehicles. Additionally, employ a cross-layer scheme</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>based on hash key and public key cryptography.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#4.5</cell><cell>Adopt a trust-based system, such as ConTrust, to establish a</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>reputation-based system safeguarding vehicles against potential</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Sybil attacks. This includes managing multiple packets with</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>identical messages, detecting malicious vehicles through a trust-</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>based model, and incorporating a security scheme for detecting and</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>localizing Sybil nodes in VANETs.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#4.6</cell><cell>Validate entities through signatures, digital certificates, sequence</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>numbers, timestamps, and temporary certificates.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#4.7</cell><cell>Implement distance bounding protocols based on cryptographic</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>techniques, Secret Key Cryptography (SKC), the Diffie-Hellman</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>algorithm, and k-anonymity.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#4.8</cell><cell>Update regularly the firmware messaging software</cell><cell>2</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>Table 14</head><label>14</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_4Hm6Jqh"><s xml:id="_jMfqVtE">Practices for addressing spamming and replay attacks.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">CCC5: Spamming and replay attacks</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>S.No</cell><cell>Practices</cell><cell>Freq</cell></row><row><cell>P#5.1</cell><cell>Implement one or more of the available encryption techniques</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>using public keys, including symmetric encryption, asymmetric</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>encryption and attribute-based encryption.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#5.2</cell><cell>Use frequency hopping technique and zero-knowledge technique.</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>P#5.3</cell><cell>Follow time stamping technique for sensitive packets.</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>P#5.4</cell><cell>Adopt Message Authentication Code (MAC) and Authenticated</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Routing for Ad-hoc network (ARAN).</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head>Table 15</head><label>15</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_q2dJKJa"><s xml:id="_QyAsmFz">Practices for addressing real time adversaries.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">CCC6: Real time adversaries</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>S.No</cell><cell>Practices</cell><cell>Freq</cell></row><row><cell>P#6.1</cell><cell>Use one or more of the available protocols, including Distributed</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>and Low-Overhead Protocol for Traffic Congestion (DISTRAC),</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Inter-Cluster Multichannel Communications Protocol, Verification</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>of Packet Delay using Timing Attack Prevention Protocol and</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Secure Vehicular Social Network Incentive Protocol.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#6.2</cell><cell>Apply one or more of the available mechanisms such as time</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>stamping mechanism, multi-hop vehicle-to-vehicle (V2V)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>communications networking with relay nodes and timers and a</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>timer-triggered forwarding technique.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#6.3</cell><cell>Adopt the Cooperative Intersection Prevention Systems Initiative</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(CICAS) along with a lightweight authentication scheme.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#6.4</cell><cell>Implement real-time intrusion detection systems and an Efficient</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Certificate Management Scheme (ECVM).</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#6.5</cell><cell>For collision avoidance in vehicular ad hoc network (VANET),</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>follow the Vector Field Histogram (VFH) method, implement a</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>collision avoidance system warning, employ Collision Avoidance</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>System in the vehicle (VCAS), integrate a Path Tracking Module</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(PTM) and utilize cooperative collision avoidance.</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>Table 16</head><label>16</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_4tMEAjK"><s xml:id="_SeUd8g8">Practices for addressing black hole, grey hole, and worm hole(BGW) attacks.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">CCC7: Black hole, grey hole, and worm hole (BGW) attacks</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>S.No</cell><cell>Practices</cell><cell>Freq</cell></row><row><cell>P#7.1</cell><cell>Employ cryptographic techniques such as digital signatures,</cell><cell>12</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>symmetric encryption, asymmetric encryption, and attribute-based</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>encryption for securing information.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#7.2</cell><cell>Adopt various techniques, including Identity-Based Cryptography</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(IBC) with bilinear pairing, Roadside Units (RSU)-assisted packet</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>forwarding with bilinear pairing, and an Intelligent Intrusion</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Detection System (IIDS) for vehicular adhoc networks (VANETs).</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>The IIDS employs a Proportional Overlapping Scores (POS)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>method, a reputation score-based system, and a watchdog system.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#7.3</cell><cell>Employ an Intrusion Detection Scheme (IDS) with Support Vector</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Machine (SVM) andImplement a secure routing process.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#7.4</cell><cell>Utilize Message Authentication Code (MAC) and one-way hash</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>functions for data protection.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#7.5</cell><cell>Implement the Social-based Privacy-preserving Packet Forwarding</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Protocol (SPRING) and the Greedy Geographic Routing Protocol</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(GGRP).</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#7.6</cell><cell>Regularly update the vehicle's software and firmware over its</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>lifespan in response to identified vulnerabilities.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Table 17</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Practices for addressing eavesdropping attacks.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">CCC8: Eavesdropping attacks</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>S.No</cell><cell>Practices</cell><cell>Freq</cell></row><row><cell>P#8.1</cell><cell>Employ cryptographic techniques, including encrypting the</cell><cell>13</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>communication channel and messages, symmetric encryption,</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>asymmetric encryption, and attribute-based encryption.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#8.2</cell><cell>Regularly update the master key information.</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>P#8.3</cell><cell>Use dynamic privacy-preserving key management method.</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>P#8.4</cell><cell>Adopt a pre-authentication scheme, leveraging the one-way hash</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>chain and a group re-keying method.</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12"><head>Table 19</head><label>19</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_mSmU5aq"><s xml:id="_xSu9p2a">Practices for addressing authentication and authorization issues.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">CCC10: Authentication and authentication issues</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>S.No</cell><cell>Practices</cell><cell>Freq</cell></row><row><cell>P#10.1</cell><cell>Adopt one or more of the available techniques such as Elliptic</cell><cell>23</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Curve (EC) Digital Signature Algorithms (ECDSA), Security</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Credential Management System (SCMS), geographic location-</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>based authentication, batch verification, authentication using</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>RSU signature verification, biometric and Elliptic Curve</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Cryptography (ECC)-based authentication, multi-factor</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>authentication, and certificateless public key signature scheme..</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#10.2</cell><cell>For authentication, use one or more of the available approaches</cell><cell>17</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>such as the public key approach, symmetric and hybrid approach,</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>ID-based cryptography, attribute-based encryption, and group</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>signature-based security framework, etc.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#10.3</cell><cell>For authentication between roadside units (RSU) and vehicles,</cell><cell>7</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>use ID-based signatures, ID-based online/offline signatures,</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>symmetric keys for pairwise communication, public keys for</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>groupwise communication, identity-based batch verification,</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Efficient Privacy-Preserving Dual Authentication and Key</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Agreement Scheme.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#10.4</cell><cell>For authentication and authorization issues, follow efficient</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>cooperative authentication techniques such as hash function-</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>based authentication schemes, time-efficient and secure</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Vehicular (TSVC) method with privacy preservation, ID-based</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>online/offline authentication (IBOOS) technique, distributed</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>aggregate privacy-preserving authentication (DAPPA), shared</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>key encryptions, and holistic protocols, etc.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#10.5</cell><cell>Follow Bilinear pairing; group signatures; threshold based</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>authentication</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#10.6</cell><cell>Implement Authentication Authority (AA) credentials issued by</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>the vehicle manufacturer in collaboration with the transportation</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>authority.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#10.7</cell><cell>Adopt Binary hash tree-based Certificate Access Management</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(BCAM) system</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P#10.8</cell><cell>Employ a secret key such as the Vehicle Authentication Code</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(VAC) for the purpose of vehicle and Certification Authority (CA)</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13"><head>Table 20</head><label>20</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_ebDuyJj"><s xml:id="_HfgBbAk">Analysis of cybersecurity challenges based on study strategies.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Cybersecurity challenges</cell><cell>Study strategies</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_14"><head>Table 21</head><label>21</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_pFATxtd"><s xml:id="_gsGUH2P">Analysis of cybersecurity challenges based on publication periods.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Cybersecurity challenges</cell><cell cols="4">Occurrence in MLR (N = 101)</cell><cell cols="2">Chi-square test</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">(Linear-by-Linear</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Association) α = 0.05</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Period</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>X 2</cell><cell>df</cell><cell>P</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">2009-2015</cell><cell cols="2">2016-2021</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">(N = 21)</cell><cell cols="2">(N = 80)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Freq</cell><cell>%</cell><cell>Freq</cell><cell>%</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CC 1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>4.096</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>.043</cell></row><row><cell>CC 2</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>31</cell><cell>2.365</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>.124</cell></row><row><cell>CC 3</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>33</cell><cell>32</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>0.309</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>.578</cell></row><row><cell>CC 4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>2.885</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>.089</cell></row><row><cell>CC 5</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>33</cell><cell>49</cell><cell>61</cell><cell>5.196</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>.023</cell></row><row><cell>CC 6</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>26</cell><cell>1.301</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>.254</cell></row><row><cell>CC 7</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0.004</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>.948</cell></row><row><cell>CC 8</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>4.941</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>.026</cell></row><row><cell>CC 9</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>29</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>0.502</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>.479</cell></row><row><cell>CC 10</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>2.113</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>.146</cell></row><row><cell>CC 11</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>48</cell><cell>23</cell><cell>29</cell><cell>2.666</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>.103</cell></row><row><cell>CC 12</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>1.234</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>.267</cell></row><row><cell>CC 13</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>1.955</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>.162</cell></row><row><cell>CC 14</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0.557</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>.458</cell></row><row><cell>CC 15</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>33</cell><cell>41</cell><cell>7.320</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>.007</cell></row><row><cell>CC 16</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>44</cell><cell>55</cell><cell>6.414</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>.011</cell></row><row><cell>CC 17</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>34</cell><cell>42</cell><cell>5.648</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>.017</cell></row><row><cell>CC 18</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>2.885</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>.089</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head xml:id="_k7kebpu">Acknowledgment</head><p xml:id="_xxxM9vG"><s xml:id="_77BrKZa">We are grateful to the fellows of <rs type="institution">Software Engineering Research Group (SERG-UOM) at University of Malakand</rs> and reviewers of the WSE-2022 for their valueable suggestions in validation process of the MLR protocol.</s></p></div>
			</div>
			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_N33PJtC">Data availability</head><p xml:id="_xRwKkB7"><s xml:id="_ysktw3t">Data will be made available on request.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_BDnjttS">Supplementary materials</head><p xml:id="_RVm2vKR"><s xml:id="_E9p5j7p">Supplementary material associated with this article can be found, in the online version, at doi:10.1016/j.infsof.2024.107639.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_2eehyyR">An overview of vehicular communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Arena</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3390/fi11020027</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_x8MaauS">Future Internet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">27</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">F. Arena, G. Pau, An overview of vehicular communications, Future Internet 11 (2) (2019) 27.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_RW79yHf">Latency of cellular-based V2X: perspectives on TTI-proportional latency and TTI-independent latency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/access.2017.2731777</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_nRgMbhz">IEEe Access</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15800" to="15809" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">K. Lee, et al., Latency of cellular-based V2X: perspectives on TTI-proportional latency and TTI-independent latency, IEEe Access. 5 (2017) 15800-15809.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_vaVxhwu">The impact of various communication methods: how vehicle-to-vehicle and vehicle-to-infrastructure messages affect the performance of driving smart vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Alsaleh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2139/ssrn.4339865</idno>
		<idno>SSRN 4339865</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Alsaleh, A., The impact of various communication methods: how vehicle-to-vehicle and vehicle-to-infrastructure messages affect the performance of driving smart vehicles (2023). Available at SSRN 4339865.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Z8WpFch">Review of energy storage systems for electric vehicle applications: issues and challenges</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hannan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_HbZZHzB">Renew. Sustain. Energy Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="771" to="789" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">M. Hannan, et al., Review of energy storage systems for electric vehicle applications: issues and challenges, Renew. Sustain. Energy Rev. 69 (2017) 771-789.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_kgA7PVa">Vehicular ad hoc networks (VANETs): challenges and perspectives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yousefi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Mousavi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fathy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/itst.2006.289012</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_7ptU7V8">2006 6th International Conference on ITS Telecommunications</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">S. Yousefi, M.S. Mousavi, M. Fathy, Vehicular ad hoc networks (VANETs): challenges and perspectives, in: 2006 6th International Conference on ITS Telecommunications, IEEE, 2006.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_FPFVbWr">Vehicle-to-vehicle safety messaging in DSRC</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_FcecESU">Proceedings of the 1st ACM International Workshop on Vehicular Ad Hoc Networks</title>
		<meeting>the 1st ACM International Workshop on Vehicular Ad Hoc Networks</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Q. Xu, et al., Vehicle-to-vehicle safety messaging in DSRC, in: Proceedings of the 1st ACM International Workshop on Vehicular Ad Hoc Networks, 2004.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Pvq3pDd">Multiagent/multiobjective interaction game system for service provisioning in vehicular cloud</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Aloqaily</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kantarci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Mouftah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_gTGbW7M">IEEe Access</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3153" to="3168" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">M. Aloqaily, B. Kantarci, H.T. Mouftah, Multiagent/multiobjective interaction game system for service provisioning in vehicular cloud, IEEe Access. 4 (2016) 3153-3168.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_FGnEbgz">A survey on authentication schemes in VANETs for secured communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Manvi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tangade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Us5ktn8">Veh. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">S.S. Manvi, S. Tangade, A survey on authentication schemes in VANETs for secured communication, Veh. Commun. 9 (2017) 19-30.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_w6zMdHP">An intrusion detection system for connected vehicles in smart cities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Aloqaily</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_46r2VMe">Ad Hoc Netw</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101842</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">M. Aloqaily, et al., An intrusion detection system for connected vehicles in smart cities, Ad Hoc Netw. 90 (2019) 101842.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_mC5bgEa">Detection of known and unknown intrusive sensor behavior in critical applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Otoum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kantarci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Mouftah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_mwUqZuT">IEEe Sens. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="4" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">S. Otoum, B. Kantarci, H.T. Mouftah, Detection of known and unknown intrusive sensor behavior in critical applications, IEEe Sens. Lett. 1 (5) (2017) 1-4.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Fbsz4W7">Performance evaluation of safety applications over DSRC vehicular ad hoc networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_ftKETZv">Proceedings of the 1st ACM International Workshop on Vehicular Ad Hoc Networks</title>
		<meeting>the 1st ACM International Workshop on Vehicular Ad Hoc Networks</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">J. Yin, et al., Performance evaluation of safety applications over DSRC vehicular ad hoc networks, in: Proceedings of the 1st ACM International Workshop on Vehicular Ad Hoc Networks, 2004.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_AKdrQqE">Infotainment and road safety service support in vehicular networking: from a communication perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Shan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ymssp.2010.11.009</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_npmtqPM">Mech. Syst. Signal Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2020" to="2038" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">H.T. Cheng, H. Shan, W. Zhuang, Infotainment and road safety service support in vehicular networking: from a communication perspective, Mech. Syst. Signal Process. 25 (6) (2011) 2020-2038.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_H58x2yV">A tutorial survey on vehicle-to-vehicle communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zeadally</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Guerrero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Contreras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11235-019-00639-8</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_TZHmrAm">Telecommun. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="469" to="489" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">S. Zeadally, J. Guerrero, J. Contreras, A tutorial survey on vehicle-to-vehicle communications, Telecommun. Syst. 73 (3) (2020) 469-489.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ZPnNgwM">A deep survey on types of cyber attacks in VANET</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gayathri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Gomathy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3389/fcomp.2024.1384515</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_VPRNnfb">J. Crit. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">01</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1029" to="1039" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">M. Gayathri, C. Gomathy, A deep survey on types of cyber attacks in VANET, J. Crit. Rev. 8 (01) (2021) 1029-1039.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_2fSeaTg">Group-based authentication in V2V communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hasrouny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/dictap.2015.7113193</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_wfUxBGs">Fifth International Conference on Digital Information and Communication Technology and its Applications (DICTAP)</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">H. Hasrouny, et al., Group-based authentication in V2V communications, in: 2015 Fifth International Conference on Digital Information and Communication Technology and its Applications (DICTAP), IEEE, 2015.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_xYt43Pq">Vehicle-to-vehicle (V2V) power transfer: electrical and communication developments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Shafiqurrahman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Khadkikar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Rathore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/tte.2023.3345738</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_XptQ4FK">IEEE Trans. Transp. Electrif</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">A. Shafiqurrahman, V. Khadkikar, A.K. Rathore, Vehicle-to-vehicle (V2V) power transfer: electrical and communication developments, IEEE Trans. Transp. Electrif. (2023).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_G3hh7C2">Secure communication protocols for vehicle-to-vehicle communication in autonomous vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Vybornova</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_xEkMpa2">Distributed Learning and Broad Applications in Scientific Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="179" to="205" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">E. Vybornova, Secure communication protocols for vehicle-to-vehicle communication in autonomous vehicles, Distributed Learning and Broad Applications in Scientific Res. 10 (2024) 179-205.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_9mktjrr">How Do V2V and V2I messages affect the performance of driving smart vehicles?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Alsaleh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_R6XNxsU">Comput. Syst. Sci. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">A. Alsaleh, How Do V2V and V2I messages affect the performance of driving smart vehicles? Comput. Syst. Sci. Eng. 47 (2) (2023).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Stilinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Klaus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_PzQeQBt">Performance evaluation of cache-based V2V broadcasting in metropolitan areas</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Stilinski, D. and H. Klaus, Performance evaluation of cache-based V2V broadcasting in metropolitan areas. 2023.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Maalej</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Balti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2201.02893</idno>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_jKbsB3A">Integration of vehicular clouds and autonomous driving: survey and future perspectives</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Maalej, Y. and E. Balti, Integration of vehicular clouds and autonomous driving: survey and future perspectives. arXiv preprint arXiv:2201.02893, 2022.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Q9T7qfb">Guidelines for including grey literature and conducting multivocal literature reviews in software engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Garousi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Felderer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Mäntylä</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.infsof.2018.09.006</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_F6qACxW">Inf. Softw. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="121" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">V. Garousi, M. Felderer, M.V. Mäntylä, Guidelines for including grey literature and conducting multivocal literature reviews in software engineering, Inf. Softw. Technol. 106 (2019) 101-121.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_3ueFqC7">A maturity model for secure software design: a multivocal study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Al-Matouq</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_XuqB2vq">IEEe Access</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215758" to="215776" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">H. Al-Matouq, et al., A maturity model for secure software design: a multivocal study, IEEe Access. 8 (2020) 215758-215776.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_EauxPpf">User experience key performance indicators for industrial IoT systems: a multivocal literature review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Trendowicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.digbus.2023.100057</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_UgDJ9uS">Digital Business</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">100057</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">A. Trendowicz, et al., User experience key performance indicators for industrial IoT systems: a multivocal literature review, Digital Business (2023) 100057.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_h5rxmPN">Practices for managing machine learning products: a multivocal literature review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Leite</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Leite, L., et al., Practices for managing machine learning products: a multivocal literature review. 2023.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_64w27ks">Potential cyberattacks on automated vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Petit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Shladover</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/tits.2014.2342271</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_hGGv3sw">IEEE Trans. Intell. Transp. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="546" to="556" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">J. Petit, S.E. Shladover, Potential cyberattacks on automated vehicles, IEEE Trans. Intell. Transp. Syst. 16 (2) (2014) 546-556.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_nBQt3N6">Introduction to automotive cybersecurity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_5WxncyY">Automotive Cyber Security: Introduction, Challenges, and Standardization</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="13" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">S. Kim, et al., Introduction to automotive cybersecurity. Automotive Cyber Security: Introduction, Challenges, and Standardization, 2020, pp. 1-13.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_BHYKQHk">Security Analysis of Vehicular Ad Hoc Networks (VANET)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ghassan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Al-Salihy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sures</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_Z689Abh">2010 second International Conference on Network applications, Protocols and Services, National Advanced IPv6</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Malaysia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Center, Universiti Sains Malaysia Penang</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">S. Ghassan, W.A. Al-Salihy, R. Sures, Security Analysis of Vehicular Ad Hoc Networks (VANET). in 2010 second International Conference on Network applications, Protocols and Services, National Advanced IPv6 Center, Universiti Sains Malaysia Penang, Malaysia, 2010.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qgtSpkH">Secure V2V and V2I communication in intelligent transportation using cloudlets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_WTcUmnT">IEEe Trans. Serv. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">M. Gupta, et al., Secure V2V and V2I communication in intelligent transportation using cloudlets, IEEe Trans. Serv. Comput. (2020).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_c3mPcua">An identity-based secure VANET communication system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Naresh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Reddi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_P79W6KT">Security and Privacy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">349</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">V.S. Naresh, S. Reddi, An identity-based secure VANET communication system, Security and Privacy 7 (2) (2024) e349.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_wZug5pF">Dedicated short-range communications (DSRC) standards in the United States</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kenney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_vBSqYBr">Proc. IEEE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1162" to="1182" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">J.B. Kenney, Dedicated short-range communications (DSRC) standards in the United States, Proc. IEEE 99 (7) (2011) 1162-1182.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_wZwzQW4">Vehicle-to-vehicle communication technology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Demba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Möller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_44HGx5b">IEEE International Conference on Electro/Information Technology (EIT)</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">A. Demba, D.P. Möller, Vehicle-to-vehicle communication technology, in: 2018 IEEE International Conference on Electro/Information Technology (EIT), IEEE, 2018.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_BJkMARe">A comprehensive review on blockchains for internet of vehicles: challenges and directions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hildebrand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cosrev.2023.100547</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_eDTJut4">Comput. Sci. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">100547</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">B. Hildebrand, et al., A comprehensive review on blockchains for internet of vehicles: challenges and directions, Comput. Sci. Rev. 48 (2023) 100547.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_EMnbrHq">Vehicle-to-vehicle wireless communication protocols for enhancing highway traffic safety</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Biswas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Tatchikou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Dion</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/mcom.2006.1580935</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_gjdjZWa">IEEE Commun. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="74" to="82" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">S. Biswas, R. Tatchikou, F. Dion, Vehicle-to-vehicle wireless communication protocols for enhancing highway traffic safety, IEEE Commun. Mag. 44 (1) (2006) 74-82.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_GjcRDRp">Channel characterization for 700 MHz DSRC vehicular communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sevlian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1155/2010/840895</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_P78bffK">J. Electr. Comput. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">2010</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">R. Sevlian, et al., Channel characterization for 700 MHz DSRC vehicular communication, J. Electr. Comput. Eng. 2010 (2010).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_WsStYhS">On medium access and physical layer standards for cooperative intelligent transport systems in Europe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Strom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/jproc.2011.2136310</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Am5UqVf">Proc. IEEE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1183" to="1188" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">E.G. Strom, On medium access and physical layer standards for cooperative intelligent transport systems in Europe, Proc. IEEE 99 (7) (2011) 1183-1188.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Q2fsrrb">Interworking of DSRC and cellular network technologies for V2X communications: a survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Abboud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Omar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_taGV2Sk">IEEe Trans. Veh. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9457" to="9470" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">K. Abboud, H.A. Omar, W. Zhuang, Interworking of DSRC and cellular network technologies for V2X communications: a survey, IEEe Trans. Veh. Technol. 65 (12) (2016) 9457-9470.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_PNNk25v">Certificate policy for deployment and operation of european cooperative intelligent transport systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Union</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Union, E., Certificate policy for deployment and operation of european cooperative intelligent transport systems. 2017.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_R7EkEPw">Vehicular ad hoc networks (VANETS): status, results, and challenges</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zeadally</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11235-010-9400-5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_azMwTcJ">Telecommun. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="217" to="241" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">S. Zeadally, et al., Vehicular ad hoc networks (VANETS): status, results, and challenges, Telecommun. Syst. 50 (4) (2012) 217-241.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_2HQYdXn">A comparison of various vehicular ad hoc routing protocols based on communication environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Sharef</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_VhucKGk">Proceedings of the 7th International Conference on Ubiquitous Information Management and Communication</title>
		<meeting>the 7th International Conference on Ubiquitous Information Management and Communication</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">B.T. Sharef, et al., A comparison of various vehicular ad hoc routing protocols based on communication environments, in: Proceedings of the 7th International Conference on Ubiquitous Information Management and Communication, 2013.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_duwdzjJ">A study of V2V communication on VANET: characteristic, challenges and</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Yogha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">research trends</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">K.B. Yogha, A study of V2V communication on VANET: characteristic, challenges and, research trends (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_8qdPBDY">Attacks on self-driving cars and their countermeasures: a survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chowdhury</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_TYfZgfG">IEEe Access</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="207308" to="207342" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">A. Chowdhury, et al., Attacks on self-driving cars and their countermeasures: a survey, IEEe Access. 8 (2020) 207308-207342.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_FPyuv6f">Cybersecurity analysis in dedicated short-range communications in vehicular networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stepzinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sengupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/uemcon51285.2020.9298044</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_3VJW9BM">2020 11th IEEE Annual Ubiquitous Computing, Electronics &amp; Mobile Communication Conference (UEMCON)</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">M. Stepzinski, S. Sengupta, Cybersecurity analysis in dedicated short-range communications in vehicular networks, in: 2020 11th IEEE Annual Ubiquitous Computing, Electronics &amp; Mobile Communication Conference (UEMCON), IEEE, 2020.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sharma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Patel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Prasad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2212.08754</idno>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_t8cuydm">A systematic literature review on internet of vehicles security</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sharma, P., M. Patel, and A. Prasad, A systematic literature review on internet of vehicles security. arXiv preprint arXiv:2212.08754, 2022.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_hDuM9Fq">Vehicle To Vehicle &quot;V2V&quot; communication: scope, importance, challenges, research directions and future</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">El</forename><surname>Zorkany</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Yasser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Galal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_tyfFDks">Open Transp. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">M. El Zorkany, A. Yasser, A.I. Galal, Vehicle To Vehicle &quot;V2V&quot; communication: scope, importance, challenges, research directions and future, Open Transp. J. 14 (1) (2020).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_XaAbrTw">A review on vehicle to vehicle communication system applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ameen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.11591/ijeecs.v18.i1.pp188-198</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_MvHbRW6">Indones. J. Electr. Eng. Comput. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="188" to="198" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">H.A. Ameen, et al., A review on vehicle to vehicle communication system applications, Indones. J. Electr. Eng. Comput. Sci. 18 (1) (2020) 188-198.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_tWCaKxU">Security threats in vehicular ad hoc networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Al Hasan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hossain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Atiquzzaman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/icacci.2016.7732079</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_C2Yx3Wk">2016 International Conference on Advances in Computing, Communications and Informatics (ICACCI)</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">A.S. Al Hasan, M.S. Hossain, M. Atiquzzaman, Security threats in vehicular ad hoc networks, in: 2016 International Conference on Advances in Computing, Communications and Informatics (ICACCI), IEEE, 2016.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_q2pEv4n">Successful management of cloud-based global software development projects: a multivocal study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Akbar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/smr.2527</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_FKa4vSg">J. Softw.: Evol. Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2527</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">M.A. Akbar, et al., Successful management of cloud-based global software development projects: a multivocal study, J. Softw.: Evol. Process 36 (4) (2024) e2527.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_x8UqwB3">Using mapping studies in software engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Budgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<publisher>Ppig</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">D. Budgen, et al., Using mapping studies in software engineering. Ppig, 2008.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_5AKjAZj">Guidelines for performing systematic literature reviews in software engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Keele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1201/b19467-8</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
	<note>ver. 2.3 ebse technical report. ebse</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Keele, S., Guidelines for performing systematic literature reviews in software engineering. 2007, Technical report, ver. 2.3 ebse technical report. ebse.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_bX6eqhK">Barriers in the selection of offshore software development outsourcing vendors: an exploratory study using a systematic literature review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Niazi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ahmad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.infsof.2010.08.003</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_k62MS3A">Inf. Softw. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="693" to="706" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">S.U. Khan, M. Niazi, R. Ahmad, Barriers in the selection of offshore software development outsourcing vendors: an exploratory study using a systematic literature review, Inf. Softw. Technol. 53 (7) (2011) 693-706.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_vjQVAsj">Challenges of project management in global software development: a client-vendor analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Niazi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.infsof.2016.08.002</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_hYfaUe3">Inf. Softw. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="19" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">M. Niazi, et al., Challenges of project management in global software development: a client-vendor analysis, Inf. Softw. Technol. 80 (2016) 1-19.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_pr28Qcf">Guidelines for snowballing in systematic literature studies and a replication in software engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wohlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_N4WV6wA">Proceedings of the 18th International Conference on Evaluation and Assessment in Software Engineering</title>
		<meeting>the 18th International Conference on Evaluation and Assessment in Software Engineering</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">C. Wohlin, Guidelines for snowballing in systematic literature studies and a replication in software engineering, in: Proceedings of the 18th International Conference on Evaluation and Assessment in Software Engineering, 2014.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_RVYXHag">Architecting for sustainability of and in the cloud: a systematic literature review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ahmadisakha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Andrikopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_FCHNCSe">Inf. Softw. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">107459</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">S. Ahmadisakha, V. Andrikopoulos, Architecting for sustainability of and in the cloud: a systematic literature review, Inf. Softw. Technol. (2024) 107459.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_zKu2sMZ">The impact of human aspects on the interactions between software developers and end-users in software engineering: a systematic literature review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Gunatilake</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_8u95TxN">Inf. Softw. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">107489</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">H. Gunatilake, et al., The impact of human aspects on the interactions between software developers and end-users in software engineering: a systematic literature review, Inf. Softw. Technol. (2024) 107489.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_jdjBy9w">Inclusion of individuals with autism spectrum disorder in software engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Márquez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_DWnbBjk">Inf. Softw. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">107434</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">G. Márquez, et al., Inclusion of individuals with autism spectrum disorder in software engineering, Inf. Softw. Technol. (2024) 107434.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_bZHN4Gn">Source:&quot;Guidelines for performing systematic literature reviews in SE &quot;Kitchenham et al. guidelines for performing systematic literature reviews in software engineering source</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kitchenham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Charters</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_qPdUZ7v">Guidelines for performing Systematic Literature Reviews i</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="44" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kitchenham, B. and S. Charters, Source:&quot;Guidelines for performing systematic literature reviews in SE &quot;Kitchenham et al. guidelines for performing systematic literature reviews in software engineering source. Guidelines for performing Systematic Literature Reviews i, 2007: p. 1-44.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2109.07906</idno>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_xF2EQCh">Ethics of AI: a systematic literature review of principles and challenges</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Khan, A.A., et al., Ethics of AI: a systematic literature review of principles and challenges. arXiv preprint arXiv:2109.07906, 2021.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_cxYUJfB">How should software engineering secondary studies include grey material?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kitchenham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Madeyski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Budgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_HyYRn3S">IEEE Trans. Softw. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="872" to="882" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">B. Kitchenham, L. Madeyski, D. Budgen, How should software engineering secondary studies include grey material? IEEE Trans. Softw. Eng. 49 (2) (2022) 872-882.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_vDF3vC9">Software security patch management-a systematic literature review of challenges, approaches, tools and practices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Dissanayake</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_cxzP2PC">Inf. Softw. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">144</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">106771</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">N. Dissanayake, et al., Software security patch management-a systematic literature review of challenges, approaches, tools and practices, Inf. Softw. Technol. 144 (2022) 106771.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_SG7zJQg">Empirical studies of agile software development: a systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Dybå</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Dingsøyr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_gEGQHyQ">Inf. Softw. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9-10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="833" to="859" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">T. Dybå, T. Dingsøyr, Empirical studies of agile software development: a systematic review, Inf. Softw. Technol. 50 (9-10) (2008) 833-859.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_gzffkDv">A review on various security attacks in vehicular ad hoc networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hamdi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_CvYtX8D">Bull. Electr. Eng. Inform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2627" to="2635" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">M.M. Hamdi, et al., A review on various security attacks in vehicular ad hoc networks, Bull. Electr. Eng. Inform. 10 (5) (2021) 2627-2635.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_xUPqzM4">A review on cybersecurity of cloud computing for supporting connected vehicle applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Salek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_AEK99Az">IEEe Internet. Things. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8250" to="8268" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">M.S. Salek, et al., A review on cybersecurity of cloud computing for supporting connected vehicle applications, IEEe Internet. Things. J. 9 (11) (2022) 8250-8268.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_tTcmsR5">Security attacks and challenges of VANETs: a literature survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Quyoom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sarwar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_UASzUj2">J. Multim. Inf. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="54" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">A. Quyoom, A.A. Mir, A. Sarwar, Security attacks and challenges of VANETs: a literature survey, J. Multim. Inf. Syst. 7 (1) (2020) 45-54.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_HZM84ba">A survey of security services, attacks, and applications for vehicular ad hoc networks (vanets)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Sheikh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_dbWAyKN">Sensors</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3589</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">M.S. Sheikh, J. Liang, W. Wang, A survey of security services, attacks, and applications for vehicular ad hoc networks (vanets), Sensors 19 (16) (2019) 3589.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Xu8sYtu">Forming vehicular web of trust in VANET</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sumra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hasbullah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ahmad</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_gakBGPE">2011 Saudi International Electronics, Communications and Photonics Conference (SIECPC)</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">I.A. Sumra, H. Hasbullah, I. Ahmad, Forming vehicular web of trust in VANET, in: 2011 Saudi International Electronics, Communications and Photonics Conference (SIECPC), IEEE, 2011.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Parno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Perrig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_9Q4xRwy">Challenges in securing vehicular networks. Workshop on Hot Topics in Networks (HotNets-IV)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Maryland, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">B. Parno, A. Perrig, Challenges in securing vehicular networks. Workshop on Hot Topics in Networks (HotNets-IV), Maryland, USA, 2005.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_MSX3wn3">A survey on internet of vehicles: applications, security issues &amp; solutions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sharma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kaushik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_JZazfAr">Veh. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">100182</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">S. Sharma, B. Kaushik, A survey on internet of vehicles: applications, security issues &amp; solutions, Veh. Commun. 20 (2019) 100182.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_tHkBW5d">Blockchain-based security attack resilience schemes for autonomous vehicles in industry 4.0: a systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ZwvCb6y">Comput. Electr. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">106717</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">R. Gupta, et al., Blockchain-based security attack resilience schemes for autonomous vehicles in industry 4.0: a systematic review, Comput. Electr. Eng. 86 (2020) 106717.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_arCRzUM">Intercultural challenges in offshore software development outsourcing relationships: an exploratory study using a systematic literature review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Azeem</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_UWen9aD">IET Software</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="173" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">S.U. Khan, M.I. Azeem, Intercultural challenges in offshore software development outsourcing relationships: an exploratory study using a systematic literature review, IET Software 8 (4) (2014) 161-173.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_fVuWr3k">An Introduction to Medical Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford university press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">M. Bland, An Introduction to Medical Statistics, Oxford university press, 2015.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Stanley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_xPPRx4M">Experimental and Quasi-Experimental Designs for Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Ravenio books</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">D.T. Campbell, J.C. Stanley, Experimental and Quasi-Experimental Designs for Research, Ravenio books, 2015.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_mjbMtyv">Systematic mapping study on security approaches in secure software engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_xr3G9F9">IEEe Access</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19139" to="19160" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">R.A. Khan, et al., Systematic mapping study on security approaches in secure software engineering, IEEe Access. 9 (2021) 19139-19160.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_VKRpkQS">Factors influencing clients in the selection of offshore software outsourcing vendors: an exploratory study using a systematic literature review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Niazi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ahmad</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_GMa64JN">J. Syst. Softw</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="686" to="699" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">S.U. Khan, M. Niazi, R. Ahmad, Factors influencing clients in the selection of offshore software outsourcing vendors: an exploratory study using a systematic literature review, J. Syst. Softw. 84 (4) (2011) 686-699.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_FgjrcZH">Exploring software security approaches in software development lifecycle: a systematic mapping study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mohammed</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_RYnA5mY">Comput. Stand. Interfaces</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="115" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">N.M. Mohammed, et al., Exploring software security approaches in software development lifecycle: a systematic mapping study, Comput. Stand. Interfaces. 50 (2017) 107-115.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
