<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_uABywdj">Committed to Create Value for Researchers Survey of Attitudes toward Sharing Health Care Information in Telemedicine Ment Health Hum Resilience Int J Survey of Attitudes toward Sharing Health Care Information in Telemedicine</title>
				<funder ref="#_8YpVeG9">
					<orgName type="full">Toyota Foundation</orgName>
					<idno type="DOI" subtype="crossref">https://doi.org/10.13039/100009584</idno>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_NSqeyZy">
					<orgName type="full">unknown</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2024-03-01">March 01, 2024</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Kenji</forename><surname>Nakamura</surname></persName>
							<email>nac-k@gunma-u.ac.jp</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>1</label> Center for Mathematics and Data Science , Gunma University , Japan</note>
								<orgName type="department">Center for Mathematics and Data Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Gunma University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>2</label> Graduate School of Humanities and Social Sciences , Saitama University , Japan</note>
								<orgName type="department">Graduate School of Humanities and Social Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Saitama University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>3</label> Innovative Medical Research Center , Gunma University Hospital , Japan</note>
								<orgName type="department">Innovative Medical Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Gunma University Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Gunma University , 371-0858 , Maebashi city , Gunma , Japan ,</note>
								<orgName type="institution">Gunma University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>371-0858</postCode>
									<settlement>Maebashi city Gunma</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_v8h7xKQ">Committed to Create Value for Researchers Survey of Attitudes toward Sharing Health Care Information in Telemedicine Ment Health Hum Resilience Int J Survey of Attitudes toward Sharing Health Care Information in Telemedicine</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<idno type="ISSN">2578-5095</idno>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2024-03-01">March 01, 2024</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">03AF9C420F9213781751C6637E4A8AC8</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.23880/mhrij-16000240</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received Date: January 01, 2024</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T07:44+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term xml:id="_BZKHByY">Telemedicine</term>
					<term xml:id="_89XveRu">Digital Healthcare</term>
					<term xml:id="_5dW2qtV">Blockchain, Metaverse</term>
					<term xml:id="_XscNjTE">PHR</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_qa8cdgT"><p xml:id="_Vr7xaMA"><s xml:id="_uvraucT">Japan considers preventive healthcare crucial for extending healthy life expectancy.</s><s xml:id="_2VBGRkA">Recent medical and care industry orients to extend healthy life expectancy by utilizing preventive healthcare.</s><s xml:id="_ftzyM7f">Some preventive healthcare, which is called "digital healthcare," is developed as wearable devices with AI.</s><s xml:id="_WNHsShZ">Especially, medical apps are gaining attention as insurance coverage applications among them.</s><s xml:id="_7EmaG8p">Various services are being developed for preventive healthcare care using digital healthcare.</s><s xml:id="_tcyF9Tj">These services enhance patients' and users' knowledge about not only their health but also medical care per se, raising expectations for smart medical care.</s><s xml:id="_MDxDPE8">However, healthcare professionals need to monitor patients individually, leading to a concentrated burden.</s><s xml:id="_AbjjCvt">While efforts are being made to reduce healthcare professionals' excessive exertion through digital healthcare, many patients fail to engage consistently in using the devices/applications, often due to resistance and reluctance to enter their health information into apps.</s><s xml:id="_hMNxhZy">Therefore, we have developed an app that allows the sharing of health information among multiple users, with sufficient explanation and consent obtained from the users.</s><s xml:id="_ncASQzV">We verify whether mutual data sharing can improve each other's health habits.</s><s xml:id="_MZfVCss">As a result, we confirmed that items such as diet and exercise habits improved by 1.4 times.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_aHvYyV9">Introduction</head><p xml:id="_QYJXebs"><s xml:id="_N4xyDAR">Japan is rapidly aging, with 30% of its population aged 65 and over <ref type="bibr">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr">2]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_tm4wcXF">Furthermore, the onset of COVID-19 in 2019 has increased the complexity of infection control, disinfection, and sterilization, complicating the daily tasks of healthcare workers <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_SUvSYjE">Although there is extensive research on digitalizing the monitoring and medical care of elderly individuals at home, widespread adoption has not been achieved.</s></p><p xml:id="_PZAzcrn"><s xml:id="_V7d7h7m">The low adoption rate for digital devices is due to the significant burden on healthcare workers.</s><s xml:id="_pgCxbzK">Monitoring technologies that utilize digital technology and applications are being deployed in various fields, including mechanisms for detecting and predicting viral diseases using Fitbit or Apple Watch <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_SZbNu7f">For example, Jiang et al. have been analyzing body temperature, heart rate, heart rate variability, blood oxygen saturation, respiratory rate, and blood pressure during COVID-19 to monitor patients and predict increases in blood pressure and heart rate.</s><s xml:id="_Dgyv6WJ">This monitoring system collects data centrally and is actively supported by medical professionals.</s><s xml:id="_WqDAvKN">Unlike on-site medical services, digital technology enables a single healthcare professional to monitor many patients.</s><s xml:id="_gMHWYk5">However, data and authority are concentrated in the hands of healthcare workers <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref> leading to a concentrated burden of monitoring in medical settings.</s></p><p xml:id="_Jf5AXU8"><s xml:id="_q2kpd8P">The central management of digital data, where service providers have strong authority and users have weak authority, is referred to WEB2.0 <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_sDGzqS3">WEB2.0 systems allow for two-way communication between data managers and users, with data managers holding privileged authority.</s><s xml:id="_NAQkc2A">In contrast, WEB3.0 represents a user-centric data management system characterized by blockchain-led technology <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_afsJTap">It eliminates the concentration of authority in data managers, enabling a user-oriented decentralized data management.</s><s xml:id="_xkQehyg">However, the functionality of monitoring may decrease if there are few users.</s><s xml:id="_Yr3bugp">If this is the case, it is significant to explore what improvements can be expected by introducing a centralized structure of WEB3.0 in the relationship between healthcare workers and patients, compared to traditional monitoring.</s><s xml:id="_evmadJh">The blockchain technology at the heart of Web 3.0 has seen remarkable development in recent years.</s><s xml:id="_PYz8aer">In the blockchain, there are data management functions called nodes, and multiple nodes complement each other's data and monitor each other.</s><s xml:id="_JBYV3Xj">For example, if part of the data is lost, the nodes can check each other's data and restore it.</s><s xml:id="_gT6k8pz">Users themselves can also take on the role of nodes, provide mechanical power for encryption, and receive rewards.</s><s xml:id="_x7gqRbH">Therefore, it is difficult for a specific administrator to unilaterally exclude users, allowing users to hold onto data as a resource while monitoring each other.</s><s xml:id="_RYtUYSn">In the past, this resistance to tampering has been applied to electronic medical records and healthcare systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_V8as42N">However, there are public and private types of blockchain.</s><s xml:id="_PRNvDJm">In the public type, all information is shared among all nodes.</s><s xml:id="_fyeFDCD">The private type, combined with authentication functions, can construct systems with high confidentiality.</s><s xml:id="_4tUM5at">Medical systems tend to use the private type to increase confidentiality.</s><s xml:id="_mX2QwBp">We have examined whether this mechanism is useful to monitor the medication and medical activities of the elderly.</s><s xml:id="_TUkN4jB">Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> shows conventional and Web3 monitoring.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_acKTdkz">Purpose</head><p xml:id="_Txaexd7"><s xml:id="_TJc2vTG">In the global healthcare system, it is natural for healthcare workers to monitor patients, yet this creates a structure where the burden is concentrated on healthcare workers.</s><s xml:id="_ZwuqZqA">However, blockchain allows for the sharing of information among users, enabling them to monitor each other's healthcare information.</s><s xml:id="_mGkddeu">This potential has been explored for monitoring the medication adherence and health management activities of the elderly.</s><s xml:id="_8hgeJEM">The goal is to reduce the burden on healthcare providers and to construct a sustainable Web3-based monitoring system.</s><s xml:id="_5CkWshM">This mutual monitoring of healthcare information among the elderly aims to reduce the workload on healthcare providers and build a culture that maintains a sustainable state of health.</s><s xml:id="_tHpeHP5">This culture and mechanism, referred to as mutual aid, explores a new patient-centered remote healthcare system.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_74jQ7eY">Methods</head><p xml:id="_8AhApb7"><s xml:id="_zBB9M8X">We have developed a private blockchain-based monitoring system that allows for the sharing of healthcare information through wearable devices.</s><s xml:id="_zz6PtKE">When elderly individuals perform morning calisthenics and report their activities to their wearable devices, this information is reflected on the wearable devices of other elderly individuals as well.</s><s xml:id="_K6dXYYW">To facilitate mutual monitoring, we installed an approval button on the wearable devices.</s><s xml:id="_jxDgtcu">This button, referred to as "good," was implemented to acknowledge and sustain each other's activities.</s><s xml:id="_RUrXFZ9">We introduced this system to closely-knit elderly communities to test whether healthcare information could be improved.</s><s xml:id="_KVd2CnD">Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> displays the interface of the application.</s><s xml:id="_26K4skw">The Tic Watch Pro 3 was used as the wearable device, and the app was developed on Wear OS.</s><s xml:id="_vQG7qHs">Data communication was conducted via Bluetooth, allowing for the sharing of data by switching between each other's apps.</s><s xml:id="_29uZmfH">The apps were alternated between server mode and transmission mode every minute to share data.</s><s xml:id="_jyUEJPk">Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> shows how wearable devices communicate data.</s><s xml:id="_rGQf9Z6">The red line is the line to communicate and the black line is the line to standby.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_QJZmwnt">Result</head><p xml:id="_XQhrnSs"><s xml:id="_XFF7CNp">We built a private blockchain-type monitoring system for wearable devices.</s><s xml:id="_y3sekdM">As a pilot test, we asked six elderly residents of a care house to wear wearable devices for one month.</s><s xml:id="_JEbjNRQ">The average age was 77.1 years, and all were women.</s><s xml:id="_FvHp6Wu">The survey was conducted from April 1 to July 31, 2023, and interviews were conducted with healthcare professionals.</s><s xml:id="_SP7pEGg">Explanations were given in person and written consent was obtained.</s></p><p xml:id="_nM4vfq6"><s xml:id="_b7ASUSr">Before the intervention, the average number of times per month was 8.2, whereas, after the intervention, the average number of times per month increased to 11.7.</s><s xml:id="_C3f2xVu">A Wilcoxon signed rank sum test was conducted because a normal distribution could not be assumed owing to the small number of participants.</s><s xml:id="_hybSCqq">The hypothesis that there was no significant difference in the average number of times before and after the intervention was rejected at p=0.02.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_SYyTS7m">Conclusion</head><p xml:id="_3Bwcc8K"><s xml:id="_sBZfdJS">Although this experiment was still in its pilot phase, it yielded unique information.</s><s xml:id="_ZkzfpwN">When briefed, four participants refused to partake upon learning that their data would be mutually monitored.</s><s xml:id="_gdV53a9">Their refusal stemmed from a reluctance to have their personal data viewed by others.</s><s xml:id="_6yX6qrv">Given the nature of blockchain technology, there is a potential for medical information to be stored while shared among individuals.</s><s xml:id="_FZRSxe2">Although measures can be made to prevent viewing by unauthorized parties, individual reactions to such measures may vary.</s><s xml:id="_4BdkDyT">Alissa has reported a discrepancy in patient knowledge concerning medical care utilizing digital technologies like telemedicine <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_ZbXuyKB">This discrepancy is possibly attributed to the highly confidential nature of Japanese health information, including highly personalized data such as banking and genomic information.</s><s xml:id="_fY9zbAJ">However, once the experiment began, facility staff reported an increase in communication through digital applications, facilitated by mutual aid via digital technology.</s><s xml:id="_47bGHPQ">Notably, conversations during lunchtime and after hours, attributed to this experiment, also increased.</s></p><p xml:id="_J5SGccW"><s xml:id="_KVGRgj2">As a result, the four individuals who initially refused to participate expressed a desire to join the experiment.</s><s xml:id="_P2kesMr">This indicates that the blockchain system has created opportunities for mutual aid and suggests the experiment's success.</s><s xml:id="_cCV5qDJ">This study was conducted over a short period with a small number of participants, necessitating further investigation.</s><s xml:id="_xEheqzT">Some limitations of this study must be addressed.</s><s xml:id="_cKQE942">Firstly, the participants were from a closely-knit group, not strangers to one another.</s><s xml:id="_CYjZ2Qf">This aspect requires careful verification in our study.</s><s xml:id="_dDKtyz4">While Decentralized Autonomous Organizations (DAOs) have been gaining popularity, operating on the principle that all users have equal authority in community decision-making online, their application in medical care, especially post-operative monitoring, remains challenging due to the significant authority healthcare professionals hold in medical care <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_WAbHDRk">Therefore, for the adoption of Web3 technologies in healthcare, medical professionals must retain the authority to oversee.</s><s xml:id="_ycgxXdE">While understanding this might mitigate concerns, it appears to be a time-consuming process.</s><s xml:id="_TZND9Sm">This challenge has also been reported by Hussien et al., highlighting the need for deep user understanding <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_cgAHKKr">However, there's an unmet expectation in Japan for patients to hold their healthcare data, enhancing preventive medicine and linking it to medical care.</s><s xml:id="_cwKZZ6Z">This blockchain system, allowing patients to possess their healthcare data, could be incredibly beneficial for prevention and telemedicine.</s></p><p xml:id="_GVNPX9s"><s xml:id="_Bd2tFrp">Future challenges would include exploring the utilization of virtual spaces like the Metaverse or DAOs for users with low intimacy.</s><s xml:id="_hnkkhR8">While users with high intimacy can capture each other's presence and build mutual aid relationships, introducing such systems to unknown users is challenging.</s><s xml:id="_qMf5zFD">Hence, the Metaverse, utilizing avatars and 3D objects, could compensate for the lack of intimacy.</s><s xml:id="_sQDM82E">Examples of Metaverse implementation in education exist <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_BAmWpWk">Interaction with avatars, representing oneself, could offer various benefits for the elderly, whose social activities are diminishing.</s><s xml:id="_QFrhWb5">This approach could enable users in Japan's declining population to hold their healthcare data and connect to high-quality remote medical care.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_eYWS6JN"><s xml:id="_rTXgm9x">Figure 1: Conventional and Web3 monitoring.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,118.58,305.71,374.84,181.57" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_V5vfVWU"><s xml:id="_AwHKESV">Figure 2: App screen of wearable device.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,64.01,89.42,200.11,182.31" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_n8AqMAY"><s xml:id="_U5nr6ev">Figure 3: How wearable devices communicate data.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,46.62,423.68,235.27,200.08" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_qm6CGP7"><s xml:id="_CRFwUEm">Nakamura K, et al.</s><s xml:id="_entaDac">Survey of Attitudes toward Sharing Health Care Information in Telemedicine.</s><s xml:id="_b8g9evX">Ment Health Hum Resilience Int J 2024, 8(1): 000240.</s><s xml:id="_mrvmPN3">Copyright© Nakamura K, et al.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head xml:id="_xKFXtr4">Acknowledgements</head><p xml:id="_dBYsguz"><s xml:id="_HYR8UgV">We sincerely thank team of <rs type="institution">Gunma Prefectural Government web3</rs> team and the participants for their cooperation in the experiment.</s><s xml:id="_jJxyj69">Part of this research was supported by <rs type="funder">Toyota Foundation</rs> <rs type="grantNumber">D22-ST-0019</rs> and <rs type="grantNumber">JSPS 22K18548</rs>.</s></p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_8YpVeG9">
					<idno type="grant-number">D22-ST-0019</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_NSqeyZy">
					<idno type="grant-number">JSPS 22K18548</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_4NucJmp">Survey of Attitudes toward Sharing Health Care Information in Telemedicine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Nakamura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.23880/mhrij-16000240</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_quM9qbf">Ment Health Hum Resilience Int J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">240</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nakamura K, et al. Survey of Attitudes toward Sharing Health Care Information in Telemedicine. Ment Health Hum Resilience Int J 2024, 8(1): 000240.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Copyright©</forename><surname>Nakamura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3886/icpsr31082</idno>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_zkKuM8p">Population Census</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Japan</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Statistics Bureau</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>References 1</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Copyright© Nakamura K, et al. References 1. (2010) Population Census. Japan: Statistics Bureau.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_KPnH2a7">The impact of COVID-19 on nursing workload and planning of nursing staff on the Intensive Care: A prospective descriptive multicenter study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hoogendoorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Brinkman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bosman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Haringman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Spijkstra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2021.104005</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_3P3bkej">Int J Nurs Stud</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">104005</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hoogendoorn ME, Brinkman S, Bosman RJ, Haringman J, Spijkstra JJ, et al. (2021) The impact of COVID-19 on nursing workload and planning of nursing staff on the Intensive Care: A prospective descriptive multicenter study. Int J Nurs Stud 121: 104005.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_SQcPHEh">Project and Prototype of Mobile Application for Monitoring the Global COVID-19 Epidemiological Situation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Sawik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Plonka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3390/ijerph19031416</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_aYYmsrc">Int J Environ Res Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1416</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sawik B, Plonka J (2022) Project and Prototype of Mobile Application for Monitoring the Global COVID-19 Epidemiological Situation. Int J Environ Res Public Health 19(3): 1416.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_w2t5f6k">Emerging Telemedicine Tools for Remote COVID-19 Diagnosis, Monitoring, and Management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lukas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1021/acsnano.0c08494</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_rCAGqZz">ACS Nano</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16180" to="16193" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lukas H, Xu C, Yu Y, Gao W (2020) Emerging Telemedicine Tools for Remote COVID-19 Diagnosis, Monitoring, and Management. ACS Nano 14(12): 16180-16193.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_q3hy4bw">What is web 2.0, Design Patterns and Business Models for the Next Generation of Software</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Reilly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.18574/nyu/9780814764077.003.0008</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="21" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Reilly TO (2007) What is web 2.0, Design Patterns and Business Models for the Next Generation of Software, pp: 1-21.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_YC6ZWbt">Bitcoin: A Peer-to-Peer Electronic Cash System</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nakamoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nakamoto S (2008) Bitcoin: A Peer-to-Peer Electronic Cash System.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_wwqQ3yX">A Novel Architecture for Tamper Proof Electronic Health Record Management System using Blockchain Wrapper</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rahman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Khalil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Pcm</forename><surname>Arachchige</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bouras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1145/3327960.3332392</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_6UzG4bf">Proceedings of the 2019 ACM International Symposium on Blockchain and Secure Critical Infrastructure (BSCI &apos;19)</title>
		<meeting>the 2019 ACM International Symposium on Blockchain and Secure Critical Infrastructure (BSCI &apos;19)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Association for Computing Machinery</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="105" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rahman MS, Khalil I, Arachchige PCM, Bouras A, Xun Y (2019) A Novel Architecture for Tamper Proof Electronic Health Record Management System using Blockchain Wrapper. In Proceedings of the 2019 ACM International Symposium on Blockchain and Secure Critical Infrastructure (BSCI &apos;19). Association for Computing Machinery pp: 97-105.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_KpurytX">Digital Disparities in Patient Adoption of Telemedicine: A Qualitative Analysis of the Patient Experience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Dickey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Wasko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4018/ijhisi.318043</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_mwJFnGW">International Journal of Healthcare Information Systems and Informatics (IJHISI)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Dickey AM, Wasko MM (2023) Digital Disparities in Patient Adoption of Telemedicine: A Qualitative Analysis of the Patient Experience. International Journal of Healthcare Information Systems and Informatics (IJHISI) 18(1): 21.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_6UxsEdc">Tablet in the Consultation Room and Physician Satisfaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kumi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Reychav</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Azuri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sabherwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4018/ijhisi.318445</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_j8GvY3K">International Journal of Healthcare Information Systems and Informatics (IJHISI)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kumi R, Reychav I, Azuri J, Sabherwal R (2023) Tablet in the Consultation Room and Physician Satisfaction. International Journal of Healthcare Information Systems and Informatics (IJHISI) 18(1): 12.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_z3r3bsH">Blockchain and the Emergence of Decentralized Autonomous Organizations (Daos): An Integrative Model and Research Agenda</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Carlos</forename><surname>Santana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laura</forename><surname>Albareda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.techfore.2022.121806</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_e9KVNGc">Technological Forecasting and Social Change</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">182</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Carlos Santana, Laura Albareda (2022) Blockchain and the Emergence of Decentralized Autonomous Organizations (Daos): An Integrative Model and Research Agenda, Technological Forecasting and Social Change 182.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_6G3tzCq">Decentralized Autonomous Organizations: Concept, Model, and Applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Yuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ouyang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/tcss.2019.2938190</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_m58guFj">IEEE Transactions on Computational Social Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="870" to="878" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">S Wang, W Ding, J Li, Y Yuan, L Ouyang, et al. (2019) Decentralized Autonomous Organizations: Concept, Model, and Applications, in IEEE Transactions on Computational Social Systems 6(5): 870-878.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_JnrN7zV">A Systematic Review for Enabling of Develop a Blockchain Technology in Healthcare Application: Taxonomy, Substantially Analysis, Motivations, Challenges, Recommendations and Future Direction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hussien</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Yasin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sni</forename><surname>Udzir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Zaidan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Zaidan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10916-019-1445-8</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_UzHVn3P">J Med Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">320</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hussien HM, Yasin SM, Udzir SNI, Zaidan AA, Zaidan BB (2019) A Systematic Review for Enabling of Develop a Blockchain Technology in Healthcare Application: Taxonomy, Substantially Analysis, Motivations, Challenges, Recommendations and Future Direction. J Med Syst 43(10): 320.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_HFyhXjA">Educational applications of metaverse: possibilities and limitations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jo</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3352/jeehp.2021.18.32</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_YbBVP2x">J Educ Eval Health Prof</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">32</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kye B, Han N, Kim E, Park Y, Jo S (2021) Educational applications of metaverse: possibilities and limitations. J Educ Eval Health Prof 18: 32.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
