<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_UkHxtKU">Peer Review of &quot;Mass Testing With Contact Tracing Compared to Test and Trace for the Effective Suppression of COVID-19 in the United Kingdom: Systematic Review&quot;</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>BSc</roleName><forename type="first">Archisman</forename><surname>Roy</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Department of Physics , Faculty of Mathematical Science , Institute of Sciences , Banaras Hindu University , Asansol , India</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Mathematical Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Institute of Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Banaras Hindu University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Asansol</settlement>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_p4EaGU5">Peer Review of &quot;Mass Testing With Contact Tracing Compared to Test and Trace for the Effective Suppression of COVID-19 in the United Kingdom: Systematic Review&quot;</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">A93FA409B7ED4D7EC85B4101235C5B64</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.2196/28719</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T07:51+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term xml:id="_NGZf44t">COVID-19</term>
					<term xml:id="_pkcrS7V">SARS-CoV-2</term>
					<term xml:id="_p7fw89q">test and trace</term>
					<term xml:id="_2fdtVpW">universal testing</term>
					<term xml:id="_gxWdZDv">mass testing</term>
					<term xml:id="_a2ndRjh">contact tracing</term>
					<term xml:id="_gXDQ6js">infection surveillance</term>
					<term xml:id="_NDwKA9b">prevention and control</term>
					<term xml:id="_CNhPcEy">review</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_rVpqJFd"><p xml:id="_bTtQUYe"><s xml:id="_mrfnKBg">This is a peer-review report submitted for the paper "Mass Testing With Contact Tracing Compared to Test and Trace for the Effective Suppression of COVID-19 in the United Kingdom: Systematic Review."</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_7jKUS6h">Round 1 Review</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_fFvRwPB">General Comments</head><p xml:id="_MP6DNfQ"><s xml:id="_5eAeTXH">The paper titled, "Mass Testing With Contact Tracing Compared to Test and Trace for the Effective Suppression of COVID-19 in the United Kingdom: Systematic Review" <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> is well textured and finely written with sufficient subpoints and clear divisions.</s><s xml:id="_v6BT3gg">The English used is simple but lucid enough and enriched compared to an international journal standard.</s><s xml:id="_3RfWBss">From the very beginning, the title is so effective and descriptive that it provides a brief outline for the readers.</s><s xml:id="_GWSbpqW">The abstract is finely written, pointing to the outcomes of the paper, which also includes an applaudable inculcation of a nutshell overview of the methods in use.</s><s xml:id="_myC4eSk">The data analysis, results, and discussion, as well as the detailed structure of the major findings, P values, statistical coefficients, and so on, conform to the author's guide.</s><s xml:id="_VaZbY5g">But there are a few minor typographical errors that need to be checked to improve the write-up.</s><s xml:id="_JRN3KvV">Please consider the points in the Minor Comments section.</s><s xml:id="_rVZzJZK">The citations mentioned in the paper fit well with the context.</s><s xml:id="_nhXc5g6">Overall, the description of the content is very clear, and every point is academically backed up with either derivations or scientifically validated information, which is commendable.</s><s xml:id="_xD25DX3">The figures (mainly the flow chart) are very precise but wonderfully narrative.</s><s xml:id="_mcSGAEd">The Methods section has been presented in good harmony with the objectives, outcomes, and strategy although my view on the outcomes differs a bit (please look at the Specific Comments section).</s><s xml:id="_jrVhxmQ">The data analysis section is well structured, maintaining the flow of data management.</s><s xml:id="_Q68bwG5">In total, the paper is a worthy piece but, in my view, it may require a few minor changes.</s><s xml:id="_uvJCEaf">Kindly refer to the following comments.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_wBNKsam">Specific Comments</head><p xml:id="_QcKbhnS"><s xml:id="_zMN95Tn">1.</s><s xml:id="_QKPvFfr">It is crucial to remove a few points to make the paper easily acceptable for readers and better its viability.</s><s xml:id="_mfeztYZ">I suggest cutting a bit in the Research in Context section.</s><s xml:id="_5hXvhzE">It is fine to have a short review of the literature, but the paper overall is full of it so shortening the aforesaid section may increase its impact.</s></p><p xml:id="_USEeKdw"><s xml:id="_A8ukF4t">2. I also do not find the validity of having the Definitions section.</s><s xml:id="_7EA3wgB">When an author is proposing a new theory bearing some new terminology, this section is needed, but getting acquainted with formal terms is the prime duty of readers.</s></p><p xml:id="_H37wgta"><s xml:id="_mJV5Md6">3. In the Data Extraction section, you paced on the author's details, specifically its singularity, which seems inapplicable to me.</s><s xml:id="_Xm8kFBv">Please consider jotting that area down again in a twisted fashion.</s></p><p xml:id="_esFPbXe"><s xml:id="_tmuM87e">It is really commendable the way you have composed this paper.</s><s xml:id="_gsepCYP">As mentioned earlier, the writing style is very soothing and effective as a worthy academic contribution.</s><s xml:id="_BPchAxt">Still, a few points need more attention, which have been further segmented into major and minor comments.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_r8cvq5H">Major Comments</head><p xml:id="_AAzZKv3"><s xml:id="_RuKvXw8">1. Reviewers are not asked to look into the grammar and spelling very thoroughly, so I am giving an overview.</s><s xml:id="_JEyV7KR">Please consider reading the paper again as a few words seems to mismatch their application.</s><s xml:id="_2PnjHPS">For instance, in the following sentence in the Background section, "I concur with the...," the word "concurs" is out of context, so please look into the matter.</s></p><p xml:id="_xGxkSwe"><s xml:id="_48NQ8CB">2. In the Research to Context prior to Study section, there is mention of a review; please cite it for a better scholarly approach.</s></p><p xml:id="_vJ2S5jf"><s xml:id="_eGBU2Qr">3. The paper bears a good philosophical measure of uncertainty introduced.</s><s xml:id="_qZurcns">This section is very nicely formatted in an appreciable way.</s></p><p xml:id="_K9XqdGD"><s xml:id="_fj7tCaN">4. Outcomes occur within the Methods section, which is not advised.</s><s xml:id="_6u3U54A">Adding the outcomes here creates a sense of biasedness since outcomes can never be assumed beforehand, which is why you may consider removing these points from here.</s></p><p xml:id="_SHW3cYg"><s xml:id="_YCfknSu">5. The section How the Intervention Should Work ought to be included under Methods.</s><s xml:id="_tXnJ7zw">I would suggest replacing its name with Active Runs of Intervention as a subsection.</s><s xml:id="_m8gCkQt">The objectives and outcomes further include some basic information about COVID-19 and the strain itself.</s><s xml:id="_nG4Yu8f">This is really unimportant, so please remove that portion to reduce the word count of the paper.</s></p><p xml:id="_XHkJGAF"><s xml:id="_B3YX5md">6.</s><s xml:id="_CjTEwvA">In the Outcomes section, the third point: there is a point on safety; however, the tone of safety in mass testing methods seems to be understated so I would like to propose emphasizing the safe nature of MTT.</s><s xml:id="_QD6XmBX">Again, the paper is really a worthy piece for me, so consider these points as a proposal for improvement.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_q74rHhY">Minor Comments</head><p xml:id="_AhKu653"><s xml:id="_AfXQNmv">1.</s><s xml:id="_6HfzcAT">Many paragraphs lack the use of full stops at the end line.</s><s xml:id="_bnXmvFD">Please have it checked with a little care.</s></p><p xml:id="_hrMvVEq"><s xml:id="_cfvyrHv">2. There are some issues with grammatical usages; please consider fixing them.</s><s xml:id="_h4GFujV">You may opt for artificial intelligence-based screening to get better results (eg, Grammarly).</s></p><p xml:id="_Tr87q5B"><s xml:id="_XBdpqKn">3. The importance of the separate column for vote count in the relative study of TT and MTT is not clear to me so please try to express its viability in a line or so for clarity.</s></p></div>			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p xml:id="_EmXztXW"><s xml:id="_Qef24H3">JMIRx Med 2021 | vol. 2 | iss. 2 | e28719 | p. 1 https://xmed.jmir.org/2021/2/e28719</s><s xml:id="_arvDZZg">(page number not for citation purposes)</s></p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p xml:id="_yTv7vUR"><s xml:id="_WWz6aUS">JMIRx Med 2021 | vol. 2 | iss. 2 | e28719 | p. 2 https://xmed.jmir.org/2021/2/e28719</s><s xml:id="_uez6X8t">(page number not for citation purposes)</s></p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_3q73d5Y">Conflicts of Interest</head><p xml:id="_S7EktUh"><s xml:id="_ENF5Aw8">None declared.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_9TwtEuC">Mass Testing With Contact Tracing Compared to Test and Trace for the Effective Suppression of COVID-19 in the United Kingdom: Systematic Review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mbwogge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/27254</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_RrNQ2dW">JMIRx Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">27254</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021-04-12">2021 Apr 12</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>FREE Full text</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mbwogge M. Mass Testing With Contact Tracing Compared to Test and Trace for the Effective Suppression of COVID-19 in the United Kingdom: Systematic Review. JMIRx Med 2021 Apr 12;2(2):e27254 [FREE Full text] [doi: 10.2196/27254]</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_zZ3vmmh">Roy A Peer Review of &quot;Mass Testing With Contact Tracing Compared to Test and Trace for the Effective Suppression of COVID-19 in the United Kingdom: Systematic Review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Meinert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/28719</idno>
		<ptr target="https://med.jmirx.org),12.04" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_9ctGvg2">JMIRx Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">28719</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Submitted 11.03.21; accepted 11.03.21 this is a non-peer-reviewed article</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Edited by E Meinert; this is a non-peer-reviewed article. Submitted 11.03.21; accepted 11.03.21; published 12.04.21. Please cite as: Roy A Peer Review of &quot;Mass Testing With Contact Tracing Compared to Test and Trace for the Effective Suppression of COVID-19 in the United Kingdom: Systematic Review&quot; JMIRx Med 2021;2(2):e28719 URL: https://xmed.jmir.org/2021/2/e28719 doi: 10.2196/28719 PMID: ©Archisman Roy. Originally published in JMIRx Med (https://med.jmirx.org), 12.04</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
