<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_NNKrpyF">The effectiveness of text message delivered interventions for weight loss in developing countries: A systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Tilahun</forename><forename type="middle">Tewabe</forename><surname>Alamnia</surname></persName>
							<email>tilahun.alamnia@anu.edu.au</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>1</label> Research School of Population Health , Australian National University , Canberra , Australia</note>
								<orgName type="department">Research School of Population Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Australian National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Canberra</settlement>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>2</label> College of Medical and Health Sciences , Bahir Dar University , Bahir Dar , Ethiopia</note>
								<orgName type="department">College of Medical and Health Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Bahir Dar University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bahir Dar</settlement>
									<country key="ET">Ethiopia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wubshet</forename><surname>Tesfaye</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>3</label> Health Research Institute , University of Canberra , Canberra , Australia</note>
								<orgName type="department">Health Research Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Canberra</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Canberra</settlement>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Matthew</forename><surname>Kelly</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>4</label> Department of Global Health , Research School of Population Health , Australian National University , Canberra , Australia</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Global Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Research School of Population Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Australian National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Canberra</settlement>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Research School of Population Health , Australian National University , Canberra , Australia.</note>
								<orgName type="department">Research School of Population Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Australian National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Canberra</settlement>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_6XfPZDQ">The effectiveness of text message delivered interventions for weight loss in developing countries: A systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">8300762DE1965CA1EDBFA3F58D8C1ACE</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1111/obr.13339</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: 28 May 2021 Revised: 11 August 2021 Accepted: 11 August 2021</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T07:58+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term xml:id="_3FHBamY">developing countries</term>
					<term xml:id="_ZpuUBcu">overweight or obesity</term>
					<term xml:id="_FkkHuPk">text message</term>
					<term xml:id="_fUvDc7m">weight loss</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_UNczvJd"><p xml:id="_GpgSXuT"><s xml:id="_a4V6r4j">Recent advances in mobile technologies have provided an opportunity to disseminate health information on a variety of health conditions.</s><s xml:id="_Jdd8YDa">Randomized controlled trials (RCTs) have shown that text messaging helps people to lose weight, but the effectiveness of interventions varies between studies.</s><s xml:id="_jvRS9YQ">Thus, this review aimed to (1) identify RCTs that used text messages for overweight management, (2) identify components of the interventions, and (3) test their effectiveness.</s><s xml:id="_hj2zHRf">PubMed, Web of Science, ProQuest, and Scopus databases were searched to identify relevant studies.</s></p><p xml:id="_zVmVEhs"><s xml:id="_qs3EzAm">Quality scores for selected articles were assessed using the Joanna Briggs Institute (JBI) critical appraisal tools for interventional studies.</s><s xml:id="_pEHXhhk">The effectiveness of the interventions was tested using random effect models.</s><s xml:id="_qbk8jzD">Twelve studies that met inclusion criteria were included in this review.</s><s xml:id="_G7zEH6h">Ten of the included studies reported that text message interventions had a significant effect on weight loss.</s><s xml:id="_q9TdS99">The pooled mean difference in body mass index (BMI) change after the intervention was À0.43 kg/m 2 (95% confidence interval, À 0.63 to -0.23 kg/m 2 ).</s><s xml:id="_BnApeD2">Synthesis of the included studies provides evidence that (1) regular text messages; (2) interventions targeting weight monitoring, diet habit, and physical activity; and (3) the use of behavior change techniques led to significant weight loss.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="10" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="11" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="12" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="13" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="14" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="15" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="16" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="17" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="18" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="19" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="20" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1" xml:id="_WBJZrVU">| INTRODUCTION</head><p xml:id="_2uAH2CM"><s xml:id="_mjpy55Y">The prevalence of noncommunicable diseases (NCDs) is currently on the rise worldwide, accounting for more than two-thirds of all deaths. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> Nearly 80% of the deaths due to NCDs occur in developing countries and among adults between the ages of 30 and 70. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> The everincreasing prevalence of NCDs imposes a disproportionate health and economic burden on developing countries.</s><s xml:id="_fq4uNBU">As well, in lowand middle-income countries (LMICs), the underdiagnosis of conditions like diabetes mellitus <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> often lead to its suboptimal management, adding to a range of challenges affecting the health, social, and economic developments in these settings. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref></s><s xml:id="_qzBwYSu">However, NCDs can be prevented by reducing risk factors like overweight and obesity and its associated behavioral risk factors, such as physical inactivity, and dietary risks. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> Overweight and obesity are among the common global risk factors for NCDs and are interlinked with other risk factors including hypertension and insulin resistance. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref></s><s xml:id="_EsR8mwt">In 2016, nearly two billion adults over the age of 18 years were overweight, and more than a tenth of them were obese, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> and these conditions were responsible for five million deaths and 148 million disability-adjusted life years. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref></s><s xml:id="_ePMUAkf">Although obesity is recognized as a major problem in developed settings, obesity-related burden now causes a more severe impact among adults in developing countries.</s><s xml:id="_XNwVJ8R">For instance, 60% of obesity-related deaths in Africa occur in people under the age of 60 years, as opposed to the 18% in developed countries. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s xml:id="_TNMySmr">To prevent this, the World Health Organization (WHO) recommends the use of simple, accessible, and cost-effective interventions to reduce risk factors, although the relevance and outcome may vary depending on the infrastructure, healthcare setup, and manpower across different countries. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref></s><s xml:id="_gU3JvYb">bile communication is a rapidly expanding technology not only in developed countries but also in developing regions of the world.</s><s xml:id="_rCv2jBe">It has become the first choice of communication methods due to its easiness, adaptability, accessibility, and user preferences.</s><s xml:id="_Xm4yTU6">There are many forms of mobile communications, such as phone calls, text messages, webpages, and social media, but text messaging is most widely used both in high-and low-income countries. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref></s><s xml:id="_HreYue9">Following the rapid proliferation of mobile technologies, researchers have tried to show the acceptability and effectiveness of mobile phone delivered interventions to improve health outcomes, including maternal and child health, medication adherence, chronic disease care, clinic follow-ups, and risk behavior reductions. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref></s><s xml:id="_yPHYUQZ"><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> Mobile health is a cost-effective intervention to change people's behavior and create awareness about health risks.</s><s xml:id="_MrN3Nq5">It also helps to easily transmit health information to a wider audience, even in remote areas. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref></s><s xml:id="_5W3WTVH">Research in developing countries has shown that people are willing to receive text messages related to their health.</s><s xml:id="_aJyPm2k">For example, a feasibility study on short text messaging for chronic disease management indicated that the overwhelming majority of participants were willing to receive messages about their health conditions, such as appointments, test results, and treatments. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref></s><s xml:id="_ky6QqF9">A systematic review of short message services for disease prevention in the developing countries has also shown that text messages are acceptable to patients. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref></s><s xml:id="_TJWh9a5">th regard to the effectiveness of text-based delivered interventions for weight loss, published systematic reviews, mostly focused on studies in the United Kingdom, the United States, and Australia, reported that text message interventions are effective for weight loss in adolescents and adults. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref></s><s xml:id="_rjkmZYw">0]<ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> However, the result of these studies cannot be generalized to developing countries due to differences in mobile phone utilization patterns, infrastructure, healthcare systems, and health-seeking behavior.</s><s xml:id="_cN45Upz">In developing countries, evidence from controlled trials indicate that mobile text interventions led to improved disease-related knowledge, self-efficacy, treatment adherence, and change in health behavior in chronic diseases, such as diabetes mellitus, cancer, hypertension, and cardiovascular diseases. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref></s><s xml:id="_JPtxJEv"><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> Although overweight and obesity are manageable and reversible risk factors for NCDs, there is relatively scant evidence in the form of randomized controlled trials (RCTs) in developing countries to provide best practices or interventions for overweight management.</s><s xml:id="_AzzWZjm">For instance, a bibliometric review in Africa shows that there have been few intervention studies on NCDs, with only 11 studies conducted over the past 12 years. <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2" xml:id="_uPBkDqc">| MATERIALS AND METHODS</head><p xml:id="_MxbupTt"><s xml:id="_YkRnNwW">This systematic review and meta-analysis was conducted and reported in line with the PRISMA (Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses) guidelines. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref></s><s xml:id="_57cMAzn">Following these guidelines, we collected title, abstract, introduction, method, results, discussion, and funding for reviewed papers along with other specified information.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1" xml:id="_raGQU7W">| Research questions</head><p xml:id="_RFBBjg3"><s xml:id="_afXfc24">The main research questions that prompted this systematic review</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3" xml:id="_cuM4xZD">| Information sources</head><p xml:id="_Cyq79xv"><s xml:id="_msG54WT">Four health-related databases were searched from their inception to January 23, 2021.</s><s xml:id="_3erUes6">These were PubMed, Scopus, ProQuest, and Web of Science.</s><s xml:id="_ybkFXXb">Before the search was conducted, keywords were prepared based on the predefined PICO components.</s><s xml:id="_xvjm4EX">Combination of the following search words were generally used: mobile, phone, "mobile phone," "cell phone," "smart phone," telemedicine, "mobile health," "mHealth," telehealth, eHealth, telephone; message, text, "text messaging," "text-based messages," "text message," "voice message," "short message service," "short message," sms, internet, email; weight, "weight loss," "weight management," "weight maintenance," "weight program," "weight program," "weight reduction," overweight, obesity, adiposity, "body fat," "body weight," anthropometry, "body mass index," BMI, waist, "waist circumference," "waist-hip ratio," "body fat distribution," "obesity management," "skinfold," "overweight therapy," "obesity therapy."</s><s xml:id="_PasVv9P">The search was minimally adjusted according to databases using abstract, title, and topics of articles.</s></p><p xml:id="_AEzCZ2h"><s xml:id="_3Wpzvs2">Truncation and wild cards were used to combine keywords and expand search results.</s><s xml:id="_SGV9qps">Grey literature and reference lists of relevant retrieved articles were also hand-searched to include additional relevant studies potentially missed during the main search.</s><s xml:id="_DXxVDDn">Search limit was applied only to English literature.</s><s xml:id="_nFYDfD5">The search was not limited to developing countries, but studies in low-and middle countries were later identified based on the 2020 World Bank report, which categorizes countries by income. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30</ref></s><s xml:id="_Hrs8gsc">The complete search strategy used for PubMed electronic database is presented in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4" xml:id="_kxmHrKk">| Study selection</head><p xml:id="_7uQSCjP"><s xml:id="_hCzmk7m">Citations and abstracts of retrieved studies were downloaded to End-Note X9 reference manager system (Thomson Reuters, Philadelphia, PA, USA) and then exported to Covidence virtual library <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31</ref> for removing duplication, screening, and full-text review.</s><s xml:id="_eM9VrRg">Articles were screened and selected based on predefined inclusion and exclusion criteria.</s><s xml:id="_aZwrQxM">The initial screening was conducted by one reviewer, and then 10% of the retrieved articles were screened by the second reviewer to check the consistency and precision.</s><s xml:id="_YDHjXEE">The average agreement score of the reviewers was 100%.</s><s xml:id="_yanHRg3">Then, full-text articles were reviewed by both authors, and any disagreement arising during the selection process was resolved through discussion, and no disagreements necessitated the invitation of a third reviewer.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5" xml:id="_eetPGKM">| Data collection process</head><p xml:id="_n4AZ42y"><s xml:id="_W7Mt9Yp">A data collection form was prepared using the Joanna Briggs Institute (JBI) manual for conducting systematic reviews of intervention studies.</s><s xml:id="_5aq92K2">The form consists of study characteristics such as author, year, country, design, sample size, inclusion criteria, and exclusion criteria; participant details such as age and sex; randomization;</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">T A B L E 1</formula><p xml:id="_DgZQBG3"><s xml:id="_3v4t8jG">PubMed search strategy Serial number Themes Keywords and combinations Search results 1 Mobile related mobile* OR phone* OR "mobile phone" OR "cell phone" OR "cell phones" OR "smart phone" OR "smartphones" OR tele-medicine OR telemedicine OR "mobile health" OR "mHealth" OR telehealth OR eHealth OR mHealth OR telemetry OR telephone 267,649 2 Message related message* OR messages OR "text messaging" OR "text-based messages" OR "text messages" OR "text messaged" OR voice OR "voice message" OR "voice messages" OR "short message service" OR "short message" OR sms OR SMS OR text* OR txt OR texts OR texting OR eHealth OR internet OR email 511,372 3 Weight related weight* OR "weight loss" OR "weight management" OR "weight reduction" OR overweight OR obesity OR obese OR adiposity OR "body fat" OR "body weight" OR Anthropometry OR "Body Mass Index" OR BMI OR waist OR "waist circumference" OR "Waist-Hip Ratio" OR "Body Fat Distribution" OR "obesity management" OR "skinfold" OR "overweight therapy" OR "obesity therapy" OR (weight AND [loss OR manage* OR maintenance OR maintain OR maintain*]) OR (weight AND [intervention* OR program*]) OR (weight AND [fitness OR physical activity OR physical exercise OR diet* OR nutrition]) 1,825,046 4 Combination of themes #1 AND #2 AND #3 and with search limit only to English literature 3727 controls; intervention characteristics such as types, durations, contents, tailoring, measurements, attritions, behavior change options, behavior change techniques, and theories; and other additional relevant study findings.</s></p><p xml:id="_3Aw6DEe"><s xml:id="_GzSRcKG">The data extraction was piloted on the included studies and refined accordingly.</s><s xml:id="_x2r6nn8">One author (TA) has extracted relevant information from the included studies, and a second reviewer then extracted one fourth of included studies (four articles) and cross-matched for consistency and accuracy.</s><s xml:id="_J4Gk2ZP">However, there was no significant difference found in extracted data sets for both reviewers.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6" xml:id="_5y2jz9G">| Risk of bias assessment</head><p xml:id="_8BnQSPT"><s xml:id="_CWsdftw">The quality of the included studies was assessed using the JBI critical appraisal checklist for RCTs <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32</ref> or quasi-experimental studies (non-RCTs). <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">33</ref></s><s xml:id="_GVsqTub">The checklist for RCTs includes the following items: randomi-</s></p><p xml:id="_hmPhP4P"><s xml:id="_bTMctS6">zation, allocation concealment, treatment group similarity, treatment assignment blindness, treatment delivery blindness, outcomes assessment blindness, intervention identicality, follow-up completeness, participants analysis within their group, outcomes measurement similarity, outcome measurement reliability, statistical analysis suitability, and trial design appropriateness.</s><s xml:id="_wHXKxfG">In contrast, the checklist for quasi-experimental studies consists of the following items: clear statement of causes and effects, similarity of participants in the comparison, similarity of the intervention in the comparison, presence of control group, presence of multiple measurements of the outcome, completeness of the follow-up, similarity of outcomes measures, reliability of outcome measures, and the appropriateness of statistical analysis used.</s><s xml:id="_mhcWaN7">Articles were rated using a four point scale: yes, no, unclear, and not applicable.</s><s xml:id="_peCyp9p">Two authors independently assessed and evaluated each article.</s><s xml:id="_UfRjz7Q">Any emerging disagreement was resolved through discussion.</s><s xml:id="_fCwsBWe">Studies were considered of low (1-4), moderate</s></p><p xml:id="_a3ZRfty"><s xml:id="_TB8mDKu">(5-8), or high (9-13) quality based on the total score for each item.</s></p><p xml:id="_JHAckvX"><s xml:id="_FyjhHN5">The interrater agreement for the risk of bias assessment was generally good (k = 0.76).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.7" xml:id="_jADgWgk">| Outcome measure</head><p xml:id="_43w6VQb"><s xml:id="_7GnGCtA">The outcome of interest for this review was the change in body weight measured in kilograms (kg) or change in BMI (weight (kg)/ height (meters) square).</s><s xml:id="_PZe7FQF">Overweight and obesity were categorized based on the following definitions: overweight, defined as a BMI of 25-29.9</s><s xml:id="_xHyEJzp">kg/m 2 and obesity as BMI ≥ 30 kg/m 2 . <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34</ref></s><s xml:id="_rruAa3w">Some Asian countries defined overweight starting from a BMI score of 23 kg/ m 2 .</s><s xml:id="_bF3mbAE">Both definitions were used in this study to increase scope of the review because the main purpose of the study was to assess the effectiveness of text messaging in overweight management in developing countries.</s><s xml:id="_9RqqXb9">Other measurements of the outcome, such as waist and hip ratio, waist circumference, and level of adiposity, were extracted and narratively described when they were reported.</s><s xml:id="_SEKHHxz">The heterogeneity of the included articles was assessed by I 2 statistics and was presented as a percentage.</s><s xml:id="_SzRVbCG">In line with the JBI critical manual for evidence synthesis <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">35</ref> and Cochrane Handbook for Systematic Reviews of Interventions, <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36</ref> heterogeneity was classified as low (0%-25%), moderate (25%-75%), or high (75%-100%).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.9" xml:id="_r3FP5fe">| Subgroup analysis</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.10" xml:id="_PnQjVPe">| Publication bias</head><p xml:id="_zDpF6X6"><s xml:id="_9GBCZAP">Metafunnel and metabias analysis were performed to assess publication bias in the included studies.</s><s xml:id="_TXwWdyC">The distribution of the studies was subjectively assessed in the funnel plot graph around mean of the normal distribution.</s><s xml:id="_wfPXWB2">If the included studies were distributed around the mean, the studies would not have publication bias.</s></p><p xml:id="_tBqt6jS"><s xml:id="_jq58Sg5">Publication bias was then objectively assessed by running metabias using Begg's rank of correlation and Egger's asymmetry tests.</s><s xml:id="_qZa5Ecg">Publication bias was considered when the Egger's asymmetry test pvalue was less than 0.05.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.11" xml:id="_7rSuQ5N">| Sensitivity analysis</head><p xml:id="_AU5dpwc"><s xml:id="_GFcTW2B">Sensitivity analysis was conducted to assess the robustness of the meta-analysis model.</s><s xml:id="_ajYMFvk">If models are robust, the result would be consistent across different models, but if the results were inconsistent, it would be interpreted with caution.</s><s xml:id="_HFV2c8W">This test investigated the effect of excluding studies from the model based on study characteristics, such as sample size, and methodological quality.</s><s xml:id="_kW5Dy8Y">As part of sensitivity analysis, trim-and-fill analysis were performed to assess effect size of the intervention with the assumption to fill imputed studies into the model that might have been missed.</s></p><p xml:id="_DRG8cEU"><s xml:id="_YscDkZz">Trim-and-fill analysis estimates were considered significant if pvalue was less than 0.05.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3" xml:id="_hVrTvBn">| RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1" xml:id="_cJHdRwq">| Search results and study selection</head><p xml:id="_tzPyv5z"><s xml:id="_dqgATSA">The database search and hand search of grey literature and reference lists of relevant studies identified a total of 8875 articles.</s><s xml:id="_fUT5GP5">Of these, 2820 duplicate records were removed, and the remaining 6055 records were screened for eligibility.</s><s xml:id="_23qXGPz">Among these, 5930 irrelevant articles were excluded using titles and abstracts.</s><s xml:id="_gCEg5Cn">One hundred twenty-five articles were then selected for full-text review.</s><s xml:id="_jMawyGX">Finally, 12 studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref> (nine RCTs <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref> and three quasi-experiments <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref> were included for this systematic review and meta-analysis.</s><s xml:id="_jC6DN4h">One of the studies included a binational cohort including participants from the United Kingdom and India, <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37</ref> In this case, the results were</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_1">F I G U R E 1 Study selection flow diagram</formula><p xml:id="_C3WGvZr"><s xml:id="_JQYAyrS">analyzed individually for each country, and only characteristics related to Indian participants were extracted.</s></p><p xml:id="_W6hhjZv"><s xml:id="_XAtzxyK">Participants in the included studies were adults relatively free from chronic diseases such as diabetes and cancer.</s><s xml:id="_GNajghN">However, one study, <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47</ref> which targeted participants regardless of their health status, was included in this review after careful consideration of its alignment with our inclusion criteria.</s><s xml:id="_mTRHgWs">Methodological quality of the studies ranged from seven (out of nine scales for quasi-experiment studies) to 12 (out of 13 scales applicable to RCTs).</s><s xml:id="_Xn2ZzCK">Nine studies that mainly used text message interventions for weight loss were included in meta-analysis. <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref></s><s xml:id="_ewfCuPh">9]<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref> Two studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48</ref> were excluded from the meta-analysis because they did not involve a control group, and one due to the nature of participants. <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37</ref></s><s xml:id="_AFvVMck">The study selection process for this systematic review and meta-analysis was presented in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2" xml:id="_t2EACft">| Characteristics of included studies</head><p xml:id="_JveQehb"><s xml:id="_B56kNnu">Table <ref type="table">2</ref> presents characteristics of the studies included in this systematic review and meta-analysis.</s><s xml:id="_dpbY3Dw">Four studies were conducted in India, <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42</ref> three in China, <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">38,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43</ref> one in Brazil, <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47</ref> one in Peru, <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44</ref> one in Malaysia, <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45</ref> one in Thailand, <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48</ref> and one in Iran. <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46</ref></s><s xml:id="_GpWeYBH">Nine <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref> were RCTs, and three <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref> were quasi-experimental trials.</s><s xml:id="_cq33MR2">Nine of the included studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">38,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48</ref> were published in the last 5 years, whereas the rest three <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46</ref> were published in 2013 and 2014. Although ot</s><s xml:id="_KACbTfA">er demographic details of participants varied, the age range of participants were between 18 and 65 years in the included studies.</s><s xml:id="_Cj798QJ">Most of the studies involved both men and women; however, two studies targeted entirely women, <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48</ref> and another one targeted only men.</s><s xml:id="_DehTJrN"><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39</ref> Almost all of the studies included participants who were overweight or obese and without chronic health conditions at the baseline, but one study <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47</ref> included participants regardless of their health conditions.</s><s xml:id="_jj4veDE">Most studies, <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">38,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48</ref> in addition to text messages, included other additional behavior modification techniques, such as group meetings, telephone calls, SMART websites, guideline/documents, nutrition education, and social support.</s><s xml:id="_BXRqNVk">Eight studies had theoretical underpinnings to their interventions, including social cognitive theory, 48 cognitive behavioral therapy, <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47</ref> transtheoretical model, <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44</ref> PRECEDE-PROCEED model, <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40</ref> and motivational interviewing. <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43</ref> Ha</s><s xml:id="_DrE2haS">f of studies evaluated weight loss as a primary outcome, whereas the remaining half <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45</ref> evaluated it as a secondary outcome.</s><s xml:id="_G4nDBBu">Sample sizes in the included studies ranged from 38 participants in a pilot study <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48</ref> to 1171 in a RCT.</s><s xml:id="_zkpwp47"><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37</ref> The proportion of intervention group and control group varied in the included studies.</s><s xml:id="_KMUNf7s">Messages were tailored based on participants'</s></p><p xml:id="_89KKXZb"><s xml:id="_WXDJ6vJ">behavior in one study. <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39</ref></s><s xml:id="_yAPsvKA">The duration of interventions among the studies ranged from two months <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46</ref> to 2 years, <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41</ref> and follow-ups were complete.</s><s xml:id="_esxrh3K">The main behavioral change option used in the included studies was providing information or creating awareness on physical activity, diet habits, and weight monitoring, and through motivation.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3" xml:id="_dK87Ffy">| Risk of bias within studies</head><p xml:id="_uqjZb89"><s xml:id="_F9zhAaU">Nine studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref> were RCTs, and their quality score was rated out of 13 points.</s><s xml:id="_3Ss2uwr">The quality score range from seven 41 to 13. <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44</ref> All RCTs involved randomization, but the randomization method varies between studies: lottery, cluster, and computer generated.</s><s xml:id="_NWVgdWn">Participant allocation was not concealed in three studies. <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref></s><s xml:id="_PxzqefN">2]<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref> In two RCTs, <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41</ref> treatment groups significantly differ from comparison groups, and in all but one of the RCTs, <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44</ref> participants were not blinded to treatment.</s><s xml:id="_tUgGR2C">Except in two RCTs, <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44</ref> the person who delivered the intervention was not blinded to the group assignment, and also in other two studies, <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41</ref> the person who took measurements was not blinded to the group allocation.</s><s xml:id="_gvuhKbY">In all RCTs, treatment groups were treated identically, follow-ups were complete, results were analyzed within their group, and trial designs were appropriate; but one study <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41</ref> did not use reliable measurement, and another one <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42</ref> did not perform appropriate statistical analysis.</s></p><p xml:id="_NHFnxMF"><s xml:id="_3DKu4fj">With regard to the quality assessment of quasi-experimental studies, they were evaluated on a 9-point scale: Two studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48</ref> scored 8, and the remaining one 46 scored 7. One of the quasiexperiment studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46</ref> had a comparison group but had limitation in terms of measurement and analysis, whereas the other two trials <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48</ref> did not include a control group in their study design.</s><s xml:id="_Cd2EwNW">Overall, the methodological rigor score of the included studies is presented in Tables 3a and 3b.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4" xml:id="_KmeQQx9">| Outcome measures</head><p xml:id="_eZAGg3v"><s xml:id="_sRchFTa">The outcome measures reported for each included study are presented in Table <ref type="table">4</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_TZ7eGgD">All of the included studies in this review measured participants' weight and height and recorded BMI (weight in kilogram per height in meter square).</s><s xml:id="_w99wK4K">However, two of the included studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42</ref> did not separately report weight kilograms; instead, they reported the change in BMI.</s><s xml:id="_Jjzk9Pb">The main drivers for weight loss were physical activity and diet habits, and although all studies involved physical activity and/or diet-related messages, participant specific values of physical activity and diet habit were not reported in some studies. <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">38,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46</ref></s><s xml:id="_WgyCs5v">her measurements frequently reported in the included studies were participants' blood pressure in 11 studies, <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47</ref> fasting plasma glucose in eight studies, <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43</ref> blood lipid profiles (triglyceride, highdensity lipoproteins, low density lipoprotein, triglycerides, and total cholesterol) in nine studies, <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref> and waist circumference in eight studies. <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref></s><s xml:id="_fAQgRS9">]<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48</ref> Participants' satisfaction was assessed in four studies, <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45</ref> and self-efficacy in four studies.</s><s xml:id="_ZFAtunQ"><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48</ref> Quality of life of participants, daily sitting time, and body strength were among the less frequently reported parameters in the included studies.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5" xml:id="_GZn7ZPj">| Characteristics of studies with significant weight loss</head><p xml:id="_7v6TWqx"><s xml:id="_QvuEVGa">The effect of text message interventions for weight loss was related to characteristics of the interventions as described in Table <ref type="table">5</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_dqYFx8N">Of the RT/ quasi Intervention: This was a quasi-experimental study that assessed the effect of mobile health technology for weight management in working women using free calls and messages (tailored and feedback messages) supplemented with three group sessions over 12 weeks.</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_2">T A B L E 2</formula><p xml:id="_3vz9fjv"><s xml:id="_k4VwnSH">The intervention, mainly focused on participants' food intake and physical activity, resulted significant weight loss.</s><s xml:id="_pYsjxYX">The study used social cognitive theory.</s><s xml:id="_AryxqR9">Goal setting and reinforcement were used as behavior change techniques.</s></p><p xml:id="_arwYdGz"><s xml:id="_AzZHpDg">Control: The study did not involve control group Participants were working women who were overweight but free from chronic diseases such as diabetes "√" refers for checklists that were fulfilled in the included studies.</s><s xml:id="_Bd7R8gN">"-" refers for checklists that were not fulfilled or unclear in the included studies.</s></p><p xml:id="_4KtbeFd"><s xml:id="_rzuRtsW">studies included in this review, 10 trials reported that text message interventions had significant effect on weight loss among adults with overweight and obesity in developing countries. <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref></s><s xml:id="_tBWJJVN"><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1." xml:id="_uskXKpP">Settings of effective intervention</head><p xml:id="_jZgJj8J"><s xml:id="_E3exr3B">From the 10 effective interventions, three were institution based, <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref> and the remaining seven studies were conducted at a community level.</s><s xml:id="_Emztrqm">The reported institutions were worksites for employed participants <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48</ref> and healthcare institutions. <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47</ref></s><s xml:id="_Ety2EFw">There was not much difference in outcome variables based on the intervention setting, but the completion rate of participants in an institution setting tends to be higher than that in the community-based settings.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2." xml:id="_qgzX8fK">Doses of effective intervention</head><p xml:id="_4b9zVNa"><s xml:id="_TMaCVhe">For effective interventions, the amount of weight loss achieved by the interventions was directly associated with the doses of the intervention.</s><s xml:id="_HztHAmd">Significant weight or BMI changes were directly associated with the frequency of text messages; participants in three trials <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47</ref> who received three or more messages per week managed their weight more effectively compared with participants who received less than three messages per week.</s><s xml:id="_pEthTtd">Similarly, longterm follow-up studies resulted in better weight management than short-term studies; interventions that lasted for over 6 months <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43</ref> with frequent messages resulted in a more significant weight loss in adults with overweight and obesity than short lasting interventions.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3." xml:id="_EMfsBYB">Contents of significant intervention</head><p xml:id="_UsND4kY"><s xml:id="_5TMRsmr">With regard to the contents of messages, all of the studies included in this review contained messages on weight monitoring, physical activity tips, and dietary habits.</s><s xml:id="_AajHR5u">They also included messages on motivation, awareness about the consequence of overweight and obesity, and other messages for achieving the desired behavior change in seven studies. <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref></s><s xml:id="_pwUskAV">3]<ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4." xml:id="_wVWDSub">Behavior change techniques and theories</head><p xml:id="_K7wDQy2"><s xml:id="_pXP2uVV">The most reported behavior change techniques used in effective interventions were providing information, <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref> goal setting, <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48</ref> and self-monitoring. <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46,</ref></s><s xml:id="_cTs2Grc"><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48</ref> With regard to the use of theories, transtheoretical model, <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44</ref> social cognitive theory, <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48</ref> cognitive behavioral therapy, <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47</ref> PRECEDE-PROCEED model, <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40</ref> and motivational interviewing were reported. <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43</ref> Inter</s><s xml:id="_6AqPuZW">entions that relied on theoretical frameworks resulted in greater weight loss compared with non-theory-driven studies. "√" refers </s><s xml:id="_3hcpaW5">or checklists that were fulfilled in the included studies.</s><s xml:id="_D9xjM2K">"-" refers for checklists that were not fulfilled or unclear in the included studies.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_3nnJTX2">T A B L E 3 b Continued</head><p xml:id="_nPUjnWh"><s xml:id="_m3eCumu">Author and year of publication Was follow-up complete and if not, were differences between groups in terms of their follow up adequately described and analyzed</s></p><p xml:id="_ak74Ke4"><s xml:id="_Tg5ab5P">Were the outcomes of participants included in any comparisons measured in the same way?</s></p><p xml:id="_HfXqhDq"><s xml:id="_nsdMCjK">Were outcomes measured in a reliable way?</s></p><p xml:id="_j9hBJqQ"><s xml:id="_TB4eW2t">Gusmão LL, 2019</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_3">√ √ √ √</formula><p xml:id="_NfNkgPT"><s xml:id="_2Ygz4eR">Notes: "√" refers for checklists that were fulfilled in the included studies.</s><s xml:id="_fc8DMdf">"-" refers for checklists that were not fulfilled or unclear in the included studies.</s><s xml:id="_sFukqFM">themselves, the involvement of healthcare professionals in the interventions was associated with a more significant weight reduction in three studies. <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48</ref></s><s xml:id="_xvVqN4u">In these studies, health professionals including nurses and physicians counseled participants and responded to their queries during the intervention period.</s><s xml:id="_K45fsQ6">These agents supported different types of participants (adults only, adults with their family, adults with supporting machines) for weight loss.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_q5wQPJu">T A B L E 4 Outcome measures of text message delivered interventions for weight management among adults in developing countries</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6" xml:id="_KfyMRNb">| Effect of text message intervention on weight loss</head><p xml:id="_xYeWknD"><s xml:id="_3D4bHVq">For meta-analysis, mean changes in BMI for each trial were extracted for the intervention and control groups for time periods ranging from 2 months to 2 years.</s><s xml:id="_aW9UQAv">Of the 14 included studies, 10 were eligible for meta-analysis.</s><s xml:id="_rt7gpJb">Three studies were excluded because the effect of the intervention was not clearly presented, and the remaining two studies were excluded because they were follow-up studies of those already included using the same participants.</s><s xml:id="_N9uc8sp">Then, pooled effect sizes were calculated using DerSimonian and Laird random effect model.</s><s xml:id="_Z6UqFyV">The results of meta-analysis show that the effect size of the text message delivered intervention for weight loss in terms of BMI mean differences between the intervention group and the control group was À0.  ).</s><s xml:id="_9mcMTAY">The result of subgroup analysis is presented in Table <ref type="table">6</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.8" xml:id="_zvXS9KZ">| Risk of publication bias across studies</head><p xml:id="_W6zzpv2"><s xml:id="_7sFcqWD">The risk of bias in the included studies was assessed using a variety of statistical methods, such as Begg's and Egger's test of asymmetry test, funnel plot test, and sensitivity analysis including trim-and-fill analysis to fill imputed studies that might have been missed, but the results of these tests were not reported due to the small number of included studies that might result in misleading information. <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">49</ref></s><s xml:id="_BKdmVn6">Funnel plots are weight loss, which is consistent with previous reviews in developing countries in which text messaging positively affects chronic NCD outcomes; <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51</ref> increased adherence to self-care in chronic conditions such as to diabetes; <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">52</ref> and also led to improved level of physical activity and healthy diet habits. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27</ref></s><s xml:id="_zsZAg4P">milar reviews conducted to evaluate the effectiveness of mobile text messages for weight management, <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53</ref> largely based on studies from developed countries such as the United States, the United Kingdom, and Australia, showed that text message interventions helped participants to lose weight. Th</s><s xml:id="_Xpep4S6"> current review agrees with findings in previous studies; although people in developed countries have other alternative sources information and better healthcare systems that can easily be used to create awareness about NCDs, text message interventions were effective to help to lose weight, create awareness about overweight and obesity, and decrease level of behavioral problems.</s><s xml:id="_xZdAvMr">Text message delivered interventions could be scalable for overweight and obesity prevention and control by decreasing behavioral risk factors that could lead to excessive weight gain, such as physical inactivity and unhealthy diet including low consumption of fruit and vegetables, high fats, sugar, salt, and processed and fast foods.</s><s xml:id="_aTHExaM">T A B L E 6 Subgroup analysis text message delivered interventions for weight loss among adults in developing countries Subgroup analysis Studies (n) Participants Pooled effect size Mean difference in BMI change (95% CL) I 2 Sample size &lt;200 5 2404 À0.37 [À0.65,</s><s xml:id="_8hyMGwg">À0.10] 69% &gt;200 4 349 À0.55 [À0.78,</s><s xml:id="_G4m34df">À0.33] 0% Frequency of intervention &gt;1 per week 5 1371 À0.55 [À0.81,</s><s xml:id="_TsDqKEJ">À0.28] 63% 1 or &lt;1 4 1382 À0.34 [À0.58,</s><s xml:id="_TgNhMe6">À0.10] 26% Duration of intervention &gt;6 6 2249 À0.49 [À0.73,</s><s xml:id="_m6TqJcP">À0.25] 47% &lt;6 3 504 À0.30 [À0.57,</s><s xml:id="_QSg5uad">À0.03] 40% Theory Yes 4 1556 À0.44 [À0.76,</s><s xml:id="_QBs2WdQ">À0.13] 60% No 5 1197 À0.40[À0.67,</s><s xml:id="_NfxEdpG">À0.14] 53% Tailored message Yes 3 1249 À0.55 [À0.99,</s><s xml:id="_zwC3Qge">À0.11] 57% No 6 1504 À0.37 [À0.57,</s><s xml:id="_Rrf27Ab">À0.16] 54% With regard to the use of theory in delivering interventions, RCTs that used theory to design and deliver intervention resulted in significantly more change in outcomes than interventions that did not rely on theory.</s><s xml:id="_NhTPgED">This finding is similar with previous reviews on the effectiveness of text delivered messages for overweight management in adolescents <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref> and with other similar reviews in adults.</s><s xml:id="_AcbjcN7"><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref> This is due to the fact that behavioral theories <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55</ref> are effective in transforming behavior and shape interventions from the outset.</s><s xml:id="_MZZKb59">A theory may not result in significant outcome improvement in and of itself, but it does provide options and explanations for achieving the desired behavior.</s></p><p xml:id="_b5RjBBf"><s xml:id="_rp986MU">Besides, the use of theory would be useful for scientific application to refine or reject the theory.</s></p><p xml:id="_rPydfcp"><s xml:id="_63nRH44">On the other hand, the duration and frequency of the interventions were linked with significant weight loss in individuals with overweight and obesity.</s><s xml:id="_Pvu8TT9">This finding is in line with previous systematic reviews of overweight and obesity management <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53</ref> and with another systematic review on physical activity <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27</ref> that showed longer duration and frequent interventions resulted in a more significant weight loss than interventions that lasted shortly or delivered infrequently. Thi</s><s xml:id="_vpTV2Z4"> is understandably because behavior change is a process that requires time and repeated exposure until it becomes a habit and self-efficacy is achieved.</s><s xml:id="_Bh8Xzmn">56 Therefore, consistent and frequent delivery of messages would result in improved adherence to physical activity and healthy diet habit, which could, in turn, contribute to significant weight loss. Pe</s><s xml:id="_yrckf3z">taining to the use of additional adjuvant treatments, RCTs that incorporated combinations of interventions such as phone calls and group meetings resulted in a significant weight loss.</s><s xml:id="_qkr8e5c">This result is also consistent with previous studies 20,22 that most of the interventions that use combinations of treatments tended to increase efficiency of interventions.</s><s xml:id="_AMqa7tt">Using combinations of interventions might increase the adherence of participants to certain behaviors that would not have been realized with a single intervention modality.</s><s xml:id="_9uFKnqP">For instance, combining text messages and phone calls would result in better outcome as one might support or complement the other.</s><s xml:id="_Z5Wnnkn">However, when we use combination of interventions, it is difficult to identify or tell which part of interventions works best for achieving the desired outcome.</s><s xml:id="_kmaREj2">Overweight and obesity are on a continuous rise in developing countries and are becoming major risk factors for chronic diseases.</s><s xml:id="_9VG7xjG"><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">57</ref> Although this can be explained with different theories such as epidemiological, <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">58</ref> nutritional, <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">59</ref> and demographic transitions, <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">60</ref></s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_cZSF7nA"><s xml:id="_JRU5uXx">This indicates the clear lack of comprehensive evidence on the feasibility and effectiveness of mobile text interventions for weight control among adults in developing countries.</s><s xml:id="_DhYsBsm">Therefore, we hypothesized that: H1.</s><s xml:id="_DAy5TpW">Mobile text message delivered interventions for adults with overweight and obesity in developing countries would help in raising awareness and weight loss.</s><s xml:id="_5KNY2Xs">H2.</s><s xml:id="_yVrwyHR">Long-term and regular text messages would result in greater weight loss than short-term and infrequent interventions.</s><s xml:id="_Jw78HdX">H3.</s><s xml:id="_VkcytQ9">Providing information, setting behavioral goals, and self-monitoring would be the most effective behavioral change techniques for weight management.</s><s xml:id="_zj6W54h">H4.</s><s xml:id="_u9kD8JF">Trials that used theory as a framework to develop and deliver the intervention would result in more significant weight loss than studies without theory.</s><s xml:id="_3KQv6Jp">Therefore, the main purpose of this systematic review and metaanalysis is to summarize the evidence on the effectiveness of text message interventions for weight loss among adults with overweight and obesity in developing countries.</s><s xml:id="_fGkA9D5">The result of this study is anticipated to inform future research and health practices in developing countries.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>were: ( 1 )</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_m5VsEmc"><s xml:id="_6CkJceh">How effective are text message-based interventions in obesity management in developing countries?</s><s xml:id="_hWywwK8">(2) If they are effective, which intervention components resulted in weight control?</s><s xml:id="_wrKftYx">(3) What type of behavioral change techniques and theories in adults would result in a significant weight loss?</s><s xml:id="_P3EZCUB">2.2 | Eligibility criteria Eligibility criteria for this study were determined based on the key research questions mentioned above and in consideration of the PICO (population, intervention, comparison, and outcome) framework.</s><s xml:id="_DM5aEKa">The population were adults aged 18 years and above living in developing countries; interventions were text message delivered interventions for weight loss; comparisons were a group of adults without intervention or alternative interventions; outcome(s) was the level of weight loss achieved by the intervention measured in kilograms or measured by decreases in body mass index (BMI); and the desired settings were developing countries.</s><s xml:id="_PvZhF3T">Articles were included if they fulfill the following: RCTs or quasi-experimental studies conducted in adults with overweight and obesity; used text message interventions; measured weight two times at baseline and post-intervention; used at least one behavior change options like weight monitoring, physical activity, and dietary habit; involved healthy adults; conducted in developing countries; and published in English till January 23, 2021.</s><s xml:id="_4WwcuGC">Studies were excluded if they included pediatric population, did not use text message interventions, conducted among participants with chronic conditions such as diabetes and hypertension to avoid the confounding effect of these diseases on weight, incorporated or focused on pharmacological interventions, and not published in English.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>2. 8 |</head><label>8</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_ZqD8BhK"><s xml:id="_mjVhe3J">Synthesis of the resultsThe summary of the included studies was first presented narratively under the following subthemes: study characteristics such as study selection, settings, and risk of bias within study; intervention characteristics such as components of intervention, frequency of interventions, duration of the intervention, behavior change techniques, and use of theory; and effectiveness of the interventions.</s><s xml:id="_U5SnDUw">Then, included articles were assessed for the availability of weight or BMI measures in their pre-and post-intervention evaluation periods to perform meta-analysis to compare the difference in weight change between the intervention and control groups.</s><s xml:id="_WqvNrQj">BMI was chosen because most of the included studies reported the effect of the intervention based on change in BMI.</s><s xml:id="_MmXetN3">To conduct meta-analysis, the change in BMI from baseline to post-intervention was extracted from the eligible studies.When measurement choices were available, we chose measured values than self-reported ones; intention-to-treat analysis (that consider the missing values) versus completers was used.</s><s xml:id="_ABh4vYS">The pooled effect size was estimated using a random effect model in Review Manager (RevMan) of the Cochrane Collaboration (Version 5.4.1).</s><s xml:id="_Y36Cwps">The random effect model was chosen to take into account heterogeneity of variables in the intervention.</s><s xml:id="_JYRghSx">The significance of the estimation was assessed by inspecting the forest plot, confidence intervals (CIs), and p-values.</s><s xml:id="_PFyPwE8">If the estimated effect of intervention did not cross the line of zero effect, CIs did not include zero, and p-value less than 0.05, the intervention was deemed to have significant effect on the outcome.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_6jEZvH5"><s xml:id="_vmy8Rsj">Subgroup analyses were carried out to compare the results of the intervention based on different study characteristics, such as duration of the intervention (intervention lasted less than 6 months versus intervention delivered over more than 6 months); frequency of interventions (daily messages vs. weekly); tailored messaging (tailored messages individualized to the participants based on the initial assessment vs. generic messaging used for delivering the same content); theory (use of theory vs. no theory) and sample sizes (classified small [less than 200 participants] vs. large [&gt;200] based on authors own judgment).</s><s xml:id="_jN52CFm">The categories for subgroup analysis were mutually exclusive and would have to include at least two studies per category.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>11 T</head><label>11</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_ZUQQJNb"><s xml:id="_EDptPfH">Summary of the included studies in the text message delivered interventions for weight loss among adults in developing countriesAuthor, citation, and country Study design Brief description of intervention Study population, age range, and risk level Sample size Quality score Bernabe-Ortiz A, 2020 (Peru) RCT Intervention: This study involved with weekly text messages and monthly phone interviews to reduce the incidence of hypertension and decrease participants' body mass index.</s><s xml:id="_kCpct2a">The results of the intervention were measured at 6 months, 1 year, and 5 years.</s><s xml:id="_Q478Yy7">The trial used transtheoretical model and motivational interviewing techniques to achieve the desired behavior.</s><s xml:id="_8MX2k6X">The messages included tips on behavioral risk factors such as physical activity, diet habit, and weight monitoring and blood pressure control.</s><s xml:id="_GD3uk3G">Control: The control group did not receive text message intervention rather than usual care Adults in Peru between the ages of 30-60 and free from chronic diseases such as diabetes and hypertension, but they were at prehypertension stage (80-90 DBP and 130-139 SBP) 212 12 Müller AM, 2016 (Malaysia) RCT Intervention: The study assessed the effectiveness of text message interventions to increase participants' physical activity level.</s><s xml:id="_N8AekEH">The effect of the intervention on weight loss was assessed as a secondary outcome.</s><s xml:id="_8YCgsnA">The intervention includes five messages per week and exercise booklets for 12 weeks.</s><s xml:id="_vNDggfn">The messages were developed based on behavior change techniques such as providing information and providing rewards/praise for efforts, and it was designed to be interactive.</s><s xml:id="_33uKHSD">Control: Participants in the control group only received booklets of information about physical activity People aged between 55 and 70 (older adults) and did not exercise regularly and had no other associated chronic illness43 10 Nandita A, 2020 (India) RCT Intervention: The study was conducted among prediabetes Indian aged between 35 and 55 years and the UK people aged between 40 and 47.</s><s xml:id="_9J8587U">The primary outcome of the study was conversion of prediabetes, although body mass index change was assessed as a secondary outcome.</s><s xml:id="_m5kcYkp">All participants (both intervention and control) received baseline counseling.</s><s xml:id="_6vn3hzh">The intervention group then received two to three messages per week about healthy lifestyles over a 2-year period.</s><s xml:id="_XS3c4WU">Participants were monitored at 6, 12, and 24 months.</s><s xml:id="_waGeH28">The intervention was designed based on transtheoretical model.</s><s xml:id="_FA7hwaW">The behavior change techniques used include goal setting, physical activity, dietary planning, and personal strategies for lifestyle change.</s><s xml:id="_x5pNyqt">Control: Participants in the control group received baseline counseling Adult people between 35 and 55 without diabetes mellitus, CVD, The study assessed mobile phone-based lifestyle intervention (calls and messages) supplemented with a handbook for cardiovascular risk prevention to reduce cardiovascular risk factors among working adults based on individual assessment results.</s><s xml:id="_7yHX86j">The intervention period was for a year.</s><s xml:id="_9WQDsAT">They did not report any use of theory.</s><s xml:id="_UJC6MHQ">Control: The control group did not receive any form of interventions rather than the usual care Adults aged between 45 and 75 years and without known cardiovascular This study was a quasi-experimental study conducted among overweight/obese women.</s><s xml:id="_m9jdmQH">Participants received initial face-to-face information, booklet that contained food calorie chart, and strategies and recommendations for weight management.</s><s xml:id="_WMAf92f">The intervention group additionally received text-based messages for 2 months.</s><s xml:id="_mUg6beM">Text messages were sent two times per day and weekly feedbacks for self-monitored information.</s><s xml:id="_YJNgvMn">The study did not mention use of theory, but behavior change techniques used were supportive and self-directed weight management strategy.</s><s xml:id="_sXMdrGf">These include strategies for weight loss, food substitutions, finding inner motivations, setting realistic goals, changing perspectives, health eating strategies, and making health eating.</s><s xml:id="_aTK8mAR">Control: Participants in the control group received initial face-to-face information, booklet that contained food calorie chart, and strategies and recommendations for weight management Overweight/obese employed women aged between 25 and 55, and participants were free from any other In this study, text messages were designed to provide tips of lifestyle modifications in men to reduce the incidence of type 2 diabetes mellitus among participants who had impaired glucose tolerance and overweight.</s><s xml:id="_pdFdxu6">Participants, both treatment and control groups, received a standard lifestyle modification advice, but the text messages were delivered only to the treatment group.</s><s xml:id="_5Pyv567">The intervention was based on transtheoretical model to achieve the desired behavior and contains tailored messages based on the stage of change on physical activity, diet, and cues to start physical activity and diet and motivations.</s><s xml:id="_ycz3t9j">Control: Participants in the control group received a standard lifestyle modification advice Having overweight (23 kg/m2) and 35-55 years of age.</s><s xml:id="_KWN9saU">Participants reported free for any other chronic diseases such as diabetes and cancer 537 A B L E 2 (Continued) Author, citation, and country Study design Brief description of intervention Study population, age range, and risk level Sample size Quality score Kaur J, 2016 (India) RCT Intervention: This study used multichannel communication such as short messages services, emails, social network apps, SMART eating apps, and interpersonal communications.</s><s xml:id="_qvFn27S">It was primarily designed to alter unhealthy dietary behaviors such as high intake of fats and low fruit and vegetable consumptions.</s><s xml:id="_VexRQ5y">It assessed body weight changes as a secondary outcome.</s><s xml:id="_FHXEmPn">The intervention was designed based on PRECEDE-PROCEED model.</s><s xml:id="_zURACJD">The outcome of the intervention showed significant change in body mass index of participants.</s><s xml:id="_CCFFJFE">Control: The control group only received traditional nutrition education through pamphlets' information about dietary recommendations and amounts Participants were adults aged between 35 and 70 years and free of chronic comorbidities 712 9 Wong CKH, 2015 (China) RCT Intervention: The study aimed to evaluate the long-term effectiveness (3 years after 2 years of mobile short text messages) interventions.</s><s xml:id="_9PJZs3G">The primary outcome was to compare the incidence of diabetes among the intervention and control groups.</s><s xml:id="_AD4TfXc">Body weight and body mass index changes were assessed as a secondary outcome.</s><s xml:id="_mH7jx3y">Participants were supplied booklets of information for prediabetes and diabetes.</s><s xml:id="_xExYzmK">The intervention consisted of regular text messages (three per week for 3 months, one per week for 3 months, and once per month for 18 months).</s><s xml:id="_tgZFmgG">There was significant change in body weight after the intervention period.</s><s xml:id="_fW895zS">Control: Participants in control group received usual care Study participants were free from chronic conditions such as This study assessed the effect of mHealth (weekly text messages supplemented with monthly phone calls) to modify behavioral risk factors of noncommunicable diseases.</s><s xml:id="_dbWUePj">The intervention mainly focused on physical activity and diet.</s><s xml:id="_EDvX7XT">The result showed significant change in the body mass index of participants in the intervention group.</s><s xml:id="_bBR2e39">The intervention did not mention behavior change theory and tailoring of messages.</s><s xml:id="_Wyzw7g7">Control: The control group did not receive any intervention package Participants were adults who were free from chronic disease such as diabetes and cancer This randomized control trial involved daily text messages with three group sessions and five coaching calls over 6 months.</s><s xml:id="_2Gm4KHg">Self-monitoring and goal setting were the behavior change techniques.</s><s xml:id="_ntP2ym3">The trial used motivational interviewing for phone call coaching.</s><s xml:id="_rAt5wHx">At 6 months of assessment, the intervention group significantly reduced their weight, whereas the control group increased their weight.</s><s xml:id="_nzZdkm7">Control: The control group only received a brief advice session Participants were overweight adults aged 30 to 50 years and free from chronic conditions like diabetes and cancer 123 10 Siriwoen R, 2018 (Thailand)</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>8 / 9 T A B L E 3 a</head><label>893</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_EerSPZD"><s xml:id="_2TUSsMT">This study assessed the feasibility of text message intervention (unidirectional messages) for weight loss among obese patients.</s><s xml:id="_WsWzBqJ">They were delivered once per day in working days for 4 months, which includes physical activity, nutritional, and motivational tips.</s><s xml:id="_pqMMMnq">The messages were based on cognitive behavioral therapy.</s><s xml:id="_NpgaU8F">The intervention has resulted significant weight loss among participants.Control:</s><s xml:id="_7cHUSjV">The study did not involve control groupParticipants were patients with a variety of conditions in primary care settings aged 18 years and over 50 Methodological rigor of the included studies (RCTs) in the review of text message delivered interventions for weight loss among adults in developing countries refers for checklists that were fulfilled in the included studies.</s><s xml:id="_DqmgepU">"-" refers for checklists that were not fulfilled or unclear in the included studies.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_WPxuBWj"><s xml:id="_ebuH89y">Text messages were sent to participants by mobile phones.</s><s xml:id="_MnBRma8">The characteristics of these interventions were synthesized and presented in the following subthemes: settings of the intervention, sample sizes, doses of the intervention, contents of the intervention, behavior change options, use of theory, and additional interventions.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_xnYDXqs"><s xml:id="_wjX6tuv">T A B L E 3 b Methodological rigor of the included studies (non-RCTs) in the review of text message delivered intervention for weight loss among adults in developing countries √</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_unhguce"><s xml:id="_tsEeXB2">The green-shaded color indicates measurements performed and reported in the included studies in this systematic review and meta-analysis.The green-shaded color indicates measurements performed and reported in the included studies in this systematic review and meta-analysis.T A B L E 5 Summary of significant text message delivered interventions for weight loss among adults in developing countriesAgents of change in effective interventionsAlthough the agents of change in effective interventions were adults</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>43 kg/ m 2 (</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_xHPeP7a"><s xml:id="_FH4CR2F">95% CI: À0.63 to À0.23) with I 2 statistics 62% and p-value of heterogeneity less than 0.001.</s><s xml:id="_d8vWPwM">The effect sizes of each study for weight changes over the period of the interventions are presented Figure 2.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>3. 7 |</head><label>7</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_Y4Ueyku"><s xml:id="_n5R3gtA">Subgroup analysisSubgroup analysis was performed based on the following intervention characteristics: duration of the intervention, frequency of intervention, sample sizes, theory use, and message type (tailored message).</s><s xml:id="_DNrQ8mP">Longterm text messages (interventions lasting more than 6 months) were more effective in weight loss (À0.49</s><s xml:id="_UrzMDft">kg/m 2 ) compared with short-term messages (À0.30</s><s xml:id="_f5jxRJ3">kg/m 2 ).</s><s xml:id="_PZTxNEg">Besides, frequently delivered text of messages were associated with greater weight loss (À0.55 kg/m 2 ) compared with messages sent infrequently (less than a week) (À0.34 kg/ m 2 ).</s><s xml:id="_K9pU4nU">Tailoring messages according to individual characteristics was also associated with better weight loss (À0.55 kg/m 2 ) than text message interventions that were not tailored (À0.37 kg/m 2 ).</s><s xml:id="_DxWcwXg">With regard to the use of theory, interventions that relied on theory resulted in a significant and greater weight loss (À0.44 kg/m 2 ), even if the others without theory have also resulted in significant amount of weight loss (À0.40 kg/m 2 ).</s><s xml:id="_utexUKz">This could be because they may have used theory to design and implement their intervention but may not have reported it or fit it into theoretical framework.</s><s xml:id="_FGJNPRa">On the other hand, interventions with relatively adequate sample sizes resulted in better weight loss (À0.55 kg/m 2 ) than interventions with relatively small sample sizes (À0.37 kg/m 2</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>presented in Figure 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_NYWZd7m"><s xml:id="_B52RUpa">to show normality of data distribution of the included studies.</s><s xml:id="_yJ72xqw">The funnel plots might not fulfil the assumption of normal distribution, mainly because the characteristics of the interventions in the included studies were not stringently identical, that is, in addition to text messages, some had co-interventions in the form of phone calls and group meetings.</s><s xml:id="_EpuethY">F I G U R E 2 A forest plot of mean difference in body mass index (BMI) change at post-intervention among adults in developing countries This review identified 12 studies that examined the effect of text message interventions for weight loss among adults in developing countries.</s><s xml:id="_3tDp4bw">Ten of the included studies reported a significant effect of the intervention on weight loss.</s><s xml:id="_jnHn8v4">The remaining studies, although did not find significant weight loss, they showed positive changes in behavioral risk factors: increased level of physical activity and improved diet habit such as increased fruit and vegetable consumption or reducing fat, sugar, and salt intakes.</s><s xml:id="_rdZEXPZ">The meta-analysis showed that text message interventions were significantly associated with</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>F I G U R E 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_z6mP9Vh"><s xml:id="_d48uy5j">Distribution of studies included in review of the effect of text messaging for weight loss in the funnel graph Concerning the main behavioral change options used for overweight treatment, this review identified messages to increase physical activity level and diet habit modifications, such as increasing fruit and vegetable consumption and decreasing fat consumptions, which were the main intervention areas.</s><s xml:id="_VAvGMhu">Behavior modification techniques used to change these interventions areas were providing information, set behavioral goals, monitoring, motivation, and providing cues.</s><s xml:id="_wjrgErY">These behavioral change options were consistently reported in previous reviews,<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> and also another review supported these effective behavior change techniques to increase physical activity and healthy eating in adults with overweight and obesity.<ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54</ref></s><s xml:id="_hz62BCQ">This shows that increasing physical activity and healthy diet is the cornerstone of overweight and obesity management in both developing and developed countries, and the identified behavioral change techniques are effective and applicable in all contexts to prevent and control excess weight by modifying behavioral risk factors of weight gain.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>4. 1 |</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_NVHc624"><s xml:id="_wV3YeKn">Implications for practiceOur findings have clear implication for those developing responses to the rising burden of NCDs like cardiovascular diseases, diabetes mellitus, cancer, and chronic respiratory diseases, which are strongly linked to factors such as overweight and obesity. 1 The effectiveness of mobile text-based interventions aimed at preventing and controlling overweight and/or obesity revealed by this study should be considered by those developing health promotion interventions and raising awareness to help people manage their weight.</s><s xml:id="_V2E4dpy">In particular, it is important for health policy makers and stakeholders developing such interventions to consider those strategies this review found most effective, in terms of regularity of messaging; the importance of including weight monitoring, diet, and physical activity for holistic health promotion; and the use of behavior change techniques.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>4 . 2 |</head><label>42</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_Fk6wswT"><s xml:id="_d9ryqN2">prevention and control programs remain largely inadequate in these countries.</s><s xml:id="_s2SK6yy">Mobile technologies are among rapidly expanding infrastructures in developing countries, but their use for health promotion and diseases prevention has not been well established.</s><s xml:id="_CmcJ99Z">The current review suggests that text message interventions can create awareness and thereby result in effective weight management among adults in developing countries.</s><s xml:id="_AdGr9hy">This highlights that text message interventions can be used as an alternative intervention program for overweight and obesity management in these settings.</s><s xml:id="_k9sAMp9">This systematic review showed that text message interventions were effective for weight loss among adults in developing countries; adults who were overweight and supported with text messages lost significantly more weight than who were not supported.</s><s xml:id="_v8qsUFf">Text message interventions helped people to increase their awareness and initiate behavioral changes.</s><s xml:id="_agAJMkd">Most of the interventions were designed with a priori formative research to determine willingness of participants, contents, and duration of the interventions.</s><s xml:id="_zBWRZXc">Longer duration and more frequent interventions were associated with greater weight loss.</s><s xml:id="_zQGgZxW">This is because behavior change is a process and needs time to establish.</s><s xml:id="_FPzrVWb">Thus, when designing weight loss interventions, considering participants' need, longer duration, and persistence could result in better weight control.</s><s xml:id="_57aJquP">Concerning the use of behavior change techniques, studies that involved behavior change options such as physical activity and healthy diet habit with techniques like providing information, self-monitoring, and goal setting resulted in significant weight loss.</s><s xml:id="_hDrApCH">This demonstrates that weight loss programs and interventions would be more beneficial if they incorporated effective behavior change techniques and theories.</s><s xml:id="_KzhDBdN">Recommendations for future research Based on this systematic review and meta-analysis, the following recommendations are drawn for future RCTs that use text message delivered interventions for overweight and obesity treatment.</s><s xml:id="_292mAxm">Most of the included studies were conducted in urban areas and mainly considered people with high literacy level and were relatively close to digital technologies and other health information sources.</s><s xml:id="_ZyjwTXA">We do not have evidence on the effectiveness of text-based interventions for weight management in socioeconomically disadvantaged and rural or remote community-dwelling groups.</s><s xml:id="_eRUsJjT">Therefore, we recommend future researchers to test the feasibility and effectiveness of mobilebased text messaging for weight loss in this group of populations.</s><s xml:id="_vHCn56N">In addition, most of the studies included in this systematic review and meta-analysis were conducted among people with overweight and/or obesity and those who volunteered to participate.</s><s xml:id="_e3Yw5VP">These participants could be relatively more health conscious and might easily adapt the desired behavior, which limits the generalizability of the findings to other people with poorer health awareness.</s><s xml:id="_5bZcgCX">We suggest future RCTs to assess the relative effectiveness of mobile text message interventions by recruiting diverse group of participants using representative sampling techniques for better generalizations.</s><s xml:id="_Au85EGz">Although some of the published trials reported the effectiveness of text message-based weight loss interventions, they were conducted targeting a relatively small sample size over a short study duration.</s><s xml:id="_GdauSA8">This makes it difficult to draw firm conclusion about the effectiveness of mobile text message interventions for weight loss.</s><s xml:id="_NXrbyKg">Therefore, studies targeting large representative sample sizes with longer duration of follow-ups may provide stronger evidence to better understand the effectiveness of such types of weight loss interventions.</s><s xml:id="_qm26JE3">Most of the interventions included in this study were supplemented with additional interventions such as telephone calls, guideline/documents, face-to-face coaching, and meetings; therefore, it is difficult to assume that weight loss is caused only due to the text message interventions.</s><s xml:id="_PJEpBjP">This indicates the need for evidence to understand the differential advantage of conducting text message RCTs.</s><s xml:id="_6eq8ywE">In addition, some studies used behavior change theories and were effective.</s><s xml:id="_3q5q8Ak">But theories are different among the studies and make it difficult to choose and recommend one effective theory for weight management.</s><s xml:id="_RKsxPMk">Therefore, we recommend future researchers to replicate some of the effective theories used in previous studies to understand the best theoretical foundation for an effective intervention.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>4. 3 |</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_CnJ3AyU"><s xml:id="_q9MVb4A">Strengths and limitationsThis review summarized evidence on text message delivered interventions for overweight management among adults in developing countries.</s><s xml:id="_ek4hbn7">Previous reviews were focused on studies in high-income countries, and their findings might not be equally applicable in people from developing countries due to differences in culture, technology infrastructure, health system, and health-seeking behaviors.</s><s xml:id="_8TWdD4b">It is the strength of this review to present comprehensive evidence on the effectiveness of text message delivered interventions for weight loss among adults in developing countries.The search terms used in this review did not use any limits except to the restriction to studies published in English.</s><s xml:id="_QuyCn54">Thus, the search strategy is believed to have provided all available RCTs on weight and text messages published in English language.</s><s xml:id="_SnbT65r">We also used both narrative and quantitative approaches to report the results in a more practical and tangible way.</s><s xml:id="_4jR7Cfn">Although the review presented the feasibility of text-based interventions for weight loss among adults in LMICs, most of the included studies were conducted in upper middle-income countries, such as China and India, highlighting the need to cautiously interpret the findings in the lower bracket of the LMIC setting like, for example, parts of the sub-Saharan African region.With regard to the nature of the included studies, some studies involve a priori formative research to develop interventions, some conducted with small sample sizes, some did not use randomization, some were conducted for long duration others for short, and some had had low methodological rigor, which might have affected the meta-analysis result to precisely estimate the mean weight loss achieved by the intervention.</s><s xml:id="_Nh6D66X">Finally, most of the included studies used different forms of behavior change options, including physical activity, diet monitoring, and weight monitoring, and some studies also used different theories.</s><s xml:id="_F8YszSp">This variation among studies makes it difficult to choose the most effective theory and behavior change options for weight loss in adults from developing settings.</s><s xml:id="_VNKjpxe">Beyond this, measurements of the target behaviors such as physical activity and diet habit were self-reported in some studies, which might have overestimated the effect of the interventions.</s><s xml:id="_AWcs7GQ">5 | CONCLUSION This systematic review and meta-analysis showed that text message delivered interventions for weight loss among adults in developing countries are apparently effective given the limited evidence to reach a rough conclusion.</s><s xml:id="_x4ug9YJ">From 12 trials, 10 reported significant effect of text message interventions for weight loss.</s><s xml:id="_TucwTnJ">Frequent and extended interventions and use of behavioral theories resulted in a more significant weight reduction in adults with overweight and obesity.</s><s xml:id="_RzPUzZw">This systematic review provides evidence on the use of text message delivered interventions to provide information, to create awareness, to decrease behavioral risks for weight gain such as physical inactivity and poor dietary habits, and to reduce weight, although additional larger RCTs are needed for further conclusion.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="5,84.70,311.30,425.82,402.86" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p xml:id="_BNy2Svg"><s xml:id="_pthDW4x">1467789x, 2022, 1, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/obr.13339</s><s xml:id="_kAg9nsP">by University Of Iowa Libraries -Serials Acquisitions, Wiley Online Library on [04/08/2025].</s><s xml:id="_xZNBnby">See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions)</s><s xml:id="_JV3G82m">on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License</s></p></note>
		</body>
		<back>


			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_SHdT4ZJ">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p xml:id="_6kWuX6e"><s xml:id="_9GHrRbK">Not applicable.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_VrvUrNW">Author and year of publication</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_MKfHWAj">CONFLICT OF INTEREST</head><p xml:id="_2SRyVsP"><s xml:id="_j5kJeJm">The authors declare that they have no competing interest.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_qWepXH3">SUPPORTING INFORMATION</head><p xml:id="_rjNfY55"><s xml:id="_EeUnpEW">Additional supporting information may be found in the online version of the article at the publisher's website.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_Kx7gRKD">Global status report on noncommunicable diseases 2014</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5040/9781350220447.0022</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>World Health Organization</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">World Health Organization. Global status report on non- communicable diseases 2014. World Health Organization; 2014.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_R2VBQJB">Diabetes in developing countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Misra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Gopalan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Jayawardena</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_mExrkFh">J Diabetes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="522" to="539" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Misra A, Gopalan H, Jayawardena R, et al. Diabetes in developing countries. J Diabetes. 2019;11(7):522-539.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_rxdkHPU">Global health observatory (GHO) data; top 10 causes of death</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4135/9781412963855.n1236</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<publisher>World Health Organization</publisher>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>WHO</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">World Health Organization. Global health observatory (GHO) data; top 10 causes of death. WHO; 2017.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_t3vwBcy">Global, regional, and national comparative risk assessment of 84 behavioural, environmental and occupational, and metabolic risks or clusters of risks, 1990-2016: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Alam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hankey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Grf</forename><surname>Collaborators</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_jfbKJST">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">390</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1345" to="1422" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Alam K, Hankey GJ, Collaborators GRF. Global, regional, and national comparative risk assessment of 84 behavioural, environmental and occupational, and metabolic risks or clusters of risks, 1990-2016: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2016. Lan- cet. 2017;390(10100):1345-1422.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/obesity-and-overweight" />
		<title level="m" xml:id="_P4p3Peh">Obesity and overweight; key facts</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Geneva</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>WHO</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">World Health Organization. Obesity and overweight; key facts. WHO, Geneva; 2020. https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/ detail/obesity-and-overweight</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_3Jc2DJf">Global, regional, and national comparative risk assessment of 84 behavioural, environmental and occupational, and metabolic risks or clusters of risks for 195 countries and territories, 1990-2017: a systematic analysis for the global burden of disease study 2017</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/sj.bdj.2015.751</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_yqf3rCQ">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">392</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1923" to="1994" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Global health metrics</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Global health metrics. Global, regional, and national comparative risk assessment of 84 behavioural, environmental and occupational, and metabolic risks or clusters of risks for 195 countries and territories, 1990-2017: a systematic analysis for the global burden of disease study 2017. Lancet. 2018;392:1923-1994.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_GQ5d5jB">Global health risks: mortality and burden of disease attributable to selected major risks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mathers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Stevens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mascarenhas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<publisher>World Health Organization</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mathers C, Stevens G, Mascarenhas M. Global health risks: mortality and burden of disease attributable to selected major risks. World Health Organization; 2009.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_B5tsvdC">mHealth application areas and technology combinations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Abaza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Marschollek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3414/me17-05-0003</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_yzNfXVX">Methods Inf Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">01</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="e122" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Abaza H, Marschollek M. mHealth application areas and technology combinations. Methods Inf Med. 2017;56(S 01):e105-e122.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_sqdhhqe">Noncommunicable disease risk factors and mobile phones: a proposed research agenda</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hyder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wosu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Gibson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Labrique</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Pariyo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/jmir.7246</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_REfd2k7">J Med Internet Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e133</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hyder AA, Wosu AC, Gibson DG, Labrique AB, Ali J, Pariyo GW. Non- communicable disease risk factors and mobile phones: a proposed research agenda. J Med Internet Res. 2017;19(5):e133.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_fGcEPaW">Mobile technology, cancer prevention, and health status among diverse, low-income adults</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Purnell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Griffith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Eddens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kreuter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_5BswmaS">Am J Health Promot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="397" to="402" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Purnell JQ, Griffith J, Eddens KS, Kreuter MW. Mobile technology, cancer prevention, and health status among diverse, low-income adults. Am J Health Promot. 2014;28(6):397-402.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Df4PA7F">Mobile health devices as tools for worldwide cardiovascular risk reduction and disease management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Piette</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>List</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Rana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Townsend</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Striplin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Heisler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1161/circulationaha.114.008723</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_NAuUSDj">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2012" to="2027" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Piette JD, List J, Rana GK, Townsend W, Striplin D, Heisler M. Mobile health devices as tools for worldwide cardiovascular risk reduction and disease management. Circulation. 2015;132(21):2012- 2027.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_GuQ83ke">Mobile phone text messaging for improving secondary prevention in cardiovascular diseases: a systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Unal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Giakoumidakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Patelarou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_mewKV4k">Heart Lung</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="351" to="359" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Unal E, Giakoumidakis K, Khan E, Patelarou E. Mobile phone text messaging for improving secondary prevention in cardiovascular dis- eases: a systematic review. Heart Lung. 2018;47(4):351-359.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_3JgzhZD">The effectiveness of mobile phone text messaging in improving medication adherence for patients with chronic diseases: a systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Sarabi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Sadoughi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Orak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Bahaadinbeigy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_RUvGMT4">Iran Red Crescent Med J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">25183</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sarabi RE, Sadoughi F, Orak RJ, Bahaadinbeigy K. The effectiveness of mobile phone text messaging in improving medication adherence for patients with chronic diseases: a systematic review. Iran Red Cres- cent Med J. 2016;18(5):e25183.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_jhucZvW">Effect of lifestyle-focused text messaging on risk factor modification in patients with coronary heart disease: a randomized clinical trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Chow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Redfern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hillis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ZjjMxpY">JAMA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">314</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1255" to="1263" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Chow CK, Redfern J, Hillis GS, et al. Effect of lifestyle-focused text messaging on risk factor modification in patients with coro- nary heart disease: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA. 2015;314(12): 1255-1263.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Yts7Rv6">A randomized trial of Text2Quit: a text messaging program for smoking cessation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Abroms</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Boal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Simmens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mendel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Windsor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_H5EAKvh">Am J Prev Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="242" to="250" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Abroms LC, Boal AL, Simmens SJ, Mendel JA, Windsor RA. A random- ized trial of Text2Quit: a text messaging program for smoking cessa- tion. Am J Prev Med. 2014;47(3):242-250.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_8j5F8yF">Health technologies and innovation in the global health arena</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Sinha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Barry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1056/nejmp1108040</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Z6JT9SR">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">365</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="779" to="782" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sinha SR, Barry M. Health technologies and innovation in the global health arena. N Engl J Med. 365(9):779-782.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Thupae</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_vUTk9s9">The feasibility of using short message service (SMS) technology in the management of chronic diseases in 3 pilot clinics in Bushbuckridge</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Mpumalanga</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Thupae D. The feasibility of using short message service (SMS) tech- nology in the management of chronic diseases in 3 pilot clinics in Bushbuckridge, Mpumalanga. 2014.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qwGTwg9">Short message service (SMS) applications for disease prevention in developing countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Déglise</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Suggs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Odermatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_QHr2DNv">J Med Internet Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Déglise C, Suggs LS, Odermatt P. Short message service (SMS) appli- cations for disease prevention in developing countries. J Med Internet Res. 2012;14(1):e3.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_8RGSqSZ">Text messaging interventions for improvement in physical activity and sedentary behavior in youth: systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ludwig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Arthur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Sculthorpe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fountain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Buchan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/10799</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_q8U9jmU">JMIR Mhealth Uhealth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e10799</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ludwig K, Arthur R, Sculthorpe N, Fountain H, Buchan DS. Text mes- saging interventions for improvement in physical activity and seden- tary behavior in youth: systematic review. JMIR Mhealth Uhealth. 2018;6(9):e10799.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_myeBayB">Effectiveness of text message interventions for weight management in adolescents: systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Partridge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Raeside</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Singleton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hyun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Redfern</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_BRu57ff">JMIR Mhealth Uhealth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15849</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Partridge SR, Raeside R, Singleton A, Hyun K, Redfern J. Effectiveness of text message interventions for weight management in adolescents: systematic review. JMIR Mhealth Uhealth. 2020;8(5):e15849.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_zJrkqZJ">A systematic review and metaanalysis of interventions for weight management using text messaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Siopis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Chey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Allman-Farinelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/jhn.12207</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Y2dxgnm">J Hum Nutr Diet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Siopis G, Chey T, Allman-Farinelli M. A systematic review and meta- analysis of interventions for weight management using text messag- ing. J Hum Nutr Diet. 2015;28:1-15.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_HHNG2Bw">A systematic review with meta-analyses of text message-delivered behaviour change interventions for weight loss and weight loss maintenance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Skinner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Gonet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Currie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hoddinott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Dombrowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_9w5q6EK">Obes Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e12999</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Skinner R, Gonet V, Currie S, Hoddinott P, Dombrowski SU. A sys- tematic review with meta-analyses of text message-delivered behav- iour change interventions for weight loss and weight loss maintenance. Obes Rev. 2020;21(6):e12999.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_KPmYyJ8">Mobile phone text messages to support treatment adherence in adults with high blood pressure (SMS-text adherence support [StAR]) a single-blind, randomized trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Bobrow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Farmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Springer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1161/circulationaha.115.017530</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_suZ8yxY">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">133</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="592" to="600" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bobrow K, Farmer AJ, Springer D, et al. Mobile phone text messages to support treatment adherence in adults with high blood pressure (SMS-text adherence support [StAR]) a single-blind, randomized trial. Circulation. 2016;133(6):592-600.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_DjzyQUj">SMS education for the promotion of diabetes self-management in low &amp; middle income countries: a pilot randomized controlled trial in Egypt</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Abaza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Marschollek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/s12889-017-4973-5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ZpYj5h7">BMC Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">962</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Abaza H, Marschollek M. SMS education for the promotion of diabe- tes self-management in low &amp; middle income countries: a pilot ran- domized controlled trial in Egypt. BMC Public Health. 2017;17(1):962.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_WJJvdw5">Use of a text message program to raise type 2 diabetes risk awareness and promote health behavior change (part I): assessment of participant reach and adoption</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Buis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hirzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Turske</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Des</forename><surname>Jardins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Yarandi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bondurant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/jmir.2928</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_brCz7nK">J Med Internet Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e281</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Buis LR, Hirzel L, Turske SA, Des Jardins TR, Yarandi H, Bondurant P. Use of a text message program to raise type 2 diabetes risk aware- ness and promote health behavior change (part I): assessment of par- ticipant reach and adoption. J Med Internet Res. 2013;15(12):e281.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_75Mnf2X">The effect of text messages to support diabetes self-management in developing countries-the TEXT4DSM study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Van Olmen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kegels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Korachais</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Man</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Kristien</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kalobu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jcte.2016.12.005</idno>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">van Olmen J, Kegels G, Korachais C, Man JD, Kristien V, Kalobu J. The effect of text messages to support diabetes self-management in developing countries-the TEXT4DSM study.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_GwrJe7Z">The effectiveness of e-&amp; mHealth interventions to promote physical activity and healthy diets in developing countries: a systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Alley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Schoeppe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Vandelanotte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/s12966-016-0434-2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_t8n8SfY">Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Müller AM, Alley S, Schoeppe S, Vandelanotte C. The effectiveness of e-&amp; mHealth interventions to promote physical activity and healthy diets in developing countries: a systematic review. Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act. 2016;13(1):1-14.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_SnBSr3q">Assessing research activity on priority interventions for non-communicable disease prevention in low-and middleincome countries: a bibliometric analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Geneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_CzNJvMj">Glob Health Action</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">18847</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Jones AC, Geneau R. Assessing research activity on priority interven- tions for non-communicable disease prevention in low-and middle- income countries: a bibliometric analysis. Glob Health Action. 2012; 5(1):18847.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_mWDPjmR">The PRISMA statement for reporting systematic reviews and meta-analyses of studies that evaluate health care interventions: explanation and elaboration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Liberati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Altman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tetzlaff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2009.06.006</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_3d5ENES">J Clin Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="e34" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Liberati A, Altman DG, Tetzlaff J, et al. The PRISMA statement for reporting systematic reviews and meta-analyses of studies that evalu- ate health care interventions: explanation and elaboration. J Clin Epidemiol. 2009;62(10):e1-e34.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<idno type="DOI">10.7717/peerj.3785/fig-3</idno>
		<ptr target="https://blogs.worldbank.org/opendata/new-world-bank-country-classifications-income-level-2020-2021" />
		<title level="m" xml:id="_ez7yhhe">New World Bank country classifications by income level</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>World Bank</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2020" to="2021" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">World Bank. New World Bank country classifications by income level: 2020-2021. https://blogs.worldbank.org/opendata/new-world-bank- country-classifications-income-level-2020-2021</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_dZPrEWV">Cochrane community</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Covidence</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.covidence.org/reviewers" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-05">2020. 05/04/2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Covidence. Cochrane community. Published 2020. Accessed 05/04/2021. https://www.covidence.org/reviewers</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">The</forename><surname>Joanna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Briggs</forename><surname>Institute</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://jbi.global/sites/default/files/2020-08/Checklist_for_RCTs.pdf" />
		<title level="m" xml:id="_pcxZcXG">Critical appraisal tools for use in JBI systematic reviews. Checklist for randomized control trials</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">The Joanna Briggs Institute. Critical appraisal tools for use in JBI sys- tematic reviews. Checklist for randomized control trials. https://jbi. global/sites/default/files/2020-08/Checklist_for_RCTs.pdf</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">The</forename><surname>Joanna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Briggs</forename><surname>Institute</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://jbi.global/sites/default/files/2019-05/JBI_Quasi-Experimental_Appraisal_Tool2017_0.pdf" />
		<title level="m" xml:id="_SGhX9kh">Critical appraisal tools for use in JBI systematic reviews. Checklist for Quasi-Experimental Studies (nonrandomized experimental studies</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">The Joanna Briggs Institute. Critical appraisal tools for use in JBI sys- tematic reviews. Checklist for Quasi-Experimental Studies (non- randomized experimental studies). https://jbi.global/sites/default/ files/2019-05/JBI_Quasi-Experimental_Appraisal_Tool2017_0.pdf</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/obesity-and-overweight" />
		<title level="m" xml:id="_ACyF5pu">Obesity and overweight</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Geneva</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>WHO</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">World Health Organisation. Obesity and overweight. WHO, Geneva; 2020. https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/obesity- and-overweight</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jbi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://wiki.jbi.global/display/MANUAL/JBI+Manual+for+Evidence+Synthesis" />
		<title level="m" xml:id="_VRxspGR">Manual for evidence synthesis</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">JBI. Manual for evidence synthesis. https://wiki.jbi.global/display/ MANUAL/JBI+Manual+for+Evidence+Synthesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_vbV8CXd">Cochrane Handbook for Systematic Reviews of Interventions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Higgins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chandler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Higgins JP, Thomas J, Chandler J, et al. Cochrane Handbook for Sys- tematic Reviews of Interventions. John Wiley &amp; Sons; 2019.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qeP9hu4">A pragmatic and scalable strategy using mobile technology to promote sustained lifestyle changes to prevent type 2 diabetes in India and the UK: a randomised controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nanditha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Thomson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Susairaj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00125-019-05061-y</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_fhuGUUF">Diabetologia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="486" to="496" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nanditha A, Thomson H, Susairaj P, et al. A pragmatic and scalable strategy using mobile technology to promote sustained lifestyle changes to prevent type 2 diabetes in India and the UK: a randomised controlled trial. Diabetologia. 2020;63(3):486-496.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_4W7uRsC">Mobile phone-based lifestyle intervention for reducing overall cardiovascular disease risk in Guangzhou, China: a pilot study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lin</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_D3hY2qR">Int J Environ Res Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15993" to="16004" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Liu Z, Chen S, Zhang G, Lin A. Mobile phone-based lifestyle interven- tion for reducing overall cardiovascular disease risk in Guangzhou, China: a pilot study. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2015;12(12): 15993-16004.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_X5uR5rC">Effectiveness of mobile phone messaging in prevention of type 2 diabetes by lifestyle modification in men in India: a prospective, parallel-group, randomised controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ramachandran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Snehalatha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ram</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_F2DeY9J">Lancet Diab Endocrinol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="198" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ramachandran A, Snehalatha C, Ram J, et al. Effectiveness of mobile phone messaging in prevention of type 2 diabetes by lifestyle modifi- cation in men in India: a prospective, parallel-group, randomised con- trolled trial. Lancet Diab Endocrinol. 2013;1(3):191-198.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_NtfxdVc">Effectiveness of information technology-enabled &apos;SMART Eating&apos; health promotion intervention: a cluster randomized controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kaur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kaur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Chakrapani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Webster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0225892</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_fSQSkFP">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e0225892</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kaur J, Kaur M, Chakrapani V, Webster J, Santos JA, Kumar R. Effec- tiveness of information technology-enabled &apos;SMART Eating&apos; health promotion intervention: a cluster randomized controlled trial. PLoS ONE. 2020;15(1):e0225892.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_xbPAnYG">A short message service (SMS) intervention to prevent diabetes in Chinese professional drivers with prediabetes: a pilot single-blinded randomized controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Fung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Siu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.diabres.2013.10.002</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_RxhdTZB">Diabetes Res Clin Pract</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="158" to="166" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Wong CK, Fung CS, Siu S, et al. A short message service (SMS) inter- vention to prevent diabetes in Chinese professional drivers with pre- diabetes: a pilot single-blinded randomized controlled trial. Diabetes Res Clin Pract. 2013;102(3):158-166.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_5Czk8Fn">Effect of mHealth on modifying behavioural risk-factors of non-communicable diseases in an adult, rural population in Delhi, India</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sharma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Banerjee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ingle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Garg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.21037/mhealth.2017.08.03</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_fz8QAru">Mhealth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">42</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sharma M, Banerjee B, Ingle G, Garg S. Effect of mHealth on modifying behavioural risk-factors of non-communicable diseases in an adult, rural population in Delhi, India. Mhealth. 2017;3:42.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_d7KcU6F">A text messaging-assisted randomized lifestyle weight loss clinical trial among overweight adults in Beijing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Levine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/oby.20686</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_4AnAtPW">Obesity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="E37" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lin PH, Wang Y, Levine E, et al. A text messaging-assisted random- ized lifestyle weight loss clinical trial among overweight adults in Bei- jing. Obesity. 2014;22(5):E29-E37.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_yQqBa4w">Sustainability of mHealth effects on cardiometabolic risk factors: five-year results of a randomized clinical trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bernabe-Ortiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pauschardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Diez-Canseco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Miranda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_4zkgnJv">J Med Internet Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">14595</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bernabe-Ortiz A, Pauschardt J, Diez-Canseco F, Miranda JJ. Sustain- ability of mHealth effects on cardiometabolic risk factors: five-year results of a randomized clinical trial. J Med Internet Res. 2020;22(4): e14595.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_dkP2PyQ">Text messaging for exercise promotion in older adults from an upper-middle-income country: randomized controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Khoo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/jmir.5235</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_V268ESy">J Med Internet Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Müller AM, Khoo S, Morris T. Text messaging for exercise promotion in older adults from an upper-middle-income country: randomized controlled trial. J Med Internet Res. 2016; 18(1):e5.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_xMKYj6a">Mobile phone short message service (SMS) for weight management in Iranian overweight and obese women: a pilot study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Faghanipour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hajikazemi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nikpour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Shariatpanahi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hosseini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Ty6gNen">Int J Telemed Appl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2013</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">785654</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Faghanipour S, Hajikazemi E, Nikpour S, Shariatpanahi SA, Hosseini AF. Mobile phone short message service (SMS) for weight management in Iranian overweight and obese women: a pilot study. Int J Telemed Appl. 2013;2013:785654.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_YpWZzsf">Implementation of a text message intervention to promote behavioural change and weight loss among overweight and obese Brazilian primary care patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gusmão</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ribeiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mvr</forename><surname>Souza-Silva</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_KFB9tak">J Telemed Telecare</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="476" to="483" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Gusmão LL, Ribeiro AL, Souza-Silva MVR, et al. Implementation of a text message intervention to promote behavioural change and weight loss among overweight and obese Brazilian primary care patients. J Telemed Telecare. 2019;25(8):476-483.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_DXqhayr">Effectiveness of a weight management program applying mobile health technology as a supporting tool for overweight and obese working women</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Siriwoen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chongsuwat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tansakul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Siri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Kv5UqQG">Asia Pac J Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="572" to="581" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Siriwoen R, Chongsuwat R, Tansakul S, Siri S. Effectiveness of a weight management program applying mobile health technology as a supporting tool for overweight and obese working women. Asia Pac J Public Health. 2018;30(6):572-581.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_y2uVPRs">The appropriateness of asymmetry tests for publication bias in meta-analyses: a large survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Ioannidis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Trikalinos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1503/cmaj.060410</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_PFJSbND">Cmaj</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">176</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1091" to="1096" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ioannidis JP, Trikalinos TA. The appropriateness of asymmetry tests for publication bias in meta-analyses: a large survey. Cmaj. 2007; 176(8):1091-1096.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ecewFZv">The impact of mobile health interventions on chronic disease outcomes in developing countries: a systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Beratarrechea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Willner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Jahangir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ciapponi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rubinstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_xpdcF6u">Telemed e-Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="82" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Beratarrechea A, Lee AG, Willner JM, Jahangir E, Ciapponi A, Rubinstein A. The impact of mobile health interventions on chronic disease outcomes in developing countries: a systematic review. Telemed e-Health. 2014;20(1):75-82.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_2sQVnSf">mHealth interventions to counter noncommunicable diseases in developing countries: still an uncertain promise</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Beratarrechea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Moyano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Irazola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rubinstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_gdj4Wtb">Cardiol Clin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Beratarrechea A, Moyano D, Irazola V, Rubinstein A. mHealth inter- ventions to counter noncommunicable diseases in developing coun- tries: still an uncertain promise. Cardiol Clin. 2017;35(1):13-30.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_kbMdWxG">mHealth text and voice communication for monitoring people with chronic diseases in low-resource settings: a realist review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Watkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Goudge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Omez-Olivé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Huxley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Dodd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Griffiths</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_XzMJvrS">BMJ Glob Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">543</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Watkins JA, Goudge J, G omez-Olivé FX, Huxley C, Dodd K, Griffiths F. mHealth text and voice communication for monitoring people with chronic diseases in low-resource settings: a realist review. BMJ Glob Health. 2018;3(2):e000543.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_BR6FeDc">Effect of mobile health on obese adults: a systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S-H</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y-K</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ZUsxUhE">Healthc Inform Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Park S-H, Hwang J, Choi Y-K. Effect of mobile health on obese adults: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Healthc Inform Res. 2019; 25(1):12-26.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_9YKSxbF">Effective behaviour change techniques for physical activity and healthy eating in overweight and obese adults; systematic review and meta-regression analyses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Samdal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Eide</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Barth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Meland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/s12966-017-0494-y</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_AjemkaG">Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Samdal GB, Eide GE, Barth T, Williams G, Meland E. Effective behav- iour change techniques for physical activity and healthy eating in overweight and obese adults; systematic review and meta-regression analyses. Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act. 2017;14(1):1-14.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_xUrKpwU">The use of theory in health behavior research from 2000 to 2005: a systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Painter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Borba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hynes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mays</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Glanz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_5JChhTg">Ann Behav Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="358" to="362" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Painter JE, Borba CP, Hynes M, Mays D, Glanz K. The use of theory in health behavior research from 2000 to 2005: a systematic review. Ann Behav Med. 2008;35(3):358-362.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_5uBPyXv">Cognitive processes mediating behavioral change</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bandura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Adams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Beyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037//0022-3514.35.3.125</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_C945KQp">J Pers Soc Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="139" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bandura A, Adams NE, Beyer J. Cognitive processes mediating behav- ioral change. J Pers Soc Psychol. 1977;35(3):125-139.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_UN6jBtY">The global burden of disease, 1990-2020</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lopez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/3218</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_kWdYdyR">Nat Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1241" to="1243" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lopez AD, Murray CC. The global burden of disease, 1990-2020. Nat Med. 1998;4(11):1241-1243.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_99kCGp7">The epidemiologic transition theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mackenbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/jech.48.4.329-a</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_m68KbfS">J Epidemiol Community Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="329" to="331" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mackenbach JP. The epidemiologic transition theory. J Epidemiol Community Health. 1994;48(4):329-331.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_jrFgxHh">The nutrition transition in the developing world</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Popkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_pDQMghp">Dev Policy Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5-6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="581" to="597" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Popkin BM. The nutrition transition in the developing world. Dev Policy Rev. 2003;21(5-6):581-597.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_XgcmR7F">Demographic transition theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kirk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/0032472031000149536</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_dwWDf6a">Popul Stud</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="361" to="387" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kirk D. Demographic transition theory. Popul Stud. 1996;50(3): 361-387.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
