<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_F7bpN9a">Impact of text message reminders on immunosuppressive medication adherence among kidney transplant recipients: A randomized controlled study</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MSc</roleName><forename type="first">Kübra</forename><surname>Erdal</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0003-4669-7782</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>1</label> Akdeniz University Hospital , Prof. Dr. Tuncer Karpuzoğlu Organ Transplant Clinic , Campus / Antalya , Turkey</note>
								<orgName type="department">Prof. Dr. Tuncer Karpuzoğlu Organ Transplant Clinic</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Akdeniz University Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Campus Antalya</settlement>
									<country key="TR">Turkey</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>PhD, RN,</roleName><forename type="first">Ebru</forename><surname>Karazeybek</surname></persName>
							<email>ekarazeybek@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>2</label> Surgical Nursing Department , Faculty of Nursing , Akdeniz University , Campus/ Antalya , Turkey</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Surgical Nursing Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Nursing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Akdeniz University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Campus/ Antalya</settlement>
									<country key="TR">Turkey</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Surgical Nursing Department , Faculty of Nursing , Akdeniz University , 07058 Campus/ Antalya , Turkey.</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Surgical Nursing Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Nursing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Akdeniz University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>07058</postCode>
									<settlement>Campus/ Antalya</settlement>
									<country key="TR">Turkey</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_U4uxQCe">Impact of text message reminders on immunosuppressive medication adherence among kidney transplant recipients: A randomized controlled study</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">4CBD154725B17EF58C074D5639E769A7</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1111/jep.14178</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: 4 July 2024 | Revised: 31 July 2024 | Accepted: 25 September 2024</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T08:26+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_wnerUj7"><p xml:id="_3SFYVfK"><s xml:id="_jCACdaS">Background: One of the most common problems encountered in transplant patients is nonadherence with immunosuppressive drugs, one of the most important reasons for graft rejection.</s></p><p xml:id="_32YYBp9"><s xml:id="_3uvK5Pb">Objective: The study aimed to assess the impact of text message reminders on medication adherence among kidney transplant recipients.</s></p><p xml:id="_DjqARtP"><s xml:id="_gBwKsJZ">Design: A randomized controlled trial.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_M2hmKr9">Participants:</head><p xml:id="_6A9bgvr"><s xml:id="_wU3ZVPS">The study was conducted from January to October 2021.</s><s xml:id="_eaamwj5">This study included a total of 100 patients receiving a kidney transplant, 50 in the intervention group and 50 in the control group.</s><s xml:id="_DyfG8ks">Measurements: Patients in the intervention group were sent text message reminders four times a day during the 6th-9th months after transplantation.</s><s xml:id="_h9RcGsX">Control patients received no such intervention.</s><s xml:id="_24axWfB">Tacrolimus concentrations in the bloodstream were monitored for all participants through measurements taken at Months 7, 8 and 9. Data collection tools included Sociodemographic Form and Immunosuppressive Medication Adherence Scale.</s><s xml:id="_qsEMbKP">Results: Patients were homogeneously distributed among the groups.</s><s xml:id="_ed9BFt8">Sending daily text message reminders to transplant recipients caused an independent positive effect on medication adherence scale scores at the end of the study.</s><s xml:id="_Zh4exW3">Mean pretest medication adherence score of all patients was 45.18 ± 4.22 and posttest score was 47.4 ± 3.6.</s><s xml:id="_hdJb6pf">The intervention group exhibited a significantly higher mean posttest adherence score compared to controls, with values of 48.68 ± 2.58 and 45.62 ± 4.42, respectively (p &lt; 0.001).</s><s xml:id="_Er3yPTn">Findings demonstrated a substantial improvement in the final medication adherence scores of transplant patients when they received daily Short Message Service reminders, acting as an independent factor (β = 0.356, p &lt; 0.001).</s><s xml:id="_Nnw6Hrs">Conclusion: Sending text message reminders to kidney transplant recipients is a statistically and clinically effective intervention to improve immunosuppressive medication adherence.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="10" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
		<surface n="11" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="782.362"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1" xml:id="_9KkbTEX">| INTRODUCTION</head><p xml:id="_m4Rcc78"><s xml:id="_zPmUsNu">Kidney transplantation, one of the renal replacement therapies, is the most effective treatment modality in chronic renal failure since it not only improves the quality of life but also ensures the lowest morbidity and mortality rates.</s><s xml:id="_UQkUtv3">Transplant recipients must use immunosuppressive drugs for the rest of their lives to prolong their survival and improve quality of life, preserve functions of the transplanted kidney and prevent complications such as rejection. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref></s><s xml:id="_7ayKuGB">The side effects of lifelong immunosuppressive drug therapy can have a major impact on an individual's daily life. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> In patients undergoing kidney transplantation, immunosuppressive drugs prevent graft rejection by inhibiting activation of immune responses. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref></s><s xml:id="_azxHRdn">Graft rejection is the most prevalent complication observed in renal transplant recipients, with nonadherence to immunosuppressive drugs being a primary contributing factor to such rejections. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> Identifying factors causing poor compliance and planning effective interventions are key to improving adherence.</s><s xml:id="_vAEnztJ">Various sociodemographic characteristics, including age, gender, marital status, education level, employment and socioeconomic status influence nonadherence to immunosuppressant regimens.</s><s xml:id="_47CcQeh">Additionally, factors such as medication side effects, time elapsed after transplantation, complexity of drug regimen, frequent outpatient clinic visits, lack of belief in treatment and forgetfulness also contribute to such nonadherence. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref></s><s xml:id="_BHrJdrT">Balakrishnan et al. reported that kidney transplant patients with inadequate health literacy, high levels of depression and poor general health experienced serious challenges with adherence to prescribed medication.</s><s xml:id="_nGcBDMw">The authors also discovered that an increased number of medications was a crucial risk factor associated with noncompliance. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref></s><s xml:id="_WDgJaXX">eir lifelong use of immunosuppressive drugs renders transplant recipients even more susceptible to frequent infections and development of neoplastic diseases.</s><s xml:id="_bP38gHn">Such medications may cause adverse side effects, including but not limited to hypertension, diabetes, anaemia, thrombocytopenia, leukopenia, nausea and vomiting, fatigue and mood disorders. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s xml:id="_vRWJS6M">The organ transplant team is responsible for monitoring and assessing the side effects of immunosuppressive medications and evaluating how the ongoing therapy affects the patient's daily activities.</s><s xml:id="_UAPPARg">Nurses, as members of the organ transplant team, have crucial duties in ensuring the success of immunosuppressive drug therapy. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref></s><s xml:id="_WfbmRBV">They play a key role in evaluating patient compliance, identifying and addressing barriers to adherence and implementing interventions to enhance patient adherence.</s><s xml:id="_wAEFXrV">Additionally, nurses are integral to the healthcare team as they provide education and counselling to recipients throughout the treatment process, ensuring their adherence to the prescribed therapy. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref></s><s xml:id="_b8QffDA">e use of mobile health tools in renal transplant recipients affords an alternative solution in encouraging patient selfmanagement in daily life. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref></s><s xml:id="_9ZQr2Hk">Short Message Service (SMS) reminders, implantable electronic devices, mobile applications and systems that allow patients to record data over the internet are recommended as innovative means to support health. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref></s><s xml:id="_KG5VwxH">Sending text message reminders has become an increasingly common method to maximize patient adherence. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref></s><s xml:id="_7veJJ5F">Kidney transplant recipients exhibit a generally positive attitude toward the use of cell phones during posttransplant care practices.</s><s xml:id="_gY82Qxw">They also believe that such interventions offer convenient self-care measures and assist healthcare providers in medical care management. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref></s><s xml:id="_8yJgj8R">Three randomized controlled trials have used mobile health services and smartphone apps to improve immunosuppressive drug adherence after kidney and lung transplants. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref></s><s xml:id="_xUzPctT">Their findings suggest that sending short reminder text messages to recipients could help improve adherence to such medications as prescribed.</s><s xml:id="_sGsqqVW">To date, there has been no research conducted in Turkey to explore the influence of text message reminders on the adherence of kidney transplant recipients to their immunosuppressive medication.</s><s xml:id="_dww5qQQ">Hence, this study aimed to fill this gap and make a significant contribution by promoting improved adherence to immunosuppressive drugs, facilitating better control of tacrolimus plasma levels and potentially reducing healthcare costs associated with hospitalization.</s><s xml:id="_szprAut">The main focus of this study was to investigate the impact of sending text message reminders to kidney transplant recipients on their adherence to the prescribed immunosuppressive drug regimen.</s><s xml:id="_MVQQxFr">The study sample was determined based on the sampling formula for known population.</s><s xml:id="_AZ9YN76">Given that the total number of patients who underwent kidney transplant between January 2019 and December 2019 was 235, the sample size for the study, with a 5% error margin and 95% confidence level, was determined to be n1 (intervention) = 45 and n2 (control) = 45.</s><s xml:id="_WhSUmCF">To account for potential risks and ensure adequate statistical power, the sample size was adjusted to n1 (intervention) = 50 and n2 (control) = 50, resulting in a total sample size of n = 100 individuals, was made to enhance the reliability and validity of the research findings.</s></p><p xml:id="_24PYdGj"><s xml:id="_PMKs2nn">Before concluding the data collection phase, the sample size was recalculated on the G*Power 3.1.9</s><s xml:id="_MP3AY2D">software package.</s><s xml:id="_Fya6Vac">The minimum sample size required for the study to achieve 95% statistical power and a margin of error of 0.05 was determined to be 49 patients in total.</s><s xml:id="_AMpkKhK">The study observed a difference in mean medication adherence scores between the pretest and posttest at 3.94 ± 4.03 in the intervention group and 0.5 ± 4.91 in the control group.</s><s xml:id="_TubpA2C">Based on these results, the calculated statistical power at the end of the study was 98% for an effect size of d = 0.766 and a margin of error of 0.05.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3" xml:id="_e2Mt3DS">| Data collection tools</head><p xml:id="_AuhU4Pc"><s xml:id="_akSDAAS">Research data were collected by the Sociodemographic and Descriptive Characteristics Form, Immunosuppressive Medication Adherence Scale (IMAS) and Biological Evaluation Form.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.1" xml:id="_Rk5HCnN">| Sociodemographic and descriptive characteristics form</head><p xml:id="_T8pSTgY"><s xml:id="_TjyaqfQ">The form utilized in this study was developed based on previous literature. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref></s><s xml:id="_Bq3wutF">It contains 15 questions related to sociodemographic characteristics such as age, gender, educational background, marital status, occupation, employment status, income level and place of residence as well as another set of 15 questions pertaining to clinical characteristics, including donor type, date of kidney transplant, primary disease leading to the transplant, comorbidities and prescribed immunosuppressive drugs.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.2" xml:id="_T8Z2JcE">| IMAS</head><p xml:id="_Z8ZyaRy"><s xml:id="_UnZmjcw">The IMAS is an 11-item self-report questionnaire developed in 2015 to measure medication adherence in patients that have received solid organ transplants and are prescribed immunosuppressive drugs (Supporting Information S1: File 1).</s><s xml:id="_H7pwUrK">Eight of the items on the scale are rated on a five-point Likert scale, with responses being 'never, rarely, sometimes, often and always'.</s><s xml:id="_pgxKFKF">The other three items are answered with a simple 'yes' or 'no'.</s><s xml:id="_jeFEpzY">The total score is the sum of the item scores, with a possible range of 11-55, and higher scores indicate greater adherence to the prescribed drug regimen.</s><s xml:id="_KaTYKrz">The Cronbach's α value of the scale was calculated as 0.61. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref></s><s xml:id="_DCMyBq4">The scale reliability coefficient of this study was equal to 0.58 for the pretest and 0.60 for the posttest.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.3" xml:id="_Q8BGut9">| Biological evaluation form</head><p xml:id="_FMCZQjT"><s xml:id="_dN5TEgv">Our research centre tests the blood concentrations of three immunosuppressive drugs: tacrolimus, cyclosporine and everolimus.</s></p><p xml:id="_WSK3Ztq"><s xml:id="_bV8ARhh">Tacrolimus was the most commonly prescribed drug, so we closely monitored its levels in the bloodstream of patients.</s></p><p xml:id="_HG2Sybw"><s xml:id="_atffWsg">Patients took the immunosuppressive drugs tacrolimus, cyclosporine and everolimus every 12 h.</s><s xml:id="_qTmPhNb">Blood samples were collected 12 h after each dose to measure drug levels in the bloodstream.</s></p><p xml:id="_7XKbHEv"><s xml:id="_RPJzxyC">Biological evaluation involved analyzing blood samples at the 7th, 8th and 9th months after the initiation of immunosuppressants.</s></p><p xml:id="_zM4Y3pC"><s xml:id="_h2bS873">The individual levels of tacrolimus in plasma were recorded on the Biological Evaluation Form during the specified time points, and the mean tacrolimus plasma concentrations were calculated based on these recordings.</s></p><p xml:id="_esveqMK"><s xml:id="_qwQuZHH">In the literature, different evaluation models regarding biological evaluation are applied.</s><s xml:id="_DfpRM7X">In the study of Schafer-Keller et al., the therapeutic dose was accepted as 100-150 ng/mL for cyclosporine and 5-10 ng/mL for tacrolimus and sirolimus.</s><s xml:id="_J5BfJnq">In the same study, the percentage of each patient receiving a value below or above this therapeutic dose was examined in the compliance evaluation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref></s><s xml:id="_8dYsXEX">In the centre where the research was conducted, the normal value range for tacrolimus is 5-10 ng/mL.</s><s xml:id="_w6sWpKT">Therefore, in this study, 'Medication nonadherence' was defined tacrolimus level &lt;5 from &gt;10 ng/mL.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4" xml:id="_6hpKner">| Pilot interviews</head><p xml:id="_HVWXahj"><s xml:id="_s6XkwQX">Before commencing the main study, a preliminary small-scale study was conducted to evaluate the comprehensibility of the items in our data collection forms.</s><s xml:id="_nNKMnu8">Two patients who met the inclusion criteria were selected and asked to complete the forms.</s><s xml:id="_gjFPhUT">These patients were not included in the main study.</s><s xml:id="_C7wdASB">There was no item in the data collection forms that was not understood.</s><s xml:id="_bbGFkyW">Therefore, no changes were made to the forms.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5" xml:id="_C4297cA">| Randomization</head><p xml:id="_MJAVd5U"><s xml:id="_AZCWG64">Kidney transplant recipients who met the inclusion criteria and were scheduled for follow-up at 6th-9th month after transplantation were randomized.</s><s xml:id="_YecQsaM">Randomization was done by the thesis advisor.</s><s xml:id="_xRSmFZc">Kidney transplant recipients who met the criteria for inclusion in the study were identified from the hospital records by the thesis advisor.</s></p><p xml:id="_XGyefba"><s xml:id="_8gXmJ9K">Patients invited to the study were assigned to either intervention or control groups by simple randomization performed on an online software (<ref type="url" target="https://www.randomizer.org/">https://www.randomizer.org/</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_qm6qaQ7">Based on the machinegenerated number sequence, we determined that patients assigned number 1 would comprise the intervention group, while those assigned number 2 would be included in the control group.</s><s xml:id="_kAw6PVF">The CONSORT flowchart of this study is presented in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6" xml:id="_xeebHMr">| Implementation of the initiative</head><p xml:id="_uR29mbN"><s xml:id="_EJhN7Q2">The researchers identified patients who had completed 6 months of posttransplant care and were scheduled for follow-up until 9 months from the system's records.</s><s xml:id="_dAZDDWT">This time period was chosen based on studies in the literature.</s><s xml:id="_uhrTpvs">It has been reported in the literature that recipients value their transplanted kidneys more and are more careful in the early period after transplantation.</s><s xml:id="_bSbVeCv">It is emphasized that as time passes after transplantation, transplant recipients' compliance with the use of immunosuppressive drugs decreases. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref></s><s xml:id="_GU7chGh">Randomization of these patients was conducted, and the researchers contacted them by phone to provide information about the study.</s><s xml:id="_wU6Qu4Z">If the patients agreed to participate, their consent forms for either the intervention or control group were approved via Google forms before they were included in the study.</s><s xml:id="_vrXgSCa">akdenizorgannakli.net/pdf/organ-nakli-el-kitabi.pdf)'. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19</ref></s><s xml:id="_eTCDwYj">e text message contents prepared for the intervention group were sent automatically to patients at specified times via the purchased programme.</s><s xml:id="_SE6gzx5">A periodic text message package was acquired for this intervention, with defined start and end dates, and messages were automatically sent at the designated times.</s><s xml:id="_DXTttTA">At the end of the study, both groups of participants completing the 9-month follow-up were administered the IMAS questionnaire as a posttest.</s><s xml:id="_CHryMKA">The researchers also recorded the tacrolimus blood profiles of participants in both groups during the 7th, 8th and 9th months, accessing this information from the patient information system.</s><s xml:id="_w5QDcWw">The study was terminated when the determined sample size was reached.</s><s xml:id="_zwsKHmd">Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> illustrates the study process in a diagram.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.8" xml:id="_Nrp2ezM">| Statistical analysis</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3" xml:id="_SG9aejM">| RESULTS</head><p xml:id="_hkNcfKk"><s xml:id="_exK3JZ8">The study sample included a total of 100 transplant recipients, with 50 patients assigned to the control group and 50 patients assigned to the intervention group.</s><s xml:id="_DShvVCm">Daily SMS reminders were sent to patients in the intervention group.</s><s xml:id="_DdPCuS6">The mean age of patients was 41.83 ± 12.69 years, with ages ranging from 19 to 67 years.</s><s xml:id="_deRm8Pz">Majority (79%) of the patients were male and 72% were married.</s><s xml:id="_u7WSgU8">A total of 59 patients (59%) lived in provincial cities, 47% of the patients were primary school graduates, 33% high school graduates and 20% university graduates.</s><s xml:id="_qfhtvkr">A total of 46 patients (46.5%) had income equal to expenses, while 36 patients (36.4%) had income less than expenses.</s><s xml:id="_6bTfm52">Only 20 patients (20%) lived with their spouse, 52 patients (52%) with their spouse and children, 21 patients (21%) with their parents and 7 (7%) with other people.</s><s xml:id="_eMfBpKT">Before transplantation, 58 patients (58%) were actively employed, 23 patients (23%) were not working and 19 patients (19%) retired.</s></p><p xml:id="_eYRfBT3"><s xml:id="_hMAu9Tr">The following details pertain to the transplant-related characteristics of patients.</s><s xml:id="_jdkSQcr">Vast majority (97%) received a transplant from a living donor.</s><s xml:id="_7rPGwfF">The most common primary diseases leading to transplantation were hypertension (26.5%), unknown causes (22.4%) and other causes (21.4%).</s><s xml:id="_MV3CY59">A total of 75 patients (75%) had a waiting period of &lt;1 year before transplantation.</s><s xml:id="_SbXVfYN">A total of 57 patients (57%) were diagnosed with hypertension and 15 patients (15%) diabetes.</s></p><p xml:id="_2Gpxnsm"><s xml:id="_9RdMM5g">The most commonly used drug combination was Tacrolimus + Mycophenolate mofetil (74%).</s><s xml:id="_cpKEcfY">The median number of drugs used was 10, ranging from 5 to 21.</s><s xml:id="_bmt7GJj">Only nine patients (9%) reported having someone who would remind them to take the prescribed drugs.</s></p><p xml:id="_rtkNznk"><s xml:id="_5AvWY2Y">The sociodemographic characteristics of the control and intervention groups were similar.</s><s xml:id="_E3DAtMt">The mean age of patients in the control group was 42.86 ± 13.67, and the mean age in the intervention group was 40.8 ± 11.67.</s><s xml:id="_sxSDgnS">The proportion of male patients was 80% in the control group and 78% in the intervention group.</s><s xml:id="_Wf7V7hm">Age and gender distribution of groups were similar (p = 0.420 and p = 0.806).</s><s xml:id="_szHsWsc">There were no significant differences in marital status (p = 0.999), number Transplant-related characteristics were examined in the comparison of differences in pretest and posttest adherence scores, which showed no significant difference according to donor type (p = 0.414), length of wait before a transplant (p = 0.153), medication prescribed (p = 0.314) and presence of a person to remind medication use (p = 0.432).</s><s xml:id="_aeFUDEc">In patients with comorbidities, the mean score difference was 3.01 ± 4.76, while it was 0.53 ± 4.49 in those who had no comorbidities.</s><s xml:id="_bFHr4DZ">Patients with comorbidities showed a significantly higher increase in medication adherence scores by the end of the study (p = 0.015).</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">F I G U R E 2 Study process diagram.</formula><p xml:id="_szF3Qj3"><s xml:id="_9Xyx2gZ">Mean pretest medication adherence score of all patients was 45.18 ± 4.22 and posttest score was 47.4 ± 3.6.</s><s xml:id="_d4BF24N">Mean pretest and posttest adherence scores of patients in the control and intervention groups are presented in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_2W9vD7M">No significant difference was found in the mean pretest medication adherence scores between two groups (p = 0.299).</s><s xml:id="_Vd834Hx">The intervention group exhibited a significantly higher mean posttest adherence score compared to controls, with values of 48.68 ± 2.58 and 45.62 ± 4.42, respectively (p &lt; 0.001).</s><s xml:id="_bzvrga4">By the end of the study, the mean medication adherence score of the control group increased by 0.5 ± 4.91 points, while the intervention group had a greater improvement, by 3.94 ± 4.03 points, which was statistically significant (p &lt; 0.001, Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_rKFZMzm">There was no significant difference between the posttest and pretest scores in the control group (p = 0.475), but the mean posttest score in the intervention group (48.68 ± 2.58) was significantly higher than the mean pretest score (44.74 ± 4) (p &lt; 0.001).</s></p><p xml:id="_dRBSM83"><s xml:id="_pSUA9jY">Data regarding the correlation analysis between pretest and posttest medication adherence score differences and other variables are tabulated in Table <ref type="table">2</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_BFfPApD">No significant correlation was found between mean adherence score difference and age (p = 0.701), number of children (p = 0.357) and number of medications prescribed (p = 0.087).</s></p><p xml:id="_nemyyXz"><s xml:id="_3TB4k4m">Table <ref type="table">3</ref> summarizes the factors independently affecting the ference between pretest and posttest adherence scores of patients as determined by multiple linear regression analysis.</s><s xml:id="_HaQS7wJ">Findings demonstrated a substantial improvement in the final medication adherence scores of transplant patients when they received daily SMS reminders, acting as an independent factor (β = 0.356, p &lt; 0.001).</s></p><p xml:id="_bHCqw8B"><s xml:id="_A2aSupc">Mean tacrolimus plasma concentrations of both groups are compared in Table <ref type="table">4</ref>. Statistically, there was no significant difference in the mean tacrolimus levels between two groups (p = 0.944).</s><s xml:id="_Dwr9kRD">Medication nonadherence rate according to blood levels was 39.5% in the control group and 16.7% in the intervention group, and the nonadherence rate was significantly higher in the control group (p = 0.019).</s></p><p xml:id="_U5BBFXz"><s xml:id="_ZnBCCtn">The correlation analysis results between medication adherence scores and tacrolimus plasma concentrations can be found in Table <ref type="table">5</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_fyqnMZs"><s xml:id="_E5f9zCw">Comparisons revealed no significant correlation between the mean tacrolimus levels in blood and medication adherence scores among transplant recipients (p &gt; 0.05).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4" xml:id="_UytHVuv">| DISCUSSION</head><p xml:id="_KmgTWc5"><s xml:id="_vrFQbzH">This study, therefore, aimed to explore the impact of sending SMS reminders to kidney transplant patients on immunosuppressive medication adherence, and the findings are discussed in relation to the relevant literature.</s></p><p xml:id="_9UT2sud"><s xml:id="_RFeSbkn">The lowest possible score on the IMAS is 11 and the highest is 55.</s><s xml:id="_J8AY7ua">A higher score obtained from the scale indicates better adherence to immunosuppressants.</s><s xml:id="_x5y9kvJ">In our study, the mean IMAS score of kidney transplant recipients was 45.18 ± 4.22 in the pretest and 47.4 ± 3.6 in the posttest.</s><s xml:id="_CHc482k">In a study conducted by Köken et al. the mean IMAS score of transplant recipients was 48.10 ± 6.61. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref></s><s xml:id="_subFqF8">Another study found the mean IMAS score as 48.33 ± 3.21. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref></s><s xml:id="_uuuUh9V">Weng et al. reported that kidney transplant recipients had high levels of compliance with immunosuppressive drugs in their study using a different scale from what we used. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref></s><s xml:id="_3qkbBeS">On the other hand, there are some reports suggesting that the level of compliance with immunosuppressant is still relatively low. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24</ref></s><s xml:id="_GHEZUk5">Nonadherence to immunosuppressive drugs in transplant recipients, especially kidney transplant recipients, is still a problem.</s></p><p xml:id="_mkntjS9"><s xml:id="_xt2XvPH">In this study, no significant difference was found in terms of pretest medication adherence mean scores in both groups.</s><s xml:id="_qAAQZSU">The T A B L E 1 Mean pretest and posttest medication adherence scores of transplant recipients according to study groups.</s></p><p xml:id="_fwMmV7f"><s xml:id="_6dgDQBy">Medication adherence Control (n = 50) Intervention (n = 50) p Value a Pretest 45.62 ± 4.42 44.74 ± 4 0.299 Posttest 46.12 ± 4.02 48.68 ± 2.58 &lt;0.001 Score difference (post-pretest) 0.5 ± 4.91 3.94 ± 4.03 &lt;0.001 p Value b 0.475 &lt;0.001 a Independent t test.</s><s xml:id="_VKSg7Wk">b Paired t test.</s><s xml:id="_gcWRX55">posttest mean score was 48.68 ± 2.58 in the intervention group and 45.62 ± 4.42 in the control group.</s><s xml:id="_JhBVGmk">It was observed that the mean posttest medication adherence score of the intervention group was significantly higher.</s><s xml:id="_bcWrdwp">This finding showed that text message reminders improved medication adherence and confirmed hypothesis H1 (Sending text message reminders increases immunosuppressive medication adherence in kidney transplant recipients).</s><s xml:id="_kspu4pZ">A systematic that assessed the efficacy of interventions to enhance drug compliance found that adherence to prescribed immunosuppressants increased significantly in the intervention groups in comparison to the controls. 25</s><s xml:id="_sWDT2Ct">Reese et al. reported that interventions such as phone calls, SMS reminders and emails promoted greater compliance with</s></p><p xml:id="_q75KAwr"><s xml:id="_Hw9brjq">immunosuppressive drugs.</s><s xml:id="_gXbbHRE">They also concluded that reminder apps are promising in helping patients achieve better medication adherence but suggested that this strategy should be evaluated in research to identify differences in clinical outcomes. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26</ref></s><s xml:id="_mPxKPX7">In three randomized controlled trials, mobile health services and smartphone applications were used to improve adherence to immunosuppressive medication in kidney and lung transplant patients. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref></s><s xml:id="_gKfnraQ">McGillicuddy et al. found that the mobile health tool they developed greatly increased medication adherence and blood pressure control in kidney transplant recipients. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27</ref></s><s xml:id="_t8fX5VH">De Bleser et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28</ref> examined the effectiveness of interventions that improve drug compliance in organ transplant recipients and found that interventions could be beneficial in the long term if they were implemented in combination with a team approach. <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28</ref></s><s xml:id="_8mTtPva">A review by Eslami et al. found that mobile health tools can help kidney transplant recipients manage their health more effectively and adhere to their treatment plans.</s><s xml:id="_UxD58hH">The review authors suggested that these tools should be used both before and after transplantation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref></s><s xml:id="_5E3Djnj">In a study by Israni et al., all participants expressed an interest in using reminder tools, also highlighting some potential obstacles to ensuring the long-term use of these tools, which include reminders becoming annoying after a while, or the phone remaining switched off at certain times <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> At the end of this study, the mean medication adherence score of the control group increased by 0.5 ± 4.91 points, while it improved by 3.94 ± 4.03 points in the intervention group.</s><s xml:id="_Deusshv">The increase observed in patients receiving reminders was significantly higher than that of controls.</s><s xml:id="_eGnBZpX">There was no significant difference between the pretest and posttest scores in the control group, but the mean posttest score in the intervention group (48.68 ± 2.58) was significantly higher than the mean pretest score (44.74 ± 4).</s><s xml:id="_gBewVTd">Foster et al. attempted to improve adherence to immunosuppressive medication by using an application featuring reminders and reported a significant increase in the medication adherence score of the intervention group, but no increase in the control group. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30</ref></s><s xml:id="_KeQevtW">Contrary to our results, some research has also reported no significant difference in the improvement of medication adherence scores in both intervention and control groups.</s><s xml:id="_E4STTxG">However, they also determined that recipients who used the mobile app tended to remember their immunosuppressive drugs at a greater frequency. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31</ref></s><s xml:id="_yqxQFjv"> significant relationship was found between the difference in pretest and posttest medication adherence scores, and age, number of children and total number of medications used.</s><s xml:id="_mP78GhQ">Our findings align with the studies conducted by Weng et al., as they also found no significant relationship between age and medication adherence. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref></s><s xml:id="_dK7CgMs">On</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_1">F I G U R E 3</formula><p xml:id="_2KfeYTv"><s xml:id="_VnFeDJe">Pretest and posttest drug compliance scores of transplant patients according to study groups.</s><s xml:id="_GmzpDPS">T A B L E 2 Correlation between pretest and posttest medication adherence score differences of transplant recipients and other variables.</s><s xml:id="_rmn6SyQ">Variables r p Value Age 0.039 0.701 Number of children 0.093 0.357 Number of medications 0.172 0.087 Note: Pearson correlation test, Spearman correlation test.</s><s xml:id="_qEHFtNn">the contrary, Chisholm et al. found that kidney transplant recipients aged 18-29 years were more noncompliant than recipients aged 46-64 years. <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32</ref></s><s xml:id="_F7s4e7T">The findings from this study demonstrated that the independent act of sending daily reminder text messages to transplant recipients had a positive impact on increasing medication adherence scores by the end of the study, thus confirming our first hypothesis (H1: Sending text reminders increases immunosuppressive medication adherence in kidney transplant recipients).</s></p><p xml:id="_WcfrWrX"><s xml:id="_njhdhu4">The mean tacrolimus plasma concentrations in the control and intervention groups were statistically similar.</s><s xml:id="_QqTaZck">The rate of nonadherent patients according to blood levels was 39.5% in the control group and 16.7% in the intervention group, and the rate of nonadherent patients was significantly higher in the control group.</s></p><p xml:id="_edfUp5c"><s xml:id="_jtt8Cb9">Monitoring drug blood levels in a patient's blood and urine can serve as a valuable tool to validate drug compliance.</s><s xml:id="_nCjHpv8">Given the necessity for dose adjustments following transplantation and regular outpatient visits, the measurement of tacrolimus levels was deemed optimal for our study.</s><s xml:id="_SZX6rxp">In a similar vein, Cukor et al. also assessed tacrolimus in the bloodstream as a secondary measure to enhance medication adherence among renal transplant recipients in their study, aligning with our research approach.</s><s xml:id="_4x6huDZ">While there was no significant difference between the groups before the intervention, medication adherence was found to be higher in the intervention group according to blood levels. <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">33</ref></s><s xml:id="_Vxw2dED">Contrary to our study, there are also studies that found no statistically significant difference in tacrolimus blood levels. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31</ref></s><s xml:id="_4xyTFHS">No significant correlation was found between the mean tacrolimus concentrations and medication adherence scores.</s><s xml:id="_Gbts9yf">The reason for the lack of a significant result in our study may be that recipients generally pay more attention to their drug intake before clinical control.</s></p><p xml:id="_bcfyPKh"><s xml:id="_6GQDRVP">Drug concentrations in plasma can also be influenced by the patient's diet, other medications and laboratory conditions. 16,34</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1" xml:id="_mR9kQST">| Study limitations</head><p xml:id="_MJcfRCa"><s xml:id="_SskcZZB">This study was conducted at only one centre, which is among the limitations of the study.</s><s xml:id="_5RW5Wje">Besides, the data were mainly based on self-report by patients.</s><s xml:id="_EFXGwYe">Since sending SMS reminders continued T A B L E 3 Factors associated with pretest and posttest medication adherence score differences of transplant recipients.</s></p><p xml:id="_PEmxdBV"><s xml:id="_5w2V5px">Score difference 95% confidence interval Model 1 B SE β t p Value VIF Lower limit Upper limit Fixed -2.092 1.825 -1.146 0.255 --5.714 1.531 Pretransplant wait time -1.407 0.794 -0.164 -1.772 0.080 1.038 -2.982 0.169 Additional disease 1.837 0.943 0.180 1.947 0.054 1.029 -0.036 3.709 Number of medications 0.165 0.141 0.110 1.167 0.246 1.078 -0.115 0.445 Intervention group 3.401 0.890 0.356 3.819 &lt;0.001 1.053 1.633 5.169 Abbreviation: VIF, variance inflation factor.</s><s xml:id="_TyU9C8x">Note: R = 0.463; R 2 = 0.214; p &lt; 0.001.</s><s xml:id="_8PzzPBy">T A B L E 4 Tacrolimus blood concentrations in transplant recipients according to study groups.</s><s xml:id="_B2EvK6F">Blood level Control (n = 43) Intervention (n = 42) p Value Mean tacrolimus level in blood, X ̅ ± SS 9.09 ± 1.88 9.07 ± 1.65 0.944 Tacrolimus medication adherence, n (%) Adherent (5-10) 26 (60.5) 35 (83.3) 0.019 Nonadherent (&lt;5 or &gt;10) 17 (39.5)</s><s xml:id="_5U4TXdb">7 (16.7)</s><s xml:id="_dPBPSpG">Note: Independent t test, Pearson's chi-square test.</s><s xml:id="_SzPawXG">T A B L E 5 Mean drug compliance scores and tacrolimus blood concentrations of transplant recipients according to study groups.</s><s xml:id="_r3PPtTD">Control (n = 43) Intervention (n = 42) All patients (n = 85) Medication adherence score r p Value r p Value r p Value Pretest -0.026 0.868 -0.161 0.369 -0.082 0.454 Posttest -0.115 0.465 0.062 0.695 -0.051 0.645 Score difference -0.069 0.662 0.196 0.213 0.036 0.741</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>1. 1 |</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_8HsPh9y"><s xml:id="_wgJ2zVH">Research hypotheses H1: Sending text message reminders improves immunosuppressive medication adherence in kidney transplant recipients.</s><s xml:id="_cjgwBbE">H2: Utilization of text messages as reminders has a significant influence on tacrolimus blood profiles in kidney transplant recipients.</s><s xml:id="_NDe4Wtw">H3: There is a correlation between the scores from the Immunosuppressive Medication Adherence Scale and mean tacrolimus plasma levels in kidney transplant recipients.</s><s xml:id="_5caav4p">H4: There is a correlation between the sociodemographic and descriptive characteristics of kidney transplant recipients and their mean scores from the Immunosuppressive Medication Adherence Scale.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>2 |</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_HscVxwV"><s xml:id="_Dg75AtN">MATERIALS AND METHODS2.1 | Study designThis study single-centre, randomized controlled trial.</s><s xml:id="_5BGU4eN">The study was conducted at Akdeniz University Hospital Prof. Dr. Tuncer Karpuzoğlu Organ Transplant Centre between 01 January 2021 and 01 October 2021.</s><s xml:id="_KpH5ccj">This trial was retrospectively registered at ClinicalTrials.gov</s><s xml:id="_MrhnkvR">(NCT06004102).</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>2. 2 |</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_AQWDgWU"><s xml:id="_3eVS7at">Sample and settingThe population of the study consisted of all individuals who were followed up after kidney transplantation at Akdeniz University Hospital Prof. Dr. Tuncer Karpuzoğlu Organ Transplant Centre.</s><s xml:id="_2UeRUXe">The centre where the research was conducted is one of the few transplant centres in the world with multiorgan and composite tissue transplants.</s><s xml:id="_AhExccW">The centre, which has been performing transplantation since 1982, performs outpatient clinic follow-ups of kidney transplant patients every weekday.</s><s xml:id="_42S8ghG">The inclusion criteria were (1) age 18 years or older; (2) being a recipient of a kidney transplant for the first time; (3) being a kidney transplant recipient at posttransplant Month 6 with scheduled follow-up until Month 9; (4) ongoing immunosuppressive drug therapy; (5) absence of any disability that hinders communication; (6) no diagnosis of psychological and mental problems; (7) being an active cell phone user; (8) ability to read and write; (9) voluntary participation in the research.</s><s xml:id="_75Dk4wu">Participants were excluded for the following reasons: (1) history of combined or dual organ transplantation.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_XBaUbBF"><s xml:id="_6Vrhxnt">The research data were collected by the researcher over the phone.</s><s xml:id="_84Mj2bP">Within the SMS sending menu provided by the text message service provider, we could customize the date and time of the text F I G U R E 1 The study flowchart according to CONSORT 2010.</s><s xml:id="_NkpyjKj">messages.</s><s xml:id="_DRHHZXz">The application offered options for scheduling future messages, allowing us to choose the desired month, day, year, hour and minute for sending, as well as some functionality to edit or delete scheduled messages before the submission date.</s><s xml:id="_xs3ed9s">At the baseline of the study (6th month posttransplant), the Sociodemographic and Descriptive Characteristics Form and IMAS were administered to patients in the intervention and control groups as a pretest.</s><s xml:id="_gxAYBKY">Short text messages to remind the use of immunosuppressive medication and educational text messages were sent to patients in the intervention group four times a day, every day for 3 months.</s><s xml:id="_tZDUx4K">The control group did not receive any such intervention.</s><s xml:id="_aFGAamQ">The message times and contents sent to the intervention group were as follows: 1st message content sent at 07.00: 'Please don't forget to take your medication this morning!</s><s xml:id="_aGwjXpz">Use your medication regularly as recommended by your doctor'.</s><s xml:id="_abVnhRd">2nd message sent at 09.00: 'Please do not forget to take your full dose of medication this morning!</s><s xml:id="_68afK8z">Use your medication regularly as recommended by your doctor'.</s><s xml:id="_cNTHsVF">3rd message sent at 19.00: 'Please do not forget to take your medication this evening!</s><s xml:id="_ZYDvbuq">Use your medication regularly as recommended by your doctor'.</s><s xml:id="_7DPTReA">4th message sent at 21.00: 'Please don't forget to take your full medication tonight!</s><s xml:id="_Mx3Nb7H">Use your medication regularly as recommended by your doctor'.</s><s xml:id="_xWhUqgH">The intervention group also received educational text messages 3 days a week on Mondays, Wednesdays and Fridays, in addition to such text message reminders.</s><s xml:id="_kkfDaY2">The details of the messages were as follows: Message 1: 'You must take immunosuppressive drugs at the recommended dose at regular times for the health of the transplanted kidney.</s><s xml:id="_vD7E4cU">Otherwise, your body may reject the transplanted kidney'.</s><s xml:id="_zCrhyva">Message 2: 'Consumption of grapefruit is strictly forbidden.</s><s xml:id="_mjddT3W">Because it can cause significant increases in the levels of immunosuppressive drugs in your blood'.</s><s xml:id="_uB3fHX5">Message 3: 'Do not use herbal remedies or drink herbal teas after transplantation.</s><s xml:id="_mpwxP5b">It may harm you by affecting the absorption of the drugs you are taking.</s><s xml:id="_g7eHRpn">Avoid using any medicines and herbal treatments other than those prescribed by your doctor (http://www.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>2. 7 |</head><label>7</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_thZt7Gb"><s xml:id="_4eMGgFT">EthicsBefore starting the study, a written ethical approval (Date: April 2020, Decision No: 315) from Akdeniz University Faculty of Medicine Clinical Research Ethics Committee and permissions from the relevant institutions were obtained.</s><s xml:id="_6fQpPwc">Participants were informed about the purpose and duration of the study and the procedures to be performed during the study.</s><s xml:id="_jNnyaeb">An informed consent from each patient was received before the collection of the research data.</s><s xml:id="_ZQp8Vvm">Throughout the research, attention was paid to the ethical principle of protecting the privacy of patients, confidentiality and security of the information gathered.</s><s xml:id="_Evt5GUJ">Ethical principles of 'anonymity and security' were also fulfilled to ensure that the identity of respondents and relevant data were kept confidential.The study adhered to the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki in safeguarding the medical and personal data of the patients.</s><s xml:id="_ZTyCffA">The principle of 'respect for human dignity' was honoured, recognizing the uniqueness and integrity of each individual.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_Xx9GyzZ"><s xml:id="_cKam6Fe">Categorical variables were presented as frequencies (n) and percentages (%) and analyzed by Pearson's chi-square test and Fisher's exact test.</s><s xml:id="_US8Kp9A">Continuous variables were presented as means, standard deviations, median values, minimum and maximum levels.</s><s xml:id="_HNYgTFU">Normality was assessed using the Shapiro-Wilk test.</s><s xml:id="_wzyvq6s">Mann-Whitney U tests and Kruskal-Wallis tests were used to compare continuous variables between independent groups when the variables were not normally distributed.</s><s xml:id="_WJuV8US">Independent t tests and one-way analysis of variance were used when the variables were normally distributed.</s><s xml:id="_u2tTCmD">Differences between the pretest and posttest medication adherence scores were analyzed by paired t tests.</s><s xml:id="_4xVAhsN">Pearson and Spearman correlation tests were used to assess the relationships between medication adherence scores and other variables.</s><s xml:id="_Gz6X9CZ">Multiple linear regression analysis was used to determine the independent factors that affected medication adherence scores.</s><s xml:id="_nM82j8F">Results of tacrolimus blood tests measured for 3 months were averaged and evaluated.</s><s xml:id="_FePz9J9">All analyses were performed on IBM SPSS 23.0 software package (IBM Corp.), and p &lt; 0.05 were considered statistically significant.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_DyZquFE"><s xml:id="_hj3fyq4">of children (p = 0.245), residential status (p = 0.839), educational background (p = 0.322), income level (p = 0.730), cohabitants (p = 0.125) and pretransplant employment status (p = 0.443) between groups.Transplant-related characteristics of the groups were compared, and no significant difference was found in terms of donor type (p = 0.999), primary disease leading to transplantation (p = 0.808), length of wait before a transplant (p = 0.874), comorbidities (p = 0.198), hypertension (p = 0.840), diabetes (p = 0.401), other additional diseases (p = 0.749), medications prescribed (p = 0.140) and presence of a person to remind medication use (p = 0.999).</s><s xml:id="_KvZqmsT">Although the mean total number of drugs taken was greater in the control group, this difference was not significant (p = 0.086).Differences in pretest and posttest medication adherence scores were compared according to sociodemographic characteristics.Medication adherence scores between pretest and posttest showed no significant change for any of the following factors: gender (p = 0.293), marital status (p = 0.352), residential status (p = 0.769), educational background (p = 0.443), income level (p = 0.958), cohabitants (p = 0.669) and pretransplant employment status (p = 0.320).</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="8,45.64,48.98,311.98,227.23" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p xml:id="_qguFxdY"><s xml:id="_dsktDs6">13652753, 2025, 1, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/jep.14178,</s><s xml:id="_ufxxWgt">Wiley Online Library on [13/07/2025].</s><s xml:id="_kM5NXPs">See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions)</s><s xml:id="_W4dNmxw">on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License</s></p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_8CrWPeF">DATA AVAILABILITY STATEMENT</head><p xml:id="_JKXeyws"><s xml:id="_RMPA9Hy">The data that support the findings of this study are available on request from the corresponding author.</s><s xml:id="_arcENpk">The data are not publicly available due to privacy or ethical restrictions.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_RTPw4NZ"><p xml:id="_ztEMd3f"><s xml:id="_Ef73eY6">for 3 months as part of the study, the long-term impact of this intervention on adherence to immunosuppressants could not be evaluated.</s><s xml:id="_6V7bqX3">Research results can only be generalized to patients included in this study.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5" xml:id="_yDBfB23">| CLINICAL IMPLICATIONS</head><p xml:id="_XFpVVfN"><s xml:id="_mCXeTW2">Sending text message reminders to patients is a simple technological method that can be used to increase compliance with immunosuppressive drug therapy.</s><s xml:id="_cNSaJNw">With this method, patients can be helped to use their medications regularly.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6" xml:id="_ppnYbzA">| CONCLUSION</head><p xml:id="_FyQmr6D"><s xml:id="_qdZzjKk">on the evidence presented in this study, it can be concluded that utilizing text messages as reminders has the potential to improve adherence to immunosuppressive medications among individuals who have received a kidney transplant.</s><s xml:id="_rHYdpnr">This conclusion is supported by the higher rate of noncompliance observed in controls that receive no reminders, as suggested by their mean tacrolimus blood levels.</s></p><p xml:id="_ZVmXmmG"><s xml:id="_vZWdGv3">Our results show that sending reminder text messages to recipients after kidney transplantation can be used as an effective method to increase compliance with immunosuppressive drug use.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_aMeHjEF">CONFLICT OF INTEREST STATEMENT</head><p xml:id="_KdWcssW"><s xml:id="_QCpMbEv">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_hCFaAhY">SUPPORTING INFORMATION</head><p xml:id="_s2mwXjg"><s xml:id="_g486WEs">Additional supporting information can be found online in the Supporting Information section at the end of this article.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ZNjZXxs">The association between psychosocial and age-related factors with adherence to immunosuppressive therapies after renal transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zachciał</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Uchmanowicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Czapla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Krajewska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Banasik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3390/jcm11092386</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_JbUzxz7">J Clin Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2386</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Zachciał J, Uchmanowicz I, Czapla M, Krajewska M, Banasik M. The association between psychosocial and age-related factors with adherence to immunosuppressive therapies after renal transplanta- tion. J Clin Med. 2022;11(9):2386. doi:10.3390/jcm11092386</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qNNe9fB">Only the sufferer knows: longterm problems and experiences of kidney transplant recipients: a phenomenological study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Taşdemir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Temür</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Aksoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.colegn.2023.09.004</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_rKuGVhT">Collegian</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="835" to="842" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Taşdemir D, Temür BN, Aksoy N. Only the sufferer knows: long- term problems and experiences of kidney transplant recipients: a phenomenological study. Collegian. 2023;30(6):835-842.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_xgSnXHx">Determination of the compliance level of patients who underwent kidney transplantation in the Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus to immunosuppressive therapy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ören</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sucu</forename><surname>Dağ</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5222/head.2020.42275</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="9" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ören E, Sucu Dağ G. Determination of the compliance level of pa- tients who underwent kidney transplantation in the Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus to immunosuppressive therapy. 2020;17:1-9. doi:10.5222/HEAD.2020.42275</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_evjUvV9">The effectiveness of interventions to improve immunosuppressive adherence of renal transplantation patients: systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Akıncı</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Özbaş</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://dergipark.org.tr/tr/pub/sagakaderg/issue/64770/875578" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ZZ4SqDp">J Health Acad</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="257" to="264" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Akıncı N, Özbaş A. The effectiveness of interventions to improve immunosuppressive adherence of renal transplantation patients: systematic review. J Health Acad. 2021;8(3):257-264. https:// dergipark.org.tr/tr/pub/sagakaderg/issue/64770/875578</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Q6VPxeU">Prevalence of non-adherence to immunosuppressive medications in kidney transplant recipients: barriers and predictors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Taj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Baghaffar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Alnajjar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Almashabi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ismail</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.12659/aot.928356</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_vmkAHeZ">Ann Transplant</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="928356" to="928357" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Taj SM, Baghaffar H, Alnajjar DK, Almashabi NK, Ismail S. Prevalence of non-adherence to immunosuppressive medications in kidney transplant recipients: barriers and predictors. Ann Transplant. 2021; 26:e928356-1. doi:10.12659/AOT.928356</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_RPH8swz">Navigating medication-taking after kidney transplant</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Balakrishnan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Weinmeyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Serper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Bailey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kaiser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.sapharm.2022.05.010</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_8c4H33f">Res Social Adm Pharm</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3846" to="3854" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Balakrishnan A, Weinmeyer R, Serper M, Bailey SC, Kaiser K, Wolf M. Navigating medication-taking after kidney transplant. Res Social Adm Pharm. 2022;18:3846-3854. doi:10.1016/j. sapharm.2022.05.010</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_vP6QSFX">The impact of socio-demographic factors on the functioning of liver transplant patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kisielska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Schneider-Matyka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Rachubińska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ustanowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rybicka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Grochans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3390/ijerph19074230</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_jY8UVAm">Int J Environ Res Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4230</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kisielska A, Schneider-Matyka D, Rachubińska K, Ustanowski P, Rybicka A, Grochans E. The impact of socio-demographic factors on the functioning of liver transplant patients. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19(7):4230. doi:10.3390/ijerph19074230</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_nmf8nut">Compliance with immunosuppressant treatment in kidney transplant patients and nurse&apos;s responsibilities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tuncer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Khorshid</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_PzzsH8P">J Nephrol Nurs</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="26" to="31" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Tuncer M, Khorshid L. Compliance with immunosuppressant treat- ment in kidney transplant patients and nurse&apos;s responsibilities. J Nephrol Nurs. 2018;13(1):26-31.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qJS99TQ">Effectiveness of IT-based interventions on self-management in adult kidney transplant recipients: a systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Eslami</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Khoshrounejad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Golmakani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/s12911-020-01360-2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Mrk3JnK">BMC Med Inform Decis Mak</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Eslami S, Khoshrounejad F, Golmakani R, et al. Effectiveness of IT-based interventions on self-management in adult kidney trans- plant recipients: a systematic review. BMC Med Inform Decis Mak. 2021;21(1):2. doi:10.1186/s12911-020-01360-2</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qwfMmCY">eHealth in transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Duettmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Naik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Zukunft</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/tri.13778</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_g5Sw3sj">Transpl Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Duettmann W, Naik MG, Zukunft B, et al. eHealth in transplantation. Transpl Int. 2021;34(1):16-26. doi:10.1111/tri.13778</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_hzfs9Tz">Improving adherence to weight-loss medication (Liraglutide 3.0 mg) using mobile phone text messaging and healthcare professional support</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cunich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Fuller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Purcell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Flynn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Caterson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/oby.22930</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_dSS5pQz">Obesity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1889" to="1901" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Li A, Cunich M, Fuller N, Purcell K, Flynn A, Caterson I. Improving adherence to weight-loss medication (Liraglutide 3.0 mg) using mobile phone text messaging and healthcare professional support. Obesity. 2020;28(10):1889-1901. doi:10.1002/oby.22930</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_BgBBzua">How mobile health affects primary healthcare? Questionnaire design and attitude assessment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Erfannia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Barman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hussain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Barati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Arji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/2055207620942357</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_HAbDDPu">Digital Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2055207620942357</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Erfannia L, Barman MP, Hussain S, Barati R, Arji G. How mobile health affects primary healthcare? Questionnaire design and attitude assessment. Digital Health. 2020;6:2055207620942357. doi:10. 1177/2055207620942357</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_4jVmgbp">Mobile medication manager application to improve adherence with immunosuppressive therapy in renal transplant recipients: a randomized controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Min</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0224595</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_sMvbGZx">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">224595</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Han A, Min S, Ahn S, et al. Mobile medication manager application to improve adherence with immunosuppressive therapy in renal transplant recipients: a randomized controlled trial. PLoS One. 2019; 14(11):e0224595. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0224595</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_QWn23tn">Transplant surgery enters a new era: increasing immunosuppressive medication adherence through mobile apps and smart watches</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Levine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Torabi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Choinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Rocca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Graham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.amjsurg.2019.02.018</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_JAxVCWv">Am J Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">218</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Levine D, Torabi J, Choinski K, Rocca JP, Graham JA. Transplant surgery enters a new era: increasing immunosuppressive medication adherence through mobile apps and smart watches. Am J Surg. 2019; 218:18-20. doi:10.1016/j.amjsurg.2019.02.018</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_6b5nWfd">Development and psychometric testing of the Turkish immunosuppressive medication adherence scale</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Özdemir Köken</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Talas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gökmen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5152/turkjnephrol.2019.3371</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_vGUhUnx">Turk J Nephrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="120" to="126" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Özdemir Köken Z, Talas MS, Gökmen D. Development and psy- chometric testing of the Turkish immunosuppressive medication adherence scale. Turk J Nephrol. 2019;28(2):120-126. doi:10.5152/ turkjnephrol.2019.3371</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_FGw3fh6">Evaluation of adherence to ımmunosuppressive treatment with different methods in kidney transplant recipients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Sarıgöl Ordin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ö</forename><surname>Karayurt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ertan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yıldız</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5262/tndt.2018.3147</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_GjEMZtQ">Turk Nephrol Dial Transplant</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="254" to="261" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sarıgöl Ordin Y, Karayurt Ö, Ertan N, Yıldız S. Evaluation of adher- ence to ımmunosuppressive treatment with different methods in kidney transplant recipients. Turk Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2018; 27(3):254-261. doi:10.5262/tndt.2018.3147</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_jTddpJw">Diagnostic accuracy of measurement methods to assess nonadherence to immunosuppressive drugs in kidney transplant recipients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Schäfer-Keller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Steiger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Denhaerynck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">De</forename><surname>Geest</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1600-6143.2007.02127.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_3c7YqpP">Am J Transplant (AJT)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="616" to="626" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Schäfer-Keller P, Steiger J, Bock A, Denhaerynck K, De Geest S. Diagnostic accuracy of measurement methods to assess non- adherence to immunosuppressive drugs in kidney transplant recipients. Am J Transplant (AJT). 2008;8:616-626.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Yjm53dQ">Identification of immunosuppressive medication nonadherence factors through a combined theory model in renal transplant recipients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3389/fphar.2021.655836</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_7VPpfMb">Front Pharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">655836</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Zhang P, Zhu X, Yan J, Liu J. Identification of immunosuppressive medication nonadherence factors through a combined theory model in renal transplant recipients. Front Pharmacol. 2021;12:655836. doi:10.3389/fphar.2021.6558366</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5152/tjg.2018.18058</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.akdenizorgannakli.net/pdf/organ-nakli-el-kitabi.pdfs" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_7QpxrUZ">Organ Transplantation Center Organ Transplantation Handbook</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="42" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Akdeniz University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Akdeniz University Organ Transplantation Center Organ Transplan- tation Handbook, 2012, 1-42. https://www.akdenizorgannakli.net/ pdf/organ-nakli-el-kitabi.pdfs</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_yZ9pNeJ">Immunosuppressive medication adherence in liver transplant patients: a single center experience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Özdemir Köken</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Karahan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Sezer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Abbasoğlu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.46332/aemj.785045</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_bRURxJ4">Ahi Evran Med J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="88" to="95" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Özdemir Köken Z, Karahan S, Sezer RE, Abbasoğlu O. Immuno- suppressive medication adherence in liver transplant patients: a single center experience. Ahi Evran Med J. 2020;4(3):88-95.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_CW437rt">Life quality and compliance after transplant: the case of Turkey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Güzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Korkmaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.transproceed.2019.01.083</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_MvYcA6X">Transplant Proc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1029" to="1037" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Güzel H, Korkmaz M. Life quality and compliance after transplant: the case of Turkey. Transplant Proc. 2019;51(4):1029-1037. doi:10. 1016/j.transproceed.2019.01.083</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_45684M2">Prevalence and correlates of medication non-adherence among kidney transplant recipients more than 6 months posttransplant: a cross-sectional study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Weng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chandwani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kurtyka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zacker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Chisholm-Burns</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Demissie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/1471-2369-14-261</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_grKaBtR">BMC Nephrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">261</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Weng FL, Chandwani S, Kurtyka KM, Zacker C, Chisholm-Burns MA, Demissie K. Prevalence and correlates of medication non-adherence among kidney transplant recipients more than 6 months post- transplant: a cross-sectional study. BMC Nephrol. 2013;14(1):261. doi:10.1186/1471-2369-14-261</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_S6vVjCw">Digital health technologies to support medication adherence in chronic kidney disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>O'hara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Yi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jardine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dawson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/nep.14113</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_cjqMvFs">Nephrology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="917" to="924" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">O&apos;Hara DV, Yi TW, Lee VW, Jardine M, Dawson J. Digital health technologies to support medication adherence in chronic kidney disease. Nephrology. 2022;27(12):917-924. doi:10.1111/nep.14113</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_599dqc7">Improving medication adherence and outcomes in adult kidney transplant patients using a personal systems approach: SystemCHANGE™ results of the MAGIC randomized clinical trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Russell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hathaway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Remy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/ajt.15528</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_5WKgkpr">Am J Transplant (AJT)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="136" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Russell CL, Hathaway D, Remy LM, et al. Improving medication adherence and outcomes in adult kidney transplant patients using a personal systems approach: SystemCHANGE™ results of the MAGIC randomized clinical trial. Am J Transplant (AJT). 2020;20(1):125-136. doi:10.1111/ajt.15528</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_9QdXaQA">Efficacy of interventions for adherence to the immunosuppressive therapy in kidney transplant recipients: meta-analysis and systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/jim-2016-000265</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_XAGwjsj">J Investig Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1049" to="1056" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Zhu Y, Zhou Y, Zhang L, Zhang J, Lin J. Efficacy of interventions for adherence to the immunosuppressive therapy in kidney transplant recipients: meta-analysis and systematic review. J Investig Med. 2017;65:1049-1056. doi:10.1136/jim-2016-000265</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_uUbvgy8">Automated reminders and physician notification to promote immunosuppression adherence among kidney transplant recipients: a randomized trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Reese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Bloom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Trofe-Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1053/j.ajkd.2016.10.017</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_wpay29B">Am J Kidney Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="400" to="409" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Reese PP, Bloom RD, Trofe-Clark J, et al. Automated reminders and physician notification to promote immunosuppression adherence among kidney transplant recipients: a randomized trial. Am J Kidney Dis. 2017;69(3):400-409. doi:10.1053/j.ajkd.2016.10.017</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_3tEAuNJ">Sustainability of improvements in medication adherence through a mobile health intervention</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Mcgillicuddy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Taber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mueller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.7182/pit2015975</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_zcHcftP">Prog Transplant</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="217" to="223" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-09">2015. Sep</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">McGillicuddy JW, Taber DJ, Mueller M, et al. Sustainability of improvements in medication adherence through a mobile health intervention. Prog Transplant. 2015;Sep 25(3):217-223. doi:10.7182/ pit2015975</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_WbKqSNt">The spectrum of nonadherence with medication in heart, liver, and lung transplant patients assessed in various ways</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">De</forename><surname>Bleser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Dobbels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Berben</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1432-2277.2011.01296.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_W5XWvgB">Transpl Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="882" to="891" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">De Bleser L, Dobbels F, Berben L, et al. The spectrum of nonadherence with medication in heart, liver, and lung transplant patients assessed in various ways. Transpl Int. 2011;24(9):882-891. doi:10.1111/j.1432- 2277.2011.01296.x</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_k8yjjEG">Why do patients forget to take immunosuppression medications and miss appointments: can a mobile phone app help?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Israni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Dean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kasel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Berndt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Wildebush</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/publichealth.5285</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_xu8mkYN">JMIR Public Health Surveill</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5285</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Israni A, Dean C, Kasel B, Berndt L, Wildebush W, Wang CJ. Why do patients forget to take immunosuppression medications and miss appointments: can a mobile phone app help? JMIR Public Health Surveill. 2016;N2(1):e5285. doi:10.2196/publichealth.5285</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Ruc6MFm">A randomized trial of a multicomponent intervention to promote medication adherence: the teen adherence in kidney transplant effectiveness of intervention trial (TAKE-IT)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Foster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alh</forename><surname>Pai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Zelikovsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1053/j.ajkd.2017.12.012</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_VRBEz8X">Am J Kidney Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="30" to="41" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Foster BJ, Pai ALH, Zelikovsky N, et al. A randomized trial of a multicomponent intervention to promote medication adherence: the teen adherence in kidney transplant effectiveness of intervention trial (TAKE-IT). Am J Kidney Dis. 2018;72(1):30-41. doi:10.1053/j.ajkd.2017. 12.012</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_XQuZ5nQ">Exploring the usage of a mobile phone application in transplanted patients to encourage medication compliance and education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zanetti-Yabur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rizzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hayde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Watkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Rocca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Graham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.amjsurg.2017.01.026</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_FFzcnXb">Am J Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">214</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="743" to="747" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Zanetti-Yabur A, Rizzo A, Hayde N, Watkins AC, Rocca JP, Graham JA. Exploring the usage of a mobile phone application in transplanted patients to encourage medication compliance and education. Am J Surg. 2017;214(4):743-747. doi:10.1016/j.amjsurg.2017.01.026</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_b2mKJBu">Factors related to immunosuppressant medication adherence in renal transplant recipients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Chisholm-Burns</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Pinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Parker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1399-0012.2011.01589.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_GWxmdUR">Clin Transplant</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="706" to="713" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Chisholm-Burns M, Pinsky B, Parker G, et al. Factors related to immunosuppressant medication adherence in renal transplant recipients. Clin Transplant. 2012;26:706-713. doi:10.1111/j.1399- 0012.2011.01589.x</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_KCKyH37">A pilot randomized controlled trial to promote immunosuppressant adherence in adult kidney transplant recipients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cukor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ver Halen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pencille</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Tedla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Salifu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1159/000448627</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_J4aKYAk">Nephron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">135</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Cukor D, Ver Halen N, Pencille M, Tedla F, Salifu M. A pilot ran- domized controlled trial to promote immunosuppressant adherence in adult kidney transplant recipients. Nephron. 2017;135(1):6-14. doi:10.1159/000448627</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_BXDnsy2">Detecting, preventing and treating non-adherence to immunosuppression after kidney transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Gandolfini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Palmisano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Fiaccadori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Cravedi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Maggiore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ckj/sfac017</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_CbNJfmb">Clin Kidney J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1253" to="1274" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Gandolfini I, Palmisano A, Fiaccadori E, Cravedi P, Maggiore U. Detecting, preventing and treating non-adherence to immuno- suppression after kidney transplantation. Clin Kidney J. 2022;15: 1253-1274. doi:10.1093/ckj/sfac017</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
