<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ZX934sA">The cost-effectiveness of digital health interventions: A systematic review of the literature</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mohammed</forename><surname>Ayalew</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Victoria</forename><surname>Ramos Gonzalez</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sanjib</forename><surname>Saha</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Andrea</forename><surname>Gentili</surname></persName>
							<email>andrea.gentili@gmail.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Giovanna</forename><surname>Failla</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Andriy</forename><surname>Melnyk</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Valeria</forename><surname>Puleo</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Gian</forename><surname>Luca</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Di</forename><surname>Tanna</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Walter</forename><surname>Ricciardi</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Fidelia</forename><surname>Cascini</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Hawassa University , Ethiopia</note>
								<orgName type="institution">Hawassa University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="ET">Ethiopia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Instituto de Salud Carlos III (ISCIII) , Spain</note>
								<orgName type="institution">Instituto de Salud Carlos III (ISCIII)</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Lund University , Sweden Section of Hygiene and Public Health ,</note>
								<orgName type="department">Section of Hygiene and Public Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lund University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Department of Life Sciences and Public Health , Università Cattolica del Sacro Cuore , Roma , Italy ,</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Life Sciences and Public Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Università Cattolica del Sacro Cuore</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Roma</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Department of Public Health , University of Verona , Verona , Italy ,</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Public Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Verona</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Verona</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Statistics Division , The George Institute for Global Health , University of New South Wales , Newtown , NSW , Australia</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Statistics Division</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">The George Institute for Global Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of New South Wales</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Newtown</settlement>
									<region>NSW</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_BsAm923">The cost-effectiveness of digital health interventions: A systematic review of the literature</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">0A1FE83F0DA454ECF37DA9ED82C338DA</idno>
					<note type="submission">submitted to Digital Public Health, a section of the journal Frontiers in Public Health RECEIVED September ACCEPTED July</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T08:34+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term xml:id="_7J9mGPa">digital health</term>
					<term xml:id="_MQCzNZ6">telemedicine</term>
					<term xml:id="_2NwMaV5">mobile health</term>
					<term xml:id="_sxEz7y9">electronic health</term>
					<term xml:id="_Ez5yt2s">telehealth</term>
					<term xml:id="_WdZ2Ust">digital care</term>
					<term xml:id="_kj9jHma">cost-effectiveness</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_dUbnEFh"><p xml:id="_4ZhRmsg"><s xml:id="_5T4MMZz">Background: Digital health interventions have significant potential to improve safety, efficacy, and quality of care, reducing waste in healthcare costs.</s><s xml:id="_2TDyNNK">Despite these premises, the evidence regarding cost and effectiveness of digital tools in health is scarce and limited.</s></p><p xml:id="_kvaGa9z"><s xml:id="_n2GMgGW">Objectives: The aim of this systematic review is to summarize the evidence on the cost-effectiveness of digital health interventions and to assess whether the studies meet the established quality criteria.</s></p><p xml:id="_rezUxbb"><s xml:id="_W7CwKmT">Methods: We queried PubMed, Scopus and Web of Science databases for articles in English published from January , to December , that performed economic evaluations of digital health technologies.</s><s xml:id="_RmRQb68">The methodological rigorousness of studies was assessed with the Consolidated Health Economic Evaluation Reporting Standards (CHEERS).</s><s xml:id="_mD5qHUN">The review was conducted according to the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analysis (PRISMA) checklist.</s></p><p xml:id="_rABwB2C"><s xml:id="_jgRGt5S">Results: Search identified , results, of which were selected for abstract and were included in this review.</s><s xml:id="_vah63nS">The studies were heterogeneous by country (mostly conducted in upper and upper-middle income countries), type of eHealth intervention, method of implementation, and reporting perspectives.</s><s xml:id="_tA9N854">The qualitative analysis identified the economic and effectiveness evaluation of six different types of interventions: ( ) seventeen studies on new video-monitoring service systems; ( ) five studies on text messaging interventions; ( ) five studies on web platforms and digital health portals; ( ) two studies on telephone support; ( ) three studies on new mobile phone-based systems and applications; and ( ) three studies on digital technologies and innovations.</s><s xml:id="_xKukppu">Conclusion: Findings on cost-effectiveness of digital interventions showed a growing body of evidence and suggested a generally favorable effect in terms of costs and health outcomes.</s><s xml:id="_DrXK77x">However, due to the heterogeneity across study methods, the comparison between interventions still remains difficult.</s><s xml:id="_3qsRYjZ">Frontiers in Public Health frontiersin.org</s><s xml:id="_6qNPk3D">Gentili et al. .</s><s xml:id="_VQcy5zY">/fpubh. .</s></p><p xml:id="_sMYaW8W"><s xml:id="_PXSXg6Q">Further research based on a standardized approach is needed in order to methodically analyze incremental cost-effectiveness ratios, costs, and health benefits.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.26" lry="842.116"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.26" lry="842.116"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.26" lry="842.116"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.26" lry="842.116"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="842.116" lry="595.26"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="842.116" lry="595.26"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.26" lry="842.116"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="842.116" lry="595.26"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="842.116" lry="595.26"/>
		<surface n="10" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="842.116" lry="595.26"/>
		<surface n="11" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="842.116" lry="595.26"/>
		<surface n="12" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="842.116" lry="595.26"/>
		<surface n="13" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="842.116" lry="595.26"/>
		<surface n="14" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="842.116" lry="595.26"/>
		<surface n="15" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="842.116" lry="595.26"/>
		<surface n="16" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="842.116" lry="595.26"/>
		<surface n="17" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="842.116" lry="595.26"/>
		<surface n="18" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="842.116" lry="595.26"/>
		<surface n="19" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="842.116" lry="595.26"/>
		<surface n="20" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="842.116" lry="595.26"/>
		<surface n="21" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="842.116" lry="595.26"/>
		<surface n="22" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="842.116" lry="595.26"/>
		<surface n="23" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="842.116" lry="595.26"/>
		<surface n="24" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="842.116" lry="595.26"/>
		<surface n="25" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="842.116" lry="595.26"/>
		<surface n="26" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.26" lry="842.116"/>
		<surface n="27" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.26" lry="842.116"/>
		<surface n="28" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.26" lry="842.116"/>
		<surface n="29" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.26" lry="842.116"/>
		<surface n="30" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.26" lry="842.116"/>
		<surface n="31" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.26" lry="842.116"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_bbJT5nK">Introduction</head><p xml:id="_npQCvqF"><s xml:id="_45GSHjC">In a rapidly evolving society, the progress of digital technology used to improve human health and well-being needs to be constantly evaluated, both in its effectiveness and its efficiency.</s><s xml:id="_HXFdE8Q">The WHO defines eHealth as "the cost-effective and secure use of information and communications technologies in support of health and health-related fields, including healthcare services, health surveillance, health literature, and health education, knowledge and research" <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_8JVCaac"><s xml:id="_DhvRC2p">Digital technology encompasses many areas of eHealth, such as e-learning, telemedicine, mobile health and health information systems.</s><s xml:id="_mfQNGbJ">eHealth also benefits from progress in related fields, such as artificial intelligence, big data analytics and genomics.</s></p><p xml:id="_AtG3HCH"><s xml:id="_6W76Dx8">Digitized health-related data is easier to store and quickly analyze, especially when structuring a data-driven approach to build analytical models for safety improvement, managing clinical risk and increasing the quality of healthcare organizations <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_ARKfQx4"><s xml:id="_wPZPS8n">During the COVID-19 pandemic, digital health technologies were successfully implemented to aid contact tracing, isolation management, primary care improvement and communication between citizens and decision makers <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_FfQstVu"><s xml:id="_fY6mUbw">South Korea is a prime example of a country with widespread digital health implementation, where remotely located supercomputers are used to secure and analyze medical big data and about 50% of digitized hospitals already use a paperless and comprehensive health care system.</s><s xml:id="_zR6SRXE">A rapid response and a cutting-edge governmentrun digital contact tracing system allowed South Korea to have early success in flattening the curve during its first wave of COVID-19 <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(4)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_GkHpQur"><s xml:id="_CabdakP">Today more than 120 countries are prioritizing healthrelated digital progress, with a growing need to systematically implement standards-based interoperable solutions.</s></p><p xml:id="_gUwjdxy"><s xml:id="_5rYHcct">Despite the institutional fervor and wide applicability of digital health strategies, healthcare facilities and services are struggling to assess the cost-effectiveness of different solutions.</s><s xml:id="_G7bubcJ">The absence of standards and tools for the comparative assessment of functionality and value of fast-evolving digital health solutions exacerbates the pressing need for quality evidence to navigate normative change <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_hBmQcB5">This systematic review aims to describing the cost effectiveness of digital health interventions by assessing their impact on standardized indicators, such as Quality Adjusted Life Years (QALYs) and Disease Adjusted Life Years (DALYs), on healthcare expenditure by comparing the strategies with the Median-Based Incremental Cost-Effectiveness Ratio (ICER), and by evaluating the quality of the evidence reported.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_xAk2Rnt">Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_esWdgCB">Search strategy</head><p xml:id="_HQT3vzv"><s xml:id="_r8BqMes">A systematic review of relevant articles published on the cost-effectiveness of digital health technologies was developed in March 2021.</s><s xml:id="_QQjBNST">The researchers developed the search strategies from January to February 2021 to include a wide range of digital health innovations.</s><s xml:id="_5NPKmmN">The academic databases and systems inquired were PubMed, Web of Science and Scopus, using the query reported in Appendix 1.</s><s xml:id="_pb4yuFW">A manual search of reference lists of both relevant systematic reviews and included studies was also performed.</s><s xml:id="_6vMy8ua">Detailed information and query strings used for the search are disclosed the manuscript.</s></p><p xml:id="_BD74D7D"><s xml:id="_zEsWTVf">The systematic literature review was conducted according to the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analysis (PRISMA) 2009 checklist.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_4VGhsq2">Inclusion/exclusion criteria</head><p xml:id="_N8mDcfT"><s xml:id="_fHwM3cV">Eligible studies included any original study (cohorts, clinical trials, cross-sectional studies, case-control studies and case series) that reported an analysis of the cost effectiveness of digital health applications and innovations, with or without a comparison to standard care.</s><s xml:id="_UyjtdgP">Due to the rapidly changing nature of digital technologies and because a similar systematic review was released in 2015 <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref>, only articles published from January 1, 2016 to December 31, 2020 and written in English were included.</s><s xml:id="_AdXWR7y">Unavailable full texts, abstract-only papers, case reports and secondary research (commentaries, editorials, etc.) were excluded from the study.</s><s xml:id="_tmZSu8z">An exclusion criterion included studies where the digital health innovation was only used for recording patients' information.</s><s xml:id="_ezJ2uPN">More detailed information is contained in the PICO criteria table <ref type="table">(Table 1</ref>).</s></p><p xml:id="_9H4FhyQ"><s xml:id="_VXwQbzv">TABLE Population, Intervention, Comparison, Outcome (PICO) inclusion and exclusion criteria.</s><s xml:id="_rzgsuWe">Include Exclude Population • Users using any form of digital health implementation • Not applicable Intervention &amp; Comparator • Not applicable • Not applicable Outcomes • All reported outcomes related to cost-efficacy analysis of digital health technologies will be included • Clinical outcomes Study design • Any original study (cohorts, clinical trials, cross-sectional studies, case-control studies, and case series)</s></p><p xml:id="_tFACEX3"><s xml:id="_dJBsqWY">• Reviews (To be included in the discussion)</s></p><p xml:id="_AXr4kGP"><s xml:id="_n9eGkqN">• Unavailable full texts</s></p><p xml:id="_d7bRU8e"><s xml:id="_Eunf7vx">• Abstract-only papers</s></p><p xml:id="_5NwXPnu"><s xml:id="_wRR3Fa9">• Case reports • Secondary research (commentaries, editorials, etc.) Limits English language only Articles published in peer reviewed journals only Timespan 01/01/2016-31/12/2020</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_wcx6nw6">Selection process and data extraction</head><p xml:id="_ffETe8A"><s xml:id="_ByUxA3W">The results of the electronic search were downloaded into a reference manager library (EndNote).</s><s xml:id="_hQA3fA6">After duplicates were removed, titles and abstracts were reviewed by 2 experienced systematic reviewers working independently to determine whether each study met the eligibility criteria.</s><s xml:id="_sq3W9Jk">Full-text copies of potentially relevant studies were retrieved and further assessed against inclusion/exclusion criteria by two independent reviewers.</s><s xml:id="_ESTTRZF">At both stages, disagreements were resolved by discussion or a third reviewer.</s><s xml:id="_UFeVFPF">At the end of the full-text review, the articles that met all predefined criteria were read by two researchers to confirm the inclusion of these articles.</s></p><p xml:id="_gpQCnUM"><s xml:id="_tapz5KS">A pilot data extraction was conducted by two of the investigators.</s><s xml:id="_dXKncap">Any discrepancy pertinent to data extraction was discussed to reach a consensus.</s><s xml:id="_DRUzvQE">The collected information included the following items: (1) general information (including authors, publication date, title, and country);</s></p><p xml:id="_tKP2dKv"><s xml:id="_vQ4dTKA">(2) study characteristics (including discipline examined and kind of intervention); (3) methodology (including modeling method, time horizon, and perspective); (4) cost-effectiveness information (including cost measurement, consequence measurement, and ICER); and (5) key findings (and conclusion).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Hjxs84U">Assessment of methodological quality</head><p xml:id="_YNVCqhJ"><s xml:id="_M8JHtZk">The Consolidated Health Economic Evaluation Reporting Standards (CHEERS) checklist, developed by the International Society for Pharmacoeconomics and Outcomes Research, was the questionnaire used to assess the methodological quality of each study included at the end of the selection process.</s><s xml:id="_VjyMQGV">The CHEERS checklist included 24 items, and the recommendations were subdivided into six categories:</s></p><p xml:id="_kXc2J4S"><s xml:id="_nWungTa">(1) title and abstract, (2) introduction, (3) methods, (4) results, (5) discussion, and (6) other.</s><s xml:id="_7facRFW">One point was assigned to each item when the quality criteria were fulfilled (and zero points for not entirely conforming to the criteria) to generate a total score (maximum score is <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_tSsKcc3"><s xml:id="_XkeJcDF">Two of the investigators independently assessed the quality of each study and assigned the scores based on the CHEERS checklist.</s><s xml:id="_RyEzzxd">Any disagreement was resolved by discussion and consensus with a third investigator.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_EzAUw47">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_YCPtt8z">Search results</head><p xml:id="_9C6u4JQ"><s xml:id="_KjKYrwK">The results of the data extraction and selection process are shown in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_sS4n3uP">The database search, after duplicates were removed, returned a total of 1,476 records.</s><s xml:id="_9TmQHwq">In compliance with inclusion/exclusion criteria, the screening by title determined the inclusion of 552 abstracts.</s><s xml:id="_PhB8hH9">The abstract screening reported the inclusion of 81 full-text articles.</s><s xml:id="_8SzETzr">Following the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) guidelines, a total of 35 out of the 81 articles were included in the final review.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_xquTJee">Study characteristics</head><p xml:id="_A7vPufj"><s xml:id="_q2h6qJ5">Records information and study characteristics have been subsequently extracted and summarized in Table <ref type="table">2</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_eRuqsMZ"><s xml:id="_6Pknntb">The 35 studies spanned 17 countries, the majority of which were conducted in high income economies (28, 80%), compared to 7 in low-income economies (1, 2.9%), lowermiddle income economies (5, 14.3%) and upper-middle income economies (1, 2.9%).</s></p><p xml:id="_2fJMWUG"><s xml:id="_KCUjaYK">The most represented country was the United States of America, with 11 studies (31.4%).</s></p><p xml:id="_7wtTGsm"><s xml:id="_tV2scB7">The articles covered a wide range of disciplines: 12 studies discussed primary care (34.3%); three discussed gynecology (11.4%); pneumology and psychiatry had three studies each (8.6%); endocrinology, gastroenterology, neurology and orthopedy had two studies each (5.7%); cardiology, infectious disease, ophthalmology and pediatrics had one study each (2.9%).</s><s xml:id="_X4WYrFZ">The types of digital health intervention implemented to support citizens and patients and to reduce costs from both societal and health payer perspective, were:</s></p><p xml:id="_9acCxbw"><s xml:id="_xHBbwK7">-Video-conferencing system: 17/35, 48.6% <ref type="bibr">(7, 9, 10, 16-20, 28-31, 33, 34, 36, 37, 41)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_EdUb4Kp">-Text messaging intervention: 5/35, 14.3% <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_w53Abfc">-Web platforms and digital health portals: 5/35, 14.3% <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">35,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">38,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_Jpq8ZpM">-Telephone support: 2/35, 5.7% <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_ybyatPT">-Mobile phone-based systems and applications: 3/35, 8.6% <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_3wtuDMZ">-Digital technologies and innovations: 3/35, 8.6% <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_EyRNwGB"><s xml:id="_2WgQfyx">Cost-effectiveness analysis (CEA) was a criterion of selection, therefore all the studies included a CEA, whereas a cost-utility analysis (CUA) has been performed in addition to the primary CEA in eight studies (22.9%) <ref type="bibr">(29-32, 34, 35, 37, 38)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_3P4tsKM"><s xml:id="_XfSf6FK">The costing perspective was mostly from payer/program/health service provider perspective (24, 68.7%), whereas the costing perspective was societal in 19 studies (54.3%).</s><s xml:id="_nJXknCc">Only one study did not clearly report the costing perspective (2.9%).</s></p><p xml:id="_Hza9PCp"><s xml:id="_q5DEG7j">In order to obtain QALYs, the studies of this review referred to different instruments deriving from the trials of reference.</s><s xml:id="_D63xuaT">The questionnaires and surveys used to estimate QALYs were: ShortForm-6 Dimensions (32); a multistate body mass table model <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref>; European Quality of Life 5-Dimensions <ref type="bibr">(9-11, 19, 29, 30, 33, 34, 37, 41)</ref>;</s></p><p xml:id="_KwrMXwM"><s xml:id="_at6gqgx">. /fpubh. .</s><s xml:id="_994KyDU">TABLE Study characteristics.</s><s xml:id="_A5cu7zp">Author (published year) Country Discipline Study design Perspective Economic evaluation type Quality assessment (CHEERS) Sample size Clarke et al. (2018) (7) England Pneumology RCT Health service perspective Cost-effectiveness analysis 18/24 (75%) 227 Krishnan et al. (2019) (8) USA Primary care 2-arm parallel-group randomized controlled trial Healthcare payer perspective Cost-effectiveness analysis 21/24 (88%) 194 Lugo et al. (2019) (9) Spain Pneumology Prospective, open, randomized study Healthcare payer perspective Cost-effectiveness analysis 17/24 (71%) 186 Wan et al. (2019) (10) USA Endocrinology Prospective pragmatic trial Societal perspective Cost-effectiveness analysis 19/24 (79%) 81 Islam et al. (2020) (11) Bangladesh Endocrinology Prospective, randomized, controlled trial Health service system perspective Cost-effectiveness analysis 21/24 (88%) 236 Oostingh et al. (2019) (12) Netherlands Gynecology RCT Healthcare and societal perspective Cost-effectiveness analysis 19/24 (79%) 793 Song et al. (2018) (13) Japan Gynecology RCT Health insurance society and companies' perspective Cost-effectiveness analysis 22/24 (92%) 1,526 Lowry et al. (2020) (14) USA Gynecology Comparative modeling study Federal payer perspective Cost-effectiveness analysis 19/24 (79%) Not specified Bahrainwala et al. (2020) (15) Madagascar Infectious diseases Modeling study Healthcare perspective Cost-effectiveness analysis 21/24 (88%) 500 Thakar et al. (2018) (16) India Neurology Prospective cohort Societal perspective Cost-effectiveness analysis 19/24 (79%) 1,200 Whetten et al. (2018) (17) USA Neurology RCT Healthcare payer perspective Cost-effectiveness analysis 21/24 (88%) 777 Nguyen et al. (2016) (18) Singapore Ophtalmology Prospective Cohort Health system and societal perspectives Cost-effectiveness analysis 23/24 (96%) 757 Buvik et al. (2019) (41) Norway Orthopedy RCT Societal and health sector perspective Cost-effectiveness analysis 18/24 (75%) 389 Vestergaard et al. (2020) (19) Denmark Primary care RCT Danish public healthcare sector perspective Cost-effectiveness analysis 21/24 (88%) 274 Oksman et al. (2017) (20) Finland Primary care RCT Not specified Cost-effectiveness analysis 15/24 (63%) 1,535 (Continued) Frontiers in Public Health frontiersin.org</s><s xml:id="_7z537hg">Gentili et al. .</s><s xml:id="_35zMzUn">/fpubh. .</s><s xml:id="_gMuxPUb">TABLE Continued Author (published year) Country Discipline Study design Perspective Economic evaluation type Quality assessment (CHEERS) Sample size Levy et al. (2017) (21) USA Primary care RCT Primary health system perspective Cost-effectiveness analysis 21/24 (88%) 8,544 Kumar et al. (2018) (22) USA Primary care Prospective cohort Societal and payer perspective Cost-effectiveness analysis 23/24 (96%) 100,000 Jo et al. (2019) (23) Bangladesh Primary care RCT Program perspective (inclusive of development, start-up, and implementation phases) Cost-effectiveness analysis 21/24 (88%) 610 Cleghorn et al. (2019) (24) New Zealand Primary care RCT Health system perspective Cost-effectiveness analysis 23/24 (96%) 4,400,000 Prinja et al. (2018) (25) India Primary care RCT Both health system and societal perspective Cost-effectiveness analysis 22/24 (92%) 300,000 O'Sullivan et al. (2020) (26) Ireland Primary care RCT Publicly-funded healthcare system perspective Cost-effectiveness analysis 22/24 (92%) 565 Nordyke et al. (2019) (27) USA Primary care Prospective cohort Healthcare payer perspective Cost-effectiveness analysis 21/24 (88%) 5,145 Painter et al. (2017) (28) USA Psychiatry RCT Societal perspective Cost-effectiveness analysis 21/24 (88%) 265 de Jong et al. (2020) (29) Netherlands Gastroenterology RCT Societal perspective Cost-effectiveness and cost-utility analysis 21/24 (88%) 909 Hoyo et al. (2019) (30) Spain Gastroenterology RCT Societal perspective Cost-effectiveness and cost-utility analysis 22/24 (92%) 63 Fusco and Francesco (2016) (31) Italy Orthopedy Modeling study Health sector and society Cost-effectiveness and cost-utility analysis 22/24 (92%) 1,000 Watson et al. (2018) (32) USA Psychiatry RCT Third party-payor perspective and a partial societal perspective Cost-effectiveness and cost-utility analysis 17/24 (71%) 179 Yoo et al. (2016) (33) USA Intensive care Modeling study Healthcare perspective Cost-effectiveness 21/24 (88%) Not specified Witt Udsen et al. (2017) (34) Denmark Pneumology Cluster-randomized trial Healthcare and social care sector perspective (including hospital services, primary care, medicine, home care services and rehabilitation) Cost-effectiveness and cost-utility analysis 22/24 (92%) 1,225 (Continued) Frontiers in Public Health frontiersin.org</s><s xml:id="_4BUEcHa">Gentili et al. .</s><s xml:id="_SjgQPMm">/fpubh. .</s><s xml:id="_ZYtKtxF">TABLE Continued Author (published year) Country Discipline Study design Perspective Economic evaluation type Quality assessment (CHEERS) Sample size Romero-Sanchiz et al. (2017) (35) Spain Psychiatry Pragmatic, multi-center, three-armed parallel RCT Societal perspective Cost-effectiveness and cost-utility analysis 24/24 (100%) 296 Wang et al. (2016) (36) China Primary care RCT Societal and health payer perspective Cost-effectiveness analysis 17/24 (71%) 11,987 Lopez-Villegas et al. (2020) (37) Norway Cardiology Open-label, 1:1, randomized, non-masked, controlled trial National Healthcare System and Societal perspective Cost-effectiveness and cost-utility analysis 21/24 (88%) 50 Sjostrom et al. (2017) (38) Sweden Gynecology RCT Societal perspective Cost-effectiveness and cost-utility analysis 22/24 (92%) 123 Modi et al. (2020) (39) India Pediatrics Two-arm, parallel, stratified cluster randomized controlled trial Program perspective Cost-effectiveness analysis 21/24 (88%) 561 Sharifi et al. (2017) (40) USA Primary care RCT Societal perspective Cost-effectiveness analysis 22/24 (92%) 2,000,000 Health Related Quality of Life (8, 14, 20, 31); Generalized Anxiety Disorder 7 (22); Quebec Sleep Questionnaire and Epworth Sleepiness Scale (9); Quality of Well-being Scale and Short Form Health Survey for Veterans (28); International Consultation on Continence Modular Questionnaire on Lower Urinary Tract Symptoms and Quality of Life (38).</s><s xml:id="_3aTYSsy">For the rest of the articles, QALYs were estimated from existing literature.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_MUkHJQv">Study quality</head><p xml:id="_rgs3NDp"><s xml:id="_UFdBU48">The number of items of the CHEERS Checklist satisfied by each study and the relative percentage are shown in Table <ref type="table">3</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_6u5UqrN"><s xml:id="_4rv6JPb">The studies were graded on the bases of the number of items accomplished and classified as follows:</s></p><p xml:id="_drs6YZN"><s xml:id="_TKkVgHs">-Excellent, if all items were present in the study: only one study (3%) reported <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(35)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_WbxpjSh">-Good, if at least 80% of the items were satisfied: 24 studies (69%) reported <ref type="bibr">(8, 11, 12, 15, 17-19, 21-31, 33, 34, 37-40)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_wG6ApQE">-Fair, if at least 70% of the items were satisfied: nine studies (26%) reported <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_n6a4jNm">-Average, if at least 60% of the items were satisfied: one study (3%) reported <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_M7ujmUS"><s xml:id="_vp4U2Vd">The five items most likely to not be reported were: Characterizing heterogeneity (11, 31%); Target population and subgroups (13, 37%); Abstract <ref type="bibr">(</ref>22, 63%); Choice of model (24, 69%); Discount rate (25, 71%).</s><s xml:id="_vQHApHz">In contrast, seven CHEERS checklist items were fulfilled by all studies (100%): Title; Background and objectives; Comparators; Time horizon; Choice of health outcomes; Analytical methods; Study parameters.</s><s xml:id="_HJuT5ZC">All the other 12 CHEERS items were included in almost 80% of the studies: Measurement of effectiveness (28, 80%); Currency, price date, and conversion (28, 80%); Setting and location (29, 83%); Characterizing uncertainty (30, 86%); Study perspective (32, 91%); Measurement and valuation of preference-based outcomes (32, 91%); Estimating resources and costs (32, 91%); Source of funding (32, 91%); Assumptions (33, 94%); Incremental costs and outcomes (34, 97%); Study findings, limitations, generalizability, and current knowledge (34, 97%); Conflicts of interest (34, 97%).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_TfumVn5">Type of technologies or interventions for digital health innovation</head><p xml:id="_wAru65d"><s xml:id="_AxXePnF">A summary of findings and evidence found is reported in Table <ref type="table">4</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_GpAbKwF"><s xml:id="_2HZB69r">. /fpubh. .</s></p><p xml:id="_T6xsgpW"><s xml:id="_EARdFBG">TABLE Consolidated health economic evaluation reporting standards checklist.</s><s xml:id="_uTSCvY2">Section item Clarke et al. (7) Wang et al. (36) Sharifi et al. (40) Sjostrom et al. (38) Song et al. (13) Vestergaard et al. (19) Thakar et al. (16) Painter et al. (28) Prinja et al. (25) Target population and subgroups 1 0 1 1 1 0 0 0</s></p><p xml:id="_NTKjFke"><s xml:id="_uvGfCW6">Setting and location</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">1 1 1 1 1 1 1 0 Study perspective 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Comparators 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Time horizon 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Discount rate 0 0 1 1 1 1 0 1 Choice of health outcomes 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Measurement of effectiveness 0 0 1 1 1 1 1 1</formula><p xml:id="_qDxHG3N"><s xml:id="_7tqqBcG">Measurement and valuation of preference based outcomes</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_1">0 0 1 1 1 1 1 1</formula><p xml:id="_vdeFKPd"><s xml:id="_hVxCUQG">Estimating resources and costs</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_2">1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1</formula><p xml:id="_mjV7Pca"><s xml:id="_5dEPYSu">Currency, price date, and</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_3">conversion 0 1 1 1 0 1 0 1 Choice of model 0 0 1 0 1 0 1 0 Assumptions 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 0 Analytical methods 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Study parameters 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1</formula><p xml:id="_Swpj2WP"><s xml:id="_6Szg6NA">Incremental costs and outcomes</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_4">1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Characterizing uncertainty 1 1 0 1 1 1 1 1</formula><p xml:id="_7S4Ch5S"><s xml:id="_4HhqEDd">Characterizing heterogeneity 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 1 Study findings, limitations, generalizability, and current knowledge</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_5">1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Source of funding 1 1 1 1 1 1 0 1 (Continued)</formula><p xml:id="_YKdJsgv"><s xml:id="_TTXAA4K">Frontiers in Public Health frontiersin.org</s><s xml:id="_YMatWPn">Gentili et al. .</s><s xml:id="_Q6wbQAJ">/fpubh. .</s><s xml:id="_Drw3dr8">TABLE Continued Section item Clarke et al. (7) Wang et al. (36) Sharifi et al. (40) Sjostrom et al. (38) Song et al. (13) Vestergaard et al. (19) Thakar et al. (16) Painter et al. (28) Prinja et al. (25) Conflicts of interest 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Total 18 17 22 22 22 21 19 20 22 Ratio 0.75 0.71 0.92 0.92 0.92 0.88 0.79 0.83 0.92 Quality Fair Fair Good Good Good Good Fair Good Good Section item Levy et al. (21) Kumar et al. (22) Nguyen et al. (18) Nordyke et al. (27) O'Sullivan et al. (26) Jo et al. (23) Whetten et al. (17) Cleghorn et al. (24) Islam et al. (</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_6">) Title 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Abstract 0 1 1 1 1 0 1 1<label>11</label></formula><p xml:id="_4HSFZEX"><s xml:id="_n6tmume">Background and objectives</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_7">1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1</formula><p xml:id="_S4g4Pc8"><s xml:id="_b3y2eWV">Target population and subgroups</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_8">1 1 1 0 1 0 0 0 Setting and location 1 1 1 0 1 1 1 1 Study perspective 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Comparators 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Time horizon 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Discount rate 1 1 1 1 1 1 0 1 Choice of health outcomes 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Measurement of effectiveness 1 1 1 1 1 1 0 1</formula><p xml:id="_7vP2fB7"><s xml:id="_dzrptHv">Measurement and valuation of preference based outcomes</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_9">1 1 1 1 1 0 1 1</formula><p xml:id="_CMKhPqx"><s xml:id="_XRS35ry">Estimating resources and costs</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_10">1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1</formula><p xml:id="_X8Rqrqp"><s xml:id="_nqa3mxK">Currency, price date, and conversion 1 1</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_11">(Continued)</formula><p xml:id="_QFt8a2m"><s xml:id="_vbR8KjQ">Frontiers in Public Health frontiersin.org</s><s xml:id="_sbwsRr7">Gentili et al. .</s><s xml:id="_Az8PRFU">/fpubh. .</s><s xml:id="_paRXKKN">TABLE Continued Section item Levy et al. (21) Kumar et al. (22) Nguyen et al. (18) Nordyke et al. (27) O'Sullivan et al. (26) Jo et al. (23) Whetten et al. (17) Cleghorn et al. (24) Islam et al. (11) Characterizing heterogeneity 0 0 0 0 0 0 1 1 Study findings, limitations, generalizability, and current knowledge 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Source of funding 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Conflicts of interest 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Total 21 23 23 21 22 20 21 23 21 Ratio 0.88 0.96 0.96 0.88 0.92 0.83 0.88 0.96 0.88 Quality Good Good Good Good Good Good Good Good Good Section item Hoyo et al. (30) Modi et al. (39) Lowry et al. (14) Witt Udsen et al. (34) Romero-Sanchiz et al. (35) Lugo et al. (9) Oksman et al. (20) Fusco and Francesco (31) Lopez-Villegas et al. (</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_12">) Title 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Abstract 1 0 1 0 1 0 0 1 Background and objectives 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1<label>37</label></formula><p xml:id="_HKbn4Qb"><s xml:id="_SqeuwgQ">Target population and subgroups</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_13">1 0 0 1 1 0 0 0 Setting and location 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 0 Study perspective 1 1 0 1 1 1 0 1 Comparators 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Time horizon 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Discount rate 1 1 1 1 1 0 0 1 Choice of health outcomes 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Measurement of effectiveness 1 1 1 1 1 0 0 1</formula><p xml:id="_WN5hSVn"><s xml:id="_m6z6UxB">Measurement and valuation of preference based outcomes</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_14">1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1</formula><p xml:id="_UBzAR6Z"><s xml:id="_bu9ynP2">Estimating resources and costs</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_15">1 1 1 1 1 1 0 1</formula><p xml:id="_v2FRd4y"><s xml:id="_Ss9jkHx">Currency, price date, and conversion</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_16">1 1 1 1 1 0 0 1 (Continued)</formula><p xml:id="_wpEZVtw"><s xml:id="_cDztggD">Frontiers in Public Health frontiersin.org</s><s xml:id="_Fwdk7ZD">Gentili et al. .</s><s xml:id="_FQF7gex">/fpubh. .</s><s xml:id="_daaa9Rm">TABLE Continued Section item Hoyo et al. (30) Modi et al. (39) Lowry et al. (14) Witt Udsen et al. (34) Romero-Sanchiz et al. (35) Lugo et al. (9) Oksman et al. (20) Fusco and Francesco (31) Lopez-Villegas et al. (37)</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_17">Choice of model 0 1 1 1 1 1 0 1 0 Assumptions 1 1 1 1 1 1 0 1 1 Analytical methods 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Study parameters 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1</formula><p xml:id="_FnUpNvH"><s xml:id="_nuVDjKT">Incremental costs and outcomes</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_18">1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Characterizing uncertainty 1 1 0 1 1 0 1 1 1 Characterizing heterogeneity 0 0 0 1 1 1 1 1 1</formula><p xml:id="_c5K5tuB"><s xml:id="_Gg8aZ39">Study findings, limitations, generalizability, and current knowledge</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_19">1 1 1 1 1 0 1 1 1 Source of funding 1 1 1 0 1 1 1 1 1 Conflicts of interest 1 1 0 1 1 1 1<label>1</label></formula><p xml:id="_RQ2cx6M"><s xml:id="_SxzXB9G">1 Total 22 21 19 22 24 18 15 22 21 Ratio 0.92 0.88 0.79 0.92 1 0.71 0.63 0.92 0.88 Quality Good Good Fair Good Excellent Fair Average Good Good Section item Wan et al. (10) Watson et al. (32) Buvik et al. (41) Oostingh et al. (12) Yoo et al. (33) Krishnan et al. (8) Bahrainwala et al. (15) de Jong et al. (</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_20">) Title 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Abstract 0 0 0 1 1 0 0 Background and objectives 1 1 1 1 1 1 1<label>29</label></formula><p xml:id="_HQwmrAR"><s xml:id="_PcCuJvB">Target population and subgroups 0 0 0 0 0 1 0</s></p><p xml:id="_Vn9qS7s"><s xml:id="_Kpy2wY4">Setting and location</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_21">1 0 1 0 1 0 1 Study perspective 0 1 1 1 1 1 1 Comparators 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Time horizon 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Discount rate 0 0 1 0 1 1 1 (Continued)</formula><p xml:id="_QUAASTK"><s xml:id="_PqNnCse">Frontiers in Public Health frontiersin.org</s><s xml:id="_74NB34y">Gentili et al. .</s><s xml:id="_kHJQt5P">/fpubh. .</s><s xml:id="_2RecwDD">TABLE Continued Section item Wan et al. (10) Watson et al. (32) Buvik et al. (41) Oostingh et al. (12) Yoo et al. (33) Krishnan et al. (8) Bahrainwala et al. (15) de Jong et al. (</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_22">)<label>29</label></formula><p xml:id="_xmdxEzh"><s xml:id="_QkMt4S5">Choice of health outcomes</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_23">1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Measurement of effectiveness 1 1 1 1 1 1 1</formula><p xml:id="_USsNauX"><s xml:id="_WkxWhWH">Measurement and valuation of preference based outcomes</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_24">1 1 1 1 1 1 1</formula><p xml:id="_TksecrM"><s xml:id="_34NQS32">Estimating resources and costs</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_25">1 0 1 0 1 1<label>1</label></formula><p xml:id="_vh3u8fW"><s xml:id="_NVWMk4F">Currency, price date, and conversion</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_26">1 1 0 1 1 1 1 Choice of model 1 1 0 1 1 1 1 Assumptions 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Analytical methods 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Study parameters 1 1 1 1 1 1 1</formula><p xml:id="_S4dnKU6"><s xml:id="_SEx2D7S">Incremental costs and outcomes</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_27">1 1 0 1 1 1 1 Characterizing uncertainty 0 0 1 1 1 1 1</formula><p xml:id="_KB4SaBQ"><s xml:id="_Eg4duvZ">Characterizing heterogeneity 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 Study findings, limitations, generalizability, and current knowledge</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_28">1 1 1 1 1 1 1 Source of funding 1 1 1 1 0 1 1 Conflicts of interest 1 1 1 1 1<label>1</label></formula><p xml:id="_5kfkszZ"><s xml:id="_pFmjtXq">1 Total 19 17 18 19 21 21 21 21 Ratio 0.79 0.71 0.75 0.79 0.88 0.88 0.88 0.88 Quality Fair Fair Fair Fair Good Good Good Good Frontiers in Public Health frontiersin.org</s><s xml:id="_9jx6YUB">Gentili et al. .</s><s xml:id="_BdvxhdE">/fpubh. .</s><s xml:id="_RNveB7J">TABLE Summary of findings.</s><s xml:id="_VGf6wPf">Author (published year) Intervention Type of intervention Cost measurement (incremental cost) Consequence measurement (incremental effect) ICER Key findings (main conclusion) Bahrainwala et al. (2020) (15) Drone Observed Therapy System (DrOTS) intervention inludes: (i) drones to deliver sputum samples and tuberculosis (TB) medication; (ii) GeneXpert TM MTB/RIF (Cepheid, Sunnyvale CA USA) molecular platform to increase sensitivity and specificity of TB diagnosis; (iii) WHO endorsed evriMED TM (Wisepill, Somerset West, South Africa) digital adherence monitoring technology to remotely assess TB treatment adherence by monitoring daily opening of an electronic pill box.</s><s xml:id="_ACMVfRp">Digital technologies and innovations The incremental cost per additional TB patient diagnosed in DrOTS was 2,631$ There was a 61.2% (95% CI 58.1-65.2,</s><s xml:id="_yZEjGa6">P &lt; 0.05) increase in case finding and treatment initiation over usual care.</s><s xml:id="_XTkktYx">With the implementation of digital adherence monitoring technologies, those outcomes were respectively 405 (91.0%) and 40 (9.0%) in DrOTS.</s><s xml:id="_k2ECQZd">This represents a 2.6% (95% CI -1.8 to 7.5, P = 0.47) increase in successful outcomes DrOTS has an ICER value of $177 per DALY averted compared to usual care for diagnosis and treatment of TB Innovative technology packages including drones, digital adherence monitoring technologies, and molecular diagnostics for TB case finding and retention within the cascade of care can be cost effective.</s><s xml:id="_vVHfzjc">Their integration with other interventions within health systems may further lower costs and support access to universal health coverage Prinja et al. (2018) (25) ReMiND (REducing Maternal and Newborn Deaths), a mHealth application that tracks and supports clients for the Accredited Social Health Activist (ASHA) workers and provides inputs for individualized service and counseling needs Digital technologies and innovations From societal perspective, there was a cost saving of USD 425 million with ReMiND intervention The implementation of ReMiND from 2011 to 2020 would save 4,127,529 DALYs From societal perspective, intervention resulted in a cost saving of USD 90 per DALY averted and USD 2,569 per death averted.</s><s xml:id="_BAZHUcy">From health system perspective, the intervention determined an incremental cost of INR 12,993 (USD 205) per DALY averted and INR 371,577 (USD 5,866) per death averted Findings of our study suggest strongly that the mHealth intervention as part of the ReMiND intervention is very cost effective from Indian health system's viewpoint, and cost saving from a societal perspective, and should be considered for replication elsewhere in India (Continued) Frontiers in Public Health frontiersin.org</s><s xml:id="_dZc8REX">Gentili et al. .</s><s xml:id="_D76vKwY">/fpubh. .</s><s xml:id="_sD4A3J5">TABLE Continued Author (published year) Intervention Type of intervention Cost measurement (incremental cost) Consequence measurement (incremental effect) ICER Key findings (main conclusion) Lowry et al. (2020) (14) Digital Breast Tomosynthesis (DBT), a 3d diagnostic imaging system Digital technologies and innovations The transition from conventional Digital Mammography (DM) to DBT increased total costs by $395,553-445,722 per 1,000 screening-eligible women In the base case analysis, breast cancer mortality and life-years were overall consistent between the DBT and DM screening scenarios.</s><s xml:id="_hT2CXPp">Small QALY gains were seen with DBT compared to DM, with incremental gains ranging from 1.97 to 3.27 per 1,000 women The ICERs for DBT relative to DM ranged from $195,026-270,135 per QALY gained DBT reduces false-positive exams while achieving similar or slightly improved health benefits.</s><s xml:id="_nPtSf4N">At current reimbursement rates, the additional costs of DBT screening are likely high relative to the benefits gained; however, DBT could be cost-effective at lower screening costs Krishnan et al. (2019) (8) Shape intervention offered: TABLE Continued Author (published year) Intervention Type of intervention Cost measurement (incremental cost) Consequence measurement (incremental effect) ICER Key findings (main conclusion) Levy et al. (2017) (21) Phone conversation with a tobacco treatment specialist (TTS) about smoking cessation counseling.</s><s xml:id="_pxd2wAV">In addition, the TTS offered to connect patients with social services via HelpSteps.com,</s><s xml:id="_fJ3qe9R">a web-based clearing-house for local social services relevant to low-income individuals Telephone support The incremental cost per additional quit is $4,137 (95% CI $2,671-$8,460) over the 20-month study period Comparing intervention to usual care, we estimate a risk difference of 9.7%, or approximately 69 (95% CI 33-108) incremental quits (9.7% × 707 smoker participants) based on the intention to treat analysis The overall incremental cost per additional life year saved is $7,301 (95% CI $4,545-$15,400) The proactive population-based smoking cessation program tested in Project CLIQ under conservative assumptions did not appear as cost-effective as a related strategy, but demonstrated favorable cost-effectiveness compared to other smoking cessation programs and is likely to be TABLE Continued Author (published year) Intervention Type of intervention Cost measurement (incremental cost) Consequence measurement (incremental effect) ICER Key findings (main conclusion) Cleghorn et al. (2019) (24) Intervention was a national mass media promotion of selected smartphone apps for weight loss compared with no dedicated promotion Text messaging intervention Costs to the health system of New Zealand was $2.3 million over the lifetime of the modeled population The estimated impact of the base-case intervention was a health gain of 29 QALYs Costs per QALY gained (or the incremental cost-effectiveness ratio) were NZ $79,700 (US $53,600) for the standard download rate The mass media promotion of a smartphone app for weight loss produced relatively small health gains on a population level and was of borderline cost-effectiveness for the total population O'Sullivan et al. (2020) (26) Intervention was a "healthy lifestyle package, " including dietary and exercise advice and a smartphone app to reinforce health messages to reduce the incidence of gestational diabetes mellitus Text messaging intervention There were no significant differences across intervention and control groups in mean cost of antenatal admissions, delivery costs or total health care utilization Women in the intervention group lost fewer QALYs, though the difference was not statistically significant (2.75 vs. 2.85, P = 0.38) The ICER for QALYs was e2,914 per QALY gained Providing a mobile health-supported lifestyle intervention to pregnant women with an elevated BMI may be a cost-effective way of improving maternal and infant health Islam et al. (2020) (11) Text messaging intervention plus standard-care for patients with type 2 diabetes Text messaging intervention The calculation of the incremental costs showed that the text messaging intervention can be delivered at costs of 24 Int.$ per patient A statistically significant difference in HbA1c was observed in favor of the intervention group ICER of 38 Int.$ per 1% reduction in HbA1c and of 2,406 Intl.$ per QALY gained The mobile phone textmessaging is an effective and cost-effective method in improving glycemic control Text-messaging might be a valuable addition to standard treatment for diabetes care in low-resource settings Sjostrom et al. (2017) (38) Mobile app Tät R , a treatment program focused on pelvic floor muscle training (PFMT), and information about stress urinary incontinence and lifestyle factors Mobile phone-based systems and applications The total cost per participant was higher in the app group (e547.0)</s><s xml:id="_yUuQTej">than that in the control group (e482.4)</s><s xml:id="_QcWATNJ">In the app group, there was significant improvement in QoL at follow-up.</s><s xml:id="_sc3aPh2">In contrast, the control group did not display a significant reduction in scores.</s><s xml:id="_pTv964c">In app group, 0.01006 QALY gain.</s><s xml:id="_RXfX3FE">In control group, 0.00158 QALY gain The incremental cost effectiveness ratio was of e7,615.5 per QALY in the base case scenario The app for treating stress urinary incontinence is a new, cost-effective, first-line treatment with potential for increasing access to care in a sustainable way for this patient group (Continued) Frontiers in Public Health frontiersin.org</s><s xml:id="_gG8XJyQ">Gentili et al. .</s><s xml:id="_WVEPuNa">/fpubh. .</s><s xml:id="_EA55JZn">TABLE Continued Author (published year) Intervention Type of intervention Cost measurement (incremental cost) Consequence measurement (incremental effect) ICER Key findings (main conclusion) Kumar et al. (2018) (22) Mobile cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) program for Generalized anxiety disorder TABLE Continued Author (published year) Intervention Type of intervention Cost measurement (incremental cost) Consequence measurement (incremental effect) ICER Key findings (main conclusion) Whetten et al. (2018) (17) Telehealth platform that includes rapid radiograph image transfer and two-way audiovisual capacity, as well as report generating capacity.</s><s xml:id="_R8wtaTb">This enables consulting neurosurgeons and neurointensive care specialists to review imaging and talk with/examine the patient and generate a report Video-conferencing system The use of ACCESS led to save $4,241 ($3,952-$4,438) per patient Intervention, in comparison with usual care, increased QALYs by 0.20 (0.14-0.22)</s><s xml:id="_mYxg59C">Incremental cost effectiveness when compared to traditional care was of $-21,205 per QALYs The teleneurology program ACCESS is a cost-effective approach to managing patients with neuro-emergent conditions in rural areas.</s><s xml:id="_mEjyXMP">In addition to providing financial benefits, a teleneurology program produces better patient outcomes, and offers societal benefits through reduction of stroke related disability and increased convenience to The incremental effect in the intervention group was of 0.011 (0.005-0.017)</s><s xml:id="_jV3ezux">QALYs Incremental cost-effectiveness ratio was of $45,320 per QALY Telemedicine in the ICU is cost-effective in most cases and cost saving in some cases Thakar et al. (2018) (16) Telemedicine consultation center Video-conferencing system The mean per episode cost was INR 2,338 (38.0 USD) for TeleMedicine (TM) care vs. INR 5,479 (89.o</s><s xml:id="_DP7MPGH">USD) for routine care.</s><s xml:id="_TVuErny">Intervention resulted to be cost saving The effectiveness of telemedicine care was calculated using efficiency in terms of the percentage of successful TM consultations.</s><s xml:id="_g225zNW">The overall effectiveness of the TM-care group was 917.4 and that of routine care was 132.8</s><s xml:id="_9mrJBCp">The ICER value was calculated to be -34,900 INR (571.9</s><s xml:id="_RAkhvxD">USD)/unit of effectiveness (2,338 -5,479 [38.3-89.8]/0.89-0.80)</s><s xml:id="_Y3VUg7u">TM care dominates the in-person care strategy by providing more effective and less expensive follow-up care for a remote post-neurosurgical care population in India (Continued) Frontiers in Public Health frontiersin.org</s><s xml:id="_7zUWVtG">Gentili et al. .</s><s xml:id="_mG43ZTe">/fpubh. .</s></p><p xml:id="_vbQMgAV"><s xml:id="_t8ApJcn">TABLE Continued Author (published year) Intervention Type of intervention Cost measurement (incremental cost) Consequence measurement (incremental effect) ICER Key findings (main conclusion) Buvik et al. (2019) (41) Telemedicine consultations using real-time videoconferencing Video-conferencing system In comparison to routine care, the intervention produced an annual cost savings of e19,500 (USD 16,516) The average QALYs gained per patient in the telemedicine group was .09</s><s xml:id="_J5uS4hn">which was not significantly different to the .05</s><s xml:id="_nQfbvcQ">gain in the standard consultation group, P = 0.29 Not mentioned Video-assisted orthopedic consultations, rather than having patients travel to the specialist hospital for consultations, is cost-effective from both a societal and health sector perspective The incremental effect was measured by the knee flexion range of motion (ROM) gained and by QALY gained The ICER (adopting Ita-NHS perspective) is -e960 ($1,352)/QALY [ceiling ratio: e30,000 ($42,200)/QALY] The analysis suggested the intervention to be cost-effective, even less expensive and more effective Vestergaard et al. (2020) (19) Telehealthcare solution (TeleCare North Heart Failure) in heart failure patients as add-on to usual care Video-conferencing system Telemedicine reduced total healthcare costs by 35% [5,668 ($7,557) off a base of 16,241 British Pounds Sterling ($21,654)] The 1-year adjusted QALY difference between the telehealthcare solution and the usual care group was 0.0034 (95% CI: -0.0711 to 0.0780), indicating an insignificant gain in health-related quality of life (HRQoL) for patients receiving the tele-healthcare solutio Based on the incremental cost and QALY estimates and an assumed cost-effectiveness threshold of £20,000 ($ 26,666) per QALY,27 the telehealthcare solution provides a positive incremental net monetary benefit (NMB) of £5,164 ($ 6,885)/QALYs All scenario analyses showed the same result with telehealthcare associated with lower costs and an insignificant impact on patients' HRQoL Painter et al. (2017) (28) Telemedicine Outreach for Post-Traumatic Stress Disease intervention involving offsite PTSD care teams located at parent VAMCs to support on-site CBOC providers Video-conferencing system The overall incremental cost of the intervention was $2,495 (p &lt;.01) per patient The total QALY gain from intervention is 0.008 compared to usual care The primary analysis resulted in a median ICER of $185,565 per QALY (interquartile range $57,675 to $395,743) Because of the upfront training costs and the resource-intensive nature of the intervention, associated expenses were high.</s><s xml:id="_Sk6qEfe">Although PTSD-specific effectiveness measures were significantly improved, these changes did not translate to QALYs in the main analysis (Continued) Frontiers in Public Health frontiersin.org</s><s xml:id="_fxV2XJC">Gentili et al. .</s><s xml:id="_heSXfuD">/fpubh. .</s></p><p xml:id="_QNwbgek"><s xml:id="_cvnadt4">TABLE Continued Author (published year) Intervention Type of intervention Cost measurement (incremental cost) Consequence measurement (incremental effect) ICER Key findings (main conclusion) Wang et al. (2016) (36) Telemedicine Center at the West China Hospital (TCWCH) program intervention (a digital network with video equipment and image transfer that can be used in simultaneously conducting longdistance education or consultation) Video-conferencing system Telemedicine network resulted in an estimated net saving of $2,364,525 (if the patients traveled to the hub) or $3,759,014 (if the specialists traveled to the spoke hospitals) It is a cost-saving analysis, there is no clinical measurement There is no ICER The intervention was highly cost saving Clarke et al. (2018) Measure of effectiveness was the resource utilization data obtained from multiple sources, including A&amp;E visits, ambulance usage, and hospitalization Data did not include quality of life, and so we were unable to undertake cost/benefit analysis The wide variance on savings and the uncertainty of monitoring cost do not allow a definitive conclusion on the cost-effectiveness as an outcome of this study Witt Udsen et al. (2017) (34) Telehealthcare solution and monitoring by a community-based healthcare team, in addition to usual care for patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease Video-conferencing system The base-case adjusted mean difference in total costs between telehealthcare and usual care was e728 (967 USD) [95% CI -754 to 2,211 (1,001-2,936)] The adjusted mean difference in quality-adjusted life-years gained was 0.0132 (95% CI -0.0083 to 0.0346) The ICER is e55.327</s><s xml:id="_VvSphNj">(73,769 USD) per QALY Telehealthcare is unlikely to be a cost-effective addition to usual care, if it is offered to all patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease and if the willingness-to-pay threshold values from the National Institute for Health and Care Excellence are applied (Continued) Frontiers in Public Health frontiersin.org</s><s xml:id="_facyzXN">Gentili et al. .</s><s xml:id="_CZfURqt">/fpubh. .</s><s xml:id="_62hgp6p">TABLE Continued Author (published year) Intervention Type of intervention Cost measurement (incremental cost) Consequence measurement (incremental effect) ICER Key findings (main conclusion) Lugo, et al. (2019) An out-of-hospital Virtual Sleep Unit (VSU) based on telemedicine to manage all patients with suspected OSA Video-conferencing system Intervention on average led to save 153.34 e (181.04</s><s xml:id="_YM3Z8qu">USD) The incremental effectiveness was estimated in 0.0108 QALYs Not mentioned The VSU offered a cost-effective means of improving QALYs than routine care.</s><s xml:id="_QVEYdEH">Our findings indicate that VSU could help with the management of many patients, irrespective of CPAP use Nguyen et al. (2016) (18) A Telemedicine Program, called Singapore Integrated Diabetic Retinopathy Program (SiDRP), that provides "real-time" assessment of diabetic retinopathy photographs by a centralized team of trained and accredited graders supported by a tele-ophthalmology information technology infrastructure Video-conferencing system Intervention (SiDRP) generates a cost savings of $173 per patient The total QALY gain from the SiDRP is almost the same as the routine care model (i.e., 13.1129 vs. 13.1123</s><s xml:id="_BTfVXHR">QALYs) $-288.333</s><s xml:id="_sSeFxqp">per QALYs The SiDRP model saves costs compared with the traditional model.</s><s xml:id="_ZzzBVN4">This provides evidence in support of extending the SiDRP model across Singapore and outside the public sector de Jong et al. (2020) (29) Telemedicine with myIBDcoach (my Inflammatory Bowel Disease coach) Video-conferencing system The intervention resulted in a mean annual cost saving of e547 (612 USD) per patient [95%CI e-1,029 to e2,143 (1,152-2,400 USD)] Patients in the intervention group showed a mean gain in quality adjusted life years (QALY) of 0.002 (95%CI, [-0.022, 0.018])</s><s xml:id="_WKqt82k">Not explicited Telemedicine with myIBDcoach is cost saving and has a high probability of being cost effective for patients with IBD (Continued) Frontiers in Public Health frontiersin.org</s><s xml:id="_XcMpEBn">Gentili et al. .</s><s xml:id="_fqZ4Ajf">/fpubh. .</s><s xml:id="_4axh9Ar">TABLE Continued Author (published year) Intervention Type of intervention Cost measurement (incremental cost) Consequence measurement (incremental effect) ICER Key findings (main conclusion) Wan et al. (2019) (10) A combination of telemedicine and shared medical appointments in transition-age young adults with Type 1 Diabetes Video-conferencing system There was no significant difference in total costs No significant differences in 9-month quality-adjusted life; however, the control group had a larger decline from baseline in utility than the intervention group, indicating a quality of life (QoL) benefit of the intervention (difference in difference mean ± SD: 0.04 ± 0.09; P = 0.03) No within-trial incremental cost-effectiveness ratio was calculated due to the lack of significant difference in 9-month total costs or QALYs The intervention (CoYoT1) care model may help young adults with T1D maintain a higher QoL with no increase in costs Oksman et al. (2017) (20) A tele-based health-coaching intervention among patients with type 2 diabetes (T2D), coronary artery disease (CAD) and congestive heart failure (CHF) Video-conferencing system The incremental cost for intervention in comparison with control was of 432e (488USD) [-135e to 999e (-153USD to 1,128USD)] The cost-effectiveness plane for HRQoL (15D) after health coaching showed that the intervention was more effective compared to care as usual [0.009 (0.000-0.018)]</s><s xml:id="_RhfAWaC">The overall incremental ICER was e48,000 (54,237 USD) per QALY Based on the results of this study, health coaching improved the QoL of type 2 diabetes and coronary artery disease patients with moderate costs.</s><s xml:id="_rP6tVpQ">However, the results are grounded on a short follow-up period, and more evidence is needed to evaluate the long-term outcomes of health-coaching programs (Continued) Frontiers in Public Health frontiersin.org</s><s xml:id="_dX6MGS7">Gentili et al. .</s><s xml:id="_f7smMMg">/fpubh. .</s></p><p xml:id="_3t6pGw8"><s xml:id="_X3mzYDf">TABLE Continued Author (published year) Intervention Type of intervention Cost measurement (incremental cost) Consequence measurement (incremental effect) ICER Key findings (main conclusion) Lopez-Villegas et al. (2020) (37) Telemonitoring (TM) of patients with pacemakers in comparison with conventional monitoring (CM) Video-conferencing system Incremental costs per patient included in the TM vs. CM group constituted e1,807.87</s><s xml:id="_rx8E44N">(USD 2,006.52)</s><s xml:id="_hCydEUt">[CI: -646.99 to 4,262.73 (-718.08 to 4,731.11)] from the perspective of the NHS and e1,865.52</s><s xml:id="_PDTkmH5">(USD 2,070.50)</s><s xml:id="_r65TKTR">[CI: -608 to 4,335.25 (674.81-4,811.6)]</s><s xml:id="_wUXGxE7">including patient/family cost This study provided evidence showing that 12 months after pacemaker implantation, health-related quality of life was similar between groups of RM and conventional follow-up in hospital The mean ICER amounted to e53,345.27 (USD 59.206,38) from the perspective of the NHS or e55,046.40</s><s xml:id="_RErRxMQ">(USD 61.094.78)</s><s xml:id="_Dw92eNG">including patient/caregiver costs Cost-utility analysis of TM vs. CM shows inconclusive results because of broad confidence intervals with ICER from potential savings to high costs for an additional QALY, with the majority of ICERs being above the usual NHS thresholds for coverage decisions Hoyo et al. (2019) (30) Telemonitoring of Crohn's Disease and Ulcerative Colitis (TECCU) Web platform for telemonitoring complex inflammatory bowel disease and nurse-assisted telephone care Video-conferencing system TECCU determined a median cost reduction from a societal perspective of e211 (US $231) per patient (95% CI e-600 to 180 per patient; US $-657 to 197 per patient) The incremental efficacy of TECCU was 0.19 (0.33-0.14) relative to control (median incremental efficacy calculated with the bootstrapping procedure was 0.21, 95% CI -0.07 to 0.66) TECCU vs. control estimated a median ICER of e-1,005 (95% CI e-13,518 to 3,137; US $1,100, 95% CI US $-14,798 to 3,434) There is a high probability that the TECCU Web platform is more cost-effective than standard and telephone care in the short term Frontiers in Public Health frontiersin.org</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_pzZ3Hv2">Video-conferencing system</head><p xml:id="_U5m2qCn"><s xml:id="_fY5bBKx">Video conferencing systems consist in programs that allow the delivery of specialist consultations via video for remote patients with any kind of condition or disease.</s></p><p xml:id="_syPYyQX"><s xml:id="_SPbxeK3">In this review, a total of 17 of the included studies evaluated the cost-effectiveness of video conferencing systems <ref type="bibr">(7, 9, 10, 16-20, 28-31, 33, 34, 36, 37, 41)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_HWU36Dg"><s xml:id="_wG5BYSN">The disciplines examined were the following: (1) two studies focused on a video conferencing system applied in a teletrauma/telestroke context, delivering neurology care to remote patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17)</ref>; a network of audiovisual communications and data systems allowed to link hospital intensive care units to intensivists and other critical care professionals at remote locations (33); (2) two studies compared a standard rehabilitation program to a telerehabilitation program for patients that aimed to improve access and quality of care, avoid patient travel, and reduce health care costs <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41)</ref>; (3) two videoconferencing services for general practices consisted of telehealthcare equipment for continuous monitoring of physiological measurements <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36)</ref>; telemedicine outreach for Post-Traumatic Stress Disease (PTSD) examined the impact of telemedicine-based collaborative care for PTSD with enhanced usual care without on-site psychiatrists (28); (4) three studies focused on the effects of a videoconferencing system for patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (7, 9, 34); ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) three studies implemented telemedicine interventions for patients with diabetes <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref> two video conferencing platforms were used for telemonitoring complex inflammatory bowel disease compared to standard care <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> one study examined patients with implanted pacemakers who received home monitoring with internet-based remote monitoring service and videoconsultation service <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(37)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_2pP5dZT"><s xml:id="_3bvbkMb">Two out of the 17 articles included in this section reported not to be cost-effective <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_5kaEbSv"><s xml:id="_8CPuQRR">The remaining 15 articles stated the digital health interventions to be cost-effective: video conferencing systems gained higher QALYs with cost-saving in 9 <ref type="bibr">(7, 9, 16-18, 29-31, 41)</ref>; video conferencing systems gained QALYs with higher cost at an acceptable ICER in 6 <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">33,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Mp2CAsS">Text messaging intervention</head><p xml:id="_yKycJU6"><s xml:id="_HqZH8Sz">Text message-based health interventions provide patients with reminders, education or self-management assistance for a broad spectrum of health conditions.</s></p><p xml:id="_NX62yb5"><s xml:id="_VhebCJq">In this review, the text messaging interventions concerned the following topics: (1) a mobile phone text messaging program for people with type 2 diabetes mellitus was implemented in Bangladesh ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">11</ref>); (2) Smarter Pregnancy, a text messaging coaching program in addition to the usual care for women of subfertile couples who start their first in vitro fertilization cycle <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref>; (3) mCARE package, a short message service and home visit reminders sent to pregnant women to promote the careseeking of essential maternal and newborn care services <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(23)</ref>; (4) a New Zealand national mass media promotion of selected smartphone apps with text messaging service for weight loss <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref> the Pregnancy, Exercise And nutrition Research study (PEARs) intervention, a 'healthy lifestyle package, ' that included dietary and exercise advice and text messages to reinforce health reminders <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_qV2k5wT"><s xml:id="_dGjZNdW">All five of the included studies in this category found that text messaging interventions were cost-effective.</s><s xml:id="_NbnzWXU">Intervention groups gained higher QALYs with cost-savings in one study <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref>; intervention groups gained QALYs with slightly higher cost at an acceptable ICER in the other four studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Q57BeeG">Web platforms and digital health portals</head><p xml:id="_3gKEpQ8"><s xml:id="_nrMZG3p">A digital health portal is a secure online web portal that gives patients convenient, 24-h access to personal health information from anywhere via an Internet connection, often "tethered" to their integrated electronic health records.</s></p><p xml:id="_Gd9eAMg"><s xml:id="_zF425CG">In this review, the web portals for citizens and patients retrieved during the screening process are the following: (1) "Smiling is fun", an Internet-delivered, self-help web portal for the treatment of depression, consisting of 10 cognitive behavioral therapy modules to cope with depression (35); ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>) an e-Health portal that gives internet-based cognitive-behavioral therapy designed for patients with bulimia nervosa (32); (3) a web portal that provides digital behavioral and lifestyle intervention for type 2 diabetes mellitus and hypertension patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref>; (4) an electronic health record (EHR)-based decision support program for parents with 6-to 12-year-old children with obesity, providing behavioral therapy and support <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(40)</ref>; and (5) Tät service, a web portal support service designed to inform patients on stress urinary incontinence, that provides a pelvic floor muscle training program and prescribes pelvic floor muscle training 3 times daily during treatment <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(38)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_nJxUzK3"><s xml:id="_mwhk8Sv">The cost-effectiveness acceptability analysis indicated improved health outcomes with similar, or even lower costs for all the 5 studies of this section <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">35,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">38,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_vB5SMPB">Telephone support</head><p xml:id="_q2KYnZA"><s xml:id="_BwrHzVf">Telephone support is the use of phone calls by specialists, such as nurses, doctors and healthcare professionals in general, to deliver self-care support and/or management.</s></p><p xml:id="_KYDUyzy"><s xml:id="_TK7PktS">Studies selected in this category focused on the following topics: (1) a tobacco treatment telephone support program, that provides smoking cessation counseling to participants in the intervention group <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref>; and (2) Shape Program, an adaptive telephone-based coaching system, designed to prevent weight gain in black female primary care patients that consists of personalized obesogenic behavior change goals assigned every 2 months, a tailored skills training curriculum, patient self-monitoring delivered via a fully automated interactive voice response system and 12 counseling calls with a registered dietitian <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_tGsMrxj"><s xml:id="_n4gT84E">All of the studies in this section reported greater gains in quality-adjusted life years at a similar or slightly higher cost, resulting in cost-effectiveness based on established benchmarks <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_w8DBjp5">Mobile phone-based systems and applications</head><p xml:id="_6zszWMS"><s xml:id="_SGKgSB2">Mobile phone-based applications include all of the services and systems that provide support, delivery and promotion of care through the monitoring and sharing of health information via mobile technology, such as wearables and health tracking apps.</s></p><p xml:id="_qkfCVyd"><s xml:id="_SVENBjj">Mobile phone-based applications retrieved in this review included: (1) a mobile cognitive-based therapy program set to provide learnings and techniques to help users manage their anxiety ( <ref type="formula">22</ref>); (2) Karada-no-kimochi, a mobile application that predicts the menstrual cycle based on recorded data and provides information regarding menstruation <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>; and (3) Innovative Mobile Technology for Community Health Operation (ImTeCHO), a mHealth-based intervention that enhances health promotion using multimedia and short message reminders to increase coverage of maternal, neonatal, and child health care <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(39)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_uwB5xvv"><s xml:id="_jzsTGWc">All 3 studies declared improved QALYs with lower cost, suggesting the interventions were highly cost effective <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_ME8taZh">Digital technologies and innovations</head><p xml:id="_ND5FDad"><s xml:id="_JtqFxMj">This section includes all articles that focused on the costeffectiveness of digital health interventions that do not fall within any of the above categories, such as experimental digital diagnostic imaging or experimental technologies.</s></p><p xml:id="_kZQ4pDF"><s xml:id="_pEFesxG">Digital health innovations in this group were represented by: (1) Digital Breast Tomosynthesis (DBT), a new breast imaging modality that reconstructs cross-sectional slices of the breast, minimizing soft-tissue overlap ( <ref type="formula">14</ref>); (2) ReMiND, a program that assists healthcare professionals in the early identification, treatment, and rapid referral for appropriate care of any danger signs among pregnant women or neonates <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref>; and (3) Drone Observed Therapy System (DrOTS), a project to support community-based tuberculosis case finding using drones to deliver sputum samples and tuberculosis medication between rural communities, diagnostics and treatment facilities <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_h2mYqaU">Two out of the three studies in this section found the digital health interventions to be highly cost-effective, resulting in higher QALYs with cost-savings <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25)</ref>, while one study reported to be cost-effective but with higher costs <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_jWp9wAR">Discussion</head><p xml:id="_TKgRS8t"><s xml:id="_53XqCUD">Standardized cost-effectiveness analysis should be used to compare different interventions in terms of their consequences and costs so it can be used as a crucial tool to help decision makers or funders understand if digital health interventions and innovations actually determine an increase of QALYs or DALYs with contained costs <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(42)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_nF7frVV"><s xml:id="_kUdxjwj">In our systematic review, we opted to exclude studies that utilized digital technologies only to record information without any active participation from healthcare personnel as we wanted to focus on interventions that facilitate the communication between citizen/patient and healthcare staff.</s><s xml:id="_58dEbkf">However, the number of economic evaluations included in the review is in line with the previous review on cost-utility and cost-effectiveness of telehealth interventions published in 2015, where 35 studies assessed effectiveness, utility and costs <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_XHDSr4D"><s xml:id="_ckSnygQ">Studies show a broad range of digital interventions, reference population, focus disease and discipline interested.</s><s xml:id="_Ta2c4DT">The majority included a comparison of a digital health innovation costs and effectiveness in terms of health-related outcomes vs. standard care.</s><s xml:id="_unp4BMT">However, some did not report all recommended economic and consequence outcome items.</s><s xml:id="_yXqJ6zb">The transferability of findings across economic evaluations is based on a rigorous data collection strategy, a coherent methodology, and an explicit description of target population, study design and sample size <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(43)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_276vy4e">In our review, over half of the studies were randomized controlled trials which are considered to be of high quality and have a low risk of bias in comparison with other study designs, such as expert opinion studies.</s><s xml:id="_uCUABCj">Sample size varied significantly and ranged from 50 participants in a study where telemedicine was used to monitor patients with pacemakers compared to conventional monitoring (37) to 4.4 million participants where a text messaging intervention promoted weight loss in all of New Zealand's population <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_EmzCqWp">One article missed to indicate the sample size <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_3fKhjqV"><s xml:id="_UFTkeuP">Economic evaluations conducted from a societal perspective are generally preferred since one of the principal objectives of public health is to improve the health and the quality of life of the general population <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(44)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_UmxFSS2">Moreover, economic evaluations based on a fixed budget may lead to suboptimal decisions; they are inconsistent with decisions based on willingness to pay for QALYs and are considered to be of low quality in comparison to societal perspective.</s><s xml:id="_5gRufEV">Of the 35 studies of the review, 19 articles conducted their economic evaluations from a societal perspective, while only one study did not report the perspective <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_UFDv2dH">On the contrary, articles with a societal perspective took into account all the losses and expenses, direct and indirect, supported by society as a whole, irrespective of who the benefactors were (e.g.</s><s xml:id="_yjHEDYW">production losses, travel costs, absenteeism, presenteeism, premature death, etc.).</s><s xml:id="_QWhx7kd">Articles with a third party payer perspective encompassed intervention costs, outpatient (incl.</s><s xml:id="_KskdRBk">general practitioners and specialists) and inpatient services, medication and societal service costs.</s></p><p xml:id="_RBX8eNs"><s xml:id="_cCCYyAJ">Modeling techniques are generally used to predict the effect and the potential cost (or savings) of a determined technology where it is not feasible to wait for lifetime data to validate the cost-effectiveness <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(42)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_ssVw7Xu">In our review, several studies used modeling techniques to predict the intervention effect and cost over a long period, or even a lifetime <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_ytWRn8G">In these cases, it became fundamental to clearly express the uncertainty of the analysis described.</s><s xml:id="_ehSnaqa">All studies selected in the review that used predictive models indicated uncertainty (mostly Monte Carlo simulation, but also one-way and multiway sensitivity analyses, threshold analyses and probabilistic sensitivity analyses).</s></p><p xml:id="_WXUqJ4R"><s xml:id="_YycHDWp">According to previous reviews (6), "Videoconferencing system" was the most represented digital health intervention type but it was also the one that had the most discordant results: five studies report that the applied technology is not costeffective or that in any case there is not enough evidence to define the cost-effectiveness <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_6vBKAvM">Vestegard et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref> found that telehealth care was associated with lower costs but had an insignificant impact on patients' HRQoL.</s><s xml:id="_eTjqbVs">Painter et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(28)</ref> underlined effectiveness of the digital measures, but admitted that they did not improve QALYs in the main analysis.</s><s xml:id="_tYhBjsc">Clarke et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> could not give a definitive conclusion on the cost-effectiveness as an outcome of their study due to a wide variance on savings and the uncertainty of monitoring cost.</s><s xml:id="_AZztFFh">Also Lopez-Villegas et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(37)</ref> had inconclusive results due to broad confidence intervals with ICER from potential savings to high costs for an additional QALY, with the majority of ICERs being above the usual NHS thresholds for coverage decisions.</s></p><p xml:id="_Sx6w2jk"><s xml:id="_JnCDDax">Witt Udsen et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(34)</ref> through their study revealed that telehealthcare is unlikely to be cost-effective in addition to usual care.</s></p><p xml:id="_WgMBq2h"><s xml:id="_KWeG92G">A total of three out of the 35 studies (3/35, 8.6%) were found to not be cost-effective: two studies in the videoconferencing system category <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37)</ref> and one study in the digital technologies and innovations <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_pYw3X4K">Of the remaining articles, 12 studies (12/35, 34.3%) found digital health interventions gained QALYs with a higher cost at an acceptable ICER when compared with a relative national benchmark (six studies in videoconferencing systems, four studies in text messaging, two studies in telephone support) <ref type="bibr">(8, 10, 11, 19-21, 23, 24, 26, 33, 34, 36)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_vKHmXQr">Finally, a total of 20 out of the 35 studies (20/35, 57.1%) found the digital health interventions gained higher QALYs with cost-savings (nine studies in videoconferencing systems, one study in text messaging, five studies in web platforms and digital health portals, three studies in mobile phone-based systems and applications, two studies in digital health technologies and innovations) <ref type="bibr">(7, 9, 12, 13, 15-18, 22, 25, 27, 29-32, 35, 38-41)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_mDjNXVQ"><s xml:id="_HwcnYyt">Various benefits of digital tools to rural realities were underlined in different studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_bMGrWkT">This is a very important aspect as it could improve and revolutionize the access to care and quality of treatment for a very large number of patients.</s><s xml:id="_hwj5F2m">Video-conferencing systems offered the greatest advantages in reaching rural areas <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36)</ref>, followed by digital technologies and innovations <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25)</ref>, web platforms and digital health portals <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(32)</ref>, mobile phone-based systems and applications <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(39)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_2ZyGj4X">The most significant achievements in reaching rural areas were found in the USA <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32)</ref>, followed by India <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39)</ref>, China <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(36)</ref> and Madagascar <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_3kz2faW"><s xml:id="_YzMSYmV">It is known that cost-effectiveness is a subjective concept since it depends on the willingness to pay (WTP) for specific outcomes.</s><s xml:id="_NGUzDkq">The decision makers' WTP threshold to establish the cost-effectiveness of intervention differs in the literature.</s><s xml:id="_G7usUJq">For example, in studies from the United Kingdom, a threshold range of £20,000-£30,000/QALY gained is normally used <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_CybWxKk">While in America <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(46)</ref> and Australia (47) they use the amount of 50,000/QALY gained, each in their respective currencies <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(48)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_9Zz5Gmx"><s xml:id="_mgBsKfj">Some studies analyzed digital health interventions that exceeded the threshold <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37)</ref> while others had costs that remained below the threshold <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_u7U9vH9">However, it is crucial to consider that interventions are preferable, even with costs over the threshold, if they improve the outcome with minor or the same costs when compared with standard care.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Gt7ZQry">Limitations</head><p xml:id="_5Fv34kp"><s xml:id="_QbDQvG6">Firstly, due to the heterogeneity of interventions in the included studies, we could not provide synthetic and general conclusions about costs because most costs were expressed in different values and it was not always possible to make systematic comparisons between them.</s><s xml:id="_4AnVWp3">Secondly, by focusing only on articles written in English, our study may be subject to publication bias and the results should be interpreted appropriately.</s><s xml:id="_W5Xqj3V">Thirdly, another source of potential biastypical of economic studies -is the systematic tendency of including/excluding cost items in the analysis.</s><s xml:id="_ZDHV6Je">Therefore, results are driven toward a specific perspective, i.e., the social perspective rather than the health systems' perspective.</s><s xml:id="_DjK5yb8">Finally, even if extensively used to evaluate the quality of economic studies in systematic review of economic evaluations, the CHEERS checklist has structural limitations (e.g.</s><s xml:id="_2RQrbk3">different aspects of the study have the same importance, so the completeness of the abstract and methodological issues such as the choice of the model, the assumptions and the management of uncertainties are given the same relevance).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_sDjsJS6">Conclusion</head><p xml:id="_MpVf8vS"><s xml:id="_U4PnXR8">Despite a growing interest in investing in digital tools in healthcare, the evidence regarding cost-effectiveness of digital tools in the health sector remains scarce and limited.</s></p><p xml:id="_cPT9FDN"><s xml:id="_z3Zf6Wr">Through this review it some evidence was found that digital health interventions can affect cost-effectiveness with a favorable effect both in terms of costs and health outcomes.</s><s xml:id="_65QUzQ9">In particular, the findings showed a positive impact especially for studies that implemented a new mobile application or a web portal intervention.</s><s xml:id="_2NKZHkR">We strongly believe that the findings of this research could be used to better inform and orient health policies.</s><s xml:id="_5u8Jneb">More than half of the studies included report that the use of digital health intervention led to the achievement of a better efficiency and outcomes for patients, the optimization of available human and technological resources and the consistent reduction in the costs of the healthcare services provided.</s><s xml:id="_EHbEMEh">Recognized international examples of digital health practices being successful could be the first step to informing and orienting decision makers to structure a new, evidence-based, digital health maturity.</s></p><p xml:id="_Zr7tKdC"><s xml:id="_5gPm6kP">However, due to the heterogeneity across study methods, cost perspectives, disciplines and diseases involved, the comparison between interventions still remains difficult.</s><s xml:id="_jAZF4jb">Further research based on a standardized approach is needed in order to methodically analyze incremental cost-effectiveness ratios, costs and health benefits.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>FIGURE</head><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_eNyB8N5"><s xml:id="_TBRnbk5">FIGUREPRISMA statement flow diagram.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,127.64,106.71,340.08,399.12" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_Kz7bsqz"><s xml:id="_rg45WQ3">(a) tailored behavior change goals; (b) skills training materials; (c) weekly interactive voice response telephone calls; (d) monthly telephone coaching from a registered dietitian; (e) a no-cost 12-month membership to a facility of their choice Telephone support The incremental cost of Shape relative to usual care was US $758 The primary measure of effectiveness in the trial was weight change from baseline to 12 months.</s><s xml:id="_NUAAVXW">Weight change was converted into a health-related quality of life change score.</s><s xml:id="_aCb4FgQ">Mean difference in weight change of the intervention and usual CARE arms with regard to baseline approached statistical significance at the 12-month (-1.4 kg [-2.8 to -0.1]) assessment.</s><s xml:id="_AG3pYs3">The difference in weight change across arms was transformed to QoL change scores for Shape participants and usual care participants (+0.009 and +0.005, respectively) In the base case, the ICER was of US $55,264 per QALY gained Shape intervention is cost-effective based on established benchmarks, indicating that it can be a part of a successful strategy to address the nation's growing obesity epidemic in low-income at-risk communities</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>5 weeks- 3 ,</head><label>53</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_sGtPvzw"><s xml:id="_VjB8w7n">highly cost-effective by common cost-effectiveness thresholds ($50,000-$150,000/additional quality-adjusted life year) compared to other health interventions Romero-Sanchiz et al. (2017) (35) Internet-based Cognitive-Behavioral Therapy intervention program ("Smiling is Fun") for depression with or without psychotherapist support Web platforms and digital health portals The totally self-guided (TSG) Internet-based program led to save USD 644.11 per patient in comparison with improved treatment as usual (iTAU) The effectiveness was measured as reduction of Beck Depression Inventory II (BDI-II), and totally self-guided Internet-based program led to a reduction of 3.80 point in comparison with improved treatment as usual The complete case analyses revealed an incremental cost-effectiveness ratio (ICER) of e-169.50 for the TSG group compared with iTAU The results of this study indicate that Internet-based per abstinent patient at 1-year follow-up was $16,777 (95% CI = $10,298, $27,042) for face-to-face and $14,561 (95% CI = $10,165, $21,028) for Internet-based CBT-BN The primary outcome of abstinence for Internet-based CBT-BN was inferior to face-to-face CBT-BN at post-treatment but non-inferior at 1-year follow-up QALY gain: over the course of treatment, participants in each group gained on average ∼1 week of full health.</s><s xml:id="_zqHFc8X">At the end of one year, those in face-to-face had gained 4 weeks of full health and those in Internet-based gained 030 to -760) and -e3,050 (95% CI -3,960 to -540),</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>(</head></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_x5gAhR4"><s xml:id="_H79jyaV">Video-conferencing systemIncremental cost of $516 per patient compared with ICU without telemedicine</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_H6dr33b"><s xml:id="_w8RTRbn">Video-conferencing systemIntervention on average led to save $263 (95% CI -$382 to -$143) per person</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_vPnN6FW"><s xml:id="_5GYhEhU">Video-conferencing systemThe average saving was £1,023 ($1,280) per patient per year</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_zHP2wSv"><s xml:id="_eGhvwFE">For example, Watson et al. (32), Buvik et al. (41), Wang et al. (36), Lugo et al. (9), and De Jong et al. (29), did not calculate the incremental cost effectiveness ratio, while Nordyke et al. (27), did not indicate the incremental effect of the use of intervention to treat disease in type 2 diabetes and hypertension patients.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p xml:id="_jvj2gC9"><s xml:id="_ef9AhJq">Frontiers in Public Health frontiersin.org</s></p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_a2bD7AG">Data availability statement</head><p xml:id="_pxy8Xpv"><s xml:id="_SdqcjQP">The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/supplementary material, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Ssxdx3m">Author contributions</head><p xml:id="_jy8w2ZX"><s xml:id="_4zrwfS2">AG, FC, GF, and WR: conception or design of the work and final approval of the version to be published.</s><s xml:id="_8XVGvsm">AG: data collection.</s><s xml:id="_DbfHrpv">AG, GF, GT, AM, and VP: articles screening, data analysis, interpretation, and drafting the article.</s><s xml:id="_D8RWDfJ">FC, AG, GF, AM, and VP: critical revision of the article.</s><s xml:id="_9mPFjtp">All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_kH6bSBX">Conflict of interest</head><p xml:id="_xJcUpk9"><s xml:id="_F5DGYHw">The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_BgcrsHW">Publisher's note</head><p xml:id="_hWfZ8Wa"><s xml:id="_sQw6tDF">All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers.</s><s xml:id="_aXpTkbW">Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_ZwJTJ3A">Appendix Search string</head><p xml:id="_8GpAEMa"><s xml:id="_p6kA6tU">("digital health"[Mesh Terms] OR "digital health" OR "telemedicine"[Mesh Terms] OR "telemedicine" OR "e health"[Mesh Terms] OR "e health" OR "electronic health" OR "m health"[Mesh Terms] OR "m health" OR "mobile health" OR "remote consultation" OR "digital transformation" OR "home care services" OR "telenursing" OR "health innovation"[Mesh Terms] OR "telemetry"[Mesh Terms] OR "telehealth"[Mesh Terms] OR "telehealth" OR "telecare" OR "digital care"[Mesh Terms]) AND ("cost analysis"[Mesh Terms] OR "cost analysis" OR "cost benefit"[Mesh Terms] OR "cost benefit" OR "cost efficacy"[All Fields] OR "cost effectiveness"[All Fields] OR "cost consequence"[All Fields] OR "economic evaluation" OR "economic outcome" OR "economic assessment" OR "hta").</s><s xml:id="_68ZJAqR">Search criteria have been adjusted to each database searched.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_2zdg4zY">use of appropriate digital technologies for public health-Report by the Director-General</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Who</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mhealth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>EB142/20. (2017) 2015</idno>
		<ptr target="http://apps.who.int/gb/e/e_wha71.html" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_jM6pa7u">Exec Board</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="5" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-11">November 2017. March 1, 2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>142nd Sess provisional agenda item 44</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">WHO. mHealth, use of appropriate digital technologies for public health- Report by the Director-General. Exec Board, 142nd Sess provisional agenda item 44 EB142/20. (2017) 2015(November 2017):1-5. Available from: http://apps.who. int/gb/e/e_wha71.html (accessed March 1, 2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_epN8kht">Developing a data-driven approach in order to improve the safety and quality of patient care</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Cascini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Santaroni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lanzetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Failla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gentili</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ricciardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3389/fpubh.2021.667819</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_WBqAutM">Front Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">667819</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Cascini F, Santaroni F, Lanzetti R, Failla G, Gentili A, Ricciardi W. Developing a data-driven approach in order to improve the safety and quality of patient care. Front Public Health. (2021) 9:667819. doi: 10.3389/fpubh.2021.667819</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_RCjWHcV">How health systems approached respiratory viral pandemics over time: a systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Cascini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Hoxhaj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Zaçe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ferranti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Di</forename><surname>Pietro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Boccia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmjgh-2020-003677</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_3ZeE4mm">BMJ Global Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Cascini F, Hoxhaj I, Zaçe D, Ferranti M, Di Pietro ML, Boccia S, et al. How health systems approached respiratory viral pandemics over time: a systematic review. BMJ Global Health. (2020). doi: 10.1136/bmjgh-2020-003677</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Oh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_eJkG5wn">South Korea, the Perfect Environment for Digital Health</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Nature Portfolio</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Oh CW. South Korea, the Perfect Environment for Digital Health. Berlin: Nature Portfolio (2020).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_EcFfdAE">mHealth compendium</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mendoza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Okoko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Konopka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jonas</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.africanstrategies4health.org/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_62uqCB4">Afr Strateg Health Proj</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">82</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013-03-01">2013. March 1, 2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mendoza G, Okoko L, Konopka S, Jonas E. mHealth compendium. Afr Strateg Health Proj. (2013) 3:82. Available online at: http://www.africanstrategies4health. org/ (accessed March 1, 2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_zgcAvYa">Cost-utility and cost-effectiveness studies of telemedicine, electronic, and mobile health systems in the literature: a systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">De</forename><surname>La</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Torre</forename><forename type="middle">-</forename><surname>Diéz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>López-Coronado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vaca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Aguado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">De</forename><surname>Castro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1089/tmj.2014.0053</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_b7emKrj">Telemed J E Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81" to="85" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">De La Torre-Diéz I, López-Coronado M, Vaca C, Aguado JS, De Castro C. Cost-utility and cost-effectiveness studies of telemedicine, electronic, and mobile health systems in the literature: a systematic review. Telemed J E Health. (2015) 21:81-5. doi: 10.1089/tmj.2014.0053</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_39dUTrt">Evaluation of the National Health Service (NHS) direct pilot telehealth program: cost-effectiveness analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Clarke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fursse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Brown-Connolly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Sharma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1089/tmj.2016.0280</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_JwD4ju8">Telemed E Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="76" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Clarke M, Fursse J, Brown-Connolly NE, Sharma U, Jones R. Evaluation of the National Health Service (NHS) direct pilot telehealth program: cost-effectiveness analysis. Telemed E Health. (2018) 24:67-76. doi: 10.1089/tmj.2016.0280</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_C4GQfcM">A digital behavioral weight gain prevention intervention in primary care practice: cost and cost-effectiveness analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Krishnan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Finkelstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Levine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Foley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Askew</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Steinberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/12201</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_BZymHuH">J Med Internet Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12201</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Krishnan A, Finkelstein EA, Levine E, Foley P, Askew S, Steinberg D, et al. A digital behavioral weight gain prevention intervention in primary care practice: cost and cost-effectiveness analysis. J Med Internet Res. (2019) 21:e12201. doi: 10.2196/12201</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_FcsduKW">Comprehensive management of obstructive sleep apnea by telemedicine: clinical improvement and cost-effectiveness of a virtual sleep unit. A randomized controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lugo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Garmendia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Suarez-Girón</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Torres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Vázquez-Polo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Negrín</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0224069</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_N2MT6b8">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">224069</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lugo VM, Garmendia O, Suarez-Girón M, Torres M, Vázquez-Polo FJ, Negrín MA, et al. Comprehensive management of obstructive sleep apnea by telemedicine: clinical improvement and cost-effectiveness of a virtual sleep unit. A randomized controlled trial. PLoS ONE. (2019) 14:e0224069. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0224069</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_skK7cDH">Cost-effectiveness of shared telemedicine appointments in young adults with T1D: CoYoT1 trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wan</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Nathan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Skandari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Zarei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Reid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Raymond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2337/dc19-0363</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_FR4EKm8">Diabetes Care</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1589" to="1592" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Wan W, Nathan AG, Skandari MR, Zarei P, Reid MW, Raymond JK, et al. Cost-effectiveness of shared telemedicine appointments in young adults with T1D: CoYoT1 trial. Diabetes Care. (2019) 42:1589-92. doi: 10.2337/dc19-0363</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_9efjEY5">Cost-effectiveness of a mobile-phone text messaging intervention on type 2 diabetes-a randomized-controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Islam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Peiffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Chow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Maddison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lechner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Holle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Niessen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Laxy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.hlpt.2019.12.003</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_6kGpfyM">Health Policy Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="85" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Islam M, Peiffer R, Chow CK, Maddison R, Lechner A, Holle R, Niessen L, Laxy M. Cost-effectiveness of a mobile-phone text messaging intervention on type 2 diabetes-a randomized-controlled trial. Health Policy Technol. (2020) 9:79-85. doi: 10.1016/j.hlpt.2019.12.003</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Hc4XpQW">Mobile health coaching on nutrition and lifestyle behaviors for subfertile couples using the smarter pregnancy program: model-based cost-effectiveness analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Oostingh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Ophuis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wph</forename><surname>Koster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Polinder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Lingsma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jse</forename><surname>Laven</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/preprints.13935</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_prnNMsd">JMIR Mhealth Uhealth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">13935</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Oostingh EC, Ophuis RH, Koster WPH, Polinder S, Lingsma HF, Laven JSE, et al. Mobile health coaching on nutrition and lifestyle behaviors for subfertile couples using the smarter pregnancy program: model-based cost-effectiveness analysis. JMIR Mhealth Uhealth. (2019) 7:e13935. doi: 10.2196/preprints.13935</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_BY8p6xp">Effectiveness of mobile application for menstrual management of working women in Japan: randomized controlled trial and medical economic evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kanaoka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/13696998.2018.1515082</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_rEJgmPw">J Med Econ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1131" to="1138" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Song M, Kanaoka H. Effectiveness of mobile application for menstrual management of working women in Japan: randomized controlled trial and medical economic evaluation. J Med Econ. (2018) 21:1131-8. doi: 10.1080/13696998.2018.1515082</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_68cj6SB">Long-term outcomes and cost-effectiveness of breast cancer screening with digital breast tomosynthesis in the United States</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Lowry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Trentham-Dietz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Schechter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Alagoz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Barlow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Burnside</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/jnci/djz184</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_77DKVVA">J Natl Cancer Inst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="582" to="589" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lowry KP, Trentham-Dietz A, Schechter CB, Alagoz O, Barlow WE, Burnside ES, et al. Long-term outcomes and cost-effectiveness of breast cancer screening with digital breast tomosynthesis in the United States. J Natl Cancer Inst. (2020) 112:582-9. doi: 10.1093/jnci/djz184</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_env4nPd">Drones and digital adherence monitoring for community-based tuberculosis control in remote Madagascar: a cost-effectiveness analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bahrainwala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Knoblauch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Andriamiadanarivo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Diab</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mckinney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Small</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0235572</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_5mFBaP6">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">235572</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bahrainwala L, Knoblauch AM, Andriamiadanarivo A, Diab MM, McKinney J, Small PM, et al. Drones and digital adherence monitoring for community-based tuberculosis control in remote Madagascar: a cost-effectiveness analysis. PLoS ONE. (2020) 15:e0235572. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0235572</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_tADeNh5">Comparison of telemedicine with in-person care for follow-up after elective neurosurgery: results of a cost-effectiveness analysis of 1200 patients using patient-perceived utility scores</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Thakar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Rajagopal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Shyam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Aryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3171/2018.2.focus17543</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_JzgP7zq">Neurosurg Focus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">17</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Thakar S, Rajagopal N, Mani S, Shyam M, Aryan S, Rao AS, et al. Comparison of telemedicine with in-person care for follow-up after elective neurosurgery: results of a cost-effectiveness analysis of 1200 patients using patient-perceived utility scores. Neurosurg Focus. (2018) 44:E17. doi: 10.3171/2018.2.FOCUS17543</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_tKpQFXs">Cost-effectiveness of Access to Critical Cerebral Emergency Support Services (ACCESS): a neuro-emergent telemedicine consultation program</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Whetten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Van Der Goes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Tran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Moffett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Semper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yonas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/13696998.2018.1426591</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_KmY6bWg">J Med Econ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="398" to="405" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Whetten J, van der Goes DN, Tran H, Moffett M, Semper C, Yonas H. Cost-effectiveness of Access to Critical Cerebral Emergency Support Services (ACCESS): a neuro-emergent telemedicine consultation program. J Med Econ. (2018) 21:398-405. doi: 10.1080/13696998.2018.1426591</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_U3SmkJE">Cost-effectiveness of a National Telemedicine Diabetic Retinopathy Screening Program in Singapore</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Nguyen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gsw</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Tapp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mital</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dsw</forename><surname>Ting</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ophtha.2016.08.021</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_bMZS8Kz">Ophthalmology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">123</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2571" to="2580" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nguyen H V, Tan GSW, Tapp RJ, Mital S, Ting DSW, Wong HT, et al. Cost-effectiveness of a National Telemedicine Diabetic Retinopathy Screening Program in Singapore. Ophthalmology. (2016) 123:2571-80. doi: 10.1016/j.ophtha.2016.08.021</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_7AZ9ECu">Is telehealthcare for heart failure patients cost-effective? An economic evaluation alongside the Danish TeleCare North heart failure trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Vestergaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Sorensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Ehlers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmjopen-2019-031670</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_xz5kwUm">BMJ Open</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">31670</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Vestergaard AS, Hansen L, Sorensen SS, Jensen MB, Ehlers LH. Is telehealthcare for heart failure patients cost-effective? An economic evaluation alongside the Danish TeleCare North heart failure trial. BMJ Open. (2020) 10:e031670. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2019-031670</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_mQxEbFh">Cost-effectiveness analysis for a tele-based health coaching program for chronic disease in primary care</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Oksman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Linna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Hörhammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lammintakanen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Talja</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/s12913-017-2088-4</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_mWCq4k3">BMC Health Serv Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">138</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Oksman E, Linna M, Hörhammer I, Lammintakanen J, Talja M. Cost-effectiveness analysis for a tele-based health coaching program for chronic disease in primary care. BMC Health Serv Res. (2017) 17:138. doi: 10.1186/s12913-017-2088-4</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_BfRCggQ">Cost-effectiveness of a health system-based smoking cessation program</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Levy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E V</forename><surname>Klinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Linder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Fleegler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rigotti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ntr/ntw243</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_UJmgX3G">Nicotine Tob Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1508" to="1515" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Levy DE, Klinger E V, Linder JA, Fleegler EW, Rigotti NA, Park ER, et al. Cost-effectiveness of a health system-based smoking cessation program. Nicotine Tob Res. (2017) 19:1508-15. doi: 10.1093/ntr/ntw243</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_VqNRBKh">Mobile and traditional cognitive behavioral therapy programs for generalized anxiety disorder: a cost-effectiveness analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Juusola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0190554</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_WsMyQQB">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">190554</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kumar S, Bell MJ, Juusola JL. Mobile and traditional cognitive behavioral therapy programs for generalized anxiety disorder: a cost-effectiveness analysis. PLoS ONE. (2018) 13:e0190554. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0190554</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_xQzgSrB">Costs and cost-effectiveness analyses of mCARE strategies for promoting care seeking of maternal and newborn health services in rural Bangladesh</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Jo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lefevre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Healy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Singh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Alland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mehra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0223004</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ujKCXmD">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">223004</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Jo Y, LeFevre AE, Healy K, Singh N, Alland K, Mehra S, et al. Costs and cost-effectiveness analyses of mCARE strategies for promoting care seeking of maternal and newborn health services in rural Bangladesh. PLoS ONE. (2019) 14:e0223004. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0223004</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_fGrqt3C">Health benefits and cost-effectiveness from promoting smartphone apps for weight loss: multistate life table modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cleghorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Nair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kvizhinadze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Nghiem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mcleod</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/11118</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_6ZyBGeZ">JMIR Mhealth Uhealth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">11118</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Cleghorn C, Wilson N, Nair N, Kvizhinadze G, Nghiem N, McLeod M, et al. Health benefits and cost-effectiveness from promoting smartphone apps for weight loss: multistate life table modeling. JMIR Mhealth Uhealth. (2019) 7:e11118. doi: 10.2196/11118</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_MJAgrTY">Cost effectiveness of mHealth intervention by community health workers for reducing maternal and newborn mortality in rural Uttar Pradesh, India</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Prinja</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bahuguna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Nimesh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Thakur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/s12962-018-0110-2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_NzsnPfg">Cost Eff Resour Alloc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">25</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Prinja S, Bahuguna P, Gupta A, Nimesh R, Gupta M, Thakur JS. Cost effectiveness of mHealth intervention by community health workers for reducing maternal and newborn mortality in rural Uttar Pradesh, India. Cost Eff Resour Alloc. (2018) 16:25. doi: 10.1186/s12962-018- 0110-2</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_4Yk4vrb">Cost-effectiveness of a mobile health-supported lifestyle intervention for pregnant women with an elevated body mass index</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>O'sullivan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rokicki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kennelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ainscough</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mcauliffe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O'</forename><surname>Sullivan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41366-020-0531-9</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_CAp9YMh">Int J Obes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="999" to="1010" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">O&apos;Sullivan EJ, Rokicki S, Kennelly M, Ainscough K, McAuliffe FM, O&apos;Sullivan EJ, et al. Cost-effectiveness of a mobile health-supported lifestyle intervention for pregnant women with an elevated body mass index. Int J Obes. (2020) 44:999- 1010. doi: 10.1038/s41366-020-0531-9</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_WZsBHxB">Estimating the impact of novel digital therapeutics in type 2 diabetes and hypertension: health economic analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Nordyke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Appelbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Berman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/preprints.15814</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_BtG6teG">J Med Internet Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15814</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nordyke RJ, Appelbaum K, Berman MA. Estimating the impact of novel digital therapeutics in type 2 diabetes and hypertension: health economic analysis. J Med Internet Res. (2019) 21:e15814. doi: 10.2196/preprints. 15814</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_2bBWRDC">Cost-effectiveness of telemedicine-based collaborative care for posttraumatic stress disorder</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Painter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Fortney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Austen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Pyne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1176/appi.ps.201600485</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_59SMc9w">Psychiatr Serv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1157" to="1163" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Painter JT, Fortney JC, Austen MA, Pyne JM. Cost-effectiveness of telemedicine-based collaborative care for posttraumatic stress disorder. Psychiatr Serv. (2017) 68:1157-63. doi: 10.1176/appi.ps.201600485</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ZGfQrcK">Cost-effectiveness of telemedicinedirected specialized vs standard care for patients with inflammatory bowel diseases in a randomized trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>De Jong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Boonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Van Der Meulen-De Jong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Romberg-Camps</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Van Bodegraven</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mahmmod</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cgh.2020.04.038</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_8FTVNUq">Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1744" to="1752" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">de Jong MJ, Boonen A, van der Meulen-de Jong AE, Romberg-Camps MJ, van Bodegraven AA, Mahmmod N, et al. Cost-effectiveness of telemedicine- directed specialized vs standard care for patients with inflammatory bowel diseases in a randomized trial. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. (2020) 18:1744- 52. doi: 10.1016/j.cgh.2020.04.038</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_wum6EFC">Telemonitoring of Crohn&apos;s Disease and Ulcerative colitis (TECCU): costeffectiveness analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hoyo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Nos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bastida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Faubel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Muñoz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Garrido-Marín</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/15505</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Bpzdcqv">J Med Internet Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15505</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hoyo JD, Nos P, Bastida G, Faubel R, Muñoz D, Garrido-Marín A, et al. Telemonitoring of Crohn&apos;s Disease and Ulcerative colitis (TECCU): cost- effectiveness analysis. J Med Internet Res. (2019) 21:e15505. doi: 10.2196/15505</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_HXS27xB">Telerehabilitation after total knee replacement in Italy: cost-effectiveness and cost-utility analysis of a mixed telerehabilitationstandard rehabilitation programme compared with usual care</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Fusco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Turchetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmjopen-2015-009964</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_UbeXC7P">BMJ Open</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9964</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Fusco F, Turchetti G. Telerehabilitation after total knee replacement in Italy: cost-effectiveness and cost-utility analysis of a mixed telerehabilitation- standard rehabilitation programme compared with usual care. BMJ Open. (2016) 6:e009964. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2015-009964</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_mX4HmpR">Cost-effectiveness of internet-based cognitive-behavioral treatment for bulimia nervosa: results of a randomized controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mclagan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Zerwas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Crosby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Levine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Runfola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4088/jcp.16m11314</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_EQpCaPe">J Clin Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="11314" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Watson HJ, McLagan N, Zerwas SC, Crosby RD, Levine MD, Runfola CD, et al. Cost-effectiveness of internet-based cognitive-behavioral treatment for bulimia nervosa: results of a randomized controlled trial. J Clin Psychiatry. (2018) 79:16m11314. doi: 10.4088/JCP.16m11314</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_9k4yYyc">Economic evaluation of telemedicine for patients in ICUs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B-K</forename><surname>Yoo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Sasaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Melnikow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Marcin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/ccm.0000000000001426</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_6XVJ7bR">Crit Care Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="274" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Yoo B-K, Kim M, Sasaki T, Melnikow J, Marcin JP. Economic evaluation of telemedicine for patients in ICUs. Crit Care Med. (2016) 44:265- 74. doi: 10.1097/CCM.0000000000001426</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_9xDfQZp">Cost-effectiveness of telehealthcare to patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: results from the Danish &apos;TeleCare North&apos; cluster-randomised trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Witt Udsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lilholt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Hejlesen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ehlers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmjopen-2016-014616</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_TPXUQYU">BMJ Open</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">14616</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Witt Udsen F, Lilholt PH, Hejlesen O, Ehlers L. Cost-effectiveness of telehealthcare to patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: results from the Danish &apos;TeleCare North&apos; cluster-randomised trial. BMJ Open. (2017) 7:e014616. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2016-014616</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_GbRzzt2">Economic evaluation of a guided and unguided internetbased CBT intervention for major depression: results from a multicenter, threearmed randomized controlled trial conducted in primary care</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Romero-Sanchiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Nogueira-Arjona</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>García-Ruiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J V</forename><surname>Luciano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Campayo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gili</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0172741</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_V5fAWt7">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">172741</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Romero-Sanchiz P, Nogueira-Arjona R, García-Ruiz A, Luciano J V, Campayo JG, Gili M, et al. Economic evaluation of a guided and unguided internet- based CBT intervention for major depression: results from a multicenter, three- armed randomized controlled trial conducted in primary care. PLoS ONE. (2017) 12:e0172741. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0172741</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_E8jHhhQ">Assessment of utilization and cost-effectiveness of telemedicine program in western regions of China: a 12-year study of 249 hospitals across 112 cities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T-T</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J-M</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C-R</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D-M</forename><surname>An</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H-Y</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1089/tmj.2015.0213</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_w6JZdxV">Telemed E Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="909" to="920" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Wang T-T, Li J-M, Zhu C-R, Hong Z, An D-M, Yang H-Y, et al. Assessment of utilization and cost-effectiveness of telemedicine program in western regions of China: a 12-year study of 249 hospitals across 112 cities. Telemed E Health. (2016) 22:909-20. doi: 10.1089/tmj.2015.0213</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_66mepXt">Cost-utility analysis of telemonitoring versus conventional hospitalbased follow-up of patients with pacemakers. The NORDLAND randomized clinical trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lopez-Villegas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Catalan-Matamoros</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Peiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Lappegard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lopez-Liria</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0226188</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ES63CQ2">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">226188</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lopez-Villegas A, Catalan-Matamoros D, Peiro S, Lappegard KT, Lopez- Liria R. Cost-utility analysis of telemonitoring versus conventional hospital- based follow-up of patients with pacemakers. The NORDLAND randomized clinical trial. PLoS ONE. (2020) 15:e0226188. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.02 26188</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_F8ffHD2">Mobile app for treatment of stress urinary incontinence: a cost-effectiveness analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sjostrom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lindholm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Samuelsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/jmir.7383</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_p386wEm">J Med Internet Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">154</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sjostrom M, Lindholm L, Samuelsson E. Mobile app for treatment of stress urinary incontinence: a cost-effectiveness analysis. J Med Internet Res. (2017) 19:e154. doi: 10.2196/jmir.7383</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_42Rnr5D">Costing and cost-effectiveness of a mobile health intervention (ImTeCHO) in improving infant mortality in tribal areas of Gujarat, India: cluster randomized controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Modi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Saha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Vaghela</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dave</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Anand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Desai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/17066</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_UW6DCjw">JMIR Mhealth Uhealth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">17066</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Modi D, Saha S, Vaghela P, Dave K, Anand A, Desai S, et al. Costing and cost-effectiveness of a mobile health intervention (ImTeCHO) in improving infant mortality in tribal areas of Gujarat, India: cluster randomized controlled trial. JMIR Mhealth Uhealth. (2020) 8:e17066. doi: 10.2196/17066</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_bjwYnqK">Cost-effectiveness of a clinical childhood obesity intervention</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sharifi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Franz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Horan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Giles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Long</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1542/peds.2016-2998</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ET6zGh8">Pediatrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">140</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">20162998</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sharifi M, Franz C, Horan CM, Giles CM, Long MW, Ward ZJ, et al. Cost-effectiveness of a clinical childhood obesity intervention. Pediatrics. (2017) 140:e20162998. doi: 10.1542/peds.2016-2998</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_pCcFzs4">Cost-Effectiveness of telemedicine in remote orthopedic consultations: randomized controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Buvik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bergmo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bugge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Smaabrekke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wilsgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Olsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/11330</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_M3x6t5M">J Med Internet Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">11330</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Buvik A, Bergmo TS, Bugge E, Smaabrekke A, Wilsgaard T, Olsen JA. Cost- Effectiveness of telemedicine in remote orthopedic consultations: randomized controlled trial. J Med Internet Res. (2019) 21:e11330. doi: 10.2196/11330</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_b7MwSMC">What is the economic evidence for mHealth? A systematic review of economic evaluations of mHealth solutions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Iribarren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Cato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Falzon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0170581</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_5QJqWVC">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">170581</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Iribarren SJ, Cato K, Falzon L, Stone PW. What is the economic evidence for mHealth? A systematic review of economic evaluations of mHealth solutions. PLoS ONE. (2017) 12:e0170581. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.01 70581</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_V7cfS42">How to measure costs and benefits of ehealth interventions: An overview of methods and frameworks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bergmo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/jmir.4521</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_6NRbqFP">J Med Internet Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">254</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bergmo TS. How to measure costs and benefits of ehealth interventions: An overview of methods and frameworks. J Med Internet Res. (2015) 11:e254. doi: 10.2196/jmir.4521</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_7pU4wuq">Editorial: ten arguments for a societal perspective in the economic evaluation of medical innovations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Jönsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10198-009-0173-2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_f2Pj4ge">Eur J Health Econ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="357" to="359" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Jönsson B. Editorial: ten arguments for a societal perspective in the economic evaluation of medical innovations. Eur J Health Econ. (2009) 10:357- 9. doi: 10.1007/s10198-009-0173-2</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_njPAwWT">The NICE cost-effectiveness threshold: what it is and what that means</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mccabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Claxton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Culyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2165/00019053-200826090-00004</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Rdkyh39">Pharmacoeconomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">McCabe C, Claxton K, Culyer AJ. The NICE cost-effectiveness threshold: what it is and what that means. Pharmacoeconomics. (2008) doi: 10.2165/00019053-200826090-00004</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_sJsDQPR">How much are Americans willing to pay for a quality-adjusted life year?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Weinstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/MLR.0b013e31816a7144</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_94XpqYt">Med Care</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="733" to="744" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Weinstein MC. How much are Americans willing to pay for a quality-adjusted life year? Med Care. (2008) 26:733- 44. doi: 10.1097/MLR.0b013e31816a7144</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_eZZz483">Economic evaluation of medicines</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.18773/austprescr.2017.014</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_97BmtWr">Aust Prescr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="76" to="78" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Taylor C, Jan S. Economic evaluation of medicines. Aust Prescr. (2017) 40:76-8. doi: 10.18773/austprescr.2017.014</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_KSHUmcb">The cost-effectiveness of mobile health (Mhealth) interventions for older adults: systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Ghani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jarl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Berglund</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Andersson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Anderberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3390/ijerph17155290</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_j4AkEpD">Int J Environ Res Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="13" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ghani Z, Jarl J, Berglund JS, Andersson M, Anderberg P. The cost-effectiveness of mobile health (Mhealth) interventions for older adults: systematic review. Int J Environ Res Public Health. (2020) 17:1-13. doi: 10.3390/ijerph17155290</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
