<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_RHgVebf">Rheumatology in the digital health era: status quo and quo vadis?</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Johannes</forename><surname>Knitza</surname></persName>
							<email>knitza@uni-marburg.de</email>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0001-9695-0657</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>1</label> Institute for Digital Medicine , University Hospital of Giessen and Marburg , Marburg , Germany.</note>
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Digital Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital of Giessen and Marburg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Marburg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Latika</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0003-2753-2990</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>2</label> Department of Rheumatology , Royal Wolverhampton Hospitals NHS Trust , Wolverhampton , UK.</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Rheumatology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Royal Wolverhampton Hospitals NHS Trust</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Wolverhampton</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Hügle</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>3</label> Department of Rheumatology , Lausanne University Hospital , University of Lausanne , Lausanne , Switzerland.</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Rheumatology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Lausanne University Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Lausanne</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Lausanne</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_6CFBDsk">Rheumatology in the digital health era: status quo and quo vadis?</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">3925B13F5E58DB677F6AB57CB04B8309</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41584-024-01177-7</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T08:40+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_8xKQVQW"><p xml:id="_RCzMqT8"><s xml:id="_JeRxDpe">Rheumatology faces a critical shortage of health-care professionals, exacerbated by an ageing patient population and escalating costs, resulting in widening gaps in care.</s><s xml:id="_CBZUAbN">Exponential advances in digital health technologies (DHTs) in the past 5 years offer new opportunities to address these challenges and could contribute to overall improved health care.</s><s xml:id="_62afmfe">However, keeping pace with innovations and integrating them into clinical practice can be challenging.</s><s xml:id="_Rjebqq9">This Review explores the transformative potential of DHTs for rheumatology in reshaping the entire patient pathway and redefining the roles of patients and providers, and discusses the potential barriers to DHT integration.</s><s xml:id="_sbHV3nH">Key technologies, such as large language models, clinical decision-support systems, digital therapeutics, electronic patient-reported outcomes, digital biomarkers, robots, self-sampling devices and artificial intelligence-based scribes, can be implemented along the patient pathway.</s><s xml:id="_q3Qv9Fj">A digital-first hybrid stepped-care patient pathway could combine in-person and remote care, enabling personalized and continuous monitoring through a digital safety net.</s><s xml:id="_axHbNNM">The potential benefits and risks of transforming the traditional patientprovider relationship into a digital health triad with technology are discussed.</s><s xml:id="_GCpH37H">Collaborative efforts are needed to navigate the evolving digital health landscape and harness the potential of DHTs to improve rheumatology care.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="10" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="11" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="12" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="13" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_k2ZzRrc">Review article</head><p xml:id="_z4E7QaU"><s xml:id="_pn38CJ4">towards predictive, preventive, personalized and participatory health care (known as P4 medicine) <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_Xy9b26F">The integration of DHTs across the entire patient pathway (Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>) has the potential to contribute to achieving the overarching quadruple aims of health care: reducing costs, improving population health, and enhancing both patient and provider experience <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> .</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_mYGH2m7">Digitally supported diagnosis</head><p xml:id="_wuBtKfG"><s xml:id="_9BVcEKM">Diagnosis can often be delayed by months and numerous preceding physician visits.</s><s xml:id="_UMYjBH3">Despite various efforts, improvements in triage efficiency have been minimal and only a minority of patients presenting to rheumatologists are ultimately diagnosed with an inflammatory rheumatic disease <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> .</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_ffzcdwm">Data mining for improved identification of individuals at risk</head><p xml:id="_sHakD9M"><s xml:id="_Y8jtG5b">Ideally, individuals at risk of and patients with rheumatic diseases could be identified early by using their existing medical information, primarily stored in electronic health records.</s><s xml:id="_PWACATh">Data mining algorithms can extract meaningful information from the unstructured data within electronic health records, which aids the identification process.</s><s xml:id="_URT7BDC">However, the efficacy of these algorithms varies widely, with results ranging from highly promising <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> to modest in real-world settings <ref type="bibr">7</ref> owing to low disease incidence.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_CVQPbhc">Patient-facing diagnostic decision-support systems</head><p xml:id="_DP97gR3"><s xml:id="_XqK6JU6">Individuals first presenting with symptoms are increasingly opting for a digital-first approach, whereby individuals first assess their symptoms online and use dedicated patient-facing diagnostic decision-support systems (DDSSs) such as symptom checkers <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_PVU9abp">Symptom checkers offer standardized symptom assessments and are accessible anywhere and anytime, providing disease suggestions and recommended actions on the basis of the input provided.</s><s xml:id="_m5ZrMaZ">Although symptom checkers are well received, their diagnostic accuracy remains limited <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref> , ranging between 52% and 63% in a first multicentre evaluation study <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_Czzq3h8">Data from one study showed that only 14% of experienced rheumatologists could provide an accurate diagnosis of inflammatory rheumatic diseases on the basis of medical history alone <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_YKDVQdD">To address these limitations, symptom checkers could be improved by integrating additional objective data alongside subjective symptoms in order to enhance diagnostic accuracy and enable cross-verification.</s><s xml:id="_ARurB7h">The true value of symptom checkers could be their capacity to streamline automated history taking, thereby saving time and allowing for more in-depth, future patient-clinician dialogue.</s><s xml:id="_8rTxhDY">The incorporation of AI-based software, including LLMs, can further augment traditional history taking.</s><s xml:id="_ey2cy5M">LLMs have demonstrated the ability to detect subtle nuances in pain expression, which can be particularly effective in identifying conditions such as fibromyalgia <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_ZR4WABc">A preliminary study found that an AI-based symptom checker could make the correct diagnosis more frequently (54% versus 32%) than rheumatologists (the information given to clinicians was limited to basic health and symptom-related medical history) <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_FGFfH5g">In a direct comparison using the same patient vignettes from the previous study, the LLM ChatGPT-4 listed the correct diagnosis as one the top possibilities at a rate comparable to rheumatologists (35% versus 39%) <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref> .</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_zV33d8g">eReferrals and DDSSs for medical professionals</head><p xml:id="_QdzddYE"><s xml:id="_XjBGzjF">Manual review of electronically transmitted patient information and referral requests between health-care professionals (HCPs) (eReferrals) can improve triage by enabling a pre-appointment review of patient records, effectively decreasing unnecessary referrals if enough</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_jAzP5Jm">Introduction</head><p xml:id="_P9dvFw6"><s xml:id="_fXYwjb6">The growing scarcity of rheumatologists, escalating costs and ageing of the patient population exacerbate the strain on health-care systems and accentuate existing care deficits.</s><s xml:id="_Nm7RQdE">The assessment of often unspecific but potentially rheumatic symptoms is characterized by prolonged waiting times for specialist consultations, causing irreversible damage accrual and diminished cost-effective treatment options.</s><s xml:id="_jqsjZ6w">Despite new promising therapeutic approaches, conventional treatment is largely dominated by a trial-and-error and non-personalized approach.</s><s xml:id="_3VDnGyh">Patient monitoring seems inflexible, incomplete and limited to brief, burdensome periodic face-to-face consultations.</s><s xml:id="_hksmAay">The lack of a comprehensive picture of disease activity, lack of decision support and a disjointed flow of information often results in duplicative efforts and can substantially influence health outcomes.</s></p><p xml:id="_G6NCyaP"><s xml:id="_Y2r6pJB">In the pursuit of bridging these care gaps, digital health enables enhanced, continuous and flexible patient care that can broadly be defined as "the convergence of science and technology with health, health care, living, and society" 1 .</s><s xml:id="_gZTPXHY">Since the COVID-19 pandemic started, the number of available tools and corresponding literature has seen an unprecedented increase, making it hard to stay up to date.</s></p><p xml:id="_B6Y8cRu"><s xml:id="_PwwDx2d">In this Review, we depict the potential and barriers of digital health technologies (DHTs) in enhancing the diagnosis, treatment and monitoring of patients with rheumatic diseases.</s><s xml:id="_NsDC2Wj">Additionally, we examine the implications of DHTs for rheumatology education and research.</s><s xml:id="_BfGX654">Key technologies, such as large language models (LLMs), clinical decision-support systems, digital therapeutics, electronic patient-reported outcomes (ePROs), wearables, robots, patient self-sampling devices and artificial intelligence (AI)-based scribes, are examined.</s><s xml:id="_f4bcjGM">We outline an anticipated vision of a digital-first hybrid stepped-care patient pathway.</s><s xml:id="_Cgteekp">The integration of DHTs could improve access to care, foster evidence-based medicine and catalyse a shift</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_ZwycP53">Review article</head><p xml:id="_ydUBvF7"><s xml:id="_qXn4RJd">information is available <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_DuQXTT5">DDSSs are tailored for professional use, provide support and often incorporate broader data sets, including laboratory and imaging results, which enhances diagnostic precision.</s><s xml:id="_mzVU9Cm">The potential of DDSS-aided diagnosis is not new and the discussion around this topic started more than three decades ago <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_GtTTrtf">Yet, despite the increasing number of DDSSs for rheumatology, integration into clinical practice remains limited <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_2eM2we7">Using DDSSs to assist with diagnosis can enhance physician accuracy without demanding extra time or reducing patient satisfaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref> and could also reduce time to diagnosis for several rare rheumatic diseases (such as antisynthetase syndrome and Felty syndrome) <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">21</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_NPnS2p7">Isabel <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">22</ref> and FindZebra <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">23</ref> are examples of DDSSs that are designed for the diagnosis of rare diseases.</s><s xml:id="_AXnr5kg">Furthermore, integrating DDSSs into the rheumatology diagnostic process could help ensure that no potential diagnoses are missed.</s><s xml:id="_wb845Zc">Critical evaluation of DDSS output is crucial to avoid the blind adoption of potentially erroneous suggestions <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">24</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_HVQHW4s">LLMs are becoming increasingly powerful DDSSs, capable of interpreting multimodal data, including images, videos, laboratory results and previous medical reports <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">26</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_ERRjZgv">Interaction with LLM chatbots is more user-friendly compared to traditional DDSSs, enabling clinicians to pose custom queries, such as 'Is this patient more likely to suffer from antisynthetase syndrome or inclusion body myositis and why?'.</s><s xml:id="_2YK7rhW">Although the diagnostic accuracy of LLMs is still limited, this type of DDSS could aid physicians, especially in the diagnosis of rare diseases as shown in a preprint published in 2024 (ref.</s><s xml:id="_Ygy5VuJ">27).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_FHtrZAC">Patient self-sampling</head><p xml:id="_ftJPWJ5"><s xml:id="_VUxQ9sm">The decentralization of diagnostic assessments through home-use capillary self-sampling devices has gained acceptance <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">29</ref> because of the convenience and cost-effectiveness of these devices, with devices for upper-arm sampling preferred by patients with rheumatoid arthritis (RA) due to less discomfort compared with finger-prick methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">29</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_yFPha3s">Although asking patients to provide information from home (such as medical history taking and self-sampling) has only become more regular in rheumatology since the COVID-19 pandemic, decentralized remote diagnostic assessments have been commonly used in other areas for some time such as in the diagnosis of sexually transmitted diseases <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">30</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_eEv3AeD">A 2023 pilot study demonstrated that combining data collection at home with supervised student-led clinics created an effective hybrid approach, enabling accelerated diagnoses and timely treatment initiation in patients with suspected axial spondyloarthritis <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">31</ref> .</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_cHTFJzq">Automation of diagnostic procedures</head><p xml:id="_gHF93Wn"><s xml:id="_5bcxMqa">The automation of diagnostic procedures, such as ultrasonography exams with robotic and AI assistance <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">32</ref> , promises to enhance access, reduce variability and minimize the need for direct HCP involvement.</s><s xml:id="_vFp2Py4">Imaging is one of the first areas to harness the benefits of AI, with heatmaps guiding HCPs in objective detection and grading of pathology, including the use of conventional radiographs <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">33</ref> and nailfold capillary images <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">34</ref> .</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_VD9GVmt">Digitally supported treatment</head><p xml:id="_ZN39rsY"><s xml:id="_JThk94y">Although the introduction of targeted therapies has marked a substantial advancement, the effectiveness of these therapies seems to be constrained by a glass ceiling.</s><s xml:id="_TZDaWKK">The ideal treatment paradigm adheres to P4 medicine -predictive, preventive, personalized and participatory <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_pEVNBdN">Digital treatment support for patients and HCPs offers a promising approach to achieve P4 medicine.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_mbJDdPB">Synchronous and asynchronous communication</head><p xml:id="_BUF36gs"><s xml:id="_EqYnMVb">Digitally supported patient communication can be divided into synchronous <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">35</ref> and asynchronous <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">36</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_9KTQrrp">Traditional synchronous communication occurs in real time and includes traditional on-site face-to-face consultation as well as video-consultations and phone calls.</s><s xml:id="_Q9eTBXA">Asynchronous communication enables participants to engage at different times,</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_jGEJyHf">At-risk detection</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_hPmKyTD">Digital rehabilitation</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_r3gznqu">Adaptive monitoring alarms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_6TDUku2">Clinical decision support systems</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_2B5G8U8">Diagnosis</head><p xml:id="_Z9tz9Jt"><s xml:id="_PREKvs9">Treatment Monitoring Passive data mining of health data eReferrals Decentralized clinical trials Electronic patient-reported outcomes Asynchronous virtual visits Digital therapeutics Digital biomarkers Videoconsultations Diagnosis decision support systems for medical professionals Patient-facing diagnosis decision support systems Virtual reality Sensor-based monitoring (wearables) 24/7 telehealth patient support Automated image analysis Self-sampling Reminders Motion capture Ambient arti icial intelligence scribes Digital patient education Ultrasound robots Reduced costs Improved population health Enhanced patient and provider experience Improved access to care and reduction of health inequalities Evidence-based care • • • • • Overarching goals Fig. 1 | Digitally supported patient pathway.</s><s xml:id="_bPFF6Q3">Illustration of the integration of digital health technologies across the entire patient pathway, facilitating diagnosis, therapy and monitoring.</s><s xml:id="_qsw4SkB">These advancements aim to improve access to care, enhance evidence-based care and help to achieve the quadruple aim of health care (reduced costs, improved population health, and enhanced patient and provider experience).</s><s xml:id="_PncBFQN">A central additional goal is to facilitate evidence-based care based on objective measurements.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_xRZWR8m">Review article</head><p xml:id="_s5sasBr"><s xml:id="_PavVYGg">enabling patients to record information for later review by HCPs, and vice versa.</s><s xml:id="_rWsrNKc">This method offers more flexibility by enabling 'store-andforward' of information such as text messages, pictures and other documents.</s><s xml:id="_6rPjQe5">Replacing HCP-based feedback by automated algorithm-based answers further enables the utilization of efficiency reserves (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_gr5gf5H">Digitally supported self-management</head><p xml:id="_Zx4fjRb"><s xml:id="_9npjz6v">We envision that the digital transformation will drastically alter information gathering and care delivery (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_mfpJQaF">DHTs empower patients to autonomously collect, interpret and act on medical information, thereby catalysing effective self-management.</s><s xml:id="_zRA5ABY">Digitally supported patient self-management could contribute to overcoming care gaps while simultaneously alleviating the burden on the health-care system.</s><s xml:id="_9tQcNr8">This shift towards patient self-management exemplifies the increasing democratization of care, thereby mitigating information asymmetry and diminishing medical paternalism.</s><s xml:id="_cyZqwtA">Augmented patient autonomy and decentralized care delivery might reduce the current burden of care by alleviating constraints such as travel time, costs and response time.</s></p><p xml:id="_PBbKKqR"><s xml:id="_MztHN3y">Insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus provides an example of advanced technology-supported self-management, whereby patients use continuous glucose monitors and automated insulin delivery systems to safely and effectively improve the percentage of time that individuals with diabetes stay within their target blood sugar range <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">37</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_cthJkD4">Creating a closed-loop system for patients with rheumatic diseases is still at the early stages of development.</s><s xml:id="_XkshcMR">Nonetheless, a study assessed a wearable device that was capable of detecting inflammation via impedance sensing in Sprague-Dawley male rats; upon detection, the device initiated a synergistic treatment regimen combining subcutaneous methotrexate and electrical stimulation <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">38</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_Fdg5dKb">The promising results observed in this preclinical model warrant further investigation to evaluate the potential of such advanced technologies in clinical applications.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_8fpQFXt">Digital patient education</head><p xml:id="_s5RATA4"><s xml:id="_hKUM28Z">The recommended general patient education to promote self-management <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">39</ref> is severely limited by staff shortages and financial pressures.</s><s xml:id="_rzEd625">A patient survey carried out in 2022 revealed that only 24% of patients rated their level of disease education as very good or good <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">40</ref> .</s></p><p xml:id="_DXUQaW2"><s xml:id="_9xCZf3K">Of these patients, 89% said that they would welcome digital education tools to learn about their condition; however, validated online education programmes are currently scarce.</s><s xml:id="_Srvs5Xh">A randomized controlled trial carried out in 2024 demonstrated substantially higher self-efficacy and similar knowledge, health literacy and quality of life in patients who completed an online education course compared with face-to-face education <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">41</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_XDAmWUC">However, patients typically have to search for information themselves and older patients in particular have limited access to online health education resources and can struggle to find valid information <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">42</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_AakwSPt">The ongoing expansion of digital information makes it increasingly challenging to distinguish between reliable and misleading content, as the volume and pace of changes continue to grow.</s><s xml:id="_vgX824Q">The brief nature of doctor visits often limits effective advice regarding disease management, leaving many patient questions unanswered.</s><s xml:id="_zP6zwFA">LLM-based chatbots could provide patients with access to answers to a lot of their questions and are always available.</s><s xml:id="_Gf4aDBK">Preliminary studies that assessed ChatGTP responses to questions from patients with systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) yielded promising results, indicating that ChatGPT responses were often deemed of higher quality and more empathetic than those from SLE experts, according to both specialists and patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">44</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_M3bTqqz">To achieve clinical implementation, rigorous validation, along with the assurance of data privacy and security, must be accomplished <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">45</ref> .</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_ckZg2nA">Digital therapeutics</head><p xml:id="_Q3gbQBQ"><s xml:id="_TEwpbDn">Access to non-pharmacological treatments, such as physiotherapy and psychotherapy, can be hindered by the scarcity of HCPs and the considerable distances often involved in travelling to appointments.</s><s xml:id="_BBsvGq8">Video-consultations help to break down geographical barriers and improve patient access to care, often demonstrating comparable treatment effects.</s><s xml:id="_zJSEDB4">Digital therapeutics have the potential to address geographical, temporal and capacity-related barriers by providing automated, evidence-based treatment options that are accessible at any time and location.</s><s xml:id="_Ms8duye">Core osteoarthritis management strategies (such as patient education, exercise, physical activity and dietary weight management) might be effectively supported by digital therapeutics.</s><s xml:id="_kWj9VkP">A landmark multicentre trial this year demonstrated the non-inferiority of physiotherapy delivered by video-consultations compared to in-person care for chronic knee and back pain <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">46,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">47</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_gjquJSZ">Back pain digital therapeutics showed a greater reduction in pain compared to the gold standard of face-to-face physiotherapy, likely owing to patients exercising more frequently with the aid of their smartphones at home <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">47</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_DcW6mzw">The level of guidance for digital therapeutic-based physiotherapy varies from simple video instructions to motion capture-based <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">47</ref> or wearable-based real-time tracking and feedback.</s><s xml:id="_tHs6hh6">Preliminary evidence suggests that digital therapeutics can effectively support patients with inflammatory rheumatic diseases, including axial spondyloarthritis (axSpA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">48,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">49</ref> .</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_PzgSWxE">At home</head><p xml:id="_rYHZFud"><s xml:id="_EPVDWR8">Anywhere Hospital</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_qfE9DuN">Health</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_d6FDynz">Review article</head><p xml:id="_yvVFvhm"><s xml:id="_D5SbtbS">A phase III clinical trial carried out this year demonstrated both the effectiveness and safety of app-based psychological acceptance and commitment therapy in patients with fibromyalgia <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">50</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_BscTbnH">Virtual reality-based digital therapeutics offer a valuable complementary treatment option for patients with fibromyalgia, with notable increases in pain thresholds and pain tolerance <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">51</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_MYjHJAg">Digital therapeutics could provide general disease-specific lifestyle recommendations <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">52</ref> and addressed particular comorbidities such as depression, diabetes, weight reduction, smoking cessation and sleep disorders.</s><s xml:id="_TRnfUDJ">Well-known therapy barriers also exist with digital forms of therapy.</s><s xml:id="_cV2xUxZ">A real-world rheumatology registry study confirmed low adherence as a main barrier to the effectiveness of digital health products, with only 13% of patients completing the full digital therapeutics programme over a 3-month period <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">49</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_SkxNJe5">The study revealed that older men in particular were less likely to use digital therapeutics.</s><s xml:id="_jKz9u8U">Given the availability of immediate, standardized therapeutic options, we foresee an increase in the adoption of digital-first strategies that will help to reduce waiting times and bridge growing gaps in care.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_EbB66QR">Clinical decision-support systems</head><p xml:id="_4V5VAMy"><s xml:id="_2aherFR">Current treatment largely follows a reactive trial-and-error strategy, which fails to deliver quick and enduring benefits to many patients.</s><s xml:id="_KVWstWx">Harnessing AI seems promising to predict individual treatment responses, guide treatment choices <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">53,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">54</ref> , and further reduce drug development costs and time <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">55</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_ThwJpNr">Simple, yet effective, tools such as medication reminders aid patient adherence to treatment and prevent the waste of health-care resources <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">56</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_5SYhx7R">As patients achieve disease remission, AI-enhanced clinical decision-support systems could assist in safely tapering treatments.</s><s xml:id="_jsfWuyp">These systems could help minimize deviations from treatment protocols and bolster the confidence of rheumatologists in making informed treatment decisions <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">57</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_E6Ph6kx">The ability to 'ask' LLMs for treatment recommendations through straightforward queries such as 'How should I treat this patient?' could facilitate the translation of complex clinical guidelines into practical, actionable personalized recommendations.</s><s xml:id="_hvEFQ9d">A 2024 study demonstrated that ChatGPT was capable of generating safe and high-quality treatment plans for the majority of included patients with rheumatic diseases based on such simple queries <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">58</ref> .</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_VfsmrCA">Digitally supported patient monitoring</head><p xml:id="_x9UUR8U"><s xml:id="_WrnVQtw">Patient follow-up consists of periodic pre-planned face-to-face consultations resulting in suboptimal use of HCP and patient time and resources.</s><s xml:id="_U5ybmnU">This traditional approach leads to frequent, unnecessary clinical visits without adjustments to treatment, while changes in disease activity between appointments often go unnoticed, resulting in missed opportunities for treatment optimization.</s><s xml:id="_w2psxab">The conventional patient follow-up approach seems outdated, not based on patient needs and not flexible enough to enable a steady assessment of new patients and continuous follow-up care.</s><s xml:id="_aBr8dMG">Patient-initiated follow-up is a care delivery model in which patients reach out to the clinic as needed, rather than attending regularly scheduled follow-ups.</s><s xml:id="_gwg226E">This model is currently mainly used for patients with less complex diseases and stable disease activity <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">[59]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">[60]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[61]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">[62]</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_kyXehj7">Incorporating digital health could enhance safety, ensure continuity of care and support this proactive, patient-centred and need-adapted approach to patient follow-up <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">63</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_atjFvAt">A shift towards remote care not only reduces the burden for patients with low disease activity but also frees up capacity to treat new patients and those with severe, active disease.</s><s xml:id="_NfvZ5Up">Additionally, remote care holds the potential to enhance the work experience of HCPs, many of whom face long commutes and appreciate the increased flexibility to balance work and family life.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_hs67MdQ">Electronic patient-reported outcomes</head><p xml:id="_TUGPB2D"><s xml:id="_89QPeUX">ePROs are a cornerstone in monitoring individuals with rheumatic disease and can also be used in between planned visits to detect disease fluctuations and to inform treatment changes and the necessity for face-to-face visits.</s><s xml:id="_6h74nDA">However, ePROs should not constantly remind patients of their disease and frequency should be tailored to disease activity <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">64</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_RCnYUS2">Discussing monitoring data with patients enhances patient-provider interactions <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">65</ref> ; however, many rheumatologists are concerned about the additional time required to review and discuss these data <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">66</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_zWVB8MR">ePROs can be used effectively to streamline and prioritize face-to-face appointments.</s><s xml:id="_DNdZrF6">Weekly smartphone-based monitoring with the Routine Assessment of Patient Index Data 3 (RAPID3) led to a 38% decrease in rheumatologist consultations for patients with RA and lowered health-care costs whilst maintaining stable patient disease activity <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">67,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b68">68</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_prW39w7">An ePRO-based remote monitoring pathway for patients with RA was successfully implemented in 2020 (ref.</s><s xml:id="_nXYZBRG">60) (Box 1).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_A6stUY4">Digital biomarkers</head><p xml:id="_YdwazUr"><s xml:id="_3DW4kBH">Smartphones increasingly enable patients to independently collect medical data that goes far beyond traditional questionnaires and conduct their own objective assessments, enabling the automated detection and quantification of swollen joints <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">69</ref> , handgrip strength <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">70</ref> , nail psoriasis <ref type="bibr" target="#b71">71</ref> and range of motion <ref type="bibr" target="#b72">72</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_UJpjRcZ">The wear study currently aims to investigate a more comprehensive monitoring approach, including wearable data and traditional ePROs <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">73</ref> .</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_tFRS29X">Sensor-based monitoring</head><p xml:id="_FkhpQmj"><s xml:id="_TeVhBY3">Sensors facilitate continuous, fine-grained measurement in a passive manner, substantially reducing the burden of monitoring for patients</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_mNFXyH5">Box 1 | Successful implementation of remote monitoring for rheumatoid arthritis</head><p xml:id="_CM4FPFe"><s xml:id="_YFMJNs4">In mid-2020, the Southmead rheumatology department introduced a remote monitoring pathway for patients with rheumatoid arthritis on biologic or targeted synthetic disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">60</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_NBwW5Sn">As part of this pathway, patients were offered a smartphone app to complete electronic patient-reported outcomes (Routine Assessment of Patient Index Data 3 (RAPID3), Health Assessment Questionnaire-Disability Index and self-reported Disease Activity Score-28 for Rheumatoid Arthritis using C-reactive protein), which clinicians reviewed asynchronously via a web-based portal.</s><s xml:id="_ayeZN5j">Clinicians then sent letters to patients in remission with satisfactory and up-to-date blood monitoring data summarizing the review.</s><s xml:id="_BsktraZ">Reviews were conducted either at the default 6-month interval or sooner if requested by a clinician or patient (expedited review).</s><s xml:id="_pz7mTyZ">Face-to-face appointments were available as needed (escalated review) and an in-person review was required every 3 years.</s><s xml:id="_3AXXebA">Within the first year, this initiative saved over 140 h of clinic time and approximately £80,000 in unnecessary appointment costs.</s><s xml:id="_xDgvBh8">Patient surveys indicated high satisfaction, with more than 90% of patients expressing a preference to continue with non-face-to-face appointments.</s><s xml:id="_ywShSDX">By mid-2023, the programme had enrolled over 1,100 patients and completed more than 40,000 electronic patient-reported outcomes.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_8pmhDww">Review article</head><p xml:id="_wKHagtR"><s xml:id="_kBwFwpf">whilst generating abundant data; however, research regarding passive monitoring of patients with rheumatic diseases is limited and heterogeneous <ref type="bibr" target="#b74">74,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b75">75</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_vAqPnFP">Wristwatch tracking of physical activity has proven effective in accurately predicting disease flares in patients with RA and axSpA <ref type="bibr" target="#b76">76</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_XeGpz4M">Additionally, physical activity metrics show promise for less common conditions such as myositis, aligning closely with established physical tests and treatment response criteria <ref type="bibr" target="#b77">77</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_DsgbXzK">Sleep behaviour monitoring further refines patient profiles, offering a basis for highly personalized and automated behaviour change recommendations <ref type="bibr" target="#b78">78</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_cqP4PF4">Although self-sampling presents opportunities to predict disease flares <ref type="bibr" target="#b79">79,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b80">80</ref> , the high frequency and cost of individual blood collections remain challenging <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">28</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_9gKF8Wa">Advances in continuous, passive and non-invasive biomarker monitoring could transform rheumatology, similar to the effect of continuous glucose monitoring in diabetes management.</s><s xml:id="_qmp3dDh">Emerging technologies such as wireless patches for measuring C-reactive protein (CRP) in sweat <ref type="bibr" target="#b81">81</ref> and salivary uric acid <ref type="bibr" target="#b82">82</ref> to closed-loop systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">38</ref> , highlight future potential in the field <ref type="bibr" target="#b82">82</ref> .</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_FZptYsa">Towards a digital-first hybrid stepped-care model</head><p xml:id="_s3s7dBC"><s xml:id="_ySckVfF">In line with evolving trends in diagnosis and treatment, we anticipate a shift towards a more flexible, digital-first, hybrid stepped-care model, which incorporates five levels of monitoring (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_sVABUh4">At the core is a digital safety net based on passive, continuous sensor-based monitoring (level 1) and on-demand self-assessments (level 2), where AI models can provide instant automated feedback to patients and trigger monitoring alerts for HCPs.</s><s xml:id="_gtAR23f">Monitoring alarms and chat-based queries can trigger virtual visits (level 3) and asynchronous feedback by HCPs.</s><s xml:id="_fXBd3UY">Virtual visits to review RA flare questionnaires and CRP results by nurses or rheumatologists every 3-4 months enabled a safe reduction of face-to-face visits <ref type="bibr" target="#b83">83,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b84">84</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_cjh7PbJ">Notably, no differences were observed between rheumatology nurses or rheumatologists performing the remote monitoring of patients.</s><s xml:id="_gXTctds">A similar study in patients with axSpA investigated a fully remote approach, incorporating self-sampling to remotely generate an Ankylosing Spondylitis Disease Activity Score with CRP, which was reviewed in conjunction with more frequent questionnaires (Bath Ankylosing Spondylitis Disease Activity Index and Patient Global Assessment of Disease Activity bi-weekly and weekly flare questionnaire).</s><s xml:id="_eaTEgJw">This approach facilitated a safe reduction in face-toface visits and was highly accepted by patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b85">85</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_QMDh2Vw">Two large randomized controlled trials are currently under way to assess the efficacy of remote monitoring in patients with axSpA <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">62,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b86">86</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_CMJfYCY">Remote monitoring might also foster a treat-to-target approach and accelerate disease remission.</s><s xml:id="_QXPMszR">Monthly or bi-monthly virtual visits to assess Rheumatoid Arthritis Impact of Disease questionnaire results, along with standardized treatment intensification, significantly increased the proportion of patients with early RA achieving Clinical Disease Activity Index remission <ref type="bibr" target="#b87">87</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_YWFaFCV">Similarly, virtual visits have also been effectively implemented to improve the attainment of urate targets in patients with gout <ref type="bibr" target="#b88">88,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b89">89</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_WsKBBg2">The ongoing TELERA trial assesses treatment concordance of asynchronous virtual visits compared to traditional in-person visits in patients with RA <ref type="bibr" target="#b90">90</ref> .</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_4zQQBVe">Video-consultation (level 4)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_RgXCvCD">Level 1</head><p xml:id="_uvQh3h7"><s xml:id="_Dguwqh4">Recognition of low physical activity and automated motivating feedback</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_RD43VHM">Level 2</head><p xml:id="_y4PWMVY"><s xml:id="_feZU3K7">Electronic patientreported outcomes</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_qPREz3M">Level 3</head><p xml:id="_bCEks3Z"><s xml:id="_krZHkee">Virtual visits</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_hYmNggP">Level 4</head><p xml:id="_wkRFMkv"><s xml:id="_wfRnCCP">Video-consultations In traditional follow-up, patients attend synchronous, periodic, pre-planned, face-to-face consultations, which can result in overlooked disease flares and adverse effects.</s><s xml:id="_YkAN66H">Quick access to answers and appointments during flares is challenging.</s><s xml:id="_w3qeHGm">Conversely, digitally supported hybrid patient follow-up fosters a proactive, continuous and personalized care approach.</s><s xml:id="_DRzpEea">We anticipate a transition towards a digital-first stepped-care monitoring approach.</s><s xml:id="_3dc2rYz">Passive continuous monitoring via sensors (level 1) and on-demand self-assessments (level 2) establish a foundational digital safety net.</s><s xml:id="_8m8nZ4U">If queries cannot be solved using automated feedback, health-care professionals are prompted by monitoring alarms to perform virtual visits (level 3).</s><s xml:id="_e2X2A7r">If queries cannot be resolved on the first three asynchronous levels, monitoring is escalated to the synchronous approach (video-consultation, telephone, chat; level 4) and traditional face-to-face appointments (level 5) are only arranged as a last resort.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_8nbFRAM">Review article</head><p xml:id="_HyB4Eb7"><s xml:id="_TcTMZxx">The next monitoring escalation (level 4) would involve synchronous remote communication, including telephone calls and video-consultations.</s><s xml:id="_PJA6J7u">During the COVID-19 pandemic, the use of video-consultations increased; however, virtual examinations are still developing and have not yet reached full maturity <ref type="bibr" target="#b91">91</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_B6JdRB5">Video-consultations demonstrated a substantial reliability in identifying patients that required treatment adjustments <ref type="bibr" target="#b92">92</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_QBZ3Es4">In line with previous results <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">59</ref> , a randomized controlled trial demonstrated that for more complex diseases, such as SLE, monitoring often had to be escalated to face-to-face visits.</s><s xml:id="_JjTHSvz">We anticipate that face-to-face consultations (level 5) will be notably reduced, representing the final escalation in monitoring.</s><s xml:id="_tNhFjxd">Moreover, face-to-face care will likely predominantly involve patients with complex refractory diseases and high disease activity <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">59</ref> , with successfully treated patients being mostly monitored virtually.</s><s xml:id="_NWRGjeq">This shift could also lead to an increase in rheumatologists providing a combination of in-person and remote care.</s><s xml:id="_4V65SGj">This combination could facilitate a sustainable balance between in-person treatment of patients with highly complex and active disease with the remote management of a higher number of patients who are in remission.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_cvymvZD">Augmented in-person visits</head><p xml:id="_zM4SJGc"><s xml:id="_DqgqKBR">Physical examinations face challenges such as substantial diurnal symptom variation <ref type="bibr" target="#b93">93</ref> , time constraints and inter-rater variability.</s><s xml:id="_X6Q8pgc">Digital technologies enhance the objectivity of these examinations, possibly also rendering traditional functional capacity questionnaires obsolete.</s><s xml:id="_c5CZ5M4">Measurement of spinal mobility is, for example, heavily affected by variability and subjectivity.</s><s xml:id="_QrXwrbM">Automated motion capture systems, such as the University of Cordoba Ankylosing Spondylitis Metrology Index, provide precise and objective assessments <ref type="bibr" target="#b94">94</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_bFtKdKF">Medical documentation could be immensely facilitated by artificial intelligence-powered ambient virtual scribes such as Ambience or Nuance DAX, which instantly generate structured summaries of patient-provider interactions.</s><s xml:id="_BpGxCkv">A first real-world pilot study revealed a statistically significant yet clinically negligible average time-saving effect of less than 1 min per patient <ref type="bibr" target="#b95">95</ref> ; however, this technology does enable physicians to redirect their attention from screens to patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b95">95,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b96">96</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_wrxzqcp">Greater integration of LLMs into clinical workflows can also help to improve other administrative tasks such as appointment scheduling and correspondence with insurance companies.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_VdT75b8">Research and clinical trials</head><p xml:id="_Kb6XG7j"><s xml:id="_tCDVB4e">Reviewing the scientific literature can be a time-consuming process.</s><s xml:id="_QVwTjrU">Free tools such as AI-based Elicit can streamline this task by allowing straightforward questions, such as 'Is remote monitoring safe for patients with rheumatic diseases?', to be asked.</s><s xml:id="_YJJFEcD">Short summaries of the literature and customizable overviews of the research make it easier to gain insights efficiently.</s><s xml:id="_sQbQuQT">Rheumatology research is often held back by slow and expensive clinical trials, fragmentation of data and siloed research teams.</s><s xml:id="_rk7YjW3">Decentralized clinical trials can facilitate patient recruitment by eliminating the need for travel and reducing patient burden and costs <ref type="bibr" target="#b97">97,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b98">98</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_Cr9DHWf">The increasing online presence of patient support groups has furthered patient recruitment, co-design between patients and HCPs, and overall patient involvement in research projects.</s><s xml:id="_h8ZcTCv">Collaborative online studies offer a new frontier in medical research (particularly for rare diseases) by facilitating large-scale, patient-focused research that integrates patient perspectives as equal stakeholders and valued partners in the study of their conditions, ultimately improving clinical care <ref type="bibr" target="#b99">99</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_9pXnbDR">This approach could be particularly valuable for individuals with rare diseases who are faced with unforeseen circumstances such as establishing the safety of vaccines during a global pandemic 100 .</s></p><p xml:id="_Hzg5Yj7"><s xml:id="_hmA7N94">Remote monitoring technology leverages outcome assessments and enables rich trial data.</s><s xml:id="_HWXJAz4">Free but powerful web applications, such as REDCap, bring patient cohorts together and generate new clinical knowledge, for example, the reliability of antisynthetase antibodies 101 .</s><s xml:id="_cEErWjE">Disease activity scoring is often a tedious, labour-intensive task, which requires special training and often results in deviating scores due to high inter-rater reliability.</s><s xml:id="_u6JvTTq">AI promises to overcome these limitations, even in rare diseases.</s><s xml:id="_bVMq7Sk">A study evaluated the performance of the LLM Claude-2 in assessing disease severity in idiopathic inflammatory myopathies using the Myositis Disease Activity Assessment Tool-Visual Analogue Scale, compared with the scores of three human assessors.</s><s xml:id="_f6QWtPs">The results showed good reliability between Claude-2 and human assessors, with an average intraclass correlation coefficient of 0.93 (95% CI 0.92-0.94)</s><s xml:id="_rtJRBT5">and strong positive correlations between the global assessment of Claude-2 scores and those of experienced assessors.</s><s xml:id="_7kvZtGk">The Claude-2-generated scores were on par with those of skilled assessors and outperformed inexperienced scorers 102 .</s><s xml:id="_YbFkBte">Hence, this tool could be used to accelerate the identification of patients with severe disease while negating the need to scan records for suitable participants and potentially to manually rate disease activity.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_4vH4bJK">Training and education</head><p xml:id="_2NDxybM"><s xml:id="_5aFfgFa">Digitalization has opened a new frontier in educational approaches <ref type="bibr">103</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_CkNnEjD">Wider outreach has brought hope of reducing inequities, overcoming geographical barriers and fostering collaborative learning.</s><s xml:id="_WVdVMzW">Social media fosters the formation of an interconnected digital community 104 .</s><s xml:id="_nKNchFG">To this effect, RheumMadness, a bracket-style online competition, featuring rheumatology concepts as 'teams', fostered a community of enquiry through social media discussions, multimedia resources and prediction brackets, facilitating social constructivist learning about the field.</s><s xml:id="_KTzCyK5">The programme expanded its participant base and engagement from 2021 to 2022, particularly among early learners who credited the programme for increasing their interest in rheumatology and fostering a sense of belonging in the rheumatology community through the collaborative learning approach 105 .</s><s xml:id="_7pnAE2J">Educational content can be delivered more vividly compared to traditional textbooks using new technologies such as virtual reality 106 and chatbots <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">24</ref> , facilitating the training of HCPs and increasing the interest of medical students in rheumatology <ref type="bibr">106</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_bTAxrSF">LLMs represent a paradigm shift in medical education by offering on-demand, flexible tutoring that enables queries such as 'What are the typical symptoms of antisynthetase syndrome?'.</s><s xml:id="_vQnQSne">Blended learning approaches, similar to hybrid care (also known as blended care), combine the strengths of face-to-face and digital learning environments, allowing greater flexibility, and are particularly useful for teaching practical skills such as ultrasound <ref type="bibr">107</ref> .</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_wXcVbtM">DHT implementation barriers</head><p xml:id="_VpfTKkB"><s xml:id="_KXNkW6E">The successful deployment of DHTs is offset by numerous barriers 108 .</s><s xml:id="_NsTRwfM">HCPs could feel overwhelmed by the need to review constant streams of monitoring data <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">66</ref> and to integrate technology troubleshooting tasks into their schedules.</s><s xml:id="_ZaQxzbR">To address this, the introduction of specialized care members, such as digital navigators 109 , might be necessary to effectively implement technology into clinical routines.</s><s xml:id="_MGxMxPa">Education has a key role in overcoming resistance and scepticism <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr">110</ref> , providing the necessary knowledge and awareness to facilitate widespread adoption of these technologies.</s><s xml:id="_b4ayTbh">DHTs are still rarely integrated into student and professional curricula, which hinders widespread adoption 111 .</s><s xml:id="_9kQh4vS">To fully</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_EeMm2uw">Review article</head><p xml:id="_2RMdhcm"><s xml:id="_R3phKvy">harness the potential of LLMs, HCPs will need to develop entirely new skills, including LLM prompt engineering 112 .</s><s xml:id="_TjYy5Ty">Refined and precise LLM instructions could facilitate several clinical and academic tasks such as generating differential diagnosis or writing grant applications.</s><s xml:id="_cVj9Phv">The current scarcity of evidence supporting DHT implementation must be addressed urgently to provide solid facts that can reassure sceptical colleagues and policy-makers 113 .</s><s xml:id="_D4cCbW7">Dedicated funding of digital health research and DHT reimbursement is also crucial to fostering implementation into routine care.</s><s xml:id="_taq7fnm">Rheumatologists are unlikely to adopt remote care if video-consultations and virtual visits result in net losses.</s><s xml:id="_v7H3F5y">The USA billing codes for remote therapeutic monitoring provide a model for incentivising such services.</s><s xml:id="_WSvuFQp">Similarly, German legislation has introduced Digitale Gesundheitsanwendungen (DiGA), regulated digital health applications that can be prescribed by physicians and are fully reimbursed.</s><s xml:id="_SFYWXwG">Implementation of a pay-for-performance for digital therapeutics approach could foster digital therapeutics cost-effectiveness 114 .</s><s xml:id="_7TrbE36">Digital therapeutics are well suited for a pay-for-performance model, as adherence and effectiveness data can be easily monitored remotely.</s><s xml:id="_Fddzyp3">This enables insurance companies to reimburse digital therapeutic interventions based on their demonstrated outcomes, ensuring cost-efficiency and preventing unnecessary expenditures.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_cJyjArT">Digital divide</head><p xml:id="_EfbTjPf"><s xml:id="_gJBqYbR">Addressing infrastructural challenges, such as limited internet access and interoperability issues, requires considerable patience and persistence 110 .</s><s xml:id="_GtUyMtw">To truly close care gaps and avoid exacerbating the digital divide, it is crucial that special attention is given to vulnerable individuals.</s><s xml:id="_t2PTWRk">Shifting tasks and responsibilities to patients imposes new demands on those who are ill and should only be done voluntarily, with careful consideration given to preventing overwhelm, anxiety and the potential for medical errors <ref type="bibr">115</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_244wxSs">The World Health Organization recommends dedicated training and quality assurance mechanisms to ensure safe and effective task shifting <ref type="bibr">116</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_6HtpySf">It is important to recognize that patient preferences can vary widely, with some individuals favouring traditional, physician-led care over an increased emphasis on self-management.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_JKSFThE">Balancing benefits and risk of AI implementation</head><p xml:id="_q8VzzSw"><s xml:id="_rfxABd6">The increasing integration of AI models will likely transform the traditional patient-provider relationship into a digital health triad (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">4</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_964yhkt">Medical data collected by both patients and HCPs will be stored in data lakes (centralized repositories that store vast amounts of raw data) and AI models will constantly generate decision-support data and utilize this data for continuous model improvement.</s><s xml:id="_68et5rW">However, the effect of AI can be double-edged and potential risks need to be considered such as AI bias, blind trust in AI recommendations and the danger of AI paternalism, where HCPs and patients have to justify decisions that diverge from AI-generated suggestions 117 .</s><s xml:id="_hFuxZqz">The performance of LLMs is constrained because of limited access to large, high-quality medical data sets for training <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">26</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_SGkrEFF">To mitigate algorithmic biases, which frequently result from models trained on small, homogeneous patient populations, it is essential to include participants from diverse backgrounds 118 .</s><s xml:id="_KexA9RY">The factuality and safety of LLMs can be improved by the restructuring of clinical queries into 'search' and 'retrieval' tasks and subsequent knowledge distillation (performed by the LLMs) from the retrieved documents <ref type="bibr">119</ref> .</s></p><p xml:id="_5BfU5rV"><s xml:id="_xRyPRXU">Ensuring data privacy, security and transparency in data usage and algorithms is essential, and regulators must carefully balance fostering innovation with maintaining these standards 120 .</s><s xml:id="_fkMsxXa">The EU Artificial Intelligence Act, the world's first comprehensive legal framework specifically addressing AI, has a pivotal role in guaranteeing the safe and ethical use of AI.</s><s xml:id="_wgV89mn">However, this legislation also introduces greater complexity and costs, which are likely to disproportionately affect smaller enterprises, including those offering open-source products, potentially weakening their market position <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">45</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_hNbBjZB">Moreover, the rapid evolution of the AI health-care market and the lack of regulatory enforcement in the European Union and USA raise doubts about the actual influence of any regulations <ref type="bibr">120</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_ghyVpPa">Utilizing open-source LLMs (such as Llama) on local hardware could help to overcome the security challenges associated with using privately controlled, cloud-based LLMs such as ChatGPT-4 (ref.</s><s xml:id="_KTVcWvW">121).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_u2HerJs">Implementation guidance</head><p xml:id="_9Ssp8p6"><s xml:id="_ym8yDWK">Despite the considerable potential of DHTs, failure to adopt and premature discontinuation are extremely common <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">66,</ref><ref type="bibr">122,</ref><ref type="bibr">123</ref> ; however, frameworks, checklists and guidelines can support successful implementation <ref type="bibr">111,</ref><ref type="bibr">[124]</ref><ref type="bibr">[125]</ref><ref type="bibr">[126]</ref><ref type="bibr">[127]</ref><ref type="bibr">[128]</ref><ref type="bibr">[129]</ref><ref type="bibr">[130]</ref><ref type="bibr">[131]</ref><ref type="bibr">[132]</ref><ref type="bibr">[133]</ref><ref type="bibr">[134]</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_SBmFUGu">The Nonadoption, Abandonment, Scale-up, Spread, and Sustainability (NASSS) framework 127 is particularly useful for planning the implementation and scale-up of DHTs.</s><s xml:id="_FMhPnZF">This framework can also inform the design and evaluation of existing DHTs, providing insight into the reasons behind implementation failures.</s><s xml:id="_kRbDGMB">The NASSS framework comprises 13 questions across six domains (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref>): the condition; the technology; the value proposition; the adopter system (including staff and patients); the health-care organization; and the broader institutional and societal context 127 .</s><s xml:id="_F47jwR5">An additional seventh domain addresses adaptations over time.</s><s xml:id="_ZrFUnqG">To facilitate continuous, iterative adaptations, the Plan-Do-Check-Act cycle, which was introduced in the 1950s, serves as a valuable complement to the NASSS framework.</s><s xml:id="_pJ6H3VQ">Implementation challenges can be classified as simple,</s></p><p xml:id="_ubc4d5a"><s xml:id="_DapN9Du">Digital health technology including AI models M u lt im o d a l p a t ie n t -g e n e r a t e d d a t a C li n ic a l m e d ic a l d a t a C li n ic a l d e c is io n s u p p o r t S e lf -m a n a g e m e n t s u p p o r t Enhanced patientprovider relationship Patients Health-care professionals Continuous AI model improvement The traditional patient-provider relationship will be enhanced by integrating digital health technologies, including artificial intelligence (AI) models, forming a synergistic digital health triad.</s><s xml:id="_kPFn9qR">AI models are continuously improving by integrating new patient-generated and provider-generated data.</s><s xml:id="_TMgfEqe">Both patients and health-care professionals will benefit from continuous decision support.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_4ckXYvR">Review article</head><p xml:id="_4skK7rb"><s xml:id="_Juf8gw9">complicated or complex using the NASSS framework; managing these challenges systematically is crucial as the likelihood of successful DHT implementation decreases with the increasing complexity of implementation challenges <ref type="bibr">127</ref> .</s></p><p xml:id="_fZj2DeU"><s xml:id="_mQtuAA9">In addition, the 42-item telehealth development and implementation checklist 128 could be a useful tool for implementation.</s><s xml:id="_Sjqj3ju">This list encompasses six key components: identifying issues, needs and partners; developing a strategy; securing funding; implementing service delivery changes; monitoring and evaluation; and leadership and training.</s></p><p xml:id="_g645ndg"><s xml:id="_FBynBka">Change management 129 is especially valuable in consolidating DHT implementation.</s><s xml:id="_wYTCEfQ">Although various change management models exist, the Balanced Scorecard 130 is particularly effective in providing strategic insights; this scorecard embraces key performance indicators, such as the number of remotely monitored patients, to monitor success and guide iterative improvements.</s></p><p xml:id="_rkvkmzM"><s xml:id="_eNRvKQC">Three key factors seem to be crucial for successful implementation of DHTs: appointing a change manager who is responsible for monitoring and iterative adaptations <ref type="bibr">[127]</ref><ref type="bibr">[128]</ref><ref type="bibr">[129]</ref> ; identifying a HCP as a local champion to encourage and motivate colleagues <ref type="bibr">127,</ref><ref type="bibr">129</ref> ; and</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_jb2ADHm">Glossary</head><p xml:id="_9JvueC3"><s xml:id="_3cvAA3C">Artificial intelligence-powered ambient virtual scribes Automated systems that use artificial intelligence (AI) to passively listen to and transcribe doctor-patient interactions in real time, reducing the documentation burden on health-care professionals.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_f3Ajqmy">Balanced Scorecard</head><p xml:id="_eDUVnWW"><s xml:id="_xGST65s">A strategic management tool that tracks the performance of an organization across multiple perspectives to provide a comprehensive view of the progress made towards achieving the objectives of the organization.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_nJcKgxh">Blended learning</head><p xml:id="_w8SbTmw"><s xml:id="_4HTS8wB">An educational approach that combines traditional face-to-face learning with online and electronic education materials.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_nZtdnm3">Clinical decision-support systems</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_xYyX4C7">Closed-loop system</head><p xml:id="_YCDeWrR"><s xml:id="_u6vDwxr">An automated insulin delivery system that continuously monitors blood glucose levels and automatically adjusts insulin dosing in real time, reducing the need for manual insulin administration.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_6gpJYkA">Decentralized clinical trials</head><p xml:id="_mnxCrFV"><s xml:id="_m33P6xr">Trials that are conducted without in-person contact, utilizing remote methods for participant recruitment, medication delivery and data collection.</s><s xml:id="_uAY5vaK">Diagnostic decision-support systems (DDSSs).</s><s xml:id="_KVCVRNB">Software that helps patients and health-care professionals interpret medical data to initiate appropriate diagnostic work-up and ultimately generate accurate and timely diagnoses.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_kNHrEmc">Digital divide</head><p xml:id="_2sudYt3"><s xml:id="_4UQC7KV">In health care, refers to the disparity between individuals who have both access to digital health technologies and the necessary skills to use them effectively, and those who lack either or both.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_ZujHAbW">Digital navigators</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_RTtpFbR">Key performance indicators</head><p xml:id="_S8UqGWt"><s xml:id="_gYnVAaN">Quantifiable metrics used to assess progress in relation to specific objectives, thereby guiding strategic decision-making.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_hS7VaaM">Large language models</head><p xml:id="_HUcxG8C"><s xml:id="_UWNNBCJ">(LLMs).</s><s xml:id="_qfX4bWx">An advanced AI system trained on vast amounts data to interpret, generate and manipulate human language.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_NJWxY59">Patient self-sampling</head><p xml:id="_QHWQuuR"><s xml:id="_kCaF83H">The process through which patients collect their own biological specimens (such as saliva or blood) for diagnostic or monitoring purposes.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_gu4EJN4">Patient-initiated follow-up</head><p xml:id="_cVwZ5R3"><s xml:id="_YFdpWtq">A care delivery model that enables patients to reach out to the clinic as needed, rather than attending regularly scheduled follow-up appointments.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_QMJgjPw">Pay-for-performance for digital therapeutics</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Uwt8Fev">Plan-Do-Check-Act cycle</head><p xml:id="_Gr5EnHE"><s xml:id="_GCmRAeX">A continuous improvement process used to systematically plan, implement, evaluate and refine changes to enhance processes or products.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_ta64tS4">Prompt engineering</head><p xml:id="_64rxYmh"><s xml:id="_krebrGS">The process of designing and refining input queries or instructions to effectively guide the output of LLMs and other AI systems.</s></p><p xml:id="_waWkMRd"><s xml:id="_AraXZPH">The Nonadoption, Abandonment, Scale-up, Spread, and Sustainability (NASSS) framework A tool designed to assess and guide the implementation, scaling and sustainability of complex health and care technologies by examining challenges across seven domains.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_ukW3fX6">Virtual visits</head><p xml:id="_kWvApgt"><s xml:id="_WaGRCnV">An example of asynchronous telehealth that involves a health-care professional reviewing medical information that has been stored and forwarded by the patient; also known as an electronic visit (e-visit).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_6Q2Cwp7">Review article</head><p xml:id="_VnPaHc9"><s xml:id="_qH6M2zc">employing a participatory design <ref type="bibr">129,</ref><ref type="bibr">131</ref> .</s><s xml:id="_QV2jJ6u">Participatory design is a methodology that actively engages all relevant stakeholders to ensure a strong value proposition and usability and, most importantly, to foster ownership of DHT implementation changes 131 .</s><s xml:id="_J5jXwNz">Participatory design typically involves three overlapping phases: needs assessment, design and testing, with multiple iterations and feedback loops.</s><s xml:id="_mJcpRVB">Gathering qualitative feedback from stakeholders is vital for gaining a comprehensive understanding of both barriers and facilitators of DHT implementation.</s></p><p xml:id="_TGphdJ9"><s xml:id="_8dxwe5H">Collaborative efforts are key to effectively navigating and leveraging the rapidly evolving digital health landscape.</s><s xml:id="_mWzDgKC">Nevertheless, there is no universal solution and tailored strategies are essential to addressing the unique needs and conditions of each DHT implementation scenario.</s><s xml:id="_jAJPRFu">Various local, national and international task forces have formed to exchange experiences, to set up hands-on workshops, and to provide initial recommendations <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">60,</ref><ref type="bibr">111,</ref><ref type="bibr">[132]</ref><ref type="bibr">[133]</ref><ref type="bibr">[134]</ref> and research agendas 111 to steer future initiatives.</s><s xml:id="_SbHEU9k">The NHS Rheumatology Digital Playbook provides a collection of inspiring case studies depicting successful digital transformation in rheumatology.</s><s xml:id="_CbYdpj3">The Digital Rheumatology Network exemplifies such collaboration, serving as an international consortium dedicated to promoting the adoption of digital health in rheumatology.</s><s xml:id="_gXUB8fG">This network supports the field through the provision of educational resources and regular face-to-face and virtual congresses and by encouraging research and innovation with start-up and research awards.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_AyXGJ3B">Conclusions</head><p xml:id="_PfTAJHS"><s xml:id="_VScHeXv">The digital health era holds transformative potential for rheumatology, offering innovative solutions to longstanding challenges in patient care and system efficiency.</s><s xml:id="_qNRMMTK">DHTs can be implemented along the entire patient pathway to improve diagnostics, treatment and monitoring and to empower patients.</s><s xml:id="_hT7eVVh">AI-based automation of workflows has the potential to substantially reduce bureaucratic burdens for all stakeholders involved, decrease screen time and promote more meaningful human interactions.</s><s xml:id="_VMVTSuC">Implementation of a digital-first hybrid stepped-care strategy and decision-support systems promise to facilitate a shift towards a more personalized, predictive and participatory health-care model.</s><s xml:id="_b527HXB">However, the successful integration of these technologies into routine clinical care will require overcoming substantial barriers, including regulatory hurdles, reimbursement, and the need for widespread professional training and patient education.</s><s xml:id="_fETpcMm">By sharing lessons learned and fostering collaboration, rheumatologists can accelerate the transition and fully harness the potential of digital health to meet growing demands.</s></p><p xml:id="_2NCbVwq"><s xml:id="_Aem6KyG">Published online: 31 October 2024</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 2 |</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_FbnSHyZ"><s xml:id="_Cfhvzhj">Fig.2| Transformation of care delivery through digital health.</s><s xml:id="_KRqhwE3">Health care could be transformed via a progressive transition from traditional information gathering and care delivery (lower left), characterized by episodic, in-person visits that are reliant on health-care professionals for data collection and treatment provision, to a digitally supported, patient-centred care model (upper right).</s><s xml:id="_wDvsRMG">Examples across the transition spectrum include traditional in-person consultations (lower left), virtual consultations (middle) and sensor-based monitoring in combination with smartphone-based digital therapeutics (top right).</s><s xml:id="_KhHb47J">In this evolving paradigm, patients gain autonomy, conduct self-assessments and receive continuous therapy support, anywhere and anytime.</s><s xml:id="_xAftcER">The burden of care on patients and health-care professionals is reduced by sensor-based continuous measurements and automated patient treatment support.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3 |</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_XcR85zv"><s xml:id="_thkbtt4">Fig.3| Digital-first hybrid stepped-care model.</s><s xml:id="_CD3GMCn">a, An overview of a hybrid monitoring approach compared with traditional face-to-face visits.</s><s xml:id="_kb69A5f">b, The five levels of patient monitoring and escalation of care.</s><s xml:id="_bXPQ7rR">In traditional follow-up, patients attend synchronous, periodic, pre-planned, face-to-face consultations, which can result in overlooked disease flares and adverse effects.</s><s xml:id="_HaWCf92">Quick access to answers and appointments during flares is challenging.</s><s xml:id="_R7VwDfS">Conversely, digitally supported hybrid patient follow-up fosters a proactive, continuous and personalized care approach.</s><s xml:id="_pn4Ag4Q">We anticipate a transition towards a digital-first</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 4 |</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_QNjVhpv"><s xml:id="_5shsznk">Fig.4| Digital health triad.</s><s xml:id="_67QAkfQ">The traditional patient-provider relationship will be enhanced by integrating digital health technologies, including artificial intelligence (AI) models, forming a synergistic digital health triad.</s><s xml:id="_hgbJqTa">AI models are continuously improving by integrating new patient-generated and provider-generated data.</s><s xml:id="_emvRNZM">Both patients and health-care professionals will benefit from continuous decision support.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_pYvPW7a"><s xml:id="_xxCSNPW">Algorithm-based software to aid patients and health-care professionals in making clinical decisions, especially regarding diagnosis and treatment.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>A</head><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_ZvTVsbq"><s xml:id="_czKZZx5">video-consultations.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>A</head><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_jKYQ9D5"><s xml:id="_8DpGXDh">reimbursement model used by insurance companies to cover the costs of digital therapeutic interventions based on their proven effectiveness and patient adherence, ensuring cost-efficiency and avoiding unnecessary expenditures.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 5 |</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_FEEUKtu"><s xml:id="_Q67PXV7">Fig. 5 | NASSS framework and Plan-Do-Check-Act cycle to guide digital health technology implementation.</s><s xml:id="_6cgnZzn">The Nonadoption, Abandonment, Scale-up, Spread, and Sustainability (NASSS) framework 127 can be used to guide digital health technology implementation and consists of six core domains:(1) the condition, (2) the technology, (3) the value proposition, (4) the adopter system (including staff and patients), (5) the health-care organization and (6) the wider system (broader institutional and societal context).</s><s xml:id="_u3WkvJ5">The seventh domain addresses adaptations over time, which can be guided by the Plan-Do-Check-Act cycle.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head xml:id="_pErFasT">Acknowledgements</head><p xml:id="_rday7uQ"><s xml:id="_XpRcnah">We would like to thank all individuals and organizations dedicated to advancing digital health in rheumatology.</s><s xml:id="_vQRHPFv">We give special thanks to the members of the <rs type="institution">Digital Rheumatology Network</rs> for their invaluable contributions and particularly to <rs type="person">S. Reis</rs>, whose unwavering support has been crucial for the network.</s><s xml:id="_Qwx9mx9">We would like to express our gratitude to <rs type="person">B. Hirte</rs> for his assistance in translating ideas into images, and to <rs type="person">A. de Thurah</rs>, <rs type="person">S. Kuhn</rs> and <rs type="person">F. Lechner</rs> for their valuable and constructive advice.</s></p></div>
			</div>			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_xwHavK6">Author contributions</head><p xml:id="_ahZ8v58"><s xml:id="_3eQd6B3">All authors contributed substantially to the discussion of the content and reviewed and/or edited the manuscript before submission.</s><s xml:id="_YeGyQNv">J.K. and L.G. wrote the article and researched data for the article.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_mhenETB">Competing interests</head><p xml:id="_ddrUpxN"><s xml:id="_NUs258U">J.K. declares research support from Abbvie, BMBF, EIT Health, GSK, Sanofi and Vila Health, and honoraria and consulting fees from Abbvie, AstraZeneca, BMS, Boehringer Ingelheim,</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_MwyBBBq">Additional information</head><p xml:id="_utJgdE4"><s xml:id="_hN4r3ZX">Peer review information Nature Reviews Rheumatology thanks Jacob van Laar who co-reviewed with Chiara Ripepi, Wan-Fai Ng, Jeffrey Curtis and the other, anonymous, reviewer(s) for their contribution to the peer review of this work.</s></p><p xml:id="_Sckp29m"><s xml:id="_Dfm8jtt">Publisher's note Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</s></p><p xml:id="_QU3Ns6G"><s xml:id="_cV9KcYx">Springer Nature or its licensor (e.g. a society or other partner) holds exclusive rights to this article under a publishing agreement with the author(s) or other rightsholder(s); author self-archiving of the accepted manuscript version of this article is solely governed by the terms of such publishing agreement and applicable law.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_EhMwjeJ">How useful are digital health terms for outcomes research? An ISPOR special interest group report</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Burrell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jval.2022.04.1730</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Vc3AFFr">Value Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1469" to="1479" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Burrell, A. et al. How useful are digital health terms for outcomes research? An ISPOR special interest group report. Value Health 25, 1469-1479 (2022).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_YkZMTTu">P4 medicine: how systems medicine will transform the healthcare sector and society</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Flores</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Glusman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Brogaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Price</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2217/pme.13.57</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Y9qH8MY">Pers. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="565" to="576" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Flores, M., Glusman, G., Brogaard, K., Price, N. D. &amp; Hood, L. P4 medicine: how systems medicine will transform the healthcare sector and society. Pers. Med. 10, 565-576 (2013).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_VfHmWS7">The quadruple aim: care, health, cost and meaning in work</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sikka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Morath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Leape</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_hgchQKY">BMJ Qual. Saf</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="608" to="610" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sikka, R., Morath, J. M. &amp; Leape, L. The quadruple aim: care, health, cost and meaning in work. BMJ Qual. Saf. 24, 608-610 (2015).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_rF8xBM3">A scoping review of triage approaches for the referral of patients with suspected inflammatory arthritis, from primary to rheumatology care</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Biln</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Bansback</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Shojania</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Puil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Harrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00296-024-05575-8</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_A8PFttk">Rheumatol. Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2279" to="2292" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Biln, N. K., Bansback, N., Shojania, K., Puil, L. &amp; Harrison, M. A scoping review of triage approaches for the referral of patients with suspected inflammatory arthritis, from primary to rheumatology care. Rheumatol. Int. 44, 2279-2292 (2024).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_8jW33dY">Diagnostic accuracy of a mobile AI-based symptom checker and a web-based self-referral tool in rheumatology: multicenter randomized controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Knitza</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_bVFX3sM">J. Med. Internet Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">55542</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Knitza, J. et al. Diagnostic accuracy of a mobile AI-based symptom checker and a web-based self-referral tool in rheumatology: multicenter randomized controlled trial. J. Med. Internet Res. 26, e55542 (2024).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_aGV449X">Incorporating natural language processing to improve classification of axial spondyloarthritis using electronic health records</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_hnD2Kbq">Rheumatology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1059" to="1065" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Zhao, S. S. et al. Incorporating natural language processing to improve classification of axial spondyloarthritis using electronic health records. Rheumatology 59, 1059-1065 (2020).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_mSaehu4">Predicting a diagnosis of ankylosing spondylitis using primary care health records -a machine learning approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kennedy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_f5pRrs5">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">279076</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kennedy, J. et al. Predicting a diagnosis of ankylosing spondylitis using primary care health records -a machine learning approach. PLoS One 18, e0279076 (2023).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_3FWynnv">Digital rheumatology in the era of COVID-19: results of a national patient and physician survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kernder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/rmdopen-2020-001548</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_kxft5s7">RMD Open</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1548</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kernder, A. et al. Digital rheumatology in the era of COVID-19: results of a national patient and physician survey. RMD Open 7, e001548 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_whudG7D">Patient&apos;s perception of digital symptom assessment technologies in rheumatology: results from a multicentre study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Knitza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3389/fpubh.2022.844669</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_zTW9mQP">Front. Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">844669</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Knitza, J. et al. Patient&apos;s perception of digital symptom assessment technologies in rheumatology: results from a multicentre study. Front. Public Health 10, 844669 (2022).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_DmjcZhc">Are online symptoms checkers useful for patients with inflammatory arthritis?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Powley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mcilroy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Simons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Raza</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ttPwQbm">BMC Musculoskelet. Disord</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">362</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Powley, L., McIlroy, G., Simons, G. &amp; Raza, K. Are online symptoms checkers useful for patients with inflammatory arthritis? BMC Musculoskelet. Disord. 17, 362 (2016).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_cBn3JjK">The ability of rheumatologists blinded to prior workup to diagnose rheumatoid arthritis only by clinical assessment: a cross-sectional study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ehrenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pongratz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fleck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Hartung</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_s37G4DQ">Rheumatology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1592" to="1601" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ehrenstein, B., Pongratz, G., Fleck, M. &amp; Hartung, W. The ability of rheumatologists blinded to prior workup to diagnose rheumatoid arthritis only by clinical assessment: a cross-sectional study. Rheumatology 57, 1592-1601 (2018).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_SXRdTb8">Large language model-driven sentiment analysis for facilitating fibromyalgia diagnosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Venerito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Iannone</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_CzSf8Ab">RMD Open</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4367</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Venerito, V. &amp; Iannone, F. Large language model-driven sentiment analysis for facilitating fibromyalgia diagnosis. RMD Open 10, e004367 (2024).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_W6uTzZt">Comparison of physician and artificial intelligence-based symptom checker diagnostic accuracy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gräf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00296-022-05202-4</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_h7FGWzA">Rheumatol. Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2167" to="2176" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Gräf, M. et al. Comparison of physician and artificial intelligence-based symptom checker diagnostic accuracy. Rheumatol. Int. 42, 2167-2176 (2022).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_h5gBNxv">Diagnostic accuracy of a large language model in rheumatology: comparison of physician and ChatGPT-4</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Krusche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Callhoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Knitza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ruffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_VSZRB4s">Rheumatol. Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="303" to="306" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Krusche, M., Callhoff, J., Knitza, J. &amp; Ruffer, N. Diagnostic accuracy of a large language model in rheumatology: comparison of physician and ChatGPT-4. Rheumatol. Int. 2, 303-306 (2023).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_B5a8Zjv">eConsults&apos; impact on care access and wait times in rheumatology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Malcolm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/rhu.0000000000001825</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_xswD3Yc">J. Clin. Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="147" to="154" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Malcolm, E. J. et al. eConsults&apos; impact on care access and wait times in rheumatology. J. Clin. Rheumatol. 28, 147-154 (2022).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_dGnR4nF">Pre-appointment management of new patient referrals in rheumatology: a key strategy for improving health care delivery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Harrington</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Walsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_x6VVPkQ">Arthritis Rheum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="295" to="300" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Harrington, J. T. &amp; Walsh, M. B. Pre-appointment management of new patient referrals in rheumatology: a key strategy for improving health care delivery. Arthritis Rheum. 45, 295-300 (2001).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_gQGXBW5">Computer-assisted diagnosis of rheumatic disorders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Moens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Van Der Korst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0049-0172(91)90004-j</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_grdjheu">Semin. Arthritis Rheum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="156" to="169" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Moens, H. J. &amp; van der Korst, J. K. Computer-assisted diagnosis of rheumatic disorders. Semin. Arthritis Rheum. 21, 156-169 (1991).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_TaQGX26">Computer-based diagnostic expert systems in rheumatology: where do we stand in 2014?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Alder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1155/2014/672714</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_XyZndAH">Int. J. Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2014</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">672714</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Alder, H. et al. Computer-based diagnostic expert systems in rheumatology: where do we stand in 2014? Int. J. Rheumatol. 2014, 672714 (2014).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_PFCFxxy">Diagnostic accuracy of GPs when using an early-intervention decision support system: a high-fidelity simulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Kostopoulou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Porat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Corrigan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mahmoud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Delaney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3399/bjgp16x688417</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_KahW4Am">Br. J. Gen. Pract</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="201" to="e208" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kostopoulou, O., Porat, T., Corrigan, D., Mahmoud, S. &amp; Delaney, B. C. Diagnostic accuracy of GPs when using an early-intervention decision support system: a high-fidelity simulation. Br. J. Gen. Pract. 67, e201-e208 (2017).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_jMzAEp8">The impact of a diagnostic decision support system on the consultation: perceptions of GPs and patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Porat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Delaney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Kostopoulou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/s12911-017-0477-6</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_83Qd6aX">BMC Med. Inf. Decis. Mak</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">79</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Porat, T., Delaney, B. &amp; Kostopoulou, O. The impact of a diagnostic decision support system on the consultation: perceptions of GPs and patients. BMC Med. Inf. Decis. Mak. 17, 79 (2017).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_zJ9zTMq">Embedding and adapting over time Review article</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.64628/aaj.ena3gerf5</idno>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Embedding and adapting over time Review article</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_PAtbS8b">Can a decision support system accelerate rare disease diagnosis? Evaluating the potential impact of Ada DX in a retrospective study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ronicke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_SfEDCcG">Orphanet J. Rare Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">69</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ronicke, S. et al. Can a decision support system accelerate rare disease diagnosis? Evaluating the potential impact of Ada DX in a retrospective study. Orphanet J. Rare Dis. 14, 69 (2019).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_NtFCJVU">ISABEL: a web-based differential diagnostic aid for paediatrics: results from an initial performance evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ramnarayan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/adc.88.5.408</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_xR7QSRn">Arch. Dis. Child</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="408" to="413" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ramnarayan, P. et al. ISABEL: a web-based differential diagnostic aid for paediatrics: results from an initial performance evaluation. Arch. Dis. Child. 88, 408-413 (2003).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_VcbvJCr">FindZebra: a search engine for rare diseases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Dragusin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_WRvs22M">Int. J. Med. Inf</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="528" to="538" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Dragusin, R. et al. FindZebra: a search engine for rare diseases. Int. J. Med. Inf. 82, 528-538 (2013).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_3zbE8X9">Accuracy and usability of a diagnostic decision support system in the diagnosis of three representative rheumatic diseases: a randomized controlled trial among medical students</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Knitza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/s13075-022-02806-w</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_KBEGwee">Arthritis Res. Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">233</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Knitza, J. et al. Accuracy and usability of a diagnostic decision support system in the diagnosis of three representative rheumatic diseases: a randomized controlled trial among medical students. Arthritis Res. Ther. 23, 233 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_BVQVJ98">Large language models and rheumatology: a comparative evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Venerito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Puttaswamy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Iannone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_KYTzycw">Lancet Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="574" to="e578" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Venerito, V., Puttaswamy, D., Iannone, F. &amp; Gupta, L. Large language models and rheumatology: a comparative evaluation. Lancet Rheumatol. 5, e574-e578 (2023).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_JpGnn8h">Foundation models for generalist medical artificial intelligence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Moor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41586-023-05881-4</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_uVZPS78">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">616</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="259" to="265" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Moor, M. et al. Foundation models for generalist medical artificial intelligence. Nature 616, 259-265 (2023).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.48550/arXiv.2402.06341</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2402.06341" />
		<title level="m" xml:id="_Sb4p2Bu">RareBench: can LLMs serve as rare diseases specialists</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Preprint at</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Chen, X. et al. RareBench: can LLMs serve as rare diseases specialists? Preprint at arXiv https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2402.06341 (2024).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_puXDwuq">At-home blood self-sampling in rheumatology: a qualitative study with patients and health care professionals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Muehlensiepen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_yzxrFvJ">BMC Health Serv. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1470</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Muehlensiepen, F. et al. At-home blood self-sampling in rheumatology: a qualitative study with patients and health care professionals. BMC Health Serv. Res. 22, 1470 (2022).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_nVcEttX">Accuracy and tolerability of self-sampling of capillary blood for analysis of inflammation and autoantibodies in rheumatoid arthritis patients-results from a randomized controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Knitza</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_DmEsp4c">Arthritis Res. Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">125</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Knitza, J. et al. Accuracy and tolerability of self-sampling of capillary blood for analysis of inflammation and autoantibodies in rheumatoid arthritis patients-results from a randomized controlled trial. Arthritis Res. Ther. 24, 125 (2022).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_mKyJx4N">Direct access for patients to diagnostic testing and results using ehealth: systematic review on ehealth and diagnostics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Versluis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Schnoor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Chavannes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Talboom-Kamp</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_uQD5bmm">J. Med. Internet Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">29303</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Versluis, A., Schnoor, K., Chavannes, N. H. &amp; Talboom-Kamp, E. P. Direct access for patients to diagnostic testing and results using ehealth: systematic review on ehealth and diagnostics. J. Med. Internet Res. 24, e29303 (2022).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_E4DWfbP">Student-led clinics and ePROs to accelerate diagnosis and treatment of patients with axial spondyloarthritis: results from a prospective pilot study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Von Rohr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_KN6ywWC">Rheumatol. Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1905" to="1911" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">von Rohr, S. et al. Student-led clinics and ePROs to accelerate diagnosis and treatment of patients with axial spondyloarthritis: results from a prospective pilot study. Rheumatol. Int. 43, 1905-1911 (2023).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_FTjwh7u">Ultrasound joint examination by an automated system versus by a rheumatologist: from a patient perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Frederiksen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/s42358-022-00263-2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_QwrBQ69">Adv. Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">30</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Frederiksen, B. A. et al. Ultrasound joint examination by an automated system versus by a rheumatologist: from a patient perspective. Adv. Rheumatol. 62, 30 (2022).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_5k9Na3W">Detection and grading of radiographic hand osteoarthritis using an automated machine learning platform</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Caratsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_FgnZJkQ">ACR Open Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="388" to="395" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Caratsch, L. et al. Detection and grading of radiographic hand osteoarthritis using an automated machine learning platform. ACR Open Rheumatol. 6, 388-395 (2024).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_GSvyeD9">A deep learning system for quantitative assessment of microvascular abnormalities in nailfold capillary images</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Bharathi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_qajkxp7">Rheumatology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2325" to="2329" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bharathi, P. G. et al. A deep learning system for quantitative assessment of microvascular abnormalities in nailfold capillary images. Rheumatology 62, 2325-2329 (2023).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_mbk7TTn">Teleconsultation in rheumatology: a literature review and opinion paper</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Avouac</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_RDeqPr6">Semin. Arthritis Rheum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">152271</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Avouac, J. et al. Teleconsultation in rheumatology: a literature review and opinion paper. Semin. Arthritis Rheum. 63, 152271 (2023).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_zgcxT67">Asynchronous mHealth interventions in rheumatoid arthritis: systematic scoping review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Seppen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_dgdzmBF">JMIR mHealth uHealth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">19260</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Seppen, B. F. et al. Asynchronous mHealth interventions in rheumatoid arthritis: systematic scoping review. JMIR mHealth uHealth 8, e19260 (2020).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_nmHmTh8">A systematic review of commercial hybrid closed-loop automated insulin delivery systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Peacock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Frizelle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hussain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s13300-023-01394-5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_P5uHMfj">Diabetes Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="839" to="855" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Peacock, S., Frizelle, I. &amp; Hussain, S. A systematic review of commercial hybrid closed-loop automated insulin delivery systems. Diabetes Ther. 14, 839-855 (2023).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_8XR8xvq">A reconfigurable integrated smart device for real-time monitoring and synergistic treatment of rheumatoid arthritis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_BayfQVZ">Sci. Adv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">604</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Liu, Y. et al. A reconfigurable integrated smart device for real-time monitoring and synergistic treatment of rheumatoid arthritis. Sci. Adv. 10, eadj0604 (2024).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_z4pJvbY">EULAR recommendations for the implementation of self-management strategies in patients with inflammatory arthritis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Nikiphorou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_XVAZwXw">Ann. Rheum. Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1278" to="1285" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021. 2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nikiphorou, E. et al. 2021 EULAR recommendations for the implementation of self-management strategies in patients with inflammatory arthritis. Ann. Rheum. Dis. 80, 1278-1285 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_M788ed2">Unmet information needs of patients with rheumatic diseases: results of a cross-sectional online survey study in Germany</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_jMhJWrr">Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">7071</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Becker, C. et al. Unmet information needs of patients with rheumatic diseases: results of a cross-sectional online survey study in Germany. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health 19, 7071 (2022).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_rvXkRMK">Effectiveness of a novel digital patient education programme to support self-management of early rheumatoid arthritis: a randomised controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Knudsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/rheumatology/keae177</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_x2t9tEF">Rheumatology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2547" to="2556" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Knudsen, L. R. et al. Effectiveness of a novel digital patient education programme to support self-management of early rheumatoid arthritis: a randomised controlled trial. Rheumatology 63, 2547-2556 (2024).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_VsTFpr6">Mobile health usage, preferences, barriers, and ehealth literacy in rheumatology: patient survey study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Knitza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/19661</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_rmmbF9N">JMIR mHealth uHealth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">19661</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Knitza, J. et al. Mobile health usage, preferences, barriers, and ehealth literacy in rheumatology: patient survey study. JMIR mHealth uHealth 8, e19661 (2020).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_AW5VSRr">ChatGPT4&apos;s proficiency in addressing patients&apos; questions on systemic lupus erythematosus: a blinded comparative study with specialists</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/rheumatology/keae238</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_WzdX8TJ">Rheumatology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2450" to="2456" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Xu, D. et al. ChatGPT4&apos;s proficiency in addressing patients&apos; questions on systemic lupus erythematosus: a blinded comparative study with specialists. Rheumatology 63, 2450-2456 (2024).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_4Fdscbh">ChatSLE: consulting ChatGPT-4 for 100 frequently asked lupus questions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Haase</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_MsjZcQH">Lancet Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="196" to="e199" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Haase, I. et al. ChatSLE: consulting ChatGPT-4 for 100 frequently asked lupus questions. Lancet Rheumatol. 6, e196-e199 (2024).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_yuxQgz4">Navigating the European Union Artificial Intelligence Act for Healthcare</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Busch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_2t4C7j2">NPJ Digit. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">210</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Busch, F. et al. Navigating the European Union Artificial Intelligence Act for Healthcare. NPJ Digit. Med. 7, 210 (2024).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_tkKfrtW">Telerehabilitation consultations with a physiotherapist for chronic knee pain versus in-person consultations in Australia: the PEAK non-inferiority randomised controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hinman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_JptzmWV">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">403</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1267" to="1278" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hinman, R. S. et al. Telerehabilitation consultations with a physiotherapist for chronic knee pain versus in-person consultations in Australia: the PEAK non-inferiority randomised controlled trial. Lancet 403, 1267-1278 (2024).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_tP9X7WZ">App-based multidisciplinary back pain treatment versus combined physiotherapy plus online education: a randomized controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Toelle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Utpadel-Fischler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-K</forename><surname>Haas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Priebe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41746-019-0109-x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_38QQmtG">NPJ Digit. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">34</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Toelle, T. R., Utpadel-Fischler, D. A., Haas, K.-K. &amp; Priebe, J. A. App-based multidisciplinary back pain treatment versus combined physiotherapy plus online education: a randomized controlled trial. NPJ Digit. Med. 2, 34 (2019).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_AkwGtJz">The exercise-app Axia for axial spondyloarthritis enhances the home-based exercise frequency in axial spondyloarthritis patients -a cross-sectional survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P.-P</forename><surname>Strunz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ZhPFsM9">Rheumatol. Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1143" to="1154" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Strunz, P.-P. et al. The exercise-app Axia for axial spondyloarthritis enhances the home-based exercise frequency in axial spondyloarthritis patients -a cross-sectional survey. Rheumatol. Int. 44, 1143-1154 (2024).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_BXpY2Hz">Real-world usage of digital health applications (DiGA) in rheumatology: results from a German patient survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Labinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Raimondo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Schett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Knitza</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_hEbc8ak">Rheumatol. Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="713" to="719" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Labinsky, H., Gupta, L., Raimondo, M. G., Schett, G. &amp; Knitza, J. Real-world usage of digital health applications (DiGA) in rheumatology: results from a German patient survey. Rheumatol. Int. 43, 713-719 (2023).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_bNNbNBf">Self-guided digital behavioural therapy versus active control for fibromyalgia (PROSPER-FM): a phase 3, multicentre, randomised controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gendreau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_6e9Jwz6">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">404</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="364" to="374" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Gendreau, R. M. et al. Self-guided digital behavioural therapy versus active control for fibromyalgia (PROSPER-FM): a phase 3, multicentre, randomised controlled trial. Lancet 404, 364-374 (2024).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Em8DptT">The effect of virtual reality on cold pain sensitivity in patients with fibromyalgia and pain-free individuals: a randomized crossover study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W M</forename><surname>Christensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Almsborg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Vain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Vaegter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_cfGmGC7">Games Health J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="295" to="301" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Christensen, S. W. M., Almsborg, H., Vain, T. S. &amp; Vaegter, H. B. The effect of virtual reality on cold pain sensitivity in patients with fibromyalgia and pain-free individuals: a randomized crossover study. Games Health J. 12, 295-301 (2023).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_vpSZ8Cb">Digital health program improves quality of life in rheumatoid arthritis: a retrospective analysis of real-world data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dobies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Isberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Gudmundsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Oddsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.55563/clinexprheumatol/rng5n9</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_vHhFDXv">Clin. Exp. Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Dobies, B., White, A. J., Isberg, A., Gudmundsson, S. F. &amp; Oddsson, S. Digital health program improves quality of life in rheumatoid arthritis: a retrospective analysis of real-world data. Clin. Exp. Rheumatol. 42, 10-14 (2024).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qeW9M4b">Predicting response to tocilizumab monotherapy in rheumatoid arthritis: a real-world data analysis using machine learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Johansson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3899/jrheum.201626</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_qTmYp3m">J. Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1364" to="1370" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Johansson, F. D. et al. Predicting response to tocilizumab monotherapy in rheumatoid arthritis: a real-world data analysis using machine learning. J. Rheumatol. 48, 1364-1370 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_bcxE5SM">Toward individualized prediction of response to methotrexate in early rheumatoid arthritis: a pharmacogenomics-driven machine learning approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Myasoedova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/acr.24834</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_MX5Zqx8">Arthritis Care Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="879" to="888" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Myasoedova, E. et al. Toward individualized prediction of response to methotrexate in early rheumatoid arthritis: a pharmacogenomics-driven machine learning approach. Arthritis Care Res. 74, 879-888 (2022).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_WRnFWE9">AI can help to speed up drug discovery -but only if we give it the right data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Edavettal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Langmead</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Russell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_bPQPDdQ">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">621</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="467" to="470" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mock, M., Edavettal, S., Langmead, C. &amp; Russell, A. AI can help to speed up drug discovery -but only if we give it the right data. Nature 621, 467-470 (2023).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_m98G3kv">Use of medication reminders in patients with rheumatoid arthritis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bruera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Barbo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lopez-Olivo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ShgtGPM">Rheumatol. Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1543" to="1548" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bruera, S., Barbo, A. G. &amp; Lopez-Olivo, M. A. Use of medication reminders in patients with rheumatoid arthritis. Rheumatol. Int. 36, 1543-1548 (2016).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_eUghJrn">An AI-powered clinical decision support system to predict flares in rheumatoid arthritis: a pilot study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Labinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_BnDx8xc">Diagnostics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">148</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Labinsky, H. et al. An AI-powered clinical decision support system to predict flares in rheumatoid arthritis: a pilot study. Diagnostics 13, 148 (2023).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_M2QH89U">Vignette-based comparative analysis of ChatGPT and specialist treatment decisions for rheumatic patients: results of the Rheum2Guide study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hannah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ZtSX3wq">Rheumatol. Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2043" to="2053" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hannah, L. et al. Vignette-based comparative analysis of ChatGPT and specialist treatment decisions for rheumatic patients: results of the Rheum2Guide study. Rheumatol. Int. 44, 2043-2053 (2024).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_KfDqE3W">Telerheumatology: a technology appropriate for virtually all</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Kulcsar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Albert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ercolano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Mecchella</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_huBXgPt">Semin. Arthritis Rheum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="380" to="385" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kulcsar, Z., Albert, D., Ercolano, E. &amp; Mecchella, J. N. Telerheumatology: a technology appropriate for virtually all. Semin. Arthritis Rheum. 46, 380-385 (2016).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_SA8DYFD">Recommendation to implementation of remote patient monitoring in rheumatology: lessons learned and barriers to take</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hamann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Knitza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kuhn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Knevel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003363</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_xWRyESH">RMD Open</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3363</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hamann, P., Knitza, J., Kuhn, S. &amp; Knevel, R. Recommendation to implementation of remote patient monitoring in rheumatology: lessons learned and barriers to take. RMD Open 9, e003363 (2023).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_8xDMNmc">Investigating the influence of patient eligibility characteristics on the number of deferrable rheumatologist visits: planning for a patient-initiated follow-up (PIFU) strategy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Subdar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_D8JPd3G">J. Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="587" to="595" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Subdar, S. et al. Investigating the influence of patient eligibility characteristics on the number of deferrable rheumatologist visits: planning for a patient-initiated follow-up (PIFU) strategy. J. Rheumatol. 51, 587-595 (2024).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_q39M36E">Effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of combined asynchronous telemonitoring and patient-initiated care for spondyloarthritis: protocol for a pragmatic multicentre randomised controlled trial (TeleSpA Study)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hermans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Boonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Vonkeman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Van Tubergen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmjopen-2022-067445</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_fdTyMSa">BMJ Open</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">67445</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hermans, K., Boonen, A., Vonkeman, H. E. &amp; van Tubergen, A. Effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of combined asynchronous telemonitoring and patient-initiated care for spondyloarthritis: protocol for a pragmatic multicentre randomised controlled trial (TeleSpA Study). BMJ Open 13, e067445 (2023).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_kQQKy4q">Remote monitoring in rheumatology: seeing the right patient at the right time</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Knitza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41584-023-01008-1</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_CgGyazC">Nat. Rev. Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="680" to="681" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Chan, A. &amp; Knitza, J. Remote monitoring in rheumatology: seeing the right patient at the right time. Nat. Rev. Rheumatol. 19, 680-681 (2023).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_GyWeVec">Facilitators and barriers to adhere to monitoring disease activity with ePROs: a focus group study in patients with inflammatory arthritis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Seppen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wiegel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Nurmohamed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Bos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ter Wee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_QvSeQmQ">Rheumatol. Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="677" to="685" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Seppen, B. F., Wiegel, J., Nurmohamed, M. T., Bos, W. H. &amp; ter Wee, M. M. Facilitators and barriers to adhere to monitoring disease activity with ePROs: a focus group study in patients with inflammatory arthritis. Rheumatol. Int. 43, 677-685 (2023).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_T7s8N6F">Impact of assessing patient-reported outcomes with mobile apps on patient-provider interaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_nykjSSv">RMD Open</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1566</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Shaw, Y. et al. Impact of assessing patient-reported outcomes with mobile apps on patient-provider interaction. RMD Open 7, e001566 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_F6eGVUx">Usage, and barriers of electronic patient-reported outcomes among German rheumatologists: survey study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Krusche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/18117</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Fkj9fYA">JMIR mHealth uHealth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">18117</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Krusche, M. et al. Usage, and barriers of electronic patient-reported outcomes among German rheumatologists: survey study. JMIR mHealth uHealth 8, e18117 (2020).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_hzKRkkd">Smartphone-assisted patient-initiated care versus usual care in patients with rheumatoid arthritis and low disease activity: a randomized controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Seppen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/art.42292</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_7WrrKH5">Arthritis Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1737" to="1745" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Seppen, B. et al. Smartphone-assisted patient-initiated care versus usual care in patients with rheumatoid arthritis and low disease activity: a randomized controlled trial. Arthritis Rheumatol. 74, 1737-1745 (2022).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_HxJ2tyn">Self-monitoring combined with patient-initiated care in RA patients with low disease activity: cost-effectiveness analysis of an RCT</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Seppen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_t4K6672">Rheumatology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3366" to="3372" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Seppen, B. F. et al. Self-monitoring combined with patient-initiated care in RA patients with low disease activity: cost-effectiveness analysis of an RCT. Rheumatology 62, 3366-3372 (2023).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_YdJhyyK">Dorsal finger fold recognition by convolutional neural networks for the detection and monitoring of joint swelling in patients with rheumatoid arthritis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hügle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_dQGpG4X">Digital Biomark</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hügle, T. et al. Dorsal finger fold recognition by convolutional neural networks for the detection and monitoring of joint swelling in patients with rheumatoid arthritis. Digital Biomark. 6, 31-35 (2022).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_MJM6t7x">Handgrip strength measured by a dynamometer connected to a smartphone: a new applied health technology solution for the self-assessment of rheumatoid arthritis disease activity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Espinoza</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_SNCzWvC">Rheumatology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="897" to="901" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Espinoza, F. et al. Handgrip strength measured by a dynamometer connected to a smartphone: a new applied health technology solution for the self-assessment of rheumatoid arthritis disease activity. Rheumatology 55, 897-901 (2016).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_UXA2Nvh">DeepNAPSI multi-reader nail psoriasis prediction using deep learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Folle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_exb4Pf5">Sci. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5329</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Folle, L. et al. DeepNAPSI multi-reader nail psoriasis prediction using deep learning. Sci. Rep. 13, 5329 (2023).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_5gjWPz4">Comparison of shoulder range of motion quantified with mobile phone video-based skeletal tracking and 3D motion capture -preliminary study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Van Den Hoorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lavaill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Cutbush</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kerr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_dXxhBkq">Sensors</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">534</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">van den Hoorn, W., Lavaill, M., Cutbush, K., Gupta, A. &amp; Kerr, G. Comparison of shoulder range of motion quantified with mobile phone video-based skeletal tracking and 3D motion capture -preliminary study. Sensors 24, 534 (2024).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_6NuDZUu">Wearable activity tracker study exploring rheumatoid arthritis patients&apos; disease activity using patient-reported outcome measures, clinical measures, and biometric sensor data (the Wear study)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Stradford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_YbmMuEv">Contemp. Clin. Trials Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101272</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Stradford, L. et al. Wearable activity tracker study exploring rheumatoid arthritis patients&apos; disease activity using patient-reported outcome measures, clinical measures, and biometric sensor data (the Wear study). Contemp. Clin. Trials Commun. 38, 101272 (2024).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_zDEqBM6">Physical activity assessment with wearable devices in rheumatic diseases: a systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ocagli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_xMmGbFS">Rheumatology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1031" to="1046" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ocagli, H. et al. Physical activity assessment with wearable devices in rheumatic diseases: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Rheumatology 62, 1031-1046 (2023).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_gwgqaJF">Wearables for measuring the physical activity and sedentary behavior of patients with axial spondyloarthritis: systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Soulard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Carlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Knitza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Vuillerme</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_szBe2nS">JMIR mHealth uHealth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">34734</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Soulard, J., Carlin, T., Knitza, J. &amp; Vuillerme, N. Wearables for measuring the physical activity and sedentary behavior of patients with axial spondyloarthritis: systematic review. JMIR mHealth uHealth 10, e34734 (2022).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Y8SNHuH">Detection of flares by decrease in physical activity, collected using wearable activity trackers in rheumatoid arthritis or axial spondyloarthritis: an application of machine learning analyses in rheumatology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gossec</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_J8neYtG">Arthritis Care Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1336" to="1343" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Gossec, L. et al. Detection of flares by decrease in physical activity, collected using wearable activity trackers in rheumatoid arthritis or axial spondyloarthritis: an application of machine learning analyses in rheumatology. Arthritis Care Res. 71, 1336-1343 (2019).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b77">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_aAv7H2w">Reliability, validity and responsiveness of physical activity monitors in patients with inflammatory myopathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Rockette-Wagner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_f8gVDAy">Rheumatology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5713" to="5723" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rockette-Wagner, B. et al. Reliability, validity and responsiveness of physical activity monitors in patients with inflammatory myopathy. Rheumatology 60, 5713-5723 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b78">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_5VT4Rhc">Twenty-four hour physical activity, sedentary behaviour and sleep profiles in adults living with rheumatoid arthritis: a cross-sectional latent class analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Feehan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_K4jTFUh">JASSB</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Feehan, L., Xie, H., Lu, N. &amp; Li, L. C. Twenty-four hour physical activity, sedentary behaviour and sleep profiles in adults living with rheumatoid arthritis: a cross-sectional latent class analysis. JASSB 3, 10 (2024).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b79">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_aWHuJxM">Assessment of a dried blood spot C-reactive protein method to identify disease flares in rheumatoid arthritis patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>D'cruz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_4drc9eE">Sci. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21089</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Review article</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">D&apos;Cruz, L. G. et al. Assessment of a dried blood spot C-reactive protein method to identify disease flares in rheumatoid arthritis patients. Sci. Rep. 10, 21089 (2020). Review article</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b80">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_BgPnsCJ">RNA identification of PRIME cells predicting rheumatoid arthritis flares</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Orange</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_S2ESrST">N. Engl. J. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">383</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="218" to="228" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Orange, D. E. et al. RNA identification of PRIME cells predicting rheumatoid arthritis flares. N. Engl. J. Med. 383, 218-228 (2020).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b81">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_HAxuKZD">A wireless patch for the monitoring of C-reactive protein in sweat</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41551-023-01059-5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_8fAaHHP">Nat. Biomed. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1293" to="1306" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Tu, J. et al. A wireless patch for the monitoring of C-reactive protein in sweat. Nat. Biomed. Eng. 7, 1293-1306 (2023).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b82">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_A75nByX">Salivary uric acid: a noninvasive wonder for clinicians?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jaiswal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_qt7BbwU">Cureus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">19649</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Jaiswal, A. et al. Salivary uric acid: a noninvasive wonder for clinicians? Cureus 13, e19649 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b83">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_n6Bpgxj">Tele-health followup strategy for tight control of disease activity in rheumatoid arthritis: results of a randomized controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>De Thurah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/acr.23280</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_fpBFbZa">Arthritis Care Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="353" to="360" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">de Thurah, A. et al. Tele-health followup strategy for tight control of disease activity in rheumatoid arthritis: results of a randomized controlled trial. Arthritis Care Res. 70, 353-360 (2018).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b84">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_w4uaqRf">Cost-effectiveness of a telehealth intervention in rheumatoid arthritis: economic evaluation of the Telehealth in RA (TeRA) randomized controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Skovsgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kruse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hjollund</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Maribo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>De Thurah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/03009742.2021.2008604</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_npzH8JA">Scand. J. Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="118" to="128" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Skovsgaard, C. V., Kruse, M., Hjollund, N., Maribo, T. &amp; de Thurah, A. Cost-effectiveness of a telehealth intervention in rheumatoid arthritis: economic evaluation of the Telehealth in RA (TeRA) randomized controlled trial. Scand. J. Rheumatol. 52, 118-128 (2023).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b85">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_7JsqUTb">Evaluation of a hybrid telehealth care pathway for patients with axial spondyloarthritis including self-sampling at home: results of a longitudinal proof-ofconcept mixed-methods study (TeleSpactive)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Labinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_xfdaCA9">Rheumatol. Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1133" to="1142" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Labinsky, H. et al. Evaluation of a hybrid telehealth care pathway for patients with axial spondyloarthritis including self-sampling at home: results of a longitudinal proof-of- concept mixed-methods study (TeleSpactive). Rheumatol. Int. 44, 1133-1142 (2024).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b86">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_QjswhYv">Follow-up of patients with axial spondyloarthritis in specialist health care with remote monitoring and self-monitoring compared with regular face-to-face follow-up visits (the ReMonit Study): protocol for a randomized, controlled open-label noninferiority trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Berg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_nqamrzW">JMIR Res. Protoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">52872</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Berg, I. J. et al. Follow-up of patients with axial spondyloarthritis in specialist health care with remote monitoring and self-monitoring compared with regular face-to-face follow-up visits (the ReMonit Study): protocol for a randomized, controlled open-label noninferiority trial. JMIR Res. Protoc. 12, e52872 (2023).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b87">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_jfyNBqg">Effectiveness of a telemonitoring intensive strategy in early rheumatoid arthritis: comparison with the conventional management approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Salaffi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/s12891-016-1002-2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_99TPAEW">BMC Musculoskelet. Disord</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">146</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Salaffi, F. et al. Effectiveness of a telemonitoring intensive strategy in early rheumatoid arthritis: comparison with the conventional management approach. BMC Musculoskelet. Disord. 17, 146 (2016).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b88">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_yBPSqGJ">Using electronic visits (E-visits) to achieve goal serum urate levels in patients with gout in a rheumatology practice: a pilot study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Yokose</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_EyGPw9z">Semin. Arthritis Rheum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1382" to="1386" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Yokose, C. et al. Using electronic visits (E-visits) to achieve goal serum urate levels in patients with gout in a rheumatology practice: a pilot study. Semin. Arthritis Rheum. 50, 1382-1386 (2020).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b89">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_dUYTUc6">Evaluation of supported self-management in gout (GoutSMART): a randomised controlled feasibility trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Riches</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Alexander</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kuske</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Krause</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s2665-9913(22)00062-5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_zvYmnux">Lancet Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="320" to="e328" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Riches, P. L., Alexander, D., Hauser, B., Kuske, B. &amp; Krause, A. Evaluation of supported self-management in gout (GoutSMART): a randomised controlled feasibility trial. Lancet Rheumatol. 4, e320-e328 (2022).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b90">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_gkm9g2B">TELERA -asynchronous TELEmedicine for patients with rheumatoid arthritis: study protocol for a prospective, multi-center, randomized controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mucke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3389/fmed.2021.791715</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_9YgpgEA">Front. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2590</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mucke, J. et al. TELERA -asynchronous TELEmedicine for patients with rheumatoid arthritis: study protocol for a prospective, multi-center, randomized controlled trial. Front. Med. 8, 2590 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b91">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ddwR9cJ">The physical exam and telehealth: between past and future</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Restrepo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Henriquez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Torre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Graber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1515/dx-2023-0154</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_mwMzh2S">Diagnosis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="3" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Restrepo, J. A., Henriquez, R., Torre, D. &amp; Graber, M. L. The physical exam and telehealth: between past and future. Diagnosis 11, 1-3 (2024).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b92">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_uG3advr">Telemedicine in rheumatology: high specificity and sensitivity of follow-up virtual video consultations during COVID-19 pandemic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Piga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/rheumatology/keab632</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_cNvFycZ">Rheumatology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1795" to="1801" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Piga, M. et al. Telemedicine in rheumatology: high specificity and sensitivity of follow-up virtual video consultations during COVID-19 pandemic. Rheumatology 61, 1795-1801 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b93">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Qb2weRV">Clinically relevant differences in spinal mobility related to daytime performance in patients with axial spondyloarthritis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kiefer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_rGqtY4U">RMD Open</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3733</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kiefer, D. et al. Clinically relevant differences in spinal mobility related to daytime performance in patients with axial spondyloarthritis. RMD Open 10, e003733 (2024).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b94">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_QP2ruDq">Validation of a new objective index to measure spinal mobility: the University of Cordoba Ankylosing Spondylitis Metrology Index (UCOASMI)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Garrido-Castro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00296-013-2917-7</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_4kxfz22">Rheumatol. Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="401" to="406" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Garrido-Castro, J. L. et al. Validation of a new objective index to measure spinal mobility: the University of Cordoba Ankylosing Spondylitis Metrology Index (UCOASMI). Rheumatol. Int. 34, 401-406 (2014).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b95">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_NJHyn6C">The impact of Nuance DAX ambient listening AI documentation: a cohort study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Haberle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_twxBPmr">J. Am. Med. Inform. Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="975" to="979" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Haberle, T. et al. The impact of Nuance DAX ambient listening AI documentation: a cohort study. J. Am. Med. Inform. Assoc. 31, 975-979 (2024).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b96">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_8TtVchj">Ambient artificial intelligence scribes to alleviate the burden of clinical documentation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tierney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1056/cat.23.0404</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1056/CAT.23.0404" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_fa8bVZN">NEJM Catal. Innov. Care Deliv</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Tierney, A. A. et al. Ambient artificial intelligence scribes to alleviate the burden of clinical documentation. NEJM Catal. Innov. Care Deliv. https://doi.org/10.1056/ CAT.23.0404 (2024).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b97">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_BTF7rbh">Decentralised, patient-centric, site-less, virtual, and digital clinical trials? From confusion to consensus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Santa-Ana-Tellez</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_KzWj3wt">Drug Discov. Today</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">103520</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Santa-Ana-Tellez, Y. et al. Decentralised, patient-centric, site-less, virtual, and digital clinical trials? From confusion to consensus. Drug Discov. Today 28, 103520 (2023).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b98">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_56ztufU">Digital crowdsourcing: unleashing its power in rheumatology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Krusche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Burmester</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Knitza</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ZdzXrkb">Ann. Rheum. Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1139" to="1140" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Krusche, M., Burmester, G. R. &amp; Knitza, J. Digital crowdsourcing: unleashing its power in rheumatology. Ann. Rheum. Dis. 79, 1139-1140 (2020).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b99">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_sSxmwFY">Listening to patients, for the patients: the COVAD Study-Vision, organizational structure, and challenges</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Joshi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/1756-185x.15161</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_vAcZ2HJ">Int. J. Rheum. Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">100</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Joshi, M. et al. Listening to patients, for the patients: the COVAD Study-Vision, organizational structure, and challenges. Int. J. Rheum. Dis. 27, e15161 (2024). 100</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b100">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_GsufF8p">Long-term safety of COVID vaccination in individuals with idiopathic inflammatory myopathies: results from the COVAD study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Doskaliuk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_u9ZqGWR">Rheumatol. Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Doskaliuk, B. et al. Long-term safety of COVID vaccination in individuals with idiopathic inflammatory myopathies: results from the COVAD study. Rheumatol. Int. 43, 1651-1664 (2023). 101</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b101">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qYNptsH">Agreement between local and central anti-synthetase antibodies detection: results from the Classification Criteria of Anti-Synthetase Syndrome project biobank</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Loganathan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.55563/clinexprheumatol/s14zq8</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_pSrHFua">Clin. Exp. Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">102</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Loganathan, A. et al. Agreement between local and central anti-synthetase antibodies detection: results from the Classification Criteria of Anti-Synthetase Syndrome project biobank. Clin. Exp. Rheumatol. 42, 277-287 (2024). 102</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b102">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Z8qRRwE">Integrating large language models in medicine: a study of Claude 2&apos;s performance in MDAAT scoring for idiopathic inflammatory myopathies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Venerito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/rheumatology/keae233</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_QQwcpGX">Rheumatology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">103</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Venerito, V. et al. Integrating large language models in medicine: a study of Claude 2&apos;s performance in MDAAT scoring for idiopathic inflammatory myopathies. Rheumatology 63, e292-e293 (2024). 103</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b103">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_bc9Vzsb">Train to target -how we might learn in the future</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Krusche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Knitza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G.-R</forename><surname>Burmester</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jbspin.2020.105126</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Fypz37J">Jt Bone Spine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">104</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Krusche, M., Knitza, J. &amp; Burmester, G.-R. Train to target -how we might learn in the future. Jt Bone Spine 88, 105126 (2020). 104</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b104">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_KDQ22Rc">Online academic community in the Asia-Pacific countries: the paragon of a metamorphic world</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Gaur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/1756-185x.14196</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_y5dDBph">Int. J. Rheum. Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">105</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Gaur, P. S. et al. Online academic community in the Asia-Pacific countries: the paragon of a metamorphic world. Int. J. Rheum. Dis. 24, 1229-1234 (2021). 105</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b105">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qZahDha">RheumMadness over two years: engaging participants in active learning and connecting early trainees to the rheumatology community</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/acr2.11661</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_gwnFN6w">ACR Open Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">106</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">He, L. et al. RheumMadness over two years: engaging participants in active learning and connecting early trainees to the rheumatology community. ACR Open Rheumatol. 6, 356-364 (2024). 106</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b106">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_MeMaQUh">A virtual reality-based app to educate health care professionals and medical students about inflammatory arthritis: feasibility study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Klemm</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_FbmtGRg">JMIR Serious Games</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">107</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Klemm, P. et al. A virtual reality-based app to educate health care professionals and medical students about inflammatory arthritis: feasibility study. JMIR Serious Games 9, e23835 (2021). 107</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b107">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_YghkU9B">Scottish rheumatology sonography course: five-year experience of delivering a mentorship-model rheumatology ultrasound training programme accredited by the consortium for the accreditation of sonographic education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ciechomska</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ANCE3NM">Scott. Med. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">108</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ciechomska, A. et al. Scottish rheumatology sonography course: five-year experience of delivering a mentorship-model rheumatology ultrasound training programme accredited by the consortium for the accreditation of sonographic education. Scott. Med. J. 66, 51-57 (2021). 108</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b108">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_xJ5mPSQ">Barriers and facilitators to utilizing digital health technologies by healthcare professionals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Borges Do Nascimento</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_fJhbXQR">NPJ Digit. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">109</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Borges do Nascimento, I. J. et al. Barriers and facilitators to utilizing digital health technologies by healthcare professionals. NPJ Digit. Med. 6, 161 (2023). 109</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b109">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ScresU7">Digital navigators to implement smartphone and digital tools in care</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wisniewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Torous</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/acps.13149</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_qaXtmdD">Acta Psychiatr. Scand</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">110</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Wisniewski, H. &amp; Torous, J. Digital navigators to implement smartphone and digital tools in care. Acta Psychiatr. Scand. 141, 350-355 (2020). 110</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b110">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_XWDWSxD">Digital health transition in rheumatology: a qualitative study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mühlensiepen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3390/ijerph18052636</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ZKQEund">Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">111</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mühlensiepen, F. et al. Digital health transition in rheumatology: a qualitative study. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health 18, 2636 (2021). 111</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b111">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_dGxbVGc">EULAR points to consider for remote care in rheumatic and musculoskeletal diseases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>De Thurah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_79jCKRN">Ann. Rheum. Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">112</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022. 2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">de Thurah, A. et al. 2022 EULAR points to consider for remote care in rheumatic and musculoskeletal diseases. Ann. Rheum. Dis. 81, 1065-1071 (2022). 112</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b112">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_yxBzgKn">Prompt engineering: the next big skill in rheumatology research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Venerito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lalwani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Del Vescovo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Iannone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/1756-185x.15157</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_5wEDGJk">Int. J. Rheum. Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">113</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Venerito, V., Lalwani, D., Del Vescovo, S., Iannone, F. &amp; Gupta, L. Prompt engineering: the next big skill in rheumatology research. Int. J. Rheum. Dis. 27, e15157 (2024). 113</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b113">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_fwmPMAU">Effectiveness of remote care interventions: a systematic review informing the 2022 EULAR points to consider for remote care in rheumatic and musculoskeletal diseases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Marques</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ZEpyayF">RMD Open</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">114</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Marques, A. et al. Effectiveness of remote care interventions: a systematic review informing the 2022 EULAR points to consider for remote care in rheumatic and musculoskeletal diseases. RMD Open 8, e002290 (2022). 114</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b114">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_4M7aexR">Digital health applications: toward a lifecycle and pay-for-performance approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Knitza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Muehlensiepen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kuhn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_exZcYXc">Mayo Clin. Proc. Digital Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">115</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Knitza, J., Muehlensiepen, F. &amp; Kuhn, S. Digital health applications: toward a lifecycle and pay-for-performance approach. Mayo Clin. Proc. Digital Health 1, 393-394 (2023). 115</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b115">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_9ENYcJq">Rethinking the patient: using Burden of Treatment Theory to understand the changing dynamics of illness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>May</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_tFRawDm">BMC Health Serv. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">116</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">May, C. R. et al. Rethinking the patient: using Burden of Treatment Theory to understand the changing dynamics of illness. BMC Health Serv. Res. 14, 281 (2014). 116</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b116">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_jv8xqUK">Task Shifting: Rational Redistribution of Tasks Among Health Workforce Teams: Global Recommendations and Guidelines (WHO</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lorenzini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Arbelaez Ossa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Shaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Elger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_waCCb6k">Bioethics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">118</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007. 2023</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>World Health Organization</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Artificial intelligence and the doctor-patient relationship expanding the paradigm of shared decision making</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">World Health Organization. Task Shifting: Rational Redistribution of Tasks Among Health Workforce Teams: Global Recommendations and Guidelines (WHO, 2007). 117. Lorenzini, G., Arbelaez Ossa, L., Shaw, D. M. &amp; Elger, B. S. Artificial intelligence and the doctor-patient relationship expanding the paradigm of shared decision making. Bioethics 37, 424-429 (2023). 118</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b117">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_WuwXRfc">Ethical considerations of digital health technology in older adult care</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Finco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Gresham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Huisingh-Scheetz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_uGy8gME">Lancet Healthy Longev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">119</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Finco, M. G., Mir, N., Gresham, G. &amp; Huisingh-Scheetz, M. Ethical considerations of digital health technology in older adult care. Lancet Healthy Longev. 5, e12-e13 (2024). 119</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b118">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_4HnnrGv">Almanac -retrieval-augmented language models for clinical medicine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zakka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1056/aioa2300068</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1056/aioa2300068(2024).120" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_XkebQrF">NEJM AI</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Zakka, C. et al. Almanac -retrieval-augmented language models for clinical medicine. NEJM AI https://doi.org/10.1056/aioa2300068 (2024). 120</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b119">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_nWjqgbr">A future role for health applications of large language models depends on regulators enforcing safety standards</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Freyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wiest</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Kather</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gilbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_y5FTfyA">Lancet Digit. Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">121</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Freyer, O., Wiest, I. C., Kather, J. N. &amp; Gilbert, S. A future role for health applications of large language models depends on regulators enforcing safety standards. Lancet Digit. Health 6, e662-e672 (2024). 121</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b120">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_z7sQmzZ">Local large language models for privacy-preserving accelerated review of historic echocardiogram reports</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vaid</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_kGTY2KN">J. Am. Med. Inf. Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">122</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Vaid, A. et al. Local large language models for privacy-preserving accelerated review of historic echocardiogram reports. J. Am. Med. Inf. Assoc. 31, 2097-2102 (2024). 122</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b121">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_jBCyuYJ">Organizational issues in the implementation and adoption of health information technology innovations: an interpretative review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Cresswell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sheikh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_bMkx4ks">Int. J. Med. Inf</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">123</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Cresswell, K. &amp; Sheikh, A. Organizational issues in the implementation and adoption of health information technology innovations: an interpretative review. Int. J. Med. Inf. 82, e73-e86 (2013). 123</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b122">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_xzR7Qr7">One year of digital health applications (DiGA) in Germanyrheumatologists&apos; perspectives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Richter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_SFETUcn">Front. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">124</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Richter, J. G. et al. One year of digital health applications (DiGA) in Germany - rheumatologists&apos; perspectives. Front. Med. 9, 1000668 (2022). 124</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b123">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_JJaSrfZ">The model for assessment of telemedicine (MAST): a scoping review of empirical studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kidholm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Clemensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Caffery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_SRJnQxh">J. Telemed. Telecare</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">125</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kidholm, K., Clemensen, J., Caffery, L. J. &amp; Smith, A. C. The model for assessment of telemedicine (MAST): a scoping review of empirical studies. J. Telemed. Telecare 23, 803-813 (2017). 125</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b124">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_pyDbD26">A holistic framework to improve the uptake and impact of eHealth technologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E W C</forename><surname>Van Gemert-Pijnen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ufkyurt">J. Med. Internet Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">126</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">van Gemert-Pijnen, J. E. W. C. et al. A holistic framework to improve the uptake and impact of eHealth technologies. J. Med. Internet Res. 13, e111 (2011). 126</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b125">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_2Apc9Hf">The updated Consolidated Framework for Implementation Research based on user feedback</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Damschroder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Reardon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A O</forename><surname>Widerquist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lowery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/s13012-022-01245-0</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_S8Sn4qg">Implement. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">127</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Damschroder, L. J., Reardon, C. M., Widerquist, M. A. O. &amp; Lowery, J. The updated Consolidated Framework for Implementation Research based on user feedback. Implement. Sci. 17, 75 (2022). 127</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b126">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_azPRdyN">Beyond adoption: a new framework for theorizing and evaluating nonadoption, abandonment, and challenges to the scale-up, spread, and sustainability of health and care technologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Greenhalgh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/jmir.8775</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_bJgSb9B">J. Med. Internet Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">128</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Greenhalgh, T. et al. Beyond adoption: a new framework for theorizing and evaluating nonadoption, abandonment, and challenges to the scale-up, spread, and sustainability of health and care technologies. J. Med. Internet Res. 19, e8775 (2017). 128</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b127">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Muh3Vvw">Key challenges in the development and implementation of telehealth projects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Joseph</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>West</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Shickle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Keen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Clamp</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Zc2WdsC">J. Telemed. Telecare</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">129</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Joseph, V., West, R. M., Shickle, D., Keen, J. &amp; Clamp, S. Key challenges in the development and implementation of telehealth projects. J. Telemed. Telecare 17, 71-77 (2011). 129</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b128">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_A4r7gMc">Where do models for change management, improvement and implementation meet? A systematic review of the applications of change management models in healthcare</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Harrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_gjkgkw4">J. Healthc. Leadersh</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">130</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Harrison, R. et al. Where do models for change management, improvement and implementation meet? A systematic review of the applications of change management models in healthcare. J. Healthc. Leadersh. 13, 85-108 (2021). 130</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b129">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_3WjpFf4">Digital transformation of an academic hospital department: a case study on strategic planning using the balanced scorecard</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hügle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Grek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_vXP5R2b">PLoS Digit. Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">131</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hügle, T. &amp; Grek, V. Digital transformation of an academic hospital department: a case study on strategic planning using the balanced scorecard. PLoS Digit. Health 2, e0000385 (2023). 131</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b130">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_fnVxZ4U">Participatory design in telehealth research: practical case examples</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Clemensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1357633X241262820</idno>
		<ptr target=").132" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_5ETtkSY">J. Telemed. Telecare</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Clemensen, J. et al. Participatory design in telehealth research: practical case examples. J. Telemed. Telecare https://doi.org/10.1177/1357633X241262820 (2024). 132</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b131">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ZtMWvsE">Position paper of the commission on digital rheumatology of the German Society of Rheumatology: tasks, targets and perspectives for a modern rheumatology [German</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Knitza</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ZWCuBSG">Z. Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">133</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Knitza, J. et al. Position paper of the commission on digital rheumatology of the German Society of Rheumatology: tasks, targets and perspectives for a modern rheumatology [German]. Z. Rheumatol. 79, 562-569 (2020). 133</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b132">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_nTpHkUp">Best practices for virtual care: a consensus statement from the Canadian Rheumatology Association</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E H</forename><surname>Barber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3899/jrheum.211017</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_GXb6FrU">J. Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">134</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Barber, C. E. H. et al. Best practices for virtual care: a consensus statement from the Canadian Rheumatology Association. J. Rheumatol. 49, 408-418 (2022). 134</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b133">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_WbYnXjV">Telehealth in rheumatology: the 2021 Arab League of Rheumatology best practice guidelines</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ziade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_RzkAb6N">Rheumatol. Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="379" to="390" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ziade, N. et al. Telehealth in rheumatology: the 2021 Arab League of Rheumatology best practice guidelines. Rheumatol. Int. 42, 379-390 (2022).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b134">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_hkT9p37">research support from Fresenius Kabi, Eli Lilly and Pfizer, and honoraria and consulting fees from</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gaia</forename><surname>Review Article Chugai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Galapagos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Gsk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Janssen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Lilly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Medac</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Novartis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Pfizer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sobi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ucb</forename><surname>Rheumaakademie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Vila</forename><surname>Health</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Werfen</forename><forename type="middle">T H</forename><surname>Roche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Novartis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Eli</forename><surname>Bms</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Lilly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ucb</forename><surname>Janssen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Werfen</forename><forename type="middle">T H</forename><surname>Pfizer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://sites.duke.edu/rheummadness/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_2xNfHpr">holds patents with and is a board member of Atreon and Vtuls</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer Nature Limited</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>L.G. declares no competing interests Related links Ambience</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Review article Chugai, GAIA, Galapagos, GSK, Janssen, Lilly, Medac, Novartis, Pfizer, Sobi, Rheumaakademie, UCB, Vila Health and Werfen. T.H. declares research support from Fresenius Kabi, Eli Lilly and Pfizer, and honoraria and consulting fees from Roche, Novartis, BMS, Eli Lilly, Janssen, UCB, Pfizer and Werfen. T.H. holds patents with and is a board member of Atreon and Vtuls. L.G. declares no competing interests. Related links Ambience: https://www.ambiencehealthcare.com/ ChatGPT-4: https://chatgpt.com/ Digital Rheumatology Network: https://digitalrheumatology.org/ Elicit: https://elicit.com/ EU Artificial Intelligence Act: https://artificialintelligenceact.eu/the-act/ FindZebra: https://www.findzebra.com/ Isabel: https://symptomchecker.isabelhealthcare.com/ Llama: https://www.llama.com/ Nuance DAX: https://www.nuance.com/healthcare/dragon-ai-clinical-solutions/ dax-copilot.html REDCap: https://www.project-redcap.org/ Rheumatology digital playbook: https://transform.england.nhs. uk/key-tools-and-info/digital-playbooks/rheumatology-digital-playbook/ RheumMadness: https://sites.duke.edu/rheummadness/ © Springer Nature Limited 2024</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
