<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_s32XZWd">Evaluation of Digital Mental Health Technologies in the United States: A Systematic Literature Review and Framework Synthesis</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Julianna</forename><surname>Catania</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>1</label> Costello Medical Boston US</note>
								<orgName type="institution">Costello Medical Boston</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>US</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Steph</forename><surname>Beaver</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Rakshitha</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kamath</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>1</label> Costello Medical Boston US</note>
								<orgName type="institution">Costello Medical Boston</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>US</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MSL</roleName><forename type="first">Emma</forename><surname>Worthington</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>3</label> Costello Medical Cambridge GB</note>
								<orgName type="institution">Costello Medical Cambridge</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>GB</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Minyi</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>4</label> Otsuka Pharmaceutical Development &amp; Commercialization Inc . Princeton US</note>
								<orgName type="institution">Otsuka Pharmaceutical Development &amp; Commercialization Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Princeton</settlement>
									<country>US</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">Hema</forename><surname>Gandhi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>4</label> Otsuka Pharmaceutical Development &amp; Commercialization Inc . Princeton US</note>
								<orgName type="institution">Otsuka Pharmaceutical Development &amp; Commercialization Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Princeton</settlement>
									<country>US</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">Heidi</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Waters</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>4</label> Otsuka Pharmaceutical Development &amp; Commercialization Inc . Princeton US</note>
								<orgName type="institution">Otsuka Pharmaceutical Development &amp; Commercialization Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Princeton</settlement>
									<country>US</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Malone</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>5</label> Department of Pharmacotherapy Skaggs College of Pharmacy University of Utah Salt Lake City US</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pharmacotherapy Skaggs College of Pharmacy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Utah Salt Lake City</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>US</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mph</forename><forename type="middle">;</forename><surname>Steph Beaver</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>2</label> Costello Medical London GB</note>
								<orgName type="institution">Costello Medical London</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>GB</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Department of Pharmacotherapy Skaggs College of Pharmacy University of Utah Room 4922 30 S 2000 East Salt Lake City US</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pharmacotherapy Skaggs College of Pharmacy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Utah</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Room 4922 30 S 2000</addrLine>
									<settlement>East Salt Lake City</settlement>
									<country>US</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_dSqSr98">Evaluation of Digital Mental Health Technologies in the United States: A Systematic Literature Review and Framework Synthesis</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">A0A110AED504C51F535C816E876C8B7B</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.2196/preprints.57401</idno>
					<note type="submission">Submitted to: JMIR Mental Health on: February 15, 2024</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T09:21+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_HC6t6hU"><p xml:id="_B4P5uRm"><s xml:id="_PNeVrKx">Background: Digital mental health technologies (DMHT) have the potential to enhance mental healthcare delivery.</s><s xml:id="_7eeFHZ8">However, there is little information on how DMHT are evaluated and what factors influence their use.</s></p><p xml:id="_TEZVUfK"><s xml:id="_xUQjKYB">Objective: A systematic literature review was conducted to understand how DMHT are valued in the United States (US) from user, payer, and employer perspectives.</s></p><p xml:id="_MRhzMAW"><s xml:id="_cCBWVB6">Methods: Articles published after 2017 were identified from MEDLINE, Embase, PsycInfo, Cochrane Library, the Health Technology Assessment Database, and digital and mental health congresses.</s><s xml:id="_U96TnWX">Each article was evaluated by two independent reviewers to identify US studies reporting on factors considered in the evaluation of DMHT targeting mental health, Alzheimer's, epilepsy, autism spectrum disorder, or attention deficit hyperactive disorder.</s><s xml:id="_h73pgE7">Study quality was assessed using the Critical Appraisal Skills Program Qualitative and Cohort Studies checklists.</s><s xml:id="_fhKyQAx">Studies were coded and indexed using the American Psychiatric Association's Mental Health App Evaluation Framework to extract and synthesize relevant information.</s></p><p xml:id="_AKzCXzc"><s xml:id="_pykCmmM">Results: Of 4,353 articles screened, data from 26 unique studies from patient, caregiver, and healthcare provider perspectives were included.</s><s xml:id="_ZWSWsHR">Engagement style was the most reported theme (n=23 studies), with users valuing DMHT usability, particularly alignment with therapeutic goals through features including anxiety management tools.</s><s xml:id="_sdS98mc">Key barriers to DMHT use included limited internet access, poor technical literacy, and privacy concerns.</s><s xml:id="_TCYcNDG">Novel findings included discreetness of DMHT to avoid stigma.</s></p><p xml:id="_yMZghnk"><s xml:id="_YnAyMJD">Conclusions: Usability, cost, accessibility, technical considerations, and alignment with therapeutic goals are important to users, although DMHT valuation varies across individuals.</s><s xml:id="_XjjrXPV">DMHT apps should be developed and selected with specific user needs in mind.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="10" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="11" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="12" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="13" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="14" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="15" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="16" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="17" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="18" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="19" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="20" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="21" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="22" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="23" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="24" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="25" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="26" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="27" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="28" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="29" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="30" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="31" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="32" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="33" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="34" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="35" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="36" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="37" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="38" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
		<surface n="39" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="841.89"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_vc5VsZa">Table of Contents</head><note type="other" xml:id="_V72xa52">Original</note><p xml:id="_FNwjFzp"><s xml:id="_Gmw5mzJ">Only make the preprint title and abstract visible.</s></p><p xml:id="_y7YmZmj"><s xml:id="_BTc4XY8">No, I do not wish to publish my submitted manuscript as a preprint.</s><s xml:id="_8gyBS7K">2) If accepted for publication in a JMIR journal, would you like the PDF to be visible to the public?</s></p><p xml:id="_GcsJJaq"><s xml:id="_WSruFzJ">Yes, please make my accepted manuscript PDF available to anyone at any time (Recommended).</s></p><p xml:id="_3kZJDTg"><s xml:id="_77evyrZ">Yes, but please make my accepted manuscript PDF available only to logged-in users; I understand that the title and abstract will remain v Yes, but only make the title and abstract visible (see Important note, above).</s><s xml:id="_wM7tUse">I understand that if I later pay to participate in &lt;a href="http</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Nabr4K3">Original Manuscript</head><p xml:id="_vpqJCfk"><s xml:id="_2XG5sBX">and indexed using the American Psychiatric Association's Mental Health App Evaluation</s></p><p xml:id="_6ACz8XR"><s xml:id="_GcnbZBq">Framework to extract and synthesize relevant information, and novel themes were added iteratively as identified.</s></p><p xml:id="_8WCBMku"><s xml:id="_z8fNWVp">RESULTS: Of 4,353 articles screened, data from 26 unique studies from patient, caregiver, and healthcare provider perspectives were included.</s><s xml:id="_YFagYnA">Engagement style was the most reported theme (n=23 studies), with users valuing DMHT usability, particularly alignment with therapeutic goals through features including anxiety Nonetheless, many healthcare providers (HCPs) use MH apps in clinical practice.</s></p><p xml:id="_UUhahva"><s xml:id="_kYe2t4A">Up to 83% of behavioral health providers in a small study covering the greater Boston area reported using apps as part of their clinical care, particularly mindfulness apps for patient anxiety management <ref type="bibr">[5]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_3UvqUvs">As many DMHT are currently widely used in clinical practice without undergoing any formal assessment for quality or relevance, understanding how DMHT should be assessed based on factors impacting their value from the perspective of key stakeholders, such as patients, caregivers, providers, payers, and employers, could improve selection of DMHT for use by patients, thereby increasing care quality and outcomes for those seeking MH support.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_MAXvVKT">Objective</head><p xml:id="_apKZr7F"><s xml:id="_eVRHD8C">To address identified gaps, a systematic literature review (SLR) was conducted  <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S1-S5</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_c6QqKCb">Searches were limited to studies performed in the US and to those published from 2017 onwards.</s></p><p xml:id="_SxhEMHB"><s xml:id="_V37QjAV">Manual hand-searches of grey literature, namely, the bibliographies of relevant SLRs identified from the electronic database searches and key conference proceedings <ref type="bibr">(2019)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2020)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2021)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2022)</ref>, were performed to identify additional studies of relevance (Table <ref type="table">S6</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_6smA9yE">The FDA website was also searched to identify factors involved in the FDA's appraisal of relevant MH apps, which could supplement the factors identified in this SLR (Table <ref type="table">S7</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_ntKfeVj">Study Selection</head><p xml:id="_jjhA9zh"><s xml:id="_7PyaKVT">Studies were included in the SLR if they met pre-specified criteria defined using the SPIDER (Sample, Phenomenon of Interest, Design, Evaluation, Research type) framework, which is appropriate for mixed-methods research questions.</s><s xml:id="_QHvpYnG">Eligible studies were published in the English language, set in the US, and reported quantitative or qualitative outcomes relating to factors considered in the evaluation of DMHT.</s><s xml:id="_8VZuKz9">Only studies published in 2017 or later were included because of the rapidly evolving research area.</s><s xml:id="_fDbXmpQ">Eligible studies reported on MH, Alzheimer's, epilepsy, ASD, or ADHD from user, payer, or employer perspectives (Table <ref type="table">S8</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_FrxQyK6">While the primary focus of the SLR was MH, neurological conditions Value of DMHT Systematic Review 21 June 2024</s></p><p xml:id="_hb5bcSj"><s xml:id="_eGvmYpS">were also of interest because their pathologies, symptoms, and treatment strategies can overlap with those of mental illnesses.</s><s xml:id="_QNszvCq">Alzheimer's, epilepsy, ASD, and ADHD were selected because they are highly researched and represent diverse types of neurological conditions.</s></p><p xml:id="_ESRKtpf"><s xml:id="_HPEM5wF">The titles and abstracts of records were assessed for inclusion against these eligibility criteria by two independent reviewers and discrepancies were resolved by consensus, with arbitration by a third reviewer if necessary.</s><s xml:id="_gwAyEUh">Full texts of potentially relevant articles were acquired and screened using the same methodology.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_nNhcujE">Study Prioritization</head><p xml:id="_mEyM46K"><s xml:id="_qTVK2hp">Due to the large volume of evidence identified, further eligibility criteria were applied to prioritize primary research on DMHT valuation factors that were theoretical.</s><s xml:id="_Uj3eSvU">In line with the thematic framework synthesis objective, theoretical valuation factors were defined as user or DMHT attributes that impact interaction with or perception of DMHT; therefore, studies only reporting efficacy outcomes, such as mental illness symptom improvement, were deprioritized for full-text review.</s><s xml:id="_3Yzjzff">Secondary research was also deprioritized for full-text review.</s><s xml:id="_zrhqFWk">Studies that reviewed a select app against a framework and studies only reporting outcomes specific to a select app were deprioritized for data extraction.</s><s xml:id="_GpMzH3v">For example, a study reporting the usability of a specific app's features would have been deprioritized, while a study reporting what types of features increase MH app usability in general would not.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_NTFcmg5">Data Extraction</head><p xml:id="_Ywywuy4"><s xml:id="_Vh7fCpf">All relevant data were extracted into a pre-specified Microsoft Excel grid and a quality assessment was performed for each study.</s><s xml:id="_YpagSbf">Value of DMHT Systematic Review</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="21" xml:id="_3uz89yM">June 2024</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Bq6Qjza">Framework Synthesis</head><p xml:id="_UwRsmR6"><s xml:id="_nG2hyyx">A framework synthesis approach was undertaken to synthesize qualitative and quantitative data identified from the SLR.</s><s xml:id="_FUeDHy6">In line with the "best fit" framework synthesis approach, data were indexed deductively against an existing framework where possible, and novel themes were added inductively as needed <ref type="bibr">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr">10]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_XRb3G54">The American Psychiatric Association's (APA) Mental Health App Evaluation framework was considered the most appropriate framework to address the research objectives of this SLR because its key valuation themes:</s></p><p xml:id="_n3AR4aT"><s xml:id="_spEdx7R">were developed using psychiatrist and patient input, are broadly shared by other evaluation frameworks, are widely acknowledged in the literature, and have been described as durable and adaptable <ref type="bibr">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr">[13]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_nq8sFtf"><s xml:id="_6rB7aqM">The APA model follows a hierarchical and chronological order whereby the evaluator moves through the framework using prompting questions (e.g., "Does the app work offline?").</s><s xml:id="_YCRKm2R">For this SLR, these questions were either thematically grouped into subthemes or left as prompting questions, as appropriate.</s><s xml:id="_DxsUhfV">The framework was therefore ultimately adapted into three levels: themes, subthemes, and more granular valuation criteria (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_7X7GEXN">It should be emphasized that this SLR did not aim to formally develop an updated framework to be used in practice by HCPs and their patients, but rather was used to form a theoretical basis for understanding DMHT valuation factors, for which novel themes were expected to emerge.</s></p><p xml:id="_Zbk58Ds"><s xml:id="_R7cB9xh">A data-based convergent approach was used to synthesize quantitative and qualitative data <ref type="bibr">[14]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_RAmPwCr">Data were initially indexed deductively against the prespecified themes within the data collection instrument, then further synthesized within Docear, a mind-map software used to organize and connect data and concepts.</s><s xml:id="_84fmJv5">Indexing was performed by one reviewer and checked by a second, independent reviewer.</s><s xml:id="_f3RpSXw">New themes and subthemes that emerged from the literature through inductive coding were added post-hoc to the thematic framework, with all extracted data then considered against both the prespecified and novel themes.</s><s xml:id="_FcTpCa4">Evidence identified for each theme was synthesized narratively, taking into consideration the context and design of each study.</s><s xml:id="_ZWvCbaE">and criterion Subtheme Criteria [study reference]</s></p><p xml:id="_KUCZd7V"><s xml:id="_RsPRHNT">Engagement Style Short-term usability Ease of use <ref type="bibr">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr">[15]</ref><ref type="bibr">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr">[17]</ref> Available engagement styles <ref type="bibr">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr">16,</ref><ref type="bibr">[18]</ref><ref type="bibr">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr">[23]</ref><ref type="bibr">[24]</ref> Long-term usability Alignment of app with needs and priorities <ref type="bibr">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr">16,</ref><ref type="bibr">[18]</ref><ref type="bibr">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr">[23]</ref><ref type="bibr">[24]</ref><ref type="bibr">[25]</ref><ref type="bibr">[26]</ref><ref type="bibr">[27]</ref><ref type="bibr">[28]</ref><ref type="bibr">[29]</ref><ref type="bibr">[30]</ref><ref type="bibr">[31]</ref><ref type="bibr">[32]</ref><ref type="bibr">[33]</ref><ref type="bibr">[34]</ref><ref type="bibr">[35]</ref><ref type="bibr">[36]</ref> Forgot or unmotivated to use <ref type="bibr">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr">15,</ref><ref type="bibr">18,</ref><ref type="bibr">19]</ref> Customizability No further stratification <ref type="bibr">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr">17,</ref><ref type="bibr">19,</ref><ref type="bibr">20,</ref><ref type="bibr">22,</ref><ref type="bibr">26,</ref><ref type="bibr">28]</ref> Background and Accessibility</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_PTwc2As">Technical</head><p xml:id="_ExkXphN"><s xml:id="_QZfx9eM">Offline functionality <ref type="bibr">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr">18,</ref><ref type="bibr">21,</ref><ref type="bibr">32,</ref><ref type="bibr">37,</ref><ref type="bibr">38]</ref> Compatibility with different operating systems</s></p><p xml:id="_M5MeWCd"><s xml:id="_4Mpg4vr">Accessibility <ref type="bibr">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr">15,</ref><ref type="bibr">17,</ref><ref type="bibr">[26]</ref><ref type="bibr">[27]</ref><ref type="bibr">[28]</ref><ref type="bibr">32,</ref><ref type="bibr">35,</ref><ref type="bibr">38</ref>] Business model Funding sources/conflicts of interest Costs Additional/hidden costs [18,33] Willingness to pay [15-17,34] Insurance restrictions [22] Cost saving compared with professional care [27] No further stratification [15,16,33,38] Medical claims Specific medical claims Trustworthiness of source Stability Frequency of software updates [17,18] Privacy and Security No specific subtheme a No further stratification [16,18,30] Data collection and storage Ability to opt-out of data collection or delete data Data storage location Security associated with collection, use, and/or transmission of sensitive data (including personal health information) [5,27,28,32,38] Privacy policy Transparency and accessibility of privacy policy [16,17,35] Declaration of data use and purpose [16] Data sharing with third parties [15] Systems to respond to potential harms or safety concerns Personal health information Description of use of personal health information [16] Personal image and stigma [5,15,27,39] Security measures Security systems used [17,21,39] Clinical Foundation Impressions of use Accuracy and relevancy of app content [15,33] Alignment in app appearance and its claimed purpose User feedback Evidence of specific benefit from user feedback or user research studies [17,38] Validation of app usability and feasibility Clinical validity Supporting sources or references for use cases of the app [16,17]</s></p><p xml:id="_upgnDsk"><s xml:id="_m9H3asB">Evidence of specific benefit <ref type="bibr">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr">17,</ref><ref type="bibr">30,</ref><ref type="bibr">38]</ref> Evidence of effectiveness/efficacy <ref type="bibr">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr">18,</ref><ref type="bibr">28]</ref> Clarity in functional scope Therapeutic Goal</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_BaYR3n5">Clinically actionable</head><p xml:id="_ZfseKeP"><s xml:id="_RVNppEU">Positive change or skill acquisition <ref type="bibr">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr">16,</ref><ref type="bibr">19,</ref><ref type="bibr">21,</ref><ref type="bibr">26,</ref><ref type="bibr">30,</ref><ref type="bibr">31,</ref><ref type="bibr">33,</ref><ref type="bibr">38]</ref> Ease of sharing and interpretation of data <ref type="bibr">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr">21,</ref><ref type="bibr">33,</ref><ref type="bibr">38</ref>] Therapeutic alliance Possibility for collaboration with an HCP <ref type="bibr">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr">16,</ref><ref type="bibr">23,</ref><ref type="bibr">24,</ref><ref type="bibr">30,</ref><ref type="bibr">38]</ref> Value of DMHT Systematic Review 21 June 2024</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_ukmjZHC">Subtheme Criteria [study reference]</head><p xml:id="_nyZuudB"><s xml:id="_GgYQgXj">Therapeutic alliance between patient and HCP <ref type="bibr">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr">33]</ref> Data ownership, access, and export</s></p><p xml:id="_wsbyZ3n"><s xml:id="_fUdvnH3">User ownership of data Opportunity for sharing of data with electronic medical records and other data tools (Apple HealthKit ® , Fitbit™) Opportunity for use with a provider and ability to export or transfer data Footnotes: Subthemes and criteria in grey were included in the American Psychiatric Association's framework but were not reported on by studies included in this SLR.</s><s xml:id="_zJYnVzk">Criteria in bold were novel findings that emerged from this SLR.</s><s xml:id="_GFW68sF">Abbreviations: HCP, healthcare provider; SLR, systematic literature review.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_drQu8Gz">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_4FXvUNd">Included Studies</head><p xml:id="_nNZsGQp"><s xml:id="_n9ZK4NG">A total of 4,974 records were retrieved from the electronic databases.</s><s xml:id="_a2whUPa">Of the 3,374 unique records identified following deduplication across the databases, 2,891 were excluded based on eligibility criteria and an additional 456 were deprioritized because they were not directly related to the topic of interest for this SLR.</s><s xml:id="_pgfyQRs">Excluded and deprioritized full texts are listed in Table <ref type="table">S9</ref> and Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S10</ref>, respectively.</s><s xml:id="_Dz8sxmn">Therefore, 27 articles were included from electronic database searches.</s><s xml:id="_H83sWS7">Additionally, one article reporting on the same study as an alreadyincluded conference abstract was identified during supporting targeted searches and included as a supplementary record, resulting in a total of 28 articles reporting on 26 unique studies (Figure <ref type="figure">S1</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_JBNg4K4">No relevant FDA appraisals were identified in the supplementary search.</s></p><p xml:id="_pjKW5Hk"><s xml:id="_UbhnfEH">Of the included studies, eight were quantitative, twelve qualitative, and six used mixed-methods.</s><s xml:id="_rmgkZbP">Five studies assessed prospective cohorts and twenty-two utilized a cross-sectional approach, including one study that contained both a prospective cohort and a cross-sectional cohort <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">(Table 2)</ref>   To examine veterans' attitudes toward smartphone apps and to assess whether openness toward this technology varies by age or rurality Semistructured interviews informed by the State of the Art Access Model Cummings 2019 [33] Crosssectional, qualitative Parents and grandparents with children or grandchildren (caregivers) enrolled in a public health insurance program who received ≥2 months of ADHD treatment at four safety-net clinics (N=37) Administrators at the same clinics (N=41) To examine stakeholder perspectives regarding whether mHealth tools can improve MH treatment for lowincome youth with ADHD in safety net settings; and what functions would improve treatment Focus groups (caregivers) and interviews (HCPs and staff), both semistructured and including open-ended questions and targeted probes Dinkel 2021 [38] Crosssectional, qualitative Adult patients (≥19 years) with a current or prior diagnosis of depression, recruited during medical visits from two integrated primary care clinics (N=17) HCPs and staff at the same clinics (N=15) To explore patient and cliniclevel perceptions of the use of depression self-management apps within an integrated primary care setting Semistructured focus groups; semistructured interviews Forma 2022 [34] Crosssectional, quantitative Caregivers of patients with BD, MDD, or schizophrenia who believed their patients had adherence issues to secondgeneration oral atypical antipsychotic medication (N=184) To assess caregivers' preferences and willingness to pay for digital (ingestible sensor pill, medication containers with electronic monitoring, mobile apps, smart pill dispensers) and non-digital (medication diary, simple pill organizer) tools Custom discrete choice experiment survey Hoffman 2019 [5] Prospective interventiona l, mixedmethods HCPs (N=24) in a routine primary care behavioral health setting who reported their own and patients' (N not reported) MH app utilization and feedback; patient conditions included anxiety, stress, depression, and substance use To test the feasibility of using mHealth apps to augment integrated primary care services; solicit feedback from patients and providers to guide implementation; and develop an MH app toolkit for systemwide dissemination Custom survey Huberty 2022 [26] Crosssectional (current Calm users) and prospective interventiona l (nonusers of Calm, HCPs), qualitative General users b : cancer patients/survivors with smartphones, some of whom were current subscribers of Calm, a meditation app (N=17) HCPs, staff, and not-for-profit partners in cancer care with smartphones (N=10) To develop a mobile meditation app prototype specifically designed for cancer patients/survivors Custom surveys; focus groups Kern 2018 [27] Crosssectional, quantitative General users b : students from a midwestern university with smartphones (N=721) To investigate the potential usefulness of MH apps and attitudes toward using them Custom survey Knapp 2021 [21] Prospective cohort, qualitative Clinical staff members who provide behavioral health care for children and adolescents with conditions including ADHD and depression at a large community service organization in a midwestern To learn about considerations and perspectives of community behavioral HCPs on incorporating digital tools into their clinical care for children and adolescents Focus groups Value of DMHT Systematic Review 21 June 2024 Study Design a Perspective/Population a Objective(s) Data Collection Method(s) a state (N=37) Kornfield 2022 [19] Prospective cohort, qualitative Users: participants with at least moderate levels of depression or anxiety symptoms on the PHQ-9 or GAD-7 questionnaires, but without serious mental illnesses (e.g., BD, schizophrenia), who were not receiving formal care, recruited upon completing free online MH self-screening surveys hosted by Mental Health America (N=28) To investigate how digital technologies can engage young adults in self-managing their MH outside the formal care system Online asynchronous discussion; synchronous online design workshop Lipschitz 2019 [28] Crosssectional, quantitative Users: veterans enrolled in care at the VA Boston Healthcare System diagnosed with an anxiety disorder (including OCD), unipolar depressive disorder, or PTSD who had at least one encounter in the local primary care clinic (N=149) To assess patients' interest in mHealth interventions for MH; to identify whether provider endorsement would impact interest; to determine reasons for non-use of mHealth interventions for MH; and to identify what mHealth content or features are of most interest to patients Custom survey Mata-Greve 2021 [29] Crosssectional, mixedmethods General users b : essential workers during COVID-19 or workers who were unemployed/furloughed due to COVID-19, recruited from an online research platform (N=1,987) To document psychological stress; to explore DMHT use in response to COVID-19-related stress; to explore the usability and user burden of DMHT; to explore which aspects and features of DMHT were seen as necessary for managing stress during a pandemic by having participants design their own ideal DMHT Survey combining custom and validated measures (System Usability Scale, Use Burden Scale) Melcher 2020 [16] Crosssectional, mixedmethods General users b : college students aged 18-25 years, recruited through social media and word-of-mouth (N=100) To examine why college students show poor engagement with MH apps and how apps may be adapted to suit this population Custom survey; interviews Schueller 2018 [17] Crosssectional, mixedmethods General users b : smartphone owners, recruited from a research registry (N=827) To understand where users search for MH apps, what aspects of MH apps they find appealing, and what factors influence their decisions to use MH apps Custom survey; focus group interviews Schueller 2021 [30] To determine user preferences among the several privacy protection methods used in current mHealth apps and the reasons behind those preferences Custom survey; interview Footnotes: a Only information relevant to this SLR are reported in this table.</s><s xml:id="_BSwWUwD">b General users are participants who were not necessarily diagnosed with indications of interest.</s><s xml:id="_4J88xMg">Abbreviations: ADHD, attention deficit hyperactivity disorder; ASD, autism spectrum disorder; BD, bipolar disorder; DMHT, digital mental health technologies; GAD, general anxiety disorder; HCP, health care provider; MDD, major depressive disorder; MH, mental health; mHealth, mobile health; OCD, obsessive-compulsive disorder; PHQ, patient health questionnaire; PTSD, post-traumatic stress disorder; US, United States; VA, Veterans Affairs.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_7Qwjjht">Thematic Analysis</head><p xml:id="_ha228Nx"><s xml:id="_sVEFsdT">Evidence was identified for all five themes included in the APA framework: engagement style (n=23 studies), background and accessibility (n=16), privacy and security (n=13), therapeutic goal (n=12), and clinical foundation (n=8).</s><s xml:id="_DGU6gKW">Five novel criteria were identified and added to the framework post-hoc, one each under engagement style (forgetting or feeling unmotivated to use DMHT) and privacy and security (personal image/stigma) and three under background and accessibility (willingness-to-pay, insurance restrictions, and cost saving compared with professional care).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_kpmR3ky">Theme One: Engagement Style</head><p xml:id="_v6f6A2H"><s xml:id="_Wgr7bQ9">Engagement style was the most reported theme, with evidence identified from 23 studies.</s><s xml:id="_ZT22vW7">Engagement style encompasses how and why users do or do not interact with DMHT.</s><s xml:id="_qw3vh76">The long-term usability subtheme was reported by 22 studies, short-term usability by 12 studies, and customizability by 7 studies.</s></p><p xml:id="_BxH5a8B"><s xml:id="_6QKPrg3">Findings from short-and long-term usability subthemes were highly interconnected.</s></p><p xml:id="_Q5CVswT"><s xml:id="_5m9BKAX">Four studies reported that ease of use promoted short-term DMHT engagement.</s></p><p xml:id="_g9m5vzQ"><s xml:id="_pC87XKm">In <ref type="bibr">Schueller et al. 2018, 89</ref>.6% of a general population of smartphone users reported ease of use for MH apps as "important" or "very important," and users qualitatively reported dislike of "overwhelming," difficult-to-navigate apps <ref type="bibr">[17]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_bxXY8qS"><s xml:id="_wNBAE26">Users also valued apps that were "simplistic" [16], fit into their daily schedules, June 2024 and were available when needed, such as during acute symptom experiences <ref type="bibr">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr">15]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_tyzqAG2">Select supporting qualitative data are presented Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">3</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_RvbdDWj">Alignment of app with needs and priorities: peer support and chat functions "Incorporating lived experiences into a [smartphone] app and organize the [intervention] process to address lived experience because that's what it's all about."</head><p xml:id="_KhDwX4B"><s xml:id="_a9uNTSX">Community MH center peer support specialist, Storm 2021 [35] "So maybe the bipolar individual also has access to the same app and then so they talk to each other… That way when I get home, I know ahead of time, it was an okay day today... Or if it was not a good day o.k., so I know that I need to come in a little more reserved."</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_RhgXx7y">Spouse of an individual with BD, Casarez 2019 [20]</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_F87YZjk">Forgot or unmotivated to use "For someone who may be severely depressed, or someone who needs help, [writing messages] is almost like hard to do. Because if they're having a hard time motivating or encouraging themselves, they might not feel like this is something they could do."</head><p xml:id="_kPYCRyK"><s xml:id="_F7NvWRD">User with anxiety or depression, Kornfield 2022 <ref type="bibr">[19]</ref> "I notice a good number of patients mentions they did not continue using in home.</s><s xml:id="_uN3t6jB"><ref type="bibr">[…]</ref> Maybe because this area is still new for patients?"</s></p><p xml:id="_GymwMW8"><s xml:id="_3VJEzCM">Value of DMHT Systematic Review 21 June 2024 Subtheme Criteria: Findings Key Quotes Routine behavioral health care staff, Hoffman 2019 [5] "[My son] has one of those crazy little phones that you can do everything with.</s><s xml:id="_ruc9sgz">I just don't have an interest."</s><s xml:id="_bBbsXez">Female veteran, age 57, Connolly 2018 [15] Background and Accessibility Technical considerations Accessibility: mobility barriers "They can't figure out why my hands shake so bad...so trying to use a smartphone [is frustrating]...</s><s xml:id="_2E8QkHh">I don't have a whole lot of feeling in my hands."</s><s xml:id="_Wt7sKkF">Male veteran, age 40, Connolly 2018 [15] Accessibility: technical literacy "I haven't gotten acclimated to a smartphone yet...the technology is kind of difficult to navigate."</s><s xml:id="_mzCY6xA">Male veteran, age 66, Connolly 2018 [15] Offline functionality: internet and mobile data access as a barrier to use "[A young person's smartphone] is normally one of the first things that get taken away if they do have a bad day.</s><s xml:id="_C4HqUtU">So, this is the thing you can use when you're having a bad day to calm down, but then mom and dad won't let you use it because you had a bad day."</s><s xml:id="_eggyh68">Pediatric behavioral health clinician, Knapp 2021 [21] "There have been times I think people have suggested, 'Check this app out, check that app out,' and for the most part I don't think I have… I do only have so much data."</s><s xml:id="_jSwaRzW">Patient receiving psychiatric care, Carpenter-Song 2018 [37] Costs Willingness to pay "If they don't have the free trial and they want money, I'm not even gonna look at it.</s><s xml:id="_rChvmGU">I'm not gonna pay for something before I've gotten the chance to see if it's gonna work for me or not."</s><s xml:id="_MyaYYvK">General user, smartphone owner, Schueller 2018 [17] "...they gave the option to pay $50.00 a year.</s><s xml:id="_4Pkrz2x">And I did that, because I liked the idea of what they were trying to do."</s><s xml:id="_k9UTqDV">General user, smartphone owner, Schueller 2018 [17] Privacy and Security Data collection and storage Security associated with collection, use, and/or transmission of sensitive data (including personal health information) "I'm worried about my data."</s><s xml:id="_swFd2Wj">Patient in routine behavioral health care, Hoffman 2019 [5] "Any apps that terms and conditions you're forfeiting your information as soon as you click to that to anything so and I'm not worried about getting identity theft."</s><s xml:id="_2TEeDG8">Patient with current or prior depression diagnosis, Dinkel 2021 [38] Privacy policy Transparency and accessibility of privacy policy "To use a smartphone app with a client I would want to make sure it's secure before going any further."</s><s xml:id="_AqqE7fd">Community MH center peer support specialist, Storm 2021 [35] Personal health information Personal image and stigma "I worry about my virtual image.</s><s xml:id="_TWxnqhU">I'd feel more comfortable using an app from CHA [Cambridge Health Alliance] that is protected in the same way my EMR [electronic medical record] is protected."</s><s xml:id="_rNMgtrh">Patient in routine behavioral health care, Hoffman 2019 [5] Security measures Security systems used "The app doesn't read as something like, My Personal Diary...it reads as something that you might just pass by if you don't know what its intention is, which can be good for teenagers who are afraid of people looking into their stuff."</s><s xml:id="_s5ujsDQ">Evidence of specific benefit: increased usage if supported by research, academic institution, or reputable professional society "I would trust an app supported by my university more than a random app I found online."</s><s xml:id="_xFkcdzE">General user, college student, Melcher 2020 [16] "I think it would be helpful, too, to have like the American Psychiatric Association or something, one of those, the licensure bodies or whatever-if they had official recommendations or backing."</s><s xml:id="_enf6h7T">General user, smartphone owner, Schueller 2018 [17] Footnotes: Bolded criteria are novel criteria identified by this SLR.</s><s xml:id="_prtdEK7">Abbreviations: ADHD, attention deficit hyperactivity disorder; ASD, autism spectrum disorder; BD, bipolar disorder; HCP, healthcare provider; MH, mental health; SLR, systematic literature review.</s></p><p xml:id="_HGDD6b3"><s xml:id="_XVHFjBv">The latter finding reflects the long-term usability subtheme, as users valued DMHT features that aligned with their needs and priorities.</s><s xml:id="_Cc4sPY3">Across nine studies, quantitative and qualitative findings demonstrated high interest in anxiety management features like relaxation tools, breathing exercises, and mindfulness/ meditation activities, and ten studies identified interest in mood, symptom, or sleep tracking (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">3;</ref> <ref type="table" target="#tab_9">Table 4</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_gWspKq8">While most studies focused on MH, patients with epilepsy also reported high interest in features to record seizure dates and types <ref type="bibr">[25]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_zhz9FGw">Importantly, users in two studies emphasized the need for developers to tailor DMHT to the needs and priorities of the target population (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">3</ref>) <ref type="bibr">[19,</ref><ref type="bibr">26]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_KDgdtkz">Relatedly, mixed attitudes were reported towards positive affirmations and words of encouragement, with many users expressing interest but others emphasizing the value of a human component to DMHT or cautioning against blanket encouragement and automated messages that could feel insincere <ref type="bibr">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr">19,</ref><ref type="bibr">32]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_fJtfJS9">Both patients and caregivers expressed interest in psychoeducational content that aligned with their needs and priorities.</s><s xml:id="_gfwRb6N">When surveyed, more than 60% of veterans with anxiety or major depressive disorder (MDD), patients with epilepsy, young adults with psychosis, and essential and furloughed workers during the COVID-19 pandemic expressed interest in relevant psychoeducational content <ref type="bibr">[24,</ref><ref type="bibr">25,</ref><ref type="bibr">28,</ref><ref type="bibr">29]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_zZP2CbS">In contrast, only 4% of college students in another study reported using an MH app for information about MH, although an MH diagnosis was not required for study participation <ref type="bibr">[27]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_2cvANSf"><s xml:id="_3SpQnd5">Caregivers of young adults with psychosis, caregivers of children with ADHD, and spouses/partners of people with bipolar disorder (BD) were all interested in information related to caring for the individual with the given disorder, such as information on psychological and pharmacological treatments, symptoms and symptom changes, and the MH system <ref type="bibr">[20,</ref><ref type="bibr">23,</ref><ref type="bibr">33]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_KXz9kKY">Comparatively smaller, but still notable, proportions of caregivers of patients with psychosis were interested in caregiver-focused information; for instance, 62% to 69% were interested in relaxation exercises, stress/mood management, and community events for caregivers, while 85% to 90% were interested in the aforementioned patient- Social interaction promoted long-term engagement.</s><s xml:id="_3c3p6zx">Qualitatively, three studies found that users valued learning about similar experiences from others via social media-like features, which normalized their experiences and could provide new symptom management strategies (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">3</ref>) <ref type="bibr">[19,</ref><ref type="bibr">26,</ref><ref type="bibr">30]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_ZzFATtZ">Similarly, 67% of both young adults with psychosis and deaf or hard-of-hearing survey participants (N=9) reported interest in peer support via chat features <ref type="bibr">[24,</ref><ref type="bibr">32]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_APQzN78">However, a comparatively smaller proportion of veterans with anxiety or MDD were interested in peer support (48.3% of the full cohort, 51.3% of the smartphone user subgroup) <ref type="bibr">[28]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_RQHXk9p"><ref type="table" target="#tab_6">3</ref>) <ref type="bibr">[20,</ref><ref type="bibr">35]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_gHbDRWJ"><s xml:id="_825vKBM">However, one oncology HCP cautioned that, similar to support groups, "very strict guidelines of what is said" should be implemented to manage potential risks from shared social media-like content, although little additional context was provided <ref type="bibr">[26]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_pbGCzme"><s xml:id="_UhQku5A">Spouses/partners of people with BD also suggested both in-app information on accessing professional resources and direct counseling for the patient at times where other support might be inaccessible <ref type="bibr">[20]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_gPUwGxW">More than half of all workers, employed or unemployed during the COVID-19 pandemic, likewise endorsed links to resources, counseling, and crisis support as DMHT features and 81.6% of young adults with psychosis endorsed a feature to communicate with professional experts <ref type="bibr">[24,</ref><ref type="bibr">29]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_wQdXy8U">Importantly, patients attending private psychiatric clinics expressed a higher comfort level for in-app communication with HCPs compared with patients attending public clinics, suggesting demographic differences in the valuation of access to professional support through <ref type="bibr">DMHT [36]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_TZsXvgp"><s xml:id="_JY2ED7j">Nine studies reported on interest in DMHT reminders and notifications.</s><s xml:id="_mVptxG6">Across three studies, &gt;70% of patients or caregivers were interested in appointment reminders <ref type="bibr">[23]</ref><ref type="bibr">[24]</ref><ref type="bibr">[25]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_hyCstSP">Additionally, 73% and 68% of patients with epilepsy reported interest in reminders for medication refills and adherence, respectively <ref type="bibr">[25]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_qYKpBxf"><s xml:id="_Y75XT9A">June 2024 developed in consideration with patients' social, cognitive, and environmental needs to avoid overwhelming users <ref type="bibr">[35]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_QkcmfvF">Specifically, two studies reported language as a barrier.</s><s xml:id="_UuANyku">Deaf or hard-of-hearing participants recommended visual content presentation, such as videos and icons, alongside text and American Sign Language translations where possible <ref type="bibr">[32]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_bHHJMb8">Similarly, when discussing English-only apps, one provider stated: "language is a barrier for some</s></p><p xml:id="_emxPSD3"><s xml:id="_VswUBVc">[patients]" <ref type="bibr">[5]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_acHEXe2">Mobility issues related to MH symptoms or other conditions and technical literacy, such as difficulties remembering passwords and navigating smartphones or apps, created accessibility barriers as well (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">3</ref>) <ref type="bibr">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr">15,</ref><ref type="bibr">26,</ref><ref type="bibr">38]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_QznPvrr">Additional concerns included apps that restricted use based on geographic location <ref type="bibr">[32]</ref>; user difficulty in how to find relevant, useful apps <ref type="bibr">[28]</ref>; and limited mobile device memory for downloading apps <ref type="bibr">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr">32]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_F2fZPGE"><s xml:id="_yMAvu8A">Offline functionality, reported by six studies, was also captured under the technical considerations subtheme.</s><s xml:id="_TPkEA6n">A majority (56%, N=9) of participants included in the Borghouts et al. 2022 study expressed concern about their mobile data plans when using their devices <ref type="bibr">[32]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_aX7DRgB">Correspondingly, "availability of WiFi" was noted as a top barrier to use for apps for depression by <ref type="bibr">Stiles-Shield et al. 2017</ref> and several veterans in another study reported that home Wi-Fi connectivity facilitated app usage by eliminating cellular data fees <ref type="bibr">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr">18]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_A7dKEMu"><s xml:id="_SeKAuJz">Quotes from patients and HCPs echoed concern about apps without offline functionality (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">3</ref>) <ref type="bibr">[21,</ref><ref type="bibr">37]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_gaX4qvj"><s xml:id="_4wTsVW6">Data fees were also captured under the costs subtheme, with hidden or additional costs described as a barrier to app use by two studies <ref type="bibr">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr">33]</ref>  <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">3</ref>) <ref type="bibr">[21]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Ard8s7S">Theme Four: Therapeutic Goal</head><p xml:id="_WkbvuEB"><s xml:id="_ta89X9j">Twelve studies reported on factors relating to the integration of DMHT with users' therapeutic goals.</s><s xml:id="_xbg9KRh">The clinical actionability and therapeutic alliance subthemes were reported by ten and seven studies, respectively.</s></p><p xml:id="_9uwCV5m"><s xml:id="_AXumpKv">Nine studies reported the value of clinically actionable insights from apps where the users could acquire and practice new skills to make positive changes in their lives (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">3</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_akGF3wn">For instance, patient and caregiver app users reported interest in "daily tips," "new ideas," and "solutions or recommendations" for symptom management <ref type="bibr">[30,</ref><ref type="bibr">33,</ref><ref type="bibr">38]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_MnrpekQ">Furthermore, an app that could serve as a resource for multiple management strategies was preferable <ref type="bibr">[19,</ref><ref type="bibr">26,</ref><ref type="bibr">33]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_qxQbqgs">Quantitatively, 4% of patients receiving acute treatment in a partial hospitalization program for MH conditions, including mood and psychotic disorders, reported that the primary purpose of their DMHT use was therapy skills practice <ref type="bibr">[31]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_AnjzKPw">HCPs likewise appreciated that DMHT could facilitate patients practicing skills outside of formal treatment sessions <ref type="bibr">[5]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_HpYXvsP">In particular, clinicians from a youth behavioral health clinic noted that DMHT may be especially beneficial for young users because they could be conveniently and discreetly incorporated into their daily lives <ref type="bibr">[21]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_kryZvRe"><s xml:id="_tm2Sgmv">Users valued easy data-sharing with clinicians, particularly for mood-or symptom-tracking features, which could improve communication and the accuracy of symptom reporting during clinical visits <ref type="bibr">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr">15,</ref><ref type="bibr">16,</ref><ref type="bibr">30,</ref><ref type="bibr">33,</ref><ref type="bibr">38]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_VzPjch9">For  <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S11</ref> and <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table S12</ref>, respectively.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_8Q4V9dR">DISCUSSION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_xqVpjwQ">Principal Findings</head><p xml:id="_KUfJU3d"><s xml:id="_U9UPuuY">This SLR aimed to identify and synthesize qualitative and quantitative evidence on how DMHT are valued by users, payers, and employers in the US.</s><s xml:id="_DbD4hgk">Evidence from users with or without diagnosed relevant disorders, caregivers, and HCPs was captured across a wide range of demographics.</s><s xml:id="_DHWWYJp">No study reported evaluated an app from a payer or employer perspective.</s><s xml:id="_sZst5dR">Further, all but one included study focused on mobile apps.</s></p><p xml:id="_57Tzz9V"><s xml:id="_qMUu5FY">No relevant appraisals of DMHT were identified from the FDA website searches; however, eight relevant FDA approval labels or notifications for MH apps or guidance documents for industry and FDA staff were identified.</s><s xml:id="_qNVM74J">Assessment of these materials showed overlap with some valuation factors identified in this SLR, including evidence of clinical efficacy and safety, app maintenance, and privacy and security.</s><s xml:id="_xrjQuqE">Engagement style, although not covered by the FDA materials, was the most reported theme by studies included in the SLR and was found to overlap heavily with other themes.</s><s xml:id="_XaXVVPk">Engagement may be a key consideration for app developers, as app user retention can be low: one study showed that more than 90% of users abandon free MH apps within 30 days of installation Background and accessibility findings also identified up-front and hidden costs as barriers to DMHT use, with willingness-to-pay varying among individuals.</s><s xml:id="_9qvTHrR">This has important implications for app development considering that many MH apps currently on the market are direct-to-consumer and require out-of-pocket payment.</s><s xml:id="_cHstZxA">App developers often take this approach as it does not require the accumulation of formal evidence of clinical benefit for FDA approval <ref type="bibr">[44]</ref>, but it may present a financial barrier to use for consumers.</s></p><p xml:id="_CRRQeVr"><s xml:id="_Aza8eQ8">Privacy and security, reported by 13 studies, was a prevalent theme, with users primarily concerned with data and PHI security within apps.</s><s xml:id="_UreXuMV">This finding reflects wider research; a 2019 review of 116 depression-related apps retrieved from iTunes and Google Play stores in 2017 found that only 4% of identified apps had acceptable transparency in privacy and security, with many completely lacking a privacy policy <ref type="bibr">[45]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_nJhNnWm">Similarly, 39% of MH apps recommended by college counseling centers had no privacy policy, and of those with a policy, 88% collected user data and 49% shared that data with third parties <ref type="bibr">[4]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_mmRrdVa">Most evidence identified in this SLR under this theme, as well as findings previously published in the wider literature, focus on these remote privacy risks.</s><s xml:id="_sWCn66R">However, local privacy concerns are also important to users.</s><s xml:id="_CuFrJsz">In particular, inconspicuous naming and the ability to hide sensitive modules within MH apps were rated as June 2024 highly important by both patients and HCPs to maintain user privacy.</s><s xml:id="_5bq72md">Users emphasized a desire to avoid stigma associated with mental illness, which was also reflected by findings in the engagement style theme: more young adults with psychosis were more interested in in-app messaging with other patients in psychosis recovery (67.1%) than a provider and family member together (47.3%) or their personal support network (59.8%) <ref type="bibr">[24]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_cTc5p4n">Similarly, youths were interested in apps that could be used discreetly in school or other public settings to avoid potential MH stigma.</s><s xml:id="_GKmMfSE">This is a key, novel finding of this SLR, considering many app or DMHT components on the market are named after their target disorder.</s></p><p xml:id="_tQTSyZr"><s xml:id="_h98HK8w">The use of DMHT to achieve therapeutic goals was discussed from patient, caregiver, and HCP perspectives, all of which valued DMHT that had evidence of efficacy, presented clinically actionable information, and facilitated the patientclinician relationships.</s><s xml:id="_NEAUnKR">Of the five studies that explored how HCPs value DMHT in clinical practice, two were restricted to the oncology or ASD settings and were not readily generalizable to wider MH settings <ref type="bibr">[22,</ref><ref type="bibr">26]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_eeVBBD8">In other studies, providers reported interest in using DMHT to facilitate asynchronous communication with patients and their caregivers, promote patient skill practice, and improve care for children through use of games and visuals <ref type="bibr">[21,</ref><ref type="bibr">33]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_7TWeTDQ">However, while HCPs overall believed that DMHT improved care, some believed that their clinical training allowed for care personalization beyond what DMHT could provide.</s><s xml:id="_Z94guXR">Feature customizability and receipt of input from HCPs and users during app development and testing may be a way to mitigate these concerns, as well as concerns about safety and efficacy, as many available apps do not appropriately address user health concerns <ref type="bibr">[46]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_BmNUdUa">Findings additionally suggested that training and resources on DMHT would be beneficial to ensure that HCPs were equipped to integrate DMHT into their practices <ref type="bibr">[5]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_k5cKPFC">Collaboration between DMHT specialists and HCPs, along with a shift from randomized controlled trials to effectiveness-implementation hybrid trials, may be a way to streamline the integration of DMHT into clinical care and provide more training and resources for HCPs <ref type="bibr">[21,</ref><ref type="bibr">47]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_nrYPZR8">Strengths</head><p xml:id="_nxYre5H"><s xml:id="_cDaP9es">This review followed a pre-specified protocol and used systematic methods in line with the York Centre for Reviews and Dissemination guidelines <ref type="bibr">[48]</ref> to conduct an exhaustive search of the literature, identifying evidence relevant to</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_hdw7kZu"><s xml:id="_eGEGZrf">Manuscript ....................................................................................................................................................................... Supplementary Files ..................................................................................................................................................................... Multimedia Appendixes ................................................................................................................................................................. Multimedia Appendix 1 .................................................................................................................................................................. CONSORT (or other) checklists ...................................................................................................................................................... CONSORT (or other) checklist 0 ......................................................................................................................................................</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_73XqpFd"><s xml:id="_XYfH4H8">management tools.</s><s xml:id="_3FkjmpH">Key barriers to DMHT use included limited internet access, poor technical literacy, and privacy concerns.</s><s xml:id="_SYPzzPV">Novel findings included discreetness of DMHT to avoid stigma.</s><s xml:id="_K7D4Bu7">CONCLUSIONS: Usability, cost, accessibility, technical considerations, and alignment with therapeutic goals are important to users, although DMHT valuation varies across individuals.</s><s xml:id="_DzgFNWF">DMHT apps should be developed and selected with specific user needs in mind.</s><s xml:id="_eXmMqy8">Keywords: mental health; mHealth; digital health; digital therapeutics; systematic review; framework synthesis; mixed methods INTRODUCTION Background Digital health is comprised of a broad range of technologies, including mobile health, health information technology, wearable devices, and personalized medicine, which serve as tools to enhance health care delivery.</s><s xml:id="_ektNVK4">Recently, several digital mental health therapeutics, a category of digital mental health technologies (DMHT), have received United States (US) Food and Drug Administration (FDA) approval to prevent, manage, or treat a medical disorder or disease based on evidence from superiority trials and compliance with technical guidelines [1,2].</s><s xml:id="_HUDJD3u">However, the majority of DMHT, particularly apps, fall outside FDA jurisdiction because they are not intended to diagnose, treat, or prevent disease, and because they are "low risk" in that they would not cause harm in the event of malfunction [3].</s><s xml:id="_48w4QqM">Due to this lack of regulatory framework, few DMHT are supported by published efficacy studies.</s><s xml:id="_y6NrU5B">One study found that only 16% of mental health (MH) apps recommended by college counseling centers were supported by efficacy studies published in peer-reviewed journals [4].</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_daTkhe4"><s xml:id="_mza4Mfy">using a published framework to synthesize emerging themes from mixedmethods evidence in order to understand how digital health solutions, encompassing both digital therapeutics and direct-to-consumer digital health technologies, are valued, with a focus on MH disorders, Alzheimer's, epilepsy, autism spectrum disorder (ASD), and attention deficit hyperactive disorder (ADHD) in the US.</s><s xml:id="_UFPqVvY">performed in accordance with a pre-specified protocol and reported in line with the Enhancing Transparency in Reporting the Synthesis of Qualitative Research and Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta Analyses guidelines [6,7].</s><s xml:id="_HKp8gBd">The protocol was not registered.</s><s xml:id="_WmznaQZ">Search Strategy Electronic databases, encompassing MEDLINE (including MEDLINE In-Process, MEDLINE Daily and MEDLINE Epub Ahead of Print), Embase, the Cochrane Library (including Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews and Cochrane Central Register of Controlled Trials), PsycINFO, and the Health Technology Assessment Database, were selected in alignment with this SLR's target indications and were searched on June 17 th , 2022.</s><s xml:id="_SNKevw7">The search terms included combinations of free-text and Medical Subject Heading or Emtree terms related to indications of interest, DMHT, and relevant outcomes or assessment types (e.g., technology assessments, cost) (Tables</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_NxkzQqF"><s xml:id="_2WqAYJS">Studies only reporting qualitative data were assessed with the Critical Appraisal Skills Program (CASP) Qualitative Studies Checklist.</s><s xml:id="_NHT3TQN">Studies only reporting quantitative data were evaluated with the CASP Cohort Study Checklist, and studies reporting both qualitative and quantitative data were evaluated with both checklists [8].</s><s xml:id="_v3V7hn8">Data extractions and quality assessments were performed by a single individual for each study, with the information verified by a second, independent individual.</s><s xml:id="_z9yCRkT">Discrepancies were resolved by consensus, with arbitration by a third individual if necessary.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_4AMcjVm"><s xml:id="_XeB9f3w">. All studies investigated a user perspective, with none specifically investigating payer or employer perspectives.</s><s xml:id="_p5AnGpG">Only one study, which examined ingestible sensor pills and smart pill dispensers to track adherence, investigated a DMHT that was not an app [34].</s><s xml:id="_xPreZUK">Most frequently, studies focused on indications for mood, anxiety, or psychotic disorders (n=15) with other indications of focus including ADHD (n=2), ASD (n=1), and epilepsy (n=1).</s><s xml:id="_UBWEkVD">No relevant studies focused on Alzheimer's were identified.</s><s xml:id="_5CCtMpD">Eight studies assessed the perspectives toward DMHT of general population participants, who were not necessarily diagnosed with relevant conditions [16-Value of DMHT Systematic Review 21 June 2024 18,26,27,29,30,32].</s><s xml:id="_HcB5zQx">Of these populations, several were identified as having an increased risk of MH conditions, such as cancer patients [26], college students [16,27], deaf or hard-of-hearing individuals [32], and people who were unemployed or furloughed during the COVID-19 pandemic [29].</s><s xml:id="_6W4H7AA">Additionally, one study included a mix of patients who were above and below referral criteria for psychotherapy for depression [18].</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Users</head></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_bdP2EAC"><s xml:id="_msSgash">with diagnoses of schizophrenia, schizoaffective disorder, BD, or persistent MDD in active treatment at a</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_DHeFqeu"><s xml:id="_7QsQNJj">an easy way "Great way to have patients practice exercises between sessions; both provider and patient happy to have concrete tool."</s><s xml:id="_sAThFDG">Routine behavioral health care staff, Hoffman 2019 [5] "I almost wonder, like, if you logged in, what would you like to address today, like, symptom management versus stress… You almost need, like, an emergency toolkit and then you almost need, like, your day-today stuff."</s><s xml:id="_XaEkz4B">HCP in cancer care, Huberty 2022 [26] Ease of sharing and interpretation of data: increase of engagement and symptom reporting "[I] feel like sometimes I'll give parents follow up things to do while I'm not there, and they'll forget about it throughout the week, but because they're on their phone or whatever so much throughout the week, I feel like we could send them reminders or this is what we need to do before the next week.</s><s xml:id="_9NpfZSV">I think that that would encourage them to Value of DMHT Systematic Review think my training in behavioral medicine allows me to create a different tool with the patient that is more specific to them."</s><s xml:id="_gGRgvjB">Routine behavioral health care staff, Hoffman 2019 [5doctor tells me to use an app, I'm probably going to use it."</s><s xml:id="_guAyP3m">Patient with current or prior depression diagnosis, Dinkel 2021 [38]</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_wQ9Q7zm"><s xml:id="_2PsaG45">focused information [23].</s><s xml:id="_PffEEeS">Information delivery style preference was captured under the short-term usability subtheme.</s><s xml:id="_Wk53mt5">Two studies, one in young adults with psychosis and one in their caregivers, revealed that delivering information in a variety of formats was important; when presented with non-mutually exclusive options, &gt;50% of both populations were interested in text content, video content, audio content, and Value of DMHT Systematic Review 21 June 2024 discussion boards [23,24].</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_8wcqBrY"><s xml:id="_kdKTvnV">Users overall endorsed social features to support their MH.</s><s xml:id="_YHhuWAt">In Casarez et al. 2019, spouses/partners of people with BD likewise desired features to communicate with other caregivers, and additionally emphasized that DMHT could facilitate conversation and understanding with patients, a sentiment echoed by peer support specialists in Storm et al. 2021 (Table</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_RnabZve"><s xml:id="_7chk2cK">. Parents of children with ADHD reported that difficulty paying phone bills could result in their phones being shut off, limiting DMHT use; one MH clinic administrator stated: "We often encounter parents' phones being shut off because they haven't paid their bill… If the app were free or low cost, I imagine it could be very helpful"[33].</s><s xml:id="_JpdjavG">In addition to hidden costs, this quote identifies up-front app costs as a barrier.</s><s xml:id="_ckfpHfb">Quantitatively, over half of a general population of surveyed college students expressed that cost was a top concern for use of MH apps [16].</s><s xml:id="_AfH837p">Qualitative findings from two additional studies likewise identified cost as a barrier to DMHT use [15,38].</s><s xml:id="_v8JhvYA">Three novel cost attributes were identified by this SLR: willingness-to-pay, insurance restrictions, and cost saving compared with professional care.</s><s xml:id="_fAWsrb2">Four Value of DMHT Systematic Review 21 June 2024 preferred MH app use over seeing an MH professional due to anonymity or reduced stigma [27].</s><s xml:id="_Ue3HA3X">One participant in a study of VA health service users described access to professional care via MH apps as convenient because they could avoid disclosing their use of MH services to explain leaving work early for an appointment [15].</s><s xml:id="_7BpQFsx">In line with overarching concern about PHI privacy and security, users valued app security measures.</s><s xml:id="_shR55zK">Schueller et al. 2018 reported that 74.2% of users rated data encryption as "important" or "very important" [17].</s><s xml:id="_8rrNgCr">Users in another study perceived the level of privacy protection as highest for apps utilizing a combination of a generic app name (i.e., not reflecting the indicated MH disorder); easily hidden modules; and secure, user-authenticated Web portals for making module changes [39].</s><s xml:id="_G2NBRHa">Behavioral health clinic staff echoed the importance of discreet MH app names (Table</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_Wp5eD5w"><s xml:id="_96TsEVK">]; all others utilized custom questionnaires.</s><s xml:id="_spHdhjn">For the 18 studies with qualitative components, 4 were at risk of selection bias due to participants being exclusively recruited using online postings and research registries[16-  18,29]  and only 1 considered the relationship between researcher and participant when interpreting the results[30].</s><s xml:id="_W5X92Qc">Full quality assessments for qualitative and quantitative study components can be found in Table</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_vdUgkvK"><s xml:id="_4UGWGHv">[40].</s><s xml:id="_V6Vtabt">Engagement is also a key clinical concern in terms of DMHT efficacy; one meta-analysis of 25 studies showed that increased use of DMHT modules was significantly associated with positive outcomes regardless of the target MH condition [41].</s><s xml:id="_qDT3759">The findings of this SLR may therefore be informative to both DMHT designers and HCPs who integrate DMHT into clinical care by providing insight on DMHT valuation, and thus how use and benefit can be improved.</s><s xml:id="_9bRDTU2">For instance, users valued DMHT that were easy to use and aligned with their needs and priorities, particularly through Value of DMHT Systematic Review 21 June 2024 features that supported their therapeutic goals.</s><s xml:id="_vW2hFZF">Additionally, content presented through multiple delivery modes, such as both text and visuals, promoted engagement as well as accessibility.</s><s xml:id="_ZnRtwpU">However, engagement and feature preference varied across populations.</s><s xml:id="_eDFs2ER">For instance, DMHT valuation was affected by technical literacy, which may relate to user demographics; in this SLR, veterans repeatedly emphasized technical literacy as a barrier to DMHT use [15].</s><s xml:id="_Wg8P2Vy">Similarly, offline functionality may be more important for some users.</s><s xml:id="_TPY2eMA">Despite 85% of the total US population owning smartphones, only 59% of Medicare beneficiaries have access to a smartphone with a wireless plan.</s><s xml:id="_mKYHqqe">Moreover, beneficiaries who are older, less educated, disabled, or Black or Hispanic have even lower digital access [42,43].</s><s xml:id="_auznxPz">These findings emphasize the importance of customizability and suggest that app development and selection in the clinical setting should consider the demographics of the target population, particularly in relation to ease of use and offline functionality.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_DsCSrVA"><s xml:id="_ESz6K8b">Studies reporting on each theme, subtheme,</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Value of DMHT Systematic Review</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_fe28BNg"><s xml:id="_eA3tUnV">Summary of included study characteristics and outcomes</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Study</cell><cell>Design a</cell><cell>Perspective/Population a</cell><cell>Objective(s)</cell><cell>Data Collection Method(s) a</cell></row><row><cell>Afra 2018 [25]</cell><cell>Cross-sectional, quantitative</cell><cell>Patients with epilepsy who were regular smartphone users recruited from the University of Utah Adult Comprehensive Epilepsy Clinic (N=40)</cell><cell>To develop a drug-device combination product using an app in combination with epilepsy treatment antiseizure medications as an</cell><cell>Custom survey</cell></row><row><cell>Beard 2019 [31]</cell><cell>Cross-sectional, quantitative</cell><cell>Patients treated at a partial hospitalization program located in a non-profit, insurance-based, psychiatric hospital; diagnoses included MDD, BD, anxiety, OCD, stress-related disorders, and psychotic disorders (N=322)</cell><cell>To smartphone app and social characterize general media usage in an acute transdiagnostic psychiatric sample with high smartphone ownership; characterize current engagement interest in the use clinical predictors smartphone use of MH; and test demographic and smartphone apps to support of and</cell><cell>Custom survey</cell></row><row><cell>Borghouts 2022 [32]</cell><cell>Cross-sectional, mixed-methods</cell><cell>General users b : members of the Center on Deafness Inland Empire, comprised of people with lived experience as members of the deaf/hard-of-hearing community (N=10)</cell><cell>To investigate the MH needs of the deaf/hard-of-hearing community and how MH apps may be able to support these needs</cell><cell>Custom survey; focus group</cell></row><row><cell>Boster 2018 [22]</cell><cell>Cross-sectional, qualitative</cell><cell>Speech language pathologists experienced in augmentative and alternative communication using a device in children with ASD recruited through social media and professional listserves (N=8) Parents (caregivers) of children national organizations (N=5) with ASD recruited through</cell><cell>To gain insight from speech language pathologists and parents of children with ASD regarding appealing features of augmentative alternative apps communication and</cell><cell>Focus groups; poll questions</cell></row><row><cell>Buck 2021a [23]</cell><cell>Cross-sectional, quantitative</cell><cell>Caregivers of young adult family members who experienced early psychosis (before age 35) recruited through HCP referrals or ads (N=43)</cell><cell>To assess caregivers' interest in an array of specific potential mHealth functions to guide early psychosis caregivers of young adults with development of mHealth for</cell><cell>Custom survey</cell></row><row><cell>Buck 2021b [24]</cell><cell>Cross-sectional, quantitative</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_5WuXqf7"><s xml:id="_XTnE3Mu">Select key quotes identified for SLR findings</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Subtheme</cell><cell>Criteria: Findings</cell><cell>Key Quotes</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Engagement Style</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Ease of use</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Male veteran, age 26, Connolly 2018 [15]</cell></row><row><cell>Short-term usability</cell><cell></cell><cell>"They love badges. And decorating their avatars, like getting a new hat...So, they're very motivated to get through their modules when they get to earn something at the end."</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Available engagement styles: use of animation and visuals</cell><cell>Pediatric behavioral health clinician, Knapp 2021 [21] "It could become visually distracting -children preferring the animation rather than actually creating genuine, communicative messages." Caregiver or speech language pathologist for children with ASD, Boster</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2018 [22]</cell></row></table><note xml:id="_VxHGGUp"><p><s xml:id="_B4cg7Cm">"I like short exercises.</s><s xml:id="_Y2dcXjR">I can use them in different places."</s><s xml:id="_y6vsQMV">Patient in routine behavioral health care, Hoffman 2019 [5] "Whenever I have one of those outbursts and frustration, I can just open it up, say 'Okay, what's my first step?''"</s><s xml:id="_H3GrWbt">"I've seen some kid clients come alive because they're excited because they wanna beat their score.</s><s xml:id="_v9Z585X">And just helping them like, 'How do you have to communicate?</s><s xml:id="_JDz3byV">You have to keep talking.</s><s xml:id="_wjPae9V">You have to keep going.'</s><s xml:id="_Gs5Fcs8">It's helped with that."</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>Table 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_Dg3MEnk"><s xml:id="_AkJHxUk">Quantitative evidence related to anxiety management and mood, symptom, or sleep tracking features</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Study</cell><cell>Perspective</cell><cell>Finding</cell><cell>n</cell><cell>%</cell><cell>Mean (SD) Likert Score</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Anxiety management</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Interest in skill practices for managing stress and improving mood</cell><cell>64</cell><cell>84.2</cell><cell>3.30 (0.98) a</cell></row><row><cell>Buck 2021b [24]</cell><cell>Young adults with early psychosis</cell><cell>Interest in skill practices for relaxation Interest in information about relaxation exercises Interest in information about healthy sleep practices</cell><cell>57 59 56</cell><cell>76.0 77.6 73.7</cell><cell>3.09 (1.12) a 3.00 (1.16) a 2.93 (1.15) a</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Interest in mindfulness or meditation practices</cell><cell>44</cell><cell>59.4</cell><cell>2.61 (1.34) a</cell></row></table><note xml:id="_AvnUXma"><p><s xml:id="_23gAven">Footnotes: a A five-point (0-4) Likert scale was used.</s><s xml:id="_kCXdQ2P">b A five-point (1-5) Likert scale was used.</s><s xml:id="_z32QbwY">Abbreviations: DMHT, digital mental health technologies; GPS, global positioning system; MDD, major depressive disorder; MH, mental health; n, number of patients; PTSD, post-traumatic stress disorder.</s></p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p xml:id="_y7WJ7je"><s xml:id="_3DSvJ2b">https://preprints.jmir.org/preprint/57401[unpublished,</s><s xml:id="_RFhuXXk">peer-reviewed preprint]</s></p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head xml:id="_qmgfssN">Acknowledgements</head><p xml:id="_YFbTarG"><s xml:id="_9hzghwW">The authors acknowledge <rs type="institution">A, Costello Medical, US</rs>, for medical writing and editorial assistance based on the authors' input and direction.</s></p></div>
			</div>			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_y97Sq7j"><p xml:id="_HSJN6y3"><s xml:id="_MyPbBJZ">Value of DMHT Systematic Review</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="21" xml:id="_tsv8p7y">June 2024</head><p xml:id="_HEa4MyW"><s xml:id="_U2PGvWZ">Beyond apps, caregivers of patients with MDD, BD, and schizophrenia preferred an ingestible pill sensor that tracked medication adherence, physical activity, mood, and rest 9.79 (95% confidence interval [CI]: 4.81, 19.9), 7.47 (95% CI: 3.81, 14.65), and 6.71 (95% CI: 3.29, 13.69) times more than a non-digital pill organizer, respectively <ref type="bibr">[34]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_hPq9Hue">Qualitatively, patients and caregivers also appreciated reminders, especially if reasonably timed or delivered via text messages <ref type="bibr">[19,</ref><ref type="bibr">38]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_RsSM9gy"><s xml:id="_g5DDg4e">Short-term DMHT engagement was also supported by games and graphics, which could communicate information in an accessible way <ref type="bibr">[20]</ref>, provide tools for stress management <ref type="bibr">[25,</ref><ref type="bibr">29]</ref>, and be used therapeutically with children <ref type="bibr">[21,</ref><ref type="bibr">22]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_tu9YcFE"><s xml:id="_vszGGPd">However, some HCPs and caregivers expressed concerns that graphics and games may be distracting for certain children (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>) <ref type="bibr">[22]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_AABwwZT"><s xml:id="_JprbubE">In a novel finding, three studies reported forgetfulness or lack of motivation as influences on DMHT engagement.</s><s xml:id="_FnWYFSB">In some cases, disuse was related to stress, other MH symptoms, or poor technical literacy (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>) <ref type="bibr">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr">15,</ref><ref type="bibr">19]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_ubMZfvp">In contrast, "forgetting to use" DMHT and "lack of motivation" were perceived as relatively small barriers to use in <ref type="bibr">Stiles-Shield et al. 2017 [18]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_gVWE7Rk"><s xml:id="_bn5Uxpc">The third subtheme under engagement style was customizability, which was generally valued by users; 70.9% of a general population of smartphone users noted customization was an important factor <ref type="bibr">[17]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_kMvZHff">Similarly, 9.4% of all surveyed veterans, and 10.9% of those with smartphones, reported disliking a prior DMHT due to lack of personalization <ref type="bibr">[28]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_XCWeSAP">Users specifically wanted to be able to opt out of irrelevant features, customize audio-visual and design elements, add personal notes to tracked mood data, and provide ongoing feedback to facilitate personalization <ref type="bibr">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr">19,</ref><ref type="bibr">20,</ref><ref type="bibr">22,</ref><ref type="bibr">26]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Jc5P99d">Theme Two: Background and Accessibility</head><p xml:id="_Bq2Fym4"><s xml:id="_kESnmqK">Sixteen studies reported findings related to DMHT background and accessibility, which considers the developer of the DMHT, as well as functionality and studies, three of which focused on apps, explored willingness-to-pay for DMHT from a user perspective.</s><s xml:id="_zhdU3GT">Willingness-to-pay varied based on user preference; some surveyed college students and smartphone users among general populations valued free apps due to financial restrictions or uncertainty around app effectiveness, even though one student commented that the quality of free trials may be inferior <ref type="bibr">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr">17]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_5xKQCMa">Some smartphone users also voiced a limit on how much they would be willing to spend for an app subscription (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>) <ref type="bibr">[17]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_PnPXA5z"><s xml:id="_f99xRPP">Forma et al. 2022 found that caregivers were willing to pay $255.04 (95% CI: $123.21,</s><s xml:id="_eg8K2U7">$386.86)</s><s xml:id="_Ak3pbZS">more per month for a pill with an ingestible sensor that tracked medication adherence, physical activity, and rest, and could connect to an app that also collected self-reported mood data.</s><s xml:id="_2BQHxyn">Moreover, the caregivers were willing to pay $124.50 (95% CI: $48.18, $200.81)</s><s xml:id="_EEkK8pn">more per month for an app-connected pill organizer alone compared with a non-digital pill organizer <ref type="bibr">[34]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_WTEZj73">In contrast, some veterans expressed total disinterest in paid apps, with one user citing poor technical literacy ("don't have the knowledge") in addition to cost as affecting willingness-to-pay <ref type="bibr">[15]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_MnqqzmQ"><s xml:id="_eyqmpSp">In another novel finding, a speech-language pathologist working with children with ASD preferred a single app including multiple features over separate apps for particular features due to insurance restrictions: "I agree that teaching Apps should be an in-App feature versus their own app because sometimes insurance doesn't allow us to open the iPads purchased through insurance" <ref type="bibr">[22]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_TMekmZd">Although no further detail was provided for this finding, it suggests that there may be restrictions on the use of other apps on devices purchased under insurance, which may have implications for DMHT use in formal care settings due to the lack of financial support.</s></p><p xml:id="_FAsrSWT"><s xml:id="_swDhFp4">In a third novel cost-related finding, a small number of participants from a general population of students (3.6%) in one study preferred using an MH app over seeing an MH professional due to cost savings <ref type="bibr">[27]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_BpCS3aA"><s xml:id="_f9acrzm">Two studies reported on the theme of app stability and technical difficulties, with Quantitative and qualitative findings from the general privacy (i.e., evidence not categorized under any specific subtheme), data collection and storage, and privacy policies subthemes revealed heterogeneous concern (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_kuk4DRN">A total of 74% of a general population of college students reported privacy as a top concern for MH apps, although further detail on the specific area of concern was unclear <ref type="bibr">[16]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_7Pfvyvq">In Stiles-Shields et al. 2017, participants were highly concerned with data access, but less so with general privacy <ref type="bibr">[18]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_PY5aXuc">Echoing concern about data collection and storage, 59.1% of veterans with anxiety or MDD in one study were concerned about in-app PHI protection <ref type="bibr">[28]</ref>; however, a different, qualitative study in veterans with post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD), alcohol use disorder, or MDD reported that a relatively small number of participants expressed privacy concerns.</s><s xml:id="_ETRSUd9">In the latter study, reasons for concern included distrust in Veterans Affairs (VA), belief that digital data is inherently not confidential, and fear of phone hacking <ref type="bibr">[15]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_KFmfQM2">From an HCP perspective, 0% of surveyed behavioral health HCPs agreed with the statement "My patients are concerned about data security," despite multiple patients within the same study reporting privacy concerns <ref type="bibr">[5]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_nN6Mb44"><s xml:id="_e2XBAhX">Still, privacy policies were important overall, with 70.5% of smartphone MH app users rating having a privacy policy as "very important" or "important" <ref type="bibr">[17]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_94nCJbV">instance, 53% of a general college student population believed that the potential to share information with their clinician was "one of the top benefits" of using <ref type="bibr">DMHT [16]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_kwYMart">Additionally, many HCPs reported active use or interest in use of DMHT in clinical practice to facilitate asynchronous communication and increase patient engagement with treatment outside of formal appointments; however, some preferred traditional care strategies for their personalization and flexibility (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>) <ref type="bibr">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr">21,</ref><ref type="bibr">33]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_GHzZupQ">Theme Five: Clinical Foundation</head><p xml:id="_hUxzqMA"><s xml:id="_YYvj9Ew">Eight studies reported findings related to the clinical foundation of DMHT, meaning their utility and appropriateness for patients.</s><s xml:id="_wjfYVuV">Clinical validity was the most reported subtheme, with evidence identified from six studies.</s><s xml:id="_bBnwGzz">Two studies reported on the user feedback subtheme and two on impressions of use, which captured user perception of app content as accurate and relevant.</s></p><p xml:id="_xjms4En"><s xml:id="_VqjMU2U">Across subthemes, users valued evidence of DMHT benefit or efficacy from various sources.</s><s xml:id="_uvzS83t">A total of 71.8% of surveyed veterans said they would use a DMHT if they "saw proof that it worked" for their MH conditions <ref type="bibr">[28]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_6JV5dws">Similarly, among 811 general population participants surveyed, 69.5% ranked direct research evidence as "important" or "very important" for DMHT and 66.8% ranked indirect research evidence the same <ref type="bibr">[17]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_vqVtVX5">Qualitative data identified recommendations from HCPs or academic institutions, as well as evidence of DMHT benefit from publications or research studies, as specific sources for clinically valid evidence of benefit (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>) <ref type="bibr">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr">17,</ref><ref type="bibr">38]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_ZhwqfZ7"><s xml:id="_meGT3ZE">In addition to academic and professional support, the user feedback subtheme captured user interest in whether DMHT were beneficial for peers or recommended by other trusted individuals.</s><s xml:id="_W4tY8xc">Patients with depression reported that other users' experiences influenced their app usage, with one user wanting to know "…if other people had success using it" <ref type="bibr">[38]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_2EkxTeV">Quantitatively, user ratings and user reviews were ranked as "important" or "very important" factors in DMHT use by 59.4% and 58.7% of general population participants, respectively</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_DKjR3J3">Limitations</head><p xml:id="_YsEQzQx"><s xml:id="_cgXr6Az">Methodological limitations should be considered when interpretating the findings of this SLR.</s><s xml:id="_kWQzNHk">Namely, only publications in English and in US populations were included.</s><s xml:id="_kjvzjsH">As perceptions of value are influenced by factors including cultures, laws, and healthcare settings, the findings of this SLR should not be generalized to other countries.</s><s xml:id="_K723ZFa">For instance, trust in HCPs and rates of longstanding relationships between patients and primary care providers are lower in the US compared with many European nations <ref type="bibr">[49,</ref><ref type="bibr">50]</ref>, which could impact the type of support users want from DMHT (i.e., engagement style) or interest in DMHT integration with therapeutic goals.</s></p><p xml:id="_WTNrRpR"><s xml:id="_whMTczK">In addition to the prespecified eligibility criteria, deprioritization strategies were implemented due to the large volume of identified evidence and may have resulted in relevant articles being missed.</s><s xml:id="_kqApevs">In particular, deprioritization of secondary research and opinion pieces likely led to the exclusion of relevant discussion around payer perspectives and reimbursement, for which no evidence was included in this SLR.</s><s xml:id="_zNcgCGz">Furthermore, although unlikely, there may have been reporting biases in the included studies due to missing results, which this SLR was not able to assess.</s></p><p xml:id="_tWZfFQa"><s xml:id="_FpnRfS5">No evidence was identified by this SLR for two subthemes included in the APA framework: business model (background and accessibility), which covers DMHT funding sources and potential sources of conflict; and data ownership, access, and export (therapeutic goal), which includes sharing data with electronic health records or wellness devices (for example, Apple HealthKit ® , Fitbit™).</s><s xml:id="_kBjJhZ9">The valuation of these subthemes should be evaluated in future research.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_cZmgyyV">Conclusions</head><p xml:id="_etPq2mj"><s xml:id="_Fp4KK24">Value of DMHT Systematic Review</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="21" xml:id="_nP5mnf9">June 2024</head><p xml:id="_EYt7Ruu"><s xml:id="_V88XuPz">In summary, app usability, cost, accessibility and other technical considerations, and alignment with therapeutic goals were the most reported valuation factors identified by this SLR.</s><s xml:id="_QVmFPnH">Many studies also reported user preference for apps that incorporated privacy and security features that provided protection from stigma.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
