<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_SBH6P2P">Whether financial incentives, pharmacologic therapies, and electronic cigarettes (e-cigarettes) promote smoking cessation among unselected smokers is unknown</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><surname>Halpern</surname></persName>
							<email>shalpern@upenn.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Scott</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Halpern</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Harhay</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Kathryn</forename><surname>Saulsgiver</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Christine</forename><surname>Brophy</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Sc.D</roleName><forename type="first">Andrea</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Troxel</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Kevin</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Volpp</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">University of Penn- sylvania Perelman School of Medicine , the Center for Health Incentives and Be- havioral Economics at the Leonard Davis Institute of Health Economics (S. tive and Advanced Illness Research Cen- ter (S. Department of Health Care Management , Wharton School (K.G.V.) , University of Pennsylva- nia , and the Center for Health Equity Re- search and Promotion , Philadelphia Vet- erans Affairs Medical Center (M. O</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">the Center for Health Incentives and Be- havioral Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">tive and Advanced Illness Research Cen- ter (S</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Department of Health Care Management</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep4">Wharton School (K.G.V.)</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep5">Center for Health Equity Re- search and Promotion</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Penn- sylvania Perelman School of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Leonard Davis Institute of Health Economics (S</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">University of Pennsylva- nia</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">Philadelphia Vet- erans Affairs Medical Center (M</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>O</postBox>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">.H. , Division of Biostatistics , New York University Lan- gone Medical Center (A.B.T. University of Pennsyl- vania Perelman School of Medicine , 301 Blockley Hall , 423 Guardian Dr. , Philadel- phia , PA 19104-6021 ,</note>
								<orgName type="department">Division of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">.H</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">New York University Lan- gone Medical Center (A.B.T</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">University of Pennsyl- vania Perelman School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>301 Blockley Hall 423 Guardian Dr. Philadel- phia</addrLine>
									<postCode>19104-6021</postCode>
									<region>PA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_WZ3vagG">Whether financial incentives, pharmacologic therapies, and electronic cigarettes (e-cigarettes) promote smoking cessation among unselected smokers is unknown</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">A0573D27EDC5C6335166FDAE15236C12</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1056/nejmsa1715757</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T09:25+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="756.0"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="756.0"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="756.0"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="756.0"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="756.0"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="756.0"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="756.0"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="756.0"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="756.0"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_sZDNys9">METHODS</head><p xml:id="_GZRMbPw"><s xml:id="_YekTnNy">We randomly assigned smokers employed by 54 companies to one of four smokingcessation interventions or to usual care.</s><s xml:id="_HyfT5xF">Usual care consisted of access to information regarding the benefits of smoking cessation and to a motivational text-messaging service.</s><s xml:id="_keJJ2gZ">The four interventions consisted of usual care plus one of the following: free cessation aids (nicotine-replacement therapy or pharmacotherapy, with e-cigarettes if standard therapies failed); free e-cigarettes, without a requirement that standard therapies had been tried; free cessation aids plus $600 in rewards for sustained abstinence; or free cessation aids plus $600 in redeemable funds, deposited in a separate account for each participant, with money removed from the account if cessation milestones were not met.</s><s xml:id="_vKM7NVu">The primary outcome was sustained smoking abstinence for 6 months after the target quit date.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_6xy6FEC">RESULTS</head><p xml:id="_mab4QGr"><s xml:id="_FtvwbpB">Among 6131 smokers who were invited to enroll, 125 opted out and 6006 underwent randomization.</s><s xml:id="_aEF2nSW">Sustained abstinence rates through 6 months were 0.1% in the usual-care group, 0.5% in the free cessation aids group, 1.0% in the free e-cigarettes group, 2.0% in the rewards group, and 2.9% in the redeemable deposit group.</s><s xml:id="_Mgc5NNz">With respect to sustained abstinence rates, redeemable deposits and rewards were superior to free cessation aids (P&lt;0.001 and P = 0.006, respectively, with significance levels adjusted for multiple comparisons).</s><s xml:id="_nXGuJ2S">Redeemable deposits were superior to free e-cigarettes (P = 0.008).</s><s xml:id="_b7yu9FG">Free e-cigarettes were not superior to usual care (P = 0.20) or to free cessation aids (P = 0.43).</s><s xml:id="_2Ts7TQu">Among the 1191 employees (19.8%) who actively participated in the trial (the "engaged" cohort), sustained abstinence rates were four to six times as high as those among participants who did not actively engage in the trial, with similar relative effectiveness.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_vgMw7zq">CONCLUSIONS</head><p xml:id="_dSWzCku"><s xml:id="_cQSTU7Z">In this pragmatic trial of smoking cessation, financial incentives added to free cessation aids resulted in a higher rate of sustained smoking abstinence than free cessation aids alone.</s><s xml:id="_7uAfcsp">Among smokers who received usual care (information and motivational text messages), the addition of free cessation aids or e-cigarettes did not provide a benefit.</s><s xml:id="_4VESyGe">(Funded by the Vitality Institute; ClinicalTrials.gov</s><s xml:id="_7wqRqUY">number, NCT02328794.)</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_9DYS4Kk">A BS TR AC T</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Y22uBzd">A Pragmatic Trial of E-Cigarettes, Incentives, and Drugs for Smoking Cessation</head><p xml:id="_dKB2vgD"><s xml:id="_Dwguy88">A Pr agmatic Trial of Smoking Cessation M ost large U.S. companies offer smoking-cessation programs for their employees, and nearly half of those companies offer financial incentives for employees who successfully stop smoking. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> These benefit designs are motivated by evidence that smoking remains the leading cause of preventable illness and death in the United States <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> and that employees who smoke cost the companies several thousand dollars more per year than nonsmokers. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref></s><s xml:id="_djHFTY2">However, the benefits offered by workplace smoking-cessation programs vary considerably, and there is limited evidence regarding the absolute or comparative effectiveness of these programs.</s></p><p xml:id="_TP54hfK"><s xml:id="_qDNzVvu">Two previous randomized, controlled trials involving employees who were interested in quitting smoking -one that included 878 employees of General Electric 5 and one that included 2538 employees of CVS <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> -showed that financialincentive programs of approximately $800 tripled the rates of abstinence through 6 months as compared with approaches that offered only free access to behavioral-modification programs and informational resources.</s><s xml:id="_HuvBZW7">However, some key questions remained unanswered: How successful would workplace smoking-cessation programs be among all people to whom they were offered (rather than only among smokers who were interested in quitting, as tested in previous trials)?</s><s xml:id="_89JZFFT">How effective would incentives be when added to free nicotine-replacement therapy and pharmacotherapy (i.e., bupropion or varenicline)?</s><s xml:id="_dkjrRSC">And how effective would free electronic cigarettes (e-cigarettes) or free conventional cessation aids be when added to provision of information on smoking cessation and access to motivational text-messaging programs?</s></p><p xml:id="_8v9rFJU"><s xml:id="_GNnevnp">A fourth unanswered question was raised by the CVS trial, in which an $800 reward was compared with an $800 "deposit contract," in which participants deposited $150 that was matched with $650, such that up to $800 was forfeited if the participant did not stop smoking. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref></s><s xml:id="_EFjWYe7">Among smokers who would have accepted either the reward or deposit contract, the deposit program was more than twice as efficacious as the reward program, probably because it leverages loss aversion. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref></s><s xml:id="_THrA6zV">However, because only 13.7% of the participants who were offered deposit contracts chose to participate, the overall effectiveness of this approach was lower than that with standard financial rewards.</s><s xml:id="_dAMVk9J">Might deposit contracts that are funded in advance without participant contributions, but from which money is removed if abstinence milestones are not met, achieve higher engagement and smoking-cessation rates by leveraging loss aversion among a broader pool of participants? <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref></s><s xml:id="_drUEuP8">We conducted the current trial to address these four key questions.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_cVeVW3x">Me thods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_A5jGdzb">Trial Design</head><p xml:id="_Y7UGU8D"><s xml:id="_4ABfNkD">We conducted a randomized, controlled trial that compared five approaches to smoking cessation: usual care and four interventions designed to promote sustained smoking abstinence.</s><s xml:id="_WtsbuTS">The trial was designed to be highly pragmatic on the basis of PRECIS-2 criteria. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref></s><s xml:id="_DgQZ3ED">The protocol (available with the full text of this article at NEJM.org) was approved by the institutional review board at the University of Pennsylvania.</s><s xml:id="_n8dHfWe">The first author wrote the first draft of the manuscript and vouches for the accuracy and completeness of the data and analyses and for the fidelity of the trial to the protocol.</s><s xml:id="_UdPDb4S">NJOY provided the e-cigarettes (including battery sticks, USB charger, and the full range of flavor chambers) at no cost but had no role in the design or conduct of the trial, the analysis of the data, the writing or review of the manuscript, or the decision to submit it for publication.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_TPRdyrB">Trial Population</head><p xml:id="_YarTtB9"><s xml:id="_JmXr4KC">Eligible participants were employees and their spouses at 54 companies that used Vitality wellness programs, were at least 18 years old, and reported current smoking on a health risk assessment within the previous year.</s><s xml:id="_9wMXUbt">Enrollment proceeded in two phases, which differed slightly in the way participants were informed about the trial (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1</ref> in the Supplementary Appendix, available at NEJM.org).</s><s xml:id="_XcWRubU">In the first phase, 2229 eligible participants from 9 companies were identified in October 2014.</s><s xml:id="_dwfzqM3">In the second phase, 3902 eligible participants from 45 companies were identified in November 2015.</s><s xml:id="_D2r3DKx">The second phase was launched because the target sample size was not met in the first phase.</s></p><p xml:id="_UE87vHA"><s xml:id="_eC9naR5">Before enrollment, potential participants were contacted by email on at least four occasions to disclose that they had been selected for trial participation, to provide them with information on how to opt out (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1</ref> in the Supplementary Appendix), and to guide them through enrollment through the Way to Health Web-based research portal. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref></s><s xml:id="_4Xwpnvj">If participants did not opt out by notifying trial staff before the enrollment date, they were enrolled (a design known as "opt-out consent") and were randomly assigned to an intervention or to usual care (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_cWsj7Fb">Participants were then sent brief descriptions of their assigned intervention and were encouraged to sign into the Web portal to learn more about their smoking-cessation intervention, their assigned quit date, the processes for submitting urine and blood samples and receiving compensation for submission of those samples, and, when applicable, the processes for ordering cessation aids and receiving incentives for smoking abstinence.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_cYSezrC">Randomization and Interventions</head><p xml:id="_5KdaxPd"><s xml:id="_C56UjHk">Participants were randomly assigned on an individual basis to one of five groups, with stratification according to employer.</s><s xml:id="_8m4kpNv">Randomization probabilities were unbalanced to achieve the best possible power to test the eight betweengroup contrasts of primary interest (see below).</s><s xml:id="_EyGRJ5P">At the time of randomization, all participants were notified of usual-care resources that they could access through the wellness websites for their companies, including information regard-ing the health benefits of smoking cessation, strategies to promote cessation, and the opportunity to register for the SmokeFreeTXT program of the National Cancer Institute, a free textmessaging program that gives encouragement, advice, and tips for stopping smoking.</s><s xml:id="_kccDjvb">All materials were in English.</s></p><p xml:id="_EDe5SdG"><s xml:id="_xDfpphH">Participants in the intervention groups were also notified that they were being offered one of four additional programs: free cessation aids, which included all forms of nicotine-replacement therapy, bupropion or varenicline, and -for participants who reported lack of success with initial standard therapy -free NJOY e-cigarettes (including battery sticks, a USB charger, and up to 20 chambers with 1.0 to 1.5% nicotine per week in participants' chosen flavors); free e-cigarettes without the requirement that standard therapies had first been tried; a reward incentive worth $600 for sustained smoking abstinence, plus all options in the free cessation aids group; or a deposit account worth $600, redeemable by participants who become abstinent, plus all free cessation aids.</s><s xml:id="_d2wqTG6">In relevant groups, e-cigarettes and nicotine-replacement therapy (patches, gum, and lozenges) could be ordered directly through the trial website at no cost.</s><s xml:id="_wHCu2Ux">Costs of prescription medicines obtained through a physician were reimbursable through the website.</s><s xml:id="_YPqSqN2">Use of all products was free until 6 months after the quit date.</s><s xml:id="_knAXuZM">6006 Were enrolled and underwent randomization 1191 (19.8%)</s><s xml:id="_JS6NWUw">Logged on to the trial website over course of the program (were "engaged") 6131 Known smokers were informed of the trial 125 Declined to participate 813 Were assigned to the usual care group 129 (15.9%)</s><s xml:id="_M6EvfYA">Were engaged 1208 Were assigned to the redeemable deposit plus free cessation aids group 277 (22.9%)</s><s xml:id="_akJjDDY">Were engaged 1199 Were assigned to the free e-cigarettes group 253 (21.1%)</s><s xml:id="_D2a59vB">Were engaged 1588 Were assigned to the free cessation aids group 277 (17.4%)</s><s xml:id="_DWA43S7">Were engaged 1198 Were assigned to the reward incentives plus free cessation aids group 255 (21.3%)</s><s xml:id="_g3uudvp">Were engaged The New England Journal of Medicine is produced by NEJM Group, a division of the Massachusetts Medical Society.</s><s xml:id="_fGWDHwy">Downloaded from nejm.org at University of Iowa--Iowa City on July 28, 2025.</s><s xml:id="_rKFk7aT">Copyright © 2018 Massachusetts Medical Society.</s><s xml:id="_3GcTTth">All rights reserved, including those for text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_yEbykeM">A Pr agmatic Trial of Smoking Cessation</head><p xml:id="_VDg8jxn"><s xml:id="_tJdJSaW">Participants assigned to the rewards and redeemable deposit groups were eligible to earn $100, $200, and $300 if at 1, 3, and 6 months after the quit date, respectively, they submitted blood or urine samples for testing and the samples were negative for nicotine metabolites (see the Supplemental Methods section and Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S2</ref> in the Supplementary Appendix).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_kSFdzj2">Outcomes</head><p xml:id="_PKzsZea"><s xml:id="_mDas9En">The primary outcome was sustained smoking abstinence for 6 months after the target quit date. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref></s><s xml:id="_r3CmgKH">Achievement of sustained abstinence required that participants report smoking cessation on a survey at 1, 3, and 6 months and have biochemical confirmation of smoking cessation at each time point. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref></s><s xml:id="_2gqYzHX">A urine sample with a cotinine level of less than 20 ng per milliliter was the primary method for confirming abstinence biochemically. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref></s><s xml:id="_UV5p9hx">For users of nicotine-replacement therapy, we accepted a urine sample with an anabasine level of less than 3 ng per milliliter or a blood carboxyhemoglobin level of less than 4%. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref></s><s xml:id="_APRandW">For users of e-cigarettes who had a positive cotinine sample (cotinine level ≥20 ng per milliliter), we also accepted a blood carboxyhemoglobin level of less than 4%. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref></s><s xml:id="_AnwZkrT">All samples were evaluated by laboratory technicians who were unaware of the group assignments.</s><s xml:id="_dTQgz6J">If participants did not report abstinence, they were not instructed to submit samples for biochemical confirmation.</s><s xml:id="_RVnHKGk">Because the definition of the primary outcome was biochemically confirmed sustained abstinence, participants who did not submit samples were coded as not having met the primary outcome. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref></s><s xml:id="_pRJScvW">Secondary outcomes included the point prevalence for quitting at 1 month and sustained abstinence rates at 3 months and 12 months (i.e., 6 months after the end of the assigned intervention).</s><s xml:id="_zdmkANB">Participants were compensated for submitting urine and blood samples as shown in Table <ref type="table">S1</ref> in the Supplementary Appendix.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_ySphK4W">Statistical Analysis</head><p xml:id="_8dkPPnC"><s xml:id="_kz98EyJ">We used logistic regression to compare rates of sustained abstinence among groups, with adjustment for the phase of enrollment.</s><s xml:id="_7f6Z885">Because many employers offer cessation aids as part of their benefit designs, we designated the free cessation aids group as the primary comparator against which each of the other four groups was to be compared.</s><s xml:id="_EzDmXRf">We determined a priori that four other between-group contrasts were important; this yielded eight total contrasts (see below).</s><s xml:id="_kb2qCe4">We estimated that enrollment of 6000 participants would provide 80% power to detect an increase of at least 5 percentage points above an assumed abstinence rate of 2.5% in the free cessation aids group.</s><s xml:id="_HKzQMcE">This calculation was based on our prespecified plan to use the Holm method to handle multiple comparisons by sequentially testing the significance of each contrast against progressively less restrictive alpha levels, maintaining the family-wise type I error rate. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref></s><s xml:id="_d8aF2md">rimary analyses were conducted with the intention-to-treat approach such that all participants who underwent randomization were included.</s><s xml:id="_uDxf62h">We also conducted secondary analyses among the "engaged" cohort, which was defined as all participants in the intention-to-treat population who accessed the trial website at least once.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_3RTt5d4">R esult s</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_QQcQh4G">Participants</head><p xml:id="_2Rz6uY3"><s xml:id="_xH3EPTD">Overall, 6131 employees from 54 companies were invited to enroll.</s><s xml:id="_nN7UdUm">Of these, 125 employees (2.0%) opted out, and the remaining 6006 underwent randomization and were included in the primary analyses (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_JFn3Zb5">The demographic and smoking-related characteristics of the participants were balanced across the groups (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_yhheUtB">The engaged cohort (1191 participants [19.8%]) were included in secondary analyses.</s><s xml:id="_W9dFtJj">Participants in the engaged cohort were more highly educated, more motivated to quit, more likely to be female, and more often users of e-cigarettes currently or in the past than participants who did not actively engage in the trial.</s><s xml:id="_WEaQcuM">The 54 companies were of different sizes and in different sectors of the economy and contributed a median of 59 participants (interquartile range, 38 to 130) to the trial.</s><s xml:id="_7tXdPvj">Further details are provided in Tables S2 through S4 in the Supplementary Appendix.</s></p><p xml:id="_T3Rkc73"><s xml:id="_B7y5xGE">At each time point, fewer than 10% of the participants reported that they had quit.</s><s xml:id="_XNHRruD">A large majority of participants who reported abstinence submitted confirmatory samples at each time point, and the proportions of participants who submitted samples that confirmed abstinence were similar across groups (</s></p><p xml:id="_YHWRVQd"><s xml:id="_dQU6xzt">Table S5 in the Supplementary Appendix).</s><s xml:id="_NmcEGS6">The New England Journal of Medicine is produced by NEJM Group, a division of the Massachusetts Medical Society.</s><s xml:id="_35JhjGE">Downloaded from nejm.org at University of Iowa--Iowa City on July 28, 2025.</s><s xml:id="_6EzzCyW">Copyright © 2018 Massachusetts Medical Society.</s><s xml:id="_XC8HMrW">All rights reserved, including those for text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_6Vthq2H">Primary Analyses</head><p xml:id="_XptC8ea"><s xml:id="_WbWKUuS">Overall, sustained smoking abstinence through 6 months after the target quit date was biochemically confirmed in 80 participants (1.3%) who underwent randomization (95% confidence interval [CI], 1.0 to 1.6).</s><s xml:id="_nGswPhd">Sustained abstinence rates through 6 months were 0.1% in the usual-care group (95% CI, 0 to 0.3), 0.5% in the free cessation aids group (95% CI, 0.2 to 0.9), 1.0% in the free e-cigarettes group (95% CI, 0.4 to 1.6), 2.0% in the rewards group (95% CI, 1.2 to 2.8), and 2.9% in the redeemable deposit group (95% CI, 2.0 to 3.8).</s><s xml:id="_kW3BhBg">Three between-group comparisons met the criteria for statistical significance with respect to sustained abstinence: redeemable deposits were superior to free cessation aids (odds ratio, 5.77; 95% CI, 2.66 to 12.50; P&lt;0.001), rewards were superior to free cessation aids (odds ratio, 3.95; 95% CI, 1.77 to 8.84; P = 0.006), and redeemable deposits were superior to free e-cigarettes (odds ratio, 2.95; 95% CI, 1.52 to 5.71; P = 0.008).</s><s xml:id="_wRgSj4R">The sustained abstinence rates in the free e-cigarettes group, free cessation aids group, and usual-care group did not differ significantly,</s></p><p xml:id="_uByXawY"><s xml:id="_yV23VYB">Characteristic Usual Care (N = 813) Free Cessation Aids (N = 1588) Free E-Cigarettes (N = 1199) Rewards plus Free Cessation Aids (N = 1198) Redeemable Deposit plus Free Cessation Aids (N = 1208) Median age (IQR) -yr 44.5 (35.6-53.7)</s><s xml:id="_Hr3V3k8">43.4 (34.5-52.7)</s><s xml:id="_X5cwYzY">43.9 (35.0-52.8)</s><s xml:id="_MgTPuFX">44.0 (34.6-52.6)</s><s xml:id="_T6HeHJN">44.1 (34.4-54.0)</s><s xml:id="_TCAVgPx">Level of education -no.</s><s xml:id="_ySfFX69">(%) † Did not complete high school 28 (3.4) 65 (4.1) 46 (3.8) 37 (3.1) 34 (2.8) High-school graduate 228 (28.0) 439 (27.6) 311 (25.9) 305 (25.5) 327 (27.1)</s><s xml:id="_GUPtAr4">Some college 309 (38.0) 511 (32.2) 441 (36.8) 447 (37.3) 425 (35.2) College degree 146 (18.0) 369 (23.2) 254 (21.2) 257 (21.5) 285 (23.6)</s><s xml:id="_MMPaM7G">Postgraduate degree 37 (4.6) 74 (4.7) 51 (4.3) 54 (4.5) 41 (3.4) Missing data 65 (8.0) 130 (8.2) 96 (8.0) 98 (8.2) 96 (7.9) Female sex -no.</s><s xml:id="_K6K4qKS">(%) ‡ 415 (51.0) 832 (52.4) 597 (49.8) 614 (51.3) 618 (51.</s><s xml:id="_MWxBHWP">-reported desire to quit -no.</s><s xml:id="_bNQxYNS">(%) No plan to quit 74 (9.1) 147 (9.3) 109 (9.1) 120 (10.0) 100 (8.3) Want to quit later 490 (60.3) 994 (62.6) 754 (62.9) 725 (60.5) 744 (61.6)</s><s xml:id="_PzBhEr8">Want to quit, need help 238 (29.3) 425 (26.8) 315 (26.3) 333 (27.8) 344 (28.5)</s><s xml:id="_bBH98U2">Missing data 11 (1.4) 22 (1.4) 21 (1.8) 20 (1.7) 20 (1.7) E-cigarette use -no.</s><s xml:id="_sx4bxxX">(%) Never 317 (39.0) 677 (42.6) 461 (38.4) 495 (41.3) 452 (37.4) Past but not current use 169 (20.8) 367 (23.1) 299 (24.9) 271 (22.6) 294 (24.3)</s><s xml:id="_YnVc524">Current use 78 (9.6) 185 (11.6) 131 (10.9) 120 (10.0) 139 (11.5)</s><s xml:id="_7vSfHWx">Missing data 249 (30.6) 359 (22.6) 308 (25.7) 312 (26.0) 323 (26.7)</s></p><p xml:id="_yhRTdsy"><s xml:id="_WdvyWXS">* There were no significant differences among the groups in the participants' demographic and smoking-related characteristics, except as noted.</s><s xml:id="_XMjanrJ">Percentages may not total 100 because of rounding.</s><s xml:id="_CWvpQzU">Data were missing as follows: age for 1 participant, duration of smoking for 69 participants, and cigarette consumption for 182 participants.</s><s xml:id="_EsVWzsy">IQR denotes interquartile range.</s><s xml:id="_aNhy5Qp">† Among participants who reported their level of education, the P value for comparison of responses across trial groups was 0.049.</s><s xml:id="_5PCR8nq">‡ One participant in the redeemable deposit group did not indicate sex.</s></p><p xml:id="_Ybvtbgk"><s xml:id="_FrGmxFy">Table 1.</s><s xml:id="_tycb6SH">Characteristics of the Participants According to Trial Group.*</s><s xml:id="_bDxGjQ9">The New England Journal of Medicine is produced by NEJM Group, a division of the Massachusetts Medical Society.</s><s xml:id="_Qhhr7Qs">Downloaded from nejm.org at University of Iowa--Iowa City on July 28, 2025.</s><s xml:id="_jNtTFsN">Copyright © 2018 Massachusetts Medical Society.</s><s xml:id="_HySXuyD">All rights reserved, including those for text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies.</s></p><p xml:id="_4N85JHZ"><s xml:id="_w7u58sC">A Pr agmatic Trial of Smoking Cessation and redeemable deposits were not significantly superior to rewards (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> and Table <ref type="table">2</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_fCaqGDU">There were minor differences in the rates of smoking abstinence between the two enrollment phases, but the effects of the interventions on the primary outcome did not differ between the phases (P = 0.11 for interaction).</s><s xml:id="_FXnntg6">Additional information is provided in Figure <ref type="figure">S3</ref> and Tables S6 through S8 in the Supplementary Appendix.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Qe7Z7xY">Analyses in the Engaged Cohort</head><p xml:id="_NRF5PEr"><s xml:id="_kRPCnWs">Among participants in the engaged cohort, the rate of sustained smoking abstinence through 6 months after the target quit date was 0.7% in the usual-care group (95% CI, 0 to 2.1), 2.9% in the free cessation aids group (95% CI, 0.9 to 4.9), 4.8% in the free e-cigarettes group (95% CI, 2.1 to 7.4), 9.5% in the rewards group (95% CI, 5.9 to 13.1), and 12.7% in the redeemable deposit group (95% CI, 8.8 to 16.7).</s><s xml:id="_BCKDFBQ">The three betweengroup comparisons that met the criteria for statistical significance in the intention-to-treat population were also significant in the engaged cohort: redeemable deposits were superior to free cessation aids (odds ratio, 4.85; 95% CI, 2.21 to 10.67; P&lt;0.001) and to free e-cigarettes (odds ratio, 2.93; 95% CI, 1.49 to 5.79; P = 0.01), and rewards were superior to free cessation aids (odds ratio, 3.47; 95% CI, 1.53 to 7.87; P = 0.02) (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>, and Table <ref type="table">S6</ref> in the Supplementary Appendix).</s><s xml:id="_fyT5X4w">Again, cessation rates in the groups that had access to free e-cigarettes, free cessation aids, or usual care did not differ significantly (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_a9dJKph">There were no significant differences in engagement rates between phases (Table <ref type="table">S9</ref> in the Supplementary Appendix).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_KypZ4F6">Abstinence at Other Time Points</head><p xml:id="_VXYV6cE"><s xml:id="_y4bUdq5">The general patterns observed among the groups in 6-month outcomes were seen at the 1-month, 3-month, and 12-month time points both in the intention-to-treat population and in the engaged cohort (Fig. <ref type="figure">S4</ref> in the Supplementary Appendix).</s><s xml:id="_hvkYWaE">Approximately half the participants who had sustained abstinence through 6 months also had negative biochemical assays at 12 months (6 months after the interventions had ended).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_N6rArYy">Cost Analyses</head><p xml:id="_8u22XDw"><s xml:id="_Eph9ebM">Average costs per participant assigned to each intervention were lowest in the usual-care group ($0.82) and highest in the redeemable deposit group ($100.96).</s><s xml:id="_gAqZKKV">The overall cost of each program per participant who was abstinent for 6 months was lower in the rewards and redeemable deposit groups than in the free e-cigarettes or free cessation aids groups (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>, and Table <ref type="table">S10</ref> in the Supplementary Appendix).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_jusvzKy">Discussion</head><p xml:id="_6NuwRHQ"><s xml:id="_NemNrjD">This trial of five approaches to smoking cessation among employees of 54 U.S. companies yielded several important results.</s><s xml:id="_fN2yTg5">First, by using opt-out consent, we found that the quit rates that are likely to be achieved with workplace smoking-cessation programs were lower than would be surmised on the basis of previous workplace studies that measured cessation among smokers who were motivated to quit. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19</ref></s><s xml:id="_rcHk6XG">Specifically, the most effective intervention in the current trial produced a 6-month sustained abstinence rate of only 2.9% among all smokers to whom the program was offered.</s><s xml:id="_jExZU5q">Although these results suggest limits to the benefits of workplace smoking-cessation programs, the incentive programs may still be useful for both employers Sustained Abstinence (% of participants) 20 10 15 5 0 Usual Care Free Cessation Aids Free E-Cigarettes Rewards plus Free Cessation Aids Redeemable Deposit plus Free Cessation Aids Intention-to-treat population (N=6006) Engaged cohort (N=1191) 0.1 0.5 1.0 2.0 2.9 0.7 2.9 4.8 9.5 12.7 The New England Journal of Medicine is produced by NEJM Group, a division of the Massachusetts Medical Society.</s><s xml:id="_VD7bZdA">Downloaded from nejm.org at University of Iowa--Iowa City on July 28, 2025.</s><s xml:id="_d2fTucf">Copyright © 2018 Massachusetts Medical Society.</s><s xml:id="_SpKejN5">All rights reserved, including those for text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies.</s></p><p xml:id="_eP2Z4kg"><s xml:id="_h63WSAz">and employees because most costs are incurred only if employees successfully quit, and the overall costs are favorable in comparison with the extra costs of employing smokers. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref></s><s xml:id="_MzhR5zs">n contrast to these results among all participants, the most effective intervention produced a 12.7% sustained abstinence rate among participants who actively engaged in the trial and were more motivated to quit.</s><s xml:id="_z8KSFa2">This rate is consistent with previous trials of workplace incentive programs that showed cessation rates of 15 to 16% among smokers who enrolled with an opt-in approach. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref></s><s xml:id="_ubhn4TY">he second major finding of this trial was that among smokers who had access to informa-tion about smoking cessation and the opportunity to sign up for motivational text messages, neither the additional offer of free e-cigarettes nor the additional offer of free first-line cessation aids (plus e-cigarettes if those failed) significantly improved rates of smoking abstinence.</s><s xml:id="_J3TfKjT">The lack of effectiveness of free cessation aids is important, because this practice is a cornerstone of many employers' wellness programs. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref></s><s xml:id="_JmACn83">his trial also provided large-scale, randomized evidence that the offer of free e-cigarettes does not result in higher rates of sustained abstinence than traditional smoking-cessation aids and does not increase abstinence rates among smokers who are also offered information and</s></p><p xml:id="_XAXP4yW"><s xml:id="_UqDV5SQ">Comparator Groups Adjusted Difference Raw P Value † Holm Threshold ‡ Adjusted P Value § Intention-to-treat population ¶ Redeemable deposit vs. free cessation aids 2.4±0.5 0.000009 0.00625 &lt;0.001 Rewards vs. free cessation aids 1.5±0.4</s><s xml:id="_BcNKZxP">0.0008 0.0071 0.006 Redeemable deposit vs. free e-cigarettes 1.9±0.6 0.0013 0.0083 0.008 Free e-cigarettes vs. usual care 0.9±0.3</s><s xml:id="_8bWSxPv">0.040 0.01 0.20 Rewards vs. free e-cigarettes 1.0±0.5 0.048 0.0125 0.20 Free e-cigarettes vs. free cessation aids 0.5±0.3</s><s xml:id="_wqjgfMb">0.144 0.0167 0.43 Redeemable deposit vs. rewards 0.9±0.6 0.158 0.025 0.43 Free cessation aids vs. usual care 0.4±0.2</s><s xml:id="_th8H65m">0.165 0.05 0.43 Engaged cohort‖ Redeemable deposit vs. free cessation aids 9.8±2.3</s><s xml:id="_KBxNhwy">0.00009 0.00625 &lt;0.001 Redeemable deposit vs. free e-cigarettes 8.0±2.4 0.0019 0.0071 0.01 Rewards vs. free cessation aids 6.5±2.1 0.0029 0.0083 0.02 Rewards vs. free e-cigarettes 4.7±2.3</s><s xml:id="_NUtxXPM">0.043 0.01 0.21 Free e-cigarettes vs. usual care 4.0±1.5 0.067 0.0125 0.27 Free cessation aids vs. usual care 2.2±1.3 0.184 0.0167 0.55 Redeemable deposit vs. rewards 3.3±2.7 0.232 0.025 0.55 Free e-cigarettes vs. free cessation aids 1.8±1.7 0.279 0.05 0.55 * Plus-minus values are percentage points ±SE.</s></p><p xml:id="_p9Saunh"><s xml:id="_eUGqdxH">† The reported P values were estimated with the use of contrasts from a single logistic-regression model adjusted for trial phase (1 or 2).</s><s xml:id="_8pFgag2">The rows are ordered by the lowest to highest P value.</s><s xml:id="_3Se6CQp">‡ The Holm threshold for statistical significance was calculated sequentially to allow for eight separate contrasts. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref></s><s xml:id="_kdscvZm">The threshold for each row is calculated as 0.05 ÷ n remaining contrasts; for example, the first contrast is 0.05 ÷ 8 = 0.00625.</s><s xml:id="_f7e4sa9">§ The sequential Holm approach was implemented to test the significance of the eight prespecified contrasts.</s></p><p xml:id="_JMwEnum"><s xml:id="_9FPnm3k">Unadjusted P values from each contrast are ordered from smallest to largest, and then adjusted by multiplying each P value by the number of remaining contrasts.</s><s xml:id="_MYVU7Zu">For example, the smallest P value is multiplied by 8 to obtain the adjusted P value.</s><s xml:id="_uDSdP4z">In addition, any adjusted P value smaller than the previous one is replaced by the previous adjusted value.</s><s xml:id="_9BmVgnC">¶ The intention-to-treat population consists of 6006 employees who were identified as eligible and did not opt out of the trial.</s><s xml:id="_Q8Ky4Uu">‖ The engaged cohort consists of 1191 participants who logged on to the trial website at least once.</s></p><p xml:id="_aeQmtyF"><s xml:id="_RQFvg48">Table 2. Holm Sequential Analysis of Efficacy for Eight Prespecified Trial-Group Comparisons.*</s><s xml:id="_sgWqGMS">The New England Journal of Medicine is produced by NEJM Group, a division of the Massachusetts Medical Society.</s><s xml:id="_PGzqG3H">Downloaded from nejm.org at University of Iowa--Iowa City on July 28, 2025.</s><s xml:id="_GxXRPUe">Copyright © 2018 Massachusetts Medical Society.</s><s xml:id="_GCx4ChH">All rights reserved, including those for text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies.</s></p><p xml:id="_HsFHuGb"><s xml:id="_djuAq6w">motivational text messages.</s><s xml:id="_3uGaqgz">This pragmatic trial, which provided free e-cigarettes or any free cessation aids, did not assess the efficacy of the actual use (as compared with the offer) of these products.</s><s xml:id="_dzwCKsP">However, a study of efficacy would have to ensure that all participants in each group used those products, and would therefore not reflect real-world conditions.</s><s xml:id="_hRK7SKj">The current trial also did not assess the possibility that offering free e-cigarettes may reduce the harms associated with conventional smoking. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23</ref></s><s xml:id="_mFQjYdw">However, a recent expert report suggested that e-cigarettes would reduce short-term adverse health effects only if they led to complete cessation of the use of combustible cigarettes. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24</ref></s><s xml:id="_xnR34Xs">hird, this trial showed that financial incentives promoted smoking cessation even when free pharmacologic cessation aids and nicotinereplacement therapies were routinely available.</s><s xml:id="_MUMXxk6">These results, considered alongside those from previous trials, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> suggest that incentives at least triple cessation rates regardless of whether free cessation aids are offered concomitantly.</s></p><p xml:id="_d5XSYGj"><s xml:id="_FGEZ3jb">Finally, we found that redeemable deposit contracts were not significantly more effective than actuarially equivalent incentive programs structured as pure rewards.</s><s xml:id="_yskMdHX">This result did not confirm our hypothesis that deposit accounts, in which incentives that have already been granted would be lost if participants continued smoking, would be more effective than an intervention in which the same incentive was portrayed as a pure gain.</s><s xml:id="_jEPfTNr">Nonetheless, the observation that framing the incentives as already earned and at risk of being lost (loss framing) produced nominally higher rates of quitting at nominally lower costs per quit may motivate employers who are planning incentive programs to consider the use of loss framing.</s></p><p xml:id="_5ZGhcrV"><s xml:id="_waHeUjA">These findings should be interpreted in the context of the limitations of the trial.</s><s xml:id="_E5E8GjU">First, because of the pragmatic recruitment strategy in which opt-out consent was used across 54 different companies, our characterization of the demographic and smoking-related characteristics of the participants who underwent randomization is limited.</s><s xml:id="_CVDXzfH">For example, unlike the CVS trial, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> in which we found that the participants' income modified the effects of reward-based and depositbased incentive programs, 25 similar analyses were not possible in the current trial.</s><s xml:id="_8AGB8cu">Second, most participants were considered to be ongoing smokers if they did not respond to surveys asking whether they had quit.</s><s xml:id="_sUyYARp">This approach was used in previous trials <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> and is unlikely to have biased the comparisons of different interventions, because rates of biochemical confirmation of participant-reported abstinence were similar across groups.</s><s xml:id="_uHtAU4W">Still, it is possible that absolute rates of quitting may have been somewhat higher across groups than reported here.</s><s xml:id="_y9K5b43">In addition, the response rates to the 1-month survey were higher among participants assigned to the financial-incentives groups than among participants in the other groups.</s><s xml:id="_uzn32t5">The incentives may have increased the likelihood of survey response among those who had quit smoking, given that a response was necessary for the participant to be eligible for the financial rewards.</s><s xml:id="_A7ZReMv">Third, we did not compare free access to e-cigarettes with free access to conventional cessation aids without any option for e-cigarettes.</s><s xml:id="_x7RNuEE">Nonetheless, the observation of greater e-cigarette use in the free e-cigarette group than in the free cessation aids group (Table <ref type="table">S11</ref> in the Supplementary Appendix), coupled with the absence of benefit of free e-cigarettes versus no intervention, supports the conclusion that offering free e-cigarettes does not promote smoking cessation.</s></p><p xml:id="_Qt3xuGW"><s xml:id="_3NzDba6">This trial also had several strengths.</s><s xml:id="_wjEgsbJ">In addition to being twice as large as other trials of</s></p><p xml:id="_q4TXqNH"><s xml:id="_kAZbQy3">Trial Group Average Cost across Participants † Cost per Successful Quit U.S. $ (95% CI) U.S. $ Usual care ‡ 0.82 (0.29-1.67) 700.00 Free cessation aids 39.55 (26.76-56.30)</s><s xml:id="_9T3pkjj">7,797.52</s><s xml:id="_37j49Sg">Free e-cigarettes 54.01 (36.09-77.82)</s><s xml:id="_6p98ceY">5,416.33</s><s xml:id="_2kkuZFx">Rewards 72.65 (51.94-98.85)</s><s xml:id="_9acSCMj">3,623.13</s><s xml:id="_ch4By83">Redeemable deposit 100.96 (76.82-128.80)</s><s xml:id="_nCTdC7F">3,461.47</s></p><p xml:id="_WhfAks5"><s xml:id="_HnnNEfV">* Costs include the prices of incentives disbursed, evaluation of blood and urine samples, payments for samples submitted, and orders for nicotinereplacement therapy, cessation-promoting medications, and e-cigarettes.</s><s xml:id="_ZA5rWyC">† A two-part model was used to estimate average costs.</s><s xml:id="_RKfJrcF">The first part (for participants with zero expenditures) was estimated with the use of a probit model, and the second part (for participants with nonzero expenditures) was estimated with the use of a generalized linear model with a gamma family and log link.</s><s xml:id="_JkWcRWE">The model was adjusted for the trial phase in which the participant was enrolled.</s><s xml:id="_MqR87wK">Confidence intervals for average costs were generated with the use of bias-corrected bootstrap methods.</s><s xml:id="_Gg66gSg">‡ Only one participant in the usual-care group quit smoking.</s></p><p xml:id="_wenZPbx"><s xml:id="_neH36py">Table 3.</s><s xml:id="_7hAQ5TA">Average Cost among All Participants and Cost per Successful Quit.*</s><s xml:id="_fznuptB">The New England Journal of Medicine is produced by NEJM Group, a division of the Massachusetts Medical Society.</s><s xml:id="_sB8WWUZ">Downloaded from nejm.org at University of Iowa--Iowa City on July 28, 2025.</s><s xml:id="_QRRj8dX">Copyright © 2018 Massachusetts Medical Society.</s><s xml:id="_4BWDF98">All rights reserved, including those for text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_gcffPDY"><s xml:id="_qDa2Xeb">Figure 1.</s><s xml:id="_KM4ueBR">Eligibility and Randomization.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>2 )</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_DwhDEqQ"><s xml:id="_8e7356Y">Median duration of smoking (IQR) -yr 18.0 (10.0-29.0)</s><s xml:id="_8cvd894">18.0 (10.0-29.0)</s><s xml:id="_eFNC3nP">20.0 (10.0-27.0)</s><s xml:id="_wu6ERBg">18.0 (10.0-28.0)</s><s xml:id="_6ACwWST">18.0 (10.0-28.8)</s><s xml:id="_6CZkkHK">Median no. of cigarettes smoked per day (IQR) 10.0 (5.0-15.0)</s><s xml:id="_Ys59BsN">10.0 (5.0-15.0)</s><s xml:id="_E4wwAAt">10.0 (5.0-15.0)</s><s xml:id="_RVW72Ja">10.0 (5.0-15.0)</s><s xml:id="_TeDbZTe">10.0 (5.0-15.0)</s><s xml:id="_yvAVvef">Participant</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 .The</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_fMBejZ7"><s xml:id="_ukRGGRt">Figure 2. Sustained Smoking Abstinence at 6 Months after the Target Quit Date.</s><s xml:id="_aPWB9cR">Estimates were adjusted for the phase (1 or 2) of enrollment.</s><s xml:id="_QrhxP65">The engaged cohort consists of participants who logged on to the trial website at least once.</s><s xml:id="_gmFfgea">I bars indicate 95% confidence intervals.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p xml:id="_ZHm2Fbr"><s xml:id="_g7g88QF">n engl j med 378;24 nejm.org</s><s xml:id="_xnEHBBW">June 14, 2018</s></p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_uZDRZ97"><p xml:id="_GaHk3eT"><s xml:id="_b9UDmGM">A Pr agmatic Trial of Smoking Cessation incentives <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref>, or e-cigarettes <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27</ref> for smoking cessation, its conduct among 54 different companies suggests that the results may be generalizable to most workplace settings.</s><s xml:id="_5fMd7an">In addition, since the trial was conducted with the use of an opt-out consent design, the results reveal the real-world effects employers can expect when offering these programs to all employees who smoke.</s></p><p xml:id="_UdTRMcR"><s xml:id="_cg5xdRa">In summary, this trial showed that among unselected smokers, workplace smoking-cessation programs yielded low rates of smoking abstinence and that offering free cessation aids or free e-cigarettes did not increase abstinence among smokers who were given access to information and motivational text messages.</s><s xml:id="_NvxmpYT">In contrast, programs that offered financial incentives tripled the rates of smoking cessation, reduced employers' costs per successful quit as compared with programs that offered cessation aids alone, and yielded total costs that compared favorably with the costs of employing smokers. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref></s><s xml:id="_PE8bw8C">pported by a grant from the Vitality Institute to the University of Pennsylvania Center for Health Incentives and Behavioral Economics.</s></p><p xml:id="_mTZ94r5"><s xml:id="_29RTvQh">Disclosure forms provided by the authors are available with the full text of this article at NEJM.org.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Willis</forename><surname>Towers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Watson</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ww/9780199540884.013.247112</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.willistowerswatson.com/en/insights/2017/01/full-report-2016-21st-annual-willis-towers-watson-best-practices-in-health-care-employer-survey" />
		<title level="m" xml:id="_vUKVbbD">Full report: 2016 21st annual Willis Towers Watson Best Practices in Health Care Employer Survey -high-performance insights</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017-01-04">January 4, 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Willis Towers Watson. Full report: 2016 21st annual Willis Towers Watson Best Practices in Health Care Employer Survey -high-performance insights. January 4, 2017 (https:/ / www .willistowerswatson .com/ en/ insights/ 2017/ 01/ full-report-2016-21st -annual-willis-towers-watson-best-practices -in-health-care-employer-survey).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_rFRAS3t">Estimation of cigarette smoking-attributable morbidity in the United States</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Rostron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Pechacek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1001/jamainternmed.2014.5219</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_3wRW5EG">JAMA Intern Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">174</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1922" to="1928" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rostron BL, Chang CM, Pechacek TF. Estimation of cigarette smoking-attribut- able morbidity in the United States. JAMA Intern Med 2014; 174: 1922-8.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_KEM7TqT">The preventable causes of death in the United States: comparative risk assessment of dietary, lifestyle, and metabolic risk factors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Danaei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mozaffarian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000058</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_544dwD2">PLoS Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000058</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Danaei G, Ding EL, Mozaffarian D, et al. The preventable causes of death in the United States: comparative risk assessment of dietary, lifestyle, and metabolic risk factors. PLoS Med 2009; 6(4): e1000058.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_GErBsas">Estimating the cost of a smoking employee</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Berman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Crane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Seiber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Munur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2012-050888</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ddmJ7dP">Tob Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="428" to="433" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Berman M, Crane R, Seiber E, Munur M. Estimating the cost of a smoking em- ployee. Tob Control 2014; 23: 428-33.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_5vf3jmb">A randomized, controlled trial of financial incentives for smoking cessation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Volpp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Troxel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Pauly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1056/nejmsa0806819</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_bh9AzQj">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">360</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="699" to="709" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Volpp KG, Troxel AB, Pauly MV, et al. A randomized, controlled trial of financial incentives for smoking cessation. N Engl J Med 2009; 360: 699-709.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_APjSNMQ">Randomized trial of four financial-incentive programs for smoking cessation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Halpern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>French</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Small</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1056/nejmoa1414293</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_wbeNJPF">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">372</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2108" to="2117" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Halpern SD, French B, Small DS, et al. Randomized trial of four financial-incen- tive programs for smoking cessation. N Engl J Med 2015; 372: 2108-17.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_q9DrGrz">Prospect theory: an analysis of decision under risk</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kahneman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tversky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/1914185</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_U4SR6Re">Econometrica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="291" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kahneman D, Tversky A. Prospect theory: an analysis of decision under risk. Econometrica 1979; 47: 263-91.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_rxKY8rQ">Commitment contracts as a way to health</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Halpern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Asch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Volpp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmj.e522</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_sHUCpzM">BMJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">344</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e522</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Halpern SD, Asch DA, Volpp KG. Com- mitment contracts as a way to health. BMJ 2012; 344: e522.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_CtSXamm">The PRECIS-2 tool: designing trials that are fit for purpose</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Loudon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Treweek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Sullivan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Donnan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Thorpe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zwarenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmj.h2147</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_MCWCMaX">BMJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">350</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2147</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Loudon K, Treweek S, Sullivan F, Donnan P, Thorpe KE, Zwarenstein M. The PRECIS-2 tool: designing trials that are fit for purpose. BMJ 2015; 350: h2147.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_8v7XRwy">Individual-versus group-based financial incentives for weight loss: a ran-domized, controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Kullgren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Troxel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Loewenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_RhmJk6d">Ann Intern Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">158</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="505" to="514" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kullgren JT, Troxel AB, Loewenstein G, et al. Individual-versus group-based financial incentives for weight loss: a ran- domized, controlled trial. Ann Intern Med 2013; 158: 505-14.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_NQfb5Tq">Effect of financial incentives to physicians, patients, or both on lipid levels: a randomized clinical trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Asch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Troxel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Stewart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1001/jama.2015.14850</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_vYkXMBd">JAMA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">314</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1926" to="1935" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Asch DA, Troxel AB, Stewart WF, et al. Effect of financial incentives to physicians, patients, or both on lipid levels: a random- ized clinical trial. JAMA 2015; 314: 1926-35.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Cf59neq">Measures of abstinence in clinical trials: issues and recommendations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hughes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Keely</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Niaura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ossip-Klein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Richmond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Swan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/1462220031000070552</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_PQXASDx">Nicotine Tob Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="25" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hughes JR, Keely JP, Niaura RS, Ossip- Klein DJ, Richmond RL, Swan GE. Mea- sures of abstinence in clinical trials: issues and recommendations. Nicotine Tob Res 2003; 5: 13-25.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_UzcESkt">Outcome criteria in smoking cessation trials: proposal for a common standard</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>West</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hajek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Stead</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Stapleton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1360-0443.2004.00995.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_kqNPVCz">Addiction</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="299" to="303" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">West R, Hajek P, Stead L, Stapleton J. Outcome criteria in smoking cessation trials: proposal for a common standard. Addiction 2005; 100: 299-303.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_DpPnaKv">Biochemical verification of tobacco use and cessation</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/14622200210123581</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_F6VbBSp">Nicotine Tob Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="149" to="159" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>SRNT Subcommittee on Biochemical Verification</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">SRNT Subcommittee on Biochemical Verification. Biochemical verification of tobacco use and cessation. Nicotine Tob Res 2002; 4: 149-59.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Yr3WZay">Anabasine and anatabine as biomarkers for tobacco use during nicotine replacement therapy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Jacob</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Iii</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hatsukami</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Severson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Benowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_7jREuEV">Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1668" to="1673" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Jacob P III, Hatsukami D, Severson H, Hall S, Yu L, Benowitz NL. Anabasine and anatabine as biomarkers for tobacco use during nicotine replacement therapy. Can- cer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 2002; 11: 1668-73.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_YmJU78h">Evaluating nicotine levels selection and patterns of electronic cigarette use in a group of &quot;vapers&quot; who had achieved complete substitution of smoking</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Farsalinos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Romagna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tsiapras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kyrzopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Voudris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4137/sart.s12756</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_XKfrrQn">Subst Abuse</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="146" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Farsalinos KE, Romagna G, Tsiapras D, Kyrzopoulos S, Voudris V. Evaluating nico- tine levels selection and patterns of elec- tronic cigarette use in a group of &quot;vapers&quot; who had achieved complete substitution of smoking. Subst Abuse 2013; 7: 139-46.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_EXhfB8y">Carboxyhaemoglobin levels, health and lifestyle perceptions in smokers converting from tobacco cigarettes to electronic cigarettes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Van Staden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Groenewald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Engelbrecht</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Hazelhurst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.7196/samj.6887</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_TwHkeWc">S Afr Med J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="865" to="868" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">van Staden SR, Groenewald M, Engel- brecht R, Becker PJ, Hazelhurst LT. Carboxyhaemoglobin levels, health and lifestyle perceptions in smokers convert- ing from tobacco cigarettes to electronic cigarettes. S Afr Med J 2013; 103: 865-8.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_WA5f5sU">A simple sequentially rejective multiple test procedure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Holm</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_PvzbSk4">Scand J Stat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="70" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Holm S. A simple sequentially rejec- tive multiple test procedure. Scand J Stat 1979; 6: 65-70.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_E2bpttg">Incentives for smoking cessation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Cahill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hartmann-Boyce</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Perera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/14651858.cd004307.pub5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_bcu8r6X">Cochrane Database Syst Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4307</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Cahill K, Hartmann-Boyce J, Perera R. Incentives for smoking cessation. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 2015; 5: CD004307.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_nQfxTkK">Reducing smoking in the US federal workforce: 5-year health and economic impacts from improved cardiovascular disease outcomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Grb</forename><surname>Asay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Homa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Abramsohn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O'</forename><surname>Connor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wang</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0033354917736300</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_BXbwyWf">Public Health Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="646" to="653" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Asay GRB, Homa DM, Abramsohn EM, Xu X, O&apos;Connor EL, Wang G. Reducing smoking in the US federal workforce: 5-year health and economic impacts from improved cardiovascular disease outcomes. Public Health Rep 2017; 132: 646-53.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_6ZPGqJY">From policy to practice: tobacco use cessation for employees in the Veterans Health Administration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Schult</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Kelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Schmunk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Awosika</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/jom.0000000000000720</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_QwM8k5B">J Occup Environ Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="525" to="531" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Schult TM, Kelly Q, Schmunk SK, Awosika ER. From policy to practice: to- bacco use cessation for employees in the Veterans Health Administration. J Occup Environ Med 2016; 58: 525-31.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_mxEXWfN">Incentives, program configuration, and employee uptake of workplace wellness programs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mattke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Batorsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Miles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/jom.0000000000000613</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_4xnaJwT">J Occup Environ Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="30" to="34" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Huang H, Mattke S, Batorsky B, Miles J, Liu H, Taylor E. Incentives, program con- figuration, and employee uptake of work- place wellness programs. J Occup Environ Med 2016; 58: 30-4.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_wayukDB">E-cigarettes and the harm-reduction continuum</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Fairchild</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sung</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bayer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Curran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1056/nejmp1711991</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_8FPVqZp">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">378</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="216" to="219" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Fairchild AL, Sung Lee J, Bayer R, Cur- ran J. E-cigarettes and the harm-reduction continuum. N Engl J Med 2018; 378: 216-9.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1057/s41271-018-0132-1</idno>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_5kPeqgq">Public health consequences of e-cigarettes</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Washington, DC</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>National Academies Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">National Academies of Sciences, Engi- neering, and Medicine. Public health con- sequences of e-cigarettes. Washington, DC: National Academies Press, 2018.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_cUWe6Ge">Heterogeneity in the effects of rewardand deposit-based financial incentives on smoking cessation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Halpern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>French</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Small</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1164/rccm.201601-0108oc</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_CQXYpBJ">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">194</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="981" to="988" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Halpern SD, French B, Small DS, et al. Heterogeneity in the effects of reward- and deposit-based financial incentives on smoking cessation. Am J Respir Crit Care Med 2016; 194: 981-8.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Yqc4JmQ">Electronic cigarettes for smoking cessation: a randomised controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bullen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Howe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Laugesen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0140-6736(13)61842-5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_S4E7tuu">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">382</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1629" to="1637" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bullen C, Howe C, Laugesen M, et al. Electronic cigarettes for smoking cessa- tion: a randomised controlled trial. Lan- cet 2013; 382: 1629-37.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_CkTMGq3">EffiCiency and Safety of an eLectronic cigAreTte (ECLAT) as tobacco cigarettes substitute: a prospective 12-month randomized control design study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Caponnetto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Campagna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Cibella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0066317</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_2CX22fp">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">66317</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Caponnetto P, Campagna D, Cibella F, et al. EffiCiency and Safety of an eLec- tronic cigAreTte (ECLAT) as tobacco ciga- rettes substitute: a prospective 12-month randomized control design study. PLoS One 2013; 8(6): e66317.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
