<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_6PKBnsJ">Social Networks Help Control Hypertension</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Pfizer</orgName>
					<idno type="DOI" subtype="crossref">https://doi.org/10.13039/100004319</idno>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Bristol-Myers Squibb</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">BMS</orgName>
					<idno type="DOI" subtype="crossref">https://doi.org/10.13039/100002491</idno>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Novartis</orgName>
					<idno type="DOI" subtype="crossref">https://doi.org/10.13039/100004336</idno>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Sanofi-Aventis</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">CareFirst Foundation</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Johnson &amp; Johnson</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Bayer</orgName>
					<idno type="DOI" subtype="crossref">https://doi.org/10.13039/100004326</idno>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">CareFirst BlueCross BlueShield Foundation</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">University of Maryland Foundation</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">USMF</orgName>
					<idno type="DOI" subtype="crossref">https://doi.org/10.13039/100001365</idno>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">National Institutes of Health, Bayer</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>PhD, MPH</roleName><forename type="first">Fadia</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Shaya</surname></persName>
							<email>fshaya@rx.umaryland.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>1</label> From the Department of Pharmaceutical Health Services Research , University of Maryland School of Pharmacy , Baltimore , MD ;</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pharmaceutical Health Services Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Maryland School of Pharmacy</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MS</roleName><forename type="first">Viktor</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Chirikov</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>1</label> From the Department of Pharmaceutical Health Services Research , University of Maryland School of Pharmacy , Baltimore , MD ;</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pharmaceutical Health Services Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Maryland School of Pharmacy</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">Daniel</forename><surname>Mullins</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>1</label> From the Department of Pharmaceutical Health Services Research , University of Maryland School of Pharmacy , Baltimore , MD ;</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pharmaceutical Health Services Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Maryland School of Pharmacy</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Jon</forename><surname>Shematek</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>2</label> CareFirst BlueCross BlueShield , Owings Mills , MD ; and the Division of Cardiology ,</note>
								<orgName type="department">Division of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CareFirst BlueCross BlueShield</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Owings Mills</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MPH</roleName><forename type="first">Deleonardo</forename><surname>Howard</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>1</label> From the Department of Pharmaceutical Health Services Research , University of Maryland School of Pharmacy , Baltimore , MD ;</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pharmaceutical Health Services Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Maryland School of Pharmacy</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>RN</roleName><forename type="first">Clyde</forename><surname>Foster</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>1</label> From the Department of Pharmaceutical Health Services Research , University of Maryland School of Pharmacy , Baltimore , MD ;</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pharmaceutical Health Services Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Maryland School of Pharmacy</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Elijah</forename><surname>Saunders</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">University of Maryland School of Medicine , Baltimore , MD Department of Pharmaceutical Health Services Research ,</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pharmaceutical Health Services Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Maryland School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">University of Maryland School of Pharmacy , 220 Arch Street , Room 01-204 , Baltimore , MD 21201</note>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Maryland School of Pharmacy</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>220 Arch Street Room 01-204</addrLine>
									<postCode>21201</postCode>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_456egz6">Social Networks Help Control Hypertension</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">E4C07E93D51C84400230F13959FB5616</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1111/jch.12036</idno>
					<note type="submission">Manuscript received: August 2, 2012; revised: September 25, 2012; accepted: September 26, 2012</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T09:26+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="576.0" lry="773.858"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="576.0" lry="773.858"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="576.0" lry="773.858"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="576.0" lry="773.858"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="576.0" lry="773.858"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="576.0" lry="773.858"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="576.0" lry="773.858"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_E5QtCMb"><p xml:id="_FPMbbbD"><s xml:id="_UjSEnbx">Cardiovascular health disparities continue to pose a major public health problem.</s><s xml:id="_sRaeEwZ">The authors evaluated the effect of education administered within social networks on the improvement of hypertension in 248 African Americans compared with historical controls.</s><s xml:id="_4mPy8ek">Patients formed clusters with peers and attended monthly hypertension education sessions.</s><s xml:id="_q3t2yDh">The authors assessed the likelihood of reaching goal below predefined systolic blood pressure (SBP) and diastolic blood pressure (DBP) thresholds as well as the absolute reduction in SBP and DBP, controlling for diabetes, smoking, baseline hypertension, and demographics.</s><s xml:id="_xSf4Na7">The intervention group was more likely to have ever reached treatment goal at 12-month follow-up (odds ratio, 1.72; P=.11).</s><s xml:id="_YrzK4KM">At 18-month follow-up, the Maryland Cardiovascular Disease Promotion Program group had a statistically significant larger drop in SBP ()4.82 mm Hg, P&lt;.0001) and DBP ()3.37 mm Hg, P=.01) than the control group.</s><s xml:id="_6z7AKZ4">The clustering of patients in social networks around hypertension education has a positive impact on the management of hypertension in minority populations and may help address cardiovascular health disparities.</s><s xml:id="_AzX35c4">J Clin Hypertens (Greenwich).</s><s xml:id="_ZYz2P82">2013; 15:34-40.</s><s xml:id="_TWRF2WG">Ó2012 Wiley Periodicals, Inc.</s></p><p xml:id="_RNySuV5"><s xml:id="_YX3fbAp">Cardiovascular disease is the leading cause of death for Americans, <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> and its effect on mortality and morbidity places an especially heavy burden on African Americans.</s><s xml:id="_nfQxMnC">A recent report by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) on health disparities and inequalities concludes that hypertension prevalence in non-Hispanic blacks is 45% higher than in non-Hispanic whites. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> In addition, the report highlights persistent significant racial disparities in access to healthcare services.</s><s xml:id="_uVKXKwy">Given these statistics, it is not surprising that black men and women have the highest rates of cardiovascular-related mortality across all 10year age strata spanning 45 to 84 years among all ethnic groups. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> For example, black men younger than 75 had a 48% higher mortality rate due to coronary heart disease and a 95% higher mortality rate due to stroke than their white counterparts.</s><s xml:id="_3wUKz4n">In women younger than 75, cardiovascular-related racial disparities are even more pronounced, with a 95% higher mortality rate due coronary heart disease and a 125% higher mortality rate due to stroke among black women compared with white women. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref></s><s xml:id="_ef6hvGX">he need for a scientific exploration of these cardiovascular health issues among minorities is central to the national commitment to eliminate health disparities illustrated in the overarching goals of the Healthy People 2020 national framework. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref></s><s xml:id="_8yfCeS3">Evaluating how racial disparities in health can be addressed, the authors of CDC's Health Disparities and Inequalities report underline that ''premature deaths attributable to CHD and stroke among black adults indicate the need for evidence-based interventions to reduce the prevalence of risk factors for cardiovascular disease.'' <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref></s><s xml:id="_P2UtsNT">s well, they recommend increasing community awareness of disparities.</s><s xml:id="_ptNn3bQ">In fact, a literature review recently identified community-based participatory research as one of the best practices to tackle health disparities in African American communities. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref></s><s xml:id="_bn8EHVS">ne such interventional approach to reduce health disparities among blacks may be the leveraging of existing social networks.</s><s xml:id="_MgcJPz4">Built on the principles of trust and reciprocity, social networks facilitate the exchange of life-enhancing resources such as healthrelated information and social connections.</s><s xml:id="_EGMyZjM">They confirm the link between people's connectedness and their health.</s><s xml:id="_y7KD8VC">Studies have shown that decisions regarding health behavior are often made by groups of people connected to one another rather than by isolated persons. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref></s><s xml:id="_7XGKAGs">Furthermore, social networks trigger support mechanisms resulting in increased levels of selfefficacy, which is instrumental in maintaining healthy lifestyles and adherence to treatment. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref></s><s xml:id="_qJyfPDC">7]<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> Further exploring the effect of social networks in minority populations is even more relevant given that black diabetic patients were found to rely more heavily on social networks to manage their disease than those who were white. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref></s><s xml:id="_DQAfbgt">Additionally, in another study, African American men depended on family members as the most trusted health information source, despite health professionals' being the most common source of information. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref></s><s xml:id="_dc2SGhP">he beneficial effect of social network-based interventional programs has been well-documented in cardiovascular disease management.</s><s xml:id="_akHwXUM">Little social support was found to be associated with a 50% to 100% higher risk of coronary heart disease events in both healthy patients and in those with established disease. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref></s><s xml:id="_AEmjrP6">Additionally, participation in clubs and meetings, a larger number of siblings, and seeing friends more frequently were associated with lower systolic pressure <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref> and higher awareness of hypertension. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref></s><s xml:id="_s3qTTSJ">Furthermore, social networks might have led to lower rates of cardiovascular-related events <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref> and mortality. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref></s><s xml:id="_hQjahX6">A systematic review affiliated with the Mayo Clinic has even recommended considering the lack of social support network as a risk factor for subsequent morbidity and mortality after a myocardial infarction. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref></s><s xml:id="_6NEqKF8">imilar to the examples mentioned above, collective dynamics of social networks could play an important role in improving hypertension and in controlling other cardiovascular disease risk factors in minorities.</s><s xml:id="_h3VeZ94">Founded on the principles of social networking, this study aimed at providing preliminary findings for a full-fledged outreach, education, intervention, and research evaluation program.</s><s xml:id="_uFZVcry">The target of the program, called the Maryland CVD Promotion Program (MVP), was to improve awareness, health-seeking behavior, and outcomes of cardiovascular disease in African American communities in the larger Baltimore metropolitan area, who have significantly higher rates of risk factors that contribute to heart disease when compared with whites in either city or state and 30% higher death rates for heart disease than the state and national rates. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref></s><s xml:id="_VXFsjNP">In alignment with the Healthy People strategy and in addition to national initiatives, local public health agencies such as the Maryland Department of Health and Mental Hygiene <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref> and the Baltimore City Health Department <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref> have encouraged projects in health disparities research.</s><s xml:id="_c9mmc2J">Further, various community programs are ongoing.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_nHt6BSp">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_aWWvDEJ">Study Design</head><p xml:id="_sRQwY7N"><s xml:id="_bX8k5se">The study was based on the ''train the trainer'' approach and the community health worker (CHW) model. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19</ref></s><s xml:id="_W9pkKqv">Each patient recruited to the intervention group (MVP) was asked to reach out and extend an invitation to two relatives or friends eligible to participate to enroll in the program.</s><s xml:id="_Fu57csX">Subsequently, these two patients each recruited two patients of their own.</s><s xml:id="_kHdzeSm">This created a cluster of 7 patients in total, who were followed up as a team.</s><s xml:id="_4brvxsk">These patients were referred to or were enrolled from the primary care practices at the University of Maryland (Figure).</s><s xml:id="_72nMy7y">Patients presented to the research center with hypertension as indicated by current drug treatment for hypertension or a history of hypertension or severe risk factors for uncontrolled hypertension, eg, gastroenteritis, muscle spasm, allergy, backache, hernia, and otitis media.</s><s xml:id="_c3nBazQ">The control group was a retrospective cohort consisting of a random sample of a pool of patients who had previously enrolled in the control arm of a closely related randomized clinical trial from 2008 (Baltimore Partnership to Educate and Achieve Control of Hypertension [BPTEACH]) examining the effect of education to physicians and patients on improving blood pressure (BP) control in a mostly African American population in Baltimore. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref></s><s xml:id="_RXUVwMt">Patients in the BPTEACH trial were enrolled individually and had been followed up as such.</s></p><p xml:id="_vPeu6jY"><s xml:id="_J6McwSZ">The patients in the MVP group formed small groups or clusters and attended monthly education sessions focusing on disease education, prevention, and treatment of hypertension.</s><s xml:id="_Qmw3w9V">They received comprehensive hypertension education instruction from the clinical research education nurse and were trained to effectively share the information among one another in their cluster.</s><s xml:id="_m8mJJxt">The premise is that this process of interaction and engagement could improve hypertension awareness, education, and treatment in individual patients and in their communities.</s><s xml:id="_mcXaV67">In addition, patients also received a full 3-part hypertension education manual, which included additional inserts related to cholesterol, diabetes, medication, weight control, exercise, nutrition, and the Dietary Approach to Stop Hypertension (DASH) diet.</s><s xml:id="_kmm7vfX">The contents of the manual were discussed with the patients by the clinical research education nurse and were used as a reference guide for patients between education sessions.</s><s xml:id="_FDaMN5J">Patients in the retrospective cohort control group hadn't received hypertension counseling and had received usual care only.</s><s xml:id="_CqfDxKq">Written informed consent was obtained from all participating patients.</s><s xml:id="_dZrKbvU">The study was approved by the institutional review board of the University of Maryland, Baltimore.</s><s xml:id="_95TgVgN">The study was conducted between May 2008 and August 2011 at the University of Maryland in Baltimore.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_fAXBXM3">Inclusion and Exclusion Criteria</head><p xml:id="_TsXKhjs"><s xml:id="_g2EMfmc">Patients were excluded if they had previously been admitted for hypertensive emergency, malignant hypertension, or severe uncontrolled hypertension and if they were younger than 18, were pregnant, or had no hypertension.</s><s xml:id="_tRrkShE">Patients were considered to be hypertensive if any of the following conditions were met: patients without diabetes had systolic BP (SBP) 140 mm Hg or ⁄ and diastolic BP (DBP) 90 mm Hg and those with diabetes had SBP 130 mm Hg or ⁄ and DBP 80 mm Hg.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_fjFdVQg">Baseline Assessment</head><p xml:id="_fQvznTa"><s xml:id="_rjeMjyB">Prior to the start of the education sessions, all studyrelated data such as study consent, baseline or followup BPs, patient surveys, and demographic information of the patient were captured.</s><s xml:id="_cHtK6fB">BP was measured with patients in a sitting position, using electronically calibrated BP monitors.</s><s xml:id="_5qzPCWd">Baseline BP was obtained by the clinical research nurse.</s><s xml:id="_xJhhhNA">The average of two measurements was recorded.</s><s xml:id="_pgJ3DAx">Patients completed a medical history form, a health assessment questionnaire (measured with the Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information [PROMIS HAQ] <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> ), and a high BP survey.</s><s xml:id="_X73Nc4T">The information obtained from these forms included demographic variables (age, sex, and race), smoking status, and the diagnosis of diabetes.</s><s xml:id="_UaE6X5b">Patients' BP was captured at a variety of events including hypertension education sessions, patient consultation visits, health fairs, and various community functions throughout the Baltimore metropolitan area.</s><s xml:id="_z5JYQGP">Local organizations that MVP had partnered with, such as the Maryland Transit Authority (MTA), the League for People With Disabilities, Baltimore City Golf Association, Baltimore County Golfing, and various churches within the community, provided BP screenings and helped enroll patients.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Jyr6B6T">Follow-Up and Assessment of Outcomes</head><p xml:id="_6cqvZyc"><s xml:id="_FnudyyG">The primary outcome of the study was reaching hypertension treatment goal.</s><s xml:id="_Ch4tFV7">For patients with diabetes, the treatment goal was to achieve BP &lt;130 ⁄ 80 mm Hg, and for patients without diabetes, the treatment goal was to achieve BP &lt;140 ⁄ 90 mm Hg.</s><s xml:id="_XrZn6MU">Patients underwent follow-up every 3 months for up to 18 months and BP was measured during each follow-up.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Shd5jDW">Statistical Analysis</head><p xml:id="_mzCNK2E"><s xml:id="_MUD73Ft">Descriptive analysis was performed to compare the characteristics of the patients in the intervention and control groups.</s><s xml:id="_5MCfKPj">Ordinary least squares analyses were conducted to assess the association between the intervention and absolute mean reduction in BP, controlling for group assignment, diabetes, smoking, baseline hypertension, and demographics.</s><s xml:id="_EY2SZyX">Binary logistic regression models at follow-up of up to 6, 12, and 18 months were built to assess the likelihood of ever reaching treatment goal after baseline.</s><s xml:id="_u3dER68">An alternative model with the same control variables assessed the likelihood of reaching goal more than once through follow-up after baseline.</s><s xml:id="_csBQfbj">Furthermore, time-to-event analyses were carried out to allow for differential follow-up time between the control and the intervention groups.</s><s xml:id="_96pNKjc">Given that the intervention group consisted of social clusters of participants by design, the models were further adjusted for cluster effects.</s><s xml:id="_kYNc9bf">All analyses were conducted using SAS version 9.2 (SAS Institute, Cary, NC).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_XQAc5de">RESULTS</head><p xml:id="_s2M7BzS"><s xml:id="_Ztn5bWS">The study participants were evenly distributed into 265 participants per study group.</s><s xml:id="_eWe32cb">Since we were mostly interested in the effect of the social network intervention in African Americans, we restricted our analysis to that population and therefore excluded 25 patients of other race.</s><s xml:id="_XVdNJrg">Additionally, 9 and 55 patients were excluded from the MVP group and historic control group analyses, respectively, because they had dropped out immediately after their baseline measurement visit.</s><s xml:id="_z4z8Jvz">In a sensitivity analysis, we modeled the African American patient population (N=505) where missing observations were imputed by substituting in the last observation carried forward.</s><s xml:id="_fpsVzHY">Overall, analyses in the nonimputed model gave more conservative results than those in the imputed model and we report results of the former.</s></p><p xml:id="_kG3xByD"><s xml:id="_7UVz6FG">Participants in the MVP group were younger and there were more men than in the control group (Table <ref type="table">I</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_Jv9Nhjt">Furthermore, the MVP group had lower mean systolic and diastolic BP at baseline and had a longer follow-up period.</s><s xml:id="_HZhc8UM">Evaluating the endpoints of the study (Table <ref type="table">II</ref>), the MVP group had lower systolic and diastolic BP at their last follow-up, on average, but showed a lower proportion of patients (not statistically significant) who had achieved goal at last follow-up (10.9% vs 15.0%, P=.19) than the control group.</s><s xml:id="_ZhHaPNF">The MVP group had a greater proportion of patients who ever achieved goal (25.0%</s><s xml:id="_8SsNt4u">vs 18.7%, P=. 19), but this was not statistically significant.</s><s xml:id="_vXjzBd2">Furthermore, tracking the repeated attainment of goal</s></p><p xml:id="_nQWEy4M"><s xml:id="_NpEsVe4">TABLE I. Baseline Patient Characteristics in African Americans Control Group MVP Group P Value N=193 N=248 Age, y (SD) 55.1 (13.9) 48.0 (13.1) &lt;.0001 Men, No. (%) 70 (36) 189 (76) &lt;.0001 Diabetes, No. (%) 67 (35) 72 (29) .20 Smoking, No. (%) 37 (19) 63 (25) .12</s><s xml:id="_95Mk66H">Baseline SBP, mm Hg (SD) 150.9 (18.7) 146.0 (10.5) &lt;.01 Baseline DBP, mm Hg (SD) 90.4 (11.3) 87.9 (8.2) .01</s><s xml:id="_MU3Mwad">Goal achieved at baseline, No. (%) 12 (6) 3 (1.2) .01</s><s xml:id="_rdGVcXn">Overall follow-up time, d (SD) 291 (143) 457 (279) &lt;.0001 Abbreviations: DBP, diastolic blood pressure; SBP, systolic blood pressure; SD, standard deviation.</s></p><p xml:id="_R4yM4gR"><s xml:id="_sn5eTxp">over time, the MVP group had a significantly higher proportion of patients who had achieved goal more than once (8.9% vs 0.5%, P&lt;.0001).</s></p><p xml:id="_GMTgUBJ"><s xml:id="_zYJHbbM">Unadjusted time-to-event curves of ever achieving goal after baseline showed differences in the probability of ever achieving goal during the course of the study.</s><s xml:id="_JchhwWM">The MVP group had a higher likelihood of achieving goal at up to about 400 days of follow-up, after which the probability curves crossed, leading to a nonsignificant difference between the time-to-event curves (log-rank P=.85).</s><s xml:id="_9dyUPvH">Unadjusted time-to-event curves of achieving goal more than once after baseline, however, highlighted the finding that the MVP group reached second goal more frequently than did the control group (P=.04).</s></p><p xml:id="_VbbQRtA"><s xml:id="_xpmsNRM">Examining the absolute mean change in SBP between the two groups in African Americans (Table <ref type="table">III</ref>), controlling for baseline BP measurements and patient characteristics, we found that the MVP group had an increasingly higher mean drop in DBP over time compared with baseline, with )1.70 mm Hg (P=.16) at 6 months, )4.47 mm Hg (P=.001) at 12 months, and )4.82 mm Hg (P=.001) at 18 months of follow-up compared with the control group.</s><s xml:id="_yUYyzS6">Higher baseline SBP was associated with a significant reduction in mean SBP over time within the range of )0.43 to )0.58 mm Hg for every 1-mm Hg increase in baseline SBP (P&lt;.0001).</s></p><p xml:id="_KhsEdWh"><s xml:id="_trWSYbr">Decreases in DBP were also greater among African Americans in the MVP cohort compared with the control group (Table <ref type="table">III</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_feehVm6">The relative change in DBP from baseline in the MVP compared with the control group was )1.42 mm Hg (P=.11) at 6 months, )3.02 mm Hg (P=.01) at 12 months, and )3.37 mm Hg (P=.01) at 18 months of follow-up.</s><s xml:id="_RufnKvk">Higher baseline DBP was associated with a significant</s></p><p xml:id="_VWdDZwx"><s xml:id="_Z3dVUxg">TABLE II.</s><s xml:id="_HqBzt6J">Endpoints Evaluation (N=441) Control Group MVP Group P Value N=193 N=248 Systolic BP at last follow-up, mm Hg (SD) 150.2 (19.9) 143.8 (7.2) &lt;.0001 Diastolic BP at last follow-up, mm Hg (SD) 87.5 (14.2) 84.2 (6.5) .001</s><s xml:id="_YNzpRQj">Reached goal at last follow-up, No. (%) 29 (15.0)</s><s xml:id="_mMuryU7">27 (10.9)</s><s xml:id="_4DtVwPQ">.19</s><s xml:id="_mK5fZxp">Ever achieved goal, No. (%) 36 (18.7) 62 (25.0) .11</s><s xml:id="_KqaaAnC">By 6 months, No. (%) 11 (5.7) 24 (9.7) .13</s><s xml:id="_N2yQ83Z">By 12 months, No. (%) 25 (13.0)</s><s xml:id="_rCmTHc4">47 (19.0) .09</s><s xml:id="_S88NrVU">By 18 months, No. (%) 36 (18.7) 56 (22.6) .31</s><s xml:id="_2e6bkBJ">By 24 months, No. (%) 36 (18.7) 60 (24.2) .16</s><s xml:id="_WXtaDj6">Reached goal more than once, No (%) 1 (0.5) 22 (8.9) &lt;.0001</s><s xml:id="_gcQnGCT">By 6 months, No. (%) 0 (0) 0 (0) -By 12 months, No. (%) 1 (0.5) 5 (2.1) .18</s><s xml:id="_B25mrZA">By 18 months, No. (%) 1 (0.5) 16 (6.5)</s><s xml:id="_rhegMEh">.001</s><s xml:id="_KtJ5smm">By 24 months, No. (%) 1 (0.5) 19 (7.7) .001</s></p><p xml:id="_zSxJ62A"><s xml:id="_m4rvMpm">TABLE III.</s><s xml:id="_Pr35nN7">Regression Model for Absolute Mean Drop in SBP and DBP (mm Hg) Over Time in African Americans (N=441) At 6 Months At 12 Months At 18 Months Change, mm Hg P Value Change, mm Hg P Value Change, mm Hg P Value Mean reduction in SBP MVP Group )1.70 .16</s><s xml:id="_qmfUBsd">)4.47 a .001</s><s xml:id="_G5gUy8k">)4.82 a .001</s><s xml:id="_4T7wMjZ">Baseline SBP )0.43 a &lt;.0001 )0.52 a &lt;.0001 )0.58 a &lt;.0001 Baseline DBP 0.06 .36</s><s xml:id="_rCnbNbU">)0.11 .18</s><s xml:id="_XurCbhh">)0.08 .30</s><s xml:id="_gPNFCyy">Men )0.02 .98 0.77 .54</s><s xml:id="_RygmhxM">0.91 .48</s><s xml:id="_meHUC22">Age &lt;39 y Reference Age 40-64 y 0.27 .79</s><s xml:id="_NQvYGfV">1.16 .31</s><s xml:id="_xYaFxq4">0.66 .57</s><s xml:id="_kgByhrp">Age 65+ y 1.86 .27</s><s xml:id="_tQnjKbT">0.43 .84</s><s xml:id="_DwnFXne">1.30 .54</s><s xml:id="_mP7Uytb">Diabetes )1.48 .24</s><s xml:id="_tCDy9z4">)1.77 .21</s><s xml:id="_qfX5Kw3">)0.39 .80</s><s xml:id="_QwzZz4s">Smoker )0.74 .58</s><s xml:id="_Z3hDqyX">)2.22 .16</s><s xml:id="_55YgtuU">)0.29 .87</s><s xml:id="_ZGvtSqC">Mean reduction in DBP MVP Group )1.42 .11</s><s xml:id="_Ap8qjnG">)3.02 a .01</s><s xml:id="_Wg8qhUt">)3.37 a .01</s><s xml:id="_mvbsxmH">Baseline SBP 0.03 .37 0.10 a .03</s><s xml:id="_uJjpetf">0.13 a .01</s><s xml:id="_gskYPXY">Baseline DBP )0.33 a &lt;.0001 )0.66 a &lt;.0001 )0.70 a &lt;.0001 Men 0.35 .66</s><s xml:id="_WCQf3Pr">1.09 .37 0.90 .48</s><s xml:id="_Ee4D6QV">Age &lt;39 y Reference Age 40-64 y 1.01 .20 0.07 0.95 )0.63 .59</s><s xml:id="_rBgzJfu">Age 65+ y )0.61 .62 )4.28 a 0.01 )5.79 a .001</s><s xml:id="_ET66qjn">Diabetes )0.09 .89</s><s xml:id="_vrmPVAs">)0.36 0.69 )0.40 .66</s><s xml:id="_jkDFJck">Smoker )0.34 .70</s><s xml:id="_cTeuKzZ">)0.81 0.40 )0.28 .80 a Statistically significant at .05 level.</s></p><p xml:id="_dcDUJTS"><s xml:id="_wSvT5KG">reduction in mean DBP over time within the range of )0.33 to )0.70 mm Hg for every 1-mm Hg increase in baseline DBP (P&lt;.001).</s><s xml:id="_naa24nw">Patients in the 65-year-old group had a significant reduction in DBP, with )4.28 mm Hg (P=.01) and )5.79 mm Hg (P&lt;.01) at 12 and 18 months, respectively.</s><s xml:id="_DsEghzZ">We constructed binary logistic models for ever reaching the joint SBP ⁄ DBP therapeutic goal and more than once for up to 6, 12, and 18 months of followup (Table <ref type="table">IV</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_4m2xjTb">After controlling for confounders, the MVP group had 1.51 higher odds (P=.45) of ever reaching the joint therapeutic goal at up to 6 months after baseline, 1.72 higher odds (P=.11) at up to 12 months, and 1.42 higher odds (P=.20) at up to 18 months.</s><s xml:id="_zE9nF2D">Consistently during the follow-up, we found that every 1-mm Hg increase in baseline SBP was associated with about 3% to 5% lower odds of ever achieving goal.</s><s xml:id="_3HFDpeq">Likewise, participants with diabetes, compared with those without diabetes, had 80% to 95% lower odds of ever achieving goal.</s><s xml:id="_S7YTcCK">Participants aged 40 to 64 years had about 50% lower odds of achieving goal at 12 months (odds ratio [OR], 0.53; P=.08) and 18 months (OR,0.50;</s><s xml:id="_CSmkXsX">P=.04) of follow-up than participants in the 18-to 39-year-old group.</s><s xml:id="_Yj5HvH8">Binary logistic models pointed to a significantly higher likelihood for reaching goal more than once for the MVP group at up to 18 months (OR, 13.2; P=.03) (not shown).</s><s xml:id="_tVUMZyY">Due to decreasing observations with increased length of follow-up, the estimates of the models for more than one goal achieved (which is correlated with length of follow-up) should, however, be interpreted with caution.</s></p><p xml:id="_fDh8u23"><s xml:id="_UjTabAZ">In Cox proportional hazard time-to-event analyses accounting for differential follow-up time, the MVP group was as likely to ever achieve goal as the control group (hazard ratio [HR], 1.01; P=.96).</s><s xml:id="_3a7fTHG">Patients with higher baseline SBP (HR, 0.97; P=.01) in the 40-to 64-year-old group (HR, 0.59; P=.05, compared with the 18-to 39-year-old group), those with diabetes (HR, 0.19; P&lt;.0001), and smokers (HR=0.56,</s><s xml:id="_XTjJU4G">P=.03) had a lower likelihood of achieving goal.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_eX2EThE">DISCUSSION</head><p xml:id="_R3vH5Rq"><s xml:id="_ERjgpa3">Since the study used a random sample pool of patients from a previous trial to create its control group, it is subject to several limitations.</s><s xml:id="_rrSqT9Y">Although we controlled for important demographics and clinical characteristics, the fact that the MVP group was generally younger might have biased our results away from the null.</s><s xml:id="_BpVYPxj">On the other hand, having more men in the MVP group might have biased our results toward the null.</s><s xml:id="_rTpBpFF">Even though this was not statistically significantly, men were consistently less likely to reach goal than women in our study.</s><s xml:id="_wTwwC5f">This finding supports the general literature showing sex disparities in health primary and secondary prevention. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23</ref></s><s xml:id="_eRQEcFt">Another possible limitation is that we did not control for medication use in patients.</s><s xml:id="_VuAdXfW">The possibility of bias away from the null due to a change in prescribing patterns, in view of the retrospective cohort design, however, should be deemed minimal as the observation windows of the two groups were less than a year apart and that no major practice guidelines had changed in between.</s></p><p xml:id="_3ZhACJX"><s xml:id="_yQKqQTp">The use of a complex observational design employing a retrospective control group was driven by the authors' goal to efficiently generate a hypothesis, the testing of which could be implemented in a future major trial.</s><s xml:id="_Vmevsvq">Despite the biases accruing from utilizing a historical cohort and not recording possibly important covariates such as socioeconomic status or education, it should be noted that the patients in the MVP arm and in the control group come from a relatively homogeneous African American population pool from urban Baltimore and it could be a safe assumption to make that they share similar demographic and clinical characteristics.</s><s xml:id="_qpqxj9X">Moreover, more than half of the patients in the retrospective control group, as part of the BPTEACH trial, had been randomized to a study arm in which their treating physicians had attended a series of in-depth physician educational lectures on hypertension management.</s><s xml:id="_vRJKpNB">Patients in the BPTEACH trial who received usual care had an average reduction in SBP of 4.1 mm Hg or 2.6 mm Hg at 6 months of</s></p><p xml:id="_HGbDrA5"><s xml:id="_amKUR8p">TABLE IV.</s><s xml:id="_kSk5Uxw">Binary Logit Model for Ever Attaining Joint SBP ⁄ DBP Goal up to 6, 12, and 18 Months After Baseline in African Americans (N=441) 6 Months 12 Months 18 Months OR P Value OR P Value OR P Value MVP Group 1.51 .45</s><s xml:id="_CBjcG56">1.72 .11</s><s xml:id="_MDJtD8k">1.42 .20 Baseline SBP 0.95 a .04</s><s xml:id="_uBMCKuK">0.97 a .04</s><s xml:id="_pV8qWNe">0.96 a .01</s><s xml:id="_zsqGYVS">Baseline DBP 0.96 a .02</s><s xml:id="_hFakmFn">1.00 .84</s><s xml:id="_at6BsHM">1.02 .35</s><s xml:id="_pGQ8mAt">Men 0.68 .38 0.68 .19</s><s xml:id="_VkhJASf">0.70 .16</s><s xml:id="_YYAncpn">Age &lt;39 y Reference Age 40-64 y 0.62 .31</s><s xml:id="_SNvxxYd">0.53 b .08 0.50 a .04</s><s xml:id="_rCxMEyZ">Age, 65+ y 0.31 .16</s><s xml:id="_dPmA9Md">0.93 .89</s><s xml:id="_w256haQ">1.12 .81</s><s xml:id="_Xg49zU8">Diabetes 0.05 a .01</s><s xml:id="_3Gf73VZ">0.20 a .01</s><s xml:id="_7TeTtzJ">0.18 a &lt;.0001 Smoker 0.65 .35</s><s xml:id="_ZmJ4GKU">0.64 .24</s><s xml:id="_CtvA4B4">0.73 .34</s><s xml:id="_mz4MuMU">Abbreviations: BP, blood pressure; DBP, diastolic blood pressure; MVP, Maryland Cardiovascular Disease Promotion Program; OR, odds ratio; SBP, systolic blood pressure.</s><s xml:id="_pBymAgc">a Significant at .05 level.</s><s xml:id="_n7GQeT7">b Significant at .10 level.</s></p><p xml:id="_2mVxdCm"><s xml:id="_2MGjRZr">follow-up, depending on whether their physicians attended physician education seminars or not, respectively. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref></s><s xml:id="_fVNQ7s8">For comparison, the arm in which patients but not physicians received hypertension education, not in social networks, had an average reduction in SBP of 4.6 mm Hg at 6 months of follow-up, which is a greater SBP reduction compared with the usual care arm.</s><s xml:id="_yKuRNtR">We could extrapolate the findings from this study (a difference of 1.70 mm Hg in the average reduction in SBP at 6 months between patients who received hypertension education clustered around social networks and those who had received only usual care but whose physicians might also have received continuing hypertension education) and compare them with those from BPTEACH.</s><s xml:id="_UDRn4mC">A hypothesis could be formed that the individual effect of social networks on top of hypertension education alone was about 1 mm Hg of additional SBP reduction by month 6, although not statistically significantly.</s><s xml:id="_KzskQr9">As evidenced by our findings, however, the effect of social networks on hypertension management could be increasing over the following 12 months.</s><s xml:id="_XTT2g3w">Given that high BP varies over time in individuals due to nonclinical reasons such as environmental or physical or other stressors, it is possible that patients might have reached goal between follow-up visits.</s><s xml:id="_7WEjTKX">The study was not designed to capture those BP fluctuations.</s><s xml:id="_J6TSEAk">Measuring reduction in BP against a clinical threshold as specified in our study could possibly be better analyzed by taking into account the frequency of meeting that threshold.</s><s xml:id="_eCre4vF">Although the robustness of our models for measuring goal attainment more than once could be improved, it brings to light the possibility that the MVP program could be considered effective in mediating cardiovascular health-changing behavior by capitalizing on the positive dynamics of interactions within social networks.</s></p><p xml:id="_XGhsdv7"><s xml:id="_HhBP5zc">Although the MVP group was as likely to ever achieve goal as the control group overall, the results of the binary logistic models highlight a trend for participants in the MVP group to be more likely to achieve goal, especially for up to 12 months of followup.</s><s xml:id="_XGYQyHR">This may suggest that the effect of the social network intervention may wear off over time when not sustained with enabling factors, such as improved access to care, eg, through health insurance coverage.</s><s xml:id="_5pUAK2r">This idea is further supported by evidence from the regression models analyzing absolute mean change in SBP, which indicate that the MVP group had sustained mean drop in systolic pressure over time compared with the control group, accounting for the confounding effect of age and sex distributions, baseline BP measurement, and presence of diabetes and smoking status.</s><s xml:id="_8tCnk2g">The MVP group achieved highest reduction in SBP ()4.82 mm Hg) and DBP ()3.37 mm Hg) at 18 months from baseline.</s><s xml:id="_vB2XMCs">The magnitude of such reduction could be deemed clinically relevant as pointed out by previous studies.</s><s xml:id="_wzpSkkA">A meta-analysis of 147 prospective studies found that 10 mm Hg in SBP and 5 mm Hg in DBP were associated with 22% reduction in coronary heart disease and 41% reduction in stroke. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24</ref></s><s xml:id="_G4V7VhU">Other studies have shown that a 1mm Hg decrease in SBP decreased the risk of stroke by 5% even though many of the included studies had baseline SBP &gt;160 mm Hg, while the mean SBP at baseline in the MVP study was 143.7 mm Hg. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_MxfZDV4">CONCLUSIONS</head><p xml:id="_tX7DYPS"><s xml:id="_42BFFgM">The MVP program consolidated the efforts of health providers, payers, academic research institutions, as well as faith and community organizations in addressing cardiovascular health disparities in the Baltimore community.</s><s xml:id="_52kQGdZ">In this study, we report findings generally supportive of the positive impact structuring hypertension education around naturally existing social networks in a population of African Americans in the greater Baltimore metropolitan area.</s><s xml:id="_fHhTb3A">Further studies should capitalize on these findings and explore ways to reinforce ties within social networks, assess their impact on mediating factors such as health knowledge, self-efficacy, and social network indices, and finally measure their impact on intermediate, and if possible, long-term health outcomes such as developing heart disease.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>FIGURE.</head><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_VyFJcdm"><s xml:id="_TQnmcvZ">FIGURE.</s><s xml:id="_PDZa5P8">Study design.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,319.02,76.21,200.88,218.35" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p xml:id="_W3dJs9d"><s xml:id="_VSBhwuA">The Journal of Clinical Hypertension Vol 15 | No 1 | January 2013 Official Journal of the American Society of Hypertension, Inc. Social Networks Help Control Hypertension | Shaya et al. 17517176, 2013, 1, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/jch.12036,</s><s xml:id="_nEKnd5E">Wiley Online Library on [15/02/2025].</s><s xml:id="_NNA8zKK">See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions)</s><s xml:id="_GPSkkKM">on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License</s></p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p xml:id="_Hyjt6ce"><s xml:id="_SJdYFZP">Social Networks Help Control Hypertension | Shaya et al. 17517176, 2013, 1, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/jch.12036,</s><s xml:id="_K8Zp74A">Wiley Online Library on [15/02/2025].</s><s xml:id="_zqBq3WS">See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions)</s><s xml:id="_5KbNJXU">on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License</s></p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xml:id="_PTAm8DK"><p xml:id="_5YhQMtn"><s xml:id="_s8D6k89">Acknowledgments and disclosures: The authors are grateful to the anonymous reviewers for their suggestions that helped improve the presentation of our findings.</s><s xml:id="_krxMkAy">Acknowledgments to <rs type="funder">CareFirst Foundation</rs> for support of this grant.</s><s xml:id="_zK3h7PW"><rs type="person">Dr Shaya</rs> has received research funding from the <rs type="funder">National Institutes of Health, Bayer</rs>, and <rs type="funder">Sanofi-Aventis</rs>.</s><s xml:id="_AMqwcws"><rs type="person">Dr Mullins</rs> has received research funding from <rs type="funder">Bayer</rs> and <rs type="funder">Pfizer</rs>, and has performed consulting for <rs type="funder">Bayer</rs>, <rs type="funder">Bristol-Myers Squibb</rs>, <rs type="funder">Johnson &amp; Johnson</rs>, <rs type="funder">Pfizer</rs>, and <rs type="funder">Novartis</rs>.</s><s xml:id="_SzXjTt3">None of the other investigators have any affiliations or financial involvement that may create conflicts with the material presented in this report.</s><s xml:id="_VxmJMec">The study was supported by a donation through grant support from the <rs type="funder">CareFirst BlueCross BlueShield Foundation</rs> to the <rs type="funder">University of Maryland Foundation</rs>.</s></p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_HDNpV8a">Deaths: preliminary data for 2010</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kenneth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.15620/cdc/174614</idno>
		<ptr target="http://www.cdc.gov/nchs/data/nvsr/nvsr60/nvsr60_04.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_aK62Z57">Natl Vital Stat Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="69" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-06-21">2012. June 21, 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Murphy SL, Xu J, Kenneth D, et al. Deaths: preliminary data for 2010. Natl Vital Stat Rep. 2012;60:1-69. http://www.cdc.gov/nchs/ data/nvsr/nvsr60/nvsr60_04.pdf. Accessed June 21, 2012.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_vRcXGMS">CDC Health Disparities &amp; Inequalities Report</title>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</orgName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ofid/ofv131.60</idno>
		<ptr target="http://www.cdc.gov/minorityhealth/CHDIReport.html" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ue8SXrn">MMWR Surveill Summ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="116" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-06-21">2011. June 21, 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. CDC Health Disparities &amp; Inequalities Report. MMWR Surveill Summ. 2011;60(Suppl):1- 116. http://www.cdc.gov/minorityhealth/CHDIReport.html. Accessed June 21, 2012.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/e371392004-001</idno>
		<ptr target="http://www.cdc.gov/minorityhealth/CHDIReport.html" />
		<title level="m" xml:id="_AQ59bM5">Health Disparities in Coronary Heart Disease and Stroke</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Fact Sheet</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011-06-21">2011. June 21, 2012</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Health Disparities in Coronary Heart Disease and Stroke. Fact Sheet. 2011. http:// www.cdc.gov/minorityhealth/CHDIReport.html. Accessed June 21, 2012.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_CJYJREf">Healthy people: a 2020 vision for the social determinants approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Koh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Piotrowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kumanyika</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1090198111428646</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_aywNFXy">Health Educ Behav</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="551" to="557" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Koh HK, Piotrowski JJ, Kumanyika S, et al. Healthy people: a 2020 vision for the social determinants approach. Health Educ Behav. 2011;38:551-557.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_5f4Yj5D">Partnerships for health in the African American community: moving toward community-based participatory research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Parrill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kennedy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_VAnh59y">J Cult Divers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="150" to="154" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Parrill R, Kennedy BR. Partnerships for health in the African Ameri- can community: moving toward community-based participatory research. J Cult Divers. 2011;18:150-154.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_xdRnRFT">Social networks and health</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Christakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1146/annurev.soc.34.040507.134601</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_tZfdQfb">Annu Rev Sociol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="405" to="429" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Smith K, Christakis N. Social networks and health. Annu Rev Sociol. 2008;34:405-429.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_TSev8Rs">Social network and health outcomes among African American cardiac rehabilitation patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Tkatch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Artinian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Abrams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.hrtlng.2010.05.049</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_u9fMCyj">Heart Lung</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="193" to="200" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Tkatch R, Artinian NT, Abrams J, et al. Social network and health outcomes among African American cardiac rehabilitation patients. Heart Lung. 2011;40:193-200.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_BzM3bFZ">The impact of family behaviors and communication patterns on chronic illness outcomes: a systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rosland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Heisler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Piette</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10865-011-9354-4</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_wA3peZu">J Behav Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="221" to="239" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rosland AM, Heisler M, Piette JD. The impact of family behaviors and communication patterns on chronic illness outcomes: a system- atic review. J Behav Med. 2012;35:221-239.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_YruSR9x">Social support among African-American adults with diabetes, Part 2: a review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Ford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Tilley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Mcdonald</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_funF9uc">J Natl Med Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="425" to="432" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ford ME, Tilley BC, McDonald PE. Social support among African- American adults with diabetes, Part 2: a review. J Natl Med Assoc. 1998;90:425-432.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Kctaebq">How does health information influence African American men&apos;s health behavior?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Griffith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ellis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ober Allen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1557988311426910</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Htz6nzv">Am J Mens Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="156" to="163" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Griffith DM, Ellis KR, Ober Allen J. How does health information influence African American men&apos;s health behavior? Am J Mens Health. 2012;6:156-163.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_PvtTvJ6">Social support and coronary heart disease: epidemiologic evidence and implications for treatment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Blumenthal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Babyak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/01.psy.0000188393.73571.0a</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_VzFJssz">Psychosom Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="869" to="878" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lett HS, Blumenthal JA, Babyak MA, et al. Social support and coro- nary heart disease: epidemiologic evidence and implications for treatment. Psychosom Med. 2005;67:869-878.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_2FEmTuJ">Social network and blood pressure: a population study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Bland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Krogh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Winkelstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/00006842-199111000-00002</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_P2pwBA3">Psychosom Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="598" to="607" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bland SH, Krogh V, Winkelstein W, et al. Social network and blood pressure: a population study. Psychosom Med. 1991;53:598-607.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_H4gVKEc">Relationship between social network and hypertension in older people in Spain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Redondo-Sendino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Guallar-Castillon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Banegas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s1885-5857(06)60417-9</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_m8vuu27">Rev Esp Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1294" to="1301" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Redondo-Sendino A, Guallar-Castillon P, Banegas JR, et al. Rela- tionship between social network and hypertension in older people in Spain. Rev Esp Cardiol. 2005;58:1294-1301.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_7nc42ct">Social networks are associated with lower mortality rates among women with suspected coronary disease: the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute-Sponsored Women&apos;s Ischemia Syndrome Evaluation study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Rutledge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Reis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Olson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/01.psy.0000145819.94041.52</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_qAPjHV7">Psychosom Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="882" to="888" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rutledge T, Reis SE, Olson M, et al. Social networks are associated with lower mortality rates among women with suspected coronary disease: the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute-Sponsored Women&apos;s Ischemia Syndrome Evaluation study. Psychosom Med. 2004;66:882-888.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ZbFtexW">A prospective study of social networks in relation to total mortality and cardiovascular disease in men in the USA</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kawachi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Colditz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ascherio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/jech.50.3.245</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_YgWzkZu">J Epidemiol Community Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="245" to="251" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kawachi I, Colditz GA, Ascherio A, et al. A prospective study of social networks in relation to total mortality and cardiovascular dis- ease in men in the USA. J Epidemiol Community Health. 1996;50:245-251.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_gCJMs4t">Social support and its relationship to morbidity and mortality after acute myocardial infarction: systematic overview</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mookadam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Arthur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1001/archinte.164.14.1514</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_8PAsZwa">Arch Intern Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">164</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1514" to="1518" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mookadam F, Arthur HM. Social support and its relationship to morbidity and mortality after acute myocardial infarction: system- atic overview. Arch Intern Med. 2004;164:1514-1518.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_D4eAB9P">Vital Statistics Administration</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/e328342004-009</idno>
		<ptr target="http://vsa.maryland.gov/html/reports.cfm" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009-06-21">2009. June 21, 2012</date>
			<publisher>Maryland Annual Vital Statistics Report</publisher>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Maryland Department of Health and Mental Hygiene</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Maryland Department of Health and Mental Hygiene, Vital Statis- tics Administration. Maryland Annual Vital Statistics Report 2009. http://vsa.maryland.gov/html/reports.cfm. Accessed June 21, 2012.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_ZdH7Qst">Keep the Beat: Agenda to Reduce Cardiovascular Disease Disparities in Baltimore City</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/e310742004-001</idno>
		<ptr target="http://www.baltimorehealth.org/info/2009_04_15.CVD%20Report.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009-04">April 2009. June 21, 2012</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Baltimore City Health Department</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Report</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Baltimore City Health Department. Keep the Beat: Agenda to Reduce Cardiovascular Disease Disparities in Baltimore City. April 2009 Report. http://www.baltimorehealth.org/info/2009_04_15. CVD%20Report.pdf. Accessed June 21, 2012.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_KMqSR4Y">Social networks and social support: implications for natural helper and community level interventions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Israel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/109019818501200106</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_XEfGUDq">Health Educ Q</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="80" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Israel BA. Social networks and social support: implications for natu- ral helper and community level interventions. Health Educ Q. 1985;12:65-80.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_C4XGztB">The Baltimore Partnership to Educate and Achieve Control of Hypertension (The BPTEACH Trial): a randomized trial of the effect of education on improving blood pressure control in a largely African American population</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Shaya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Khanna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1751-7176.2011.00477.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_4St2aVD">J Clin Hypertens</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="563" to="570" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<pubPlace>Greenwich)</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Johnson W, Shaya FT, Khanna N, et al. The Baltimore Partnership to Educate and Achieve Control of Hypertension (The BPTEACH Trial): a randomized trial of the effect of education on improving blood pressure control in a largely African American population. J Clin Hypertens (Greenwich). 2011;13:563-570.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_f9k7bhb">The Stanford Health Assessment Questionnaire: dimensions and practical applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bruce</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Fries</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/1477-7525-1-20</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_N58wJRc">Health Qual Life Outcomes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">20</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bruce B, Fries JF. The Stanford Health Assessment Questionnaire: dimensions and practical applications. Health Qual Life Outcomes. 2003;1:20.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_TvtZDgn">The natural history of congestive heart failure: the Framingham study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mckee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Castelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mcnamara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1056/nejm197112232852601</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_jcjHGEn">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">285</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1441" to="1446" />
			<date type="published" when="1971">1971</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">McKee PA, Castelli WP, McNamara PM, et al. The natural history of congestive heart failure: the Framingham study. N Engl J Med. 1971;285:1441-1446.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_fpmahMu">Hormones, genetic factors, and gender differences in cardiovascular disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Rossouw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0008-6363(01)00478-3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Q6W9xbw">Cardiovasc Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="550" to="557" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rossouw JE. Hormones, genetic factors, and gender differences in cardiovascular disease. Cardiovasc Res. 2002;53:550-557.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_QXyKsYG">Use of blood pressure lowering drugs in the prevention of cardiovascular disease: meta-analysis of 147 randomised trials in the context of expectations from prospective epidemiological studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Law</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmj.b1665</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_yuHAhsY">BMJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">338</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1665</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Law MR, Morris JK, Wald NJ. Use of blood pressure lowering drugs in the prevention of cardiovascular disease: meta-analysis of 147 randomised trials in the context of expectations from prospec- tive epidemiological studies. BMJ. 2009;338:b1665.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_uzCN7UQ">Blood pressure: the lower, the better: the con side</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Grossman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2337/dc11-s245</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_5QgGjxZ">Diabetes Care</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">Suppl 2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="308" to="S312" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Grossman E. Blood pressure: the lower, the better: the con side. Diabetes Care. 2011;34(Suppl 2):S308-S312.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
