<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_xUwj8CW">Novel blood pressure monitoring methods: perspectives for achieving &quot;perfect 24-h blood pressure management&quot;</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
					<p type="raw">© The Author(s), under exclusive licence to The Japanese Society of Hypertension 2023</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2023-06-06">6 June 2023</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Naoko</forename><surname>Tomitani</surname></persName>
							<email>tomitani.n@jichi.ac.jp</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>1</label> Division of Cardiovascular Medicine , Department of Medicine , Jichi Medical University School of Medicine , Tochigi , Japan</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Cardiovascular Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Jichi Medical University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tochigi</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Satoshi</forename><surname>Hoshide</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>1</label> Division of Cardiovascular Medicine , Department of Medicine , Jichi Medical University School of Medicine , Tochigi , Japan</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Cardiovascular Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Jichi Medical University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tochigi</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kazuomi</forename><surname>Kario</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>1</label> Division of Cardiovascular Medicine , Department of Medicine , Jichi Medical University School of Medicine , Tochigi , Japan</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Cardiovascular Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Jichi Medical University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tochigi</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_DeCTQxG">Novel blood pressure monitoring methods: perspectives for achieving &quot;perfect 24-h blood pressure management&quot;</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2023-06-06">6 June 2023</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">A5E6CFF36D38611232EC4B1E28E56CAA</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41440-023-01329-4</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: 24 April 2023 / Revised: 8 May 2023 / Accepted: 10 May 2023 /</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T09:32+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term xml:id="_9hnEFt8">Blood pressure monitoring</term>
					<term xml:id="_n9SNAsG">Hypertension</term>
					<term xml:id="_TaBPXVM">Wearable blood pressure monitoring device</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_9AP93Sv"><p xml:id="_fPmC4CH"><s xml:id="_Mt3SpZj">Blood pressure (BP) is not constant and varies from shortterm to long-term.</s><s xml:id="_eskbwQR">Considering this fact, office-measured BP as a snapshot of fluctuating BP is inadequate for the diagnosis and management of hypertension.</s><s xml:id="_6uA76ce">Recent international guidelines for hypertension management recommend the assessment of out-of-office BP using ambulatory BP monitoring (ABPM) and home BP monitoring (HBPM), based on evidence that out-of-office BP is a stronger predictor of cardiovascular events than office BP <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_M3Bw4ur"><s xml:id="_MBzSzdt">Accumulating evidence has highlighted the clinical relevance of BP variability (very short-term to long-term) and circadian rhythm, beyond the effect of average BP levels on cardiovascular outcomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_z3KAXTN">To minimize the organ damage and risk of cardiovascular events, achievement of perfect BP control (i.e., 24-h BP level, circadian rhythm, and BP variability) over a 24-h period is essential <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, and 24-h continuous BP monitoring is ideal for the "perfect 24-h BP management" (Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_J85DRzh">Although ABPM and HBPM are recommended in guidelines as out-of-office BP monitoring methods, they have limitations in measurement timing and measurement period for perfect BP monitoring in daily life.</s><s xml:id="_wynTdpg">ABPM is performed with short (15-to 60-min) measurement intervals but usually performed over only a 24-h period <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_DDyFG99">ABPM can monitor diurnal BP variability, but not day-byday and longer-term BP variability.</s><s xml:id="_qYMMBa4">HBPM can monitor day-by-day and longer-term BP variability, but HBPM is usually measured on specific timing (i.e., in the morning and evening) <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_KCf3bBb"><s xml:id="_FwAAQU6">Recently, novel BP monitoring devices have been developed to overcome these pitfalls; the Aktiia bracelet (Aktiia, Neuchâtel, Switzerland [commercially available]) based on the photo-plethysmography method <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, the HeartGuide (Omron Healthcare, Kyoto, Japan [commercially available]) based on the oscillometric method <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, the NightView (Omron Healthcare, Kyoto, Japan [commercially available]) based on the oscillometric method <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, and the beat-by-beat device (developed by Omron Healthcare, Kyoto, Japan) based on the tonometry method <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_GY527TG"><s xml:id="_wYT78RW">The present study by Almeida et al. demonstrated that daytime (9 a.m. to 9 p.m.) systolic BP (SBP) and diastolic BP (DBP) averaged from 7-day data obtained from the Aktiia monitor were comparable to 1-day averaged SBP and DBP from ABPM, which is a gold standard method for ambulatory BP monitoring <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_ZRBuUZj">The results support the use of the Aktiia monitor for long-term daytime BP monitoring.</s><s xml:id="_nBYH6Hg">However, the Aktiia calculates BP only when the wearer's wrist is still for 30 s and it cannot monitor BP during daily activities with physical movement.</s><s xml:id="_A4vUeCj">On the other hand, ABPM can monitor BP including BP during daily activities involving physical activity.</s><s xml:id="_MS8XnuB">Comparisons between the Aktiia and ABPM among more active individuals may result in different outcomes.</s><s xml:id="_nmubVQC">The expression, "ambulatory resting BP" may well explain the BP obtained from the Aktiia device.</s></p><p xml:id="_U4y7C6x"><s xml:id="_9AaeHHx">The present study also demonstrated that the amount of readings performed by the Aktiia monitor varied by individuals <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_Pg3qgVR">The authors suggest that the Aktiia require at least 7-day monitoring to obtain sufficient measurements equivalent to 1-day daytime ABPM, assuming patient's compliance found in this study.</s><s xml:id="_XN5r6kQ">As described in the Limitations, longer Aktiia monitoring period might be required for some patients in order to obtain enough measurements in real-life setting.</s><s xml:id="_bbp9kAM">Further studies in larger population are warranted to confirm the appropriate Aktiia monitoring period in daily life.</s><s xml:id="_GC5KDr2">Compared to ABPM, the Aktiia has dramatically reduced the discomfort in ambulatory BP monitoring.</s><s xml:id="_wkpBwsU">The feature that the wearer is not bothered by the operation is an Aktiia's unique advantage.</s><s xml:id="_HUn9WSs">Some patients may prefer to monitor their BPs by the Aktiia during 1-week period (or even longer) rather than by ABPM during 24-h period.</s></p><p xml:id="_EnHwzBJ"><s xml:id="_hXtJ4ke">Another commercially available novel device is the HeartGuide, which is a watch-type wearable oscillometric BP monitoring device.</s><s xml:id="_5a8hqMF">Our study group demonstrated that there is no significant difference between BPs simultaneously measured by a HeartGuide and an ABPM device <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_MTpu8Ax">The HeartGuide is a wearable device for self-BP monitoring, allowing the wearers to measure their BPs anytime and anywhere in daily life and for long-term monitoring like HBPM.</s><s xml:id="_rySZkcf">We also demonstrated that the peak BP values measured by the HeartGuide were significantly associated with left ventricular mass index (LVMI) measured by cardiac MRI, indicating high peak wearable BP could be a risk factor for cardiovascular events <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_E69Zydh">The feature that wearers can self-measure their BPs at the time when their BP may be elevated (i.e., under stressful situation) is one of advantages of the HeartGuide.</s></p><p xml:id="_7y5pFus"><s xml:id="_et9MD7P">The NightView, a wrist-type oscillometric HBPM device, can be used for long-term monitoring of nighttime BP during sleep (default measurement: AM2:00, AM4:00, and 4-h after bedtime), which cannot be measured by a conventional HBPM device <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_Nhpj7kJ">The device, with technical innovations that reduce measurement noise and cuff pressure, successfully measures nighttime BP repeatedly without sleep disturbance.</s></p><p xml:id="_9Udkk3R"><s xml:id="_repVh7v">Above mentioned novel devices can monitor BP in daily life, however those devices might not capture a "true" peak BP.</s><s xml:id="_5eabSj9">In order to identify the "true" peak BP, beat-by-beat BPs should be monitored.</s><s xml:id="_ndPa99t">Continuous beat-by-beat BP monitoring over 24-h is ideal for the perfect 24-h BP management.</s><s xml:id="_68gS6Gk">Tonometry is a BP measurement method in which a pressure sensor is pressed flat against the radial artery to measure beat-by-beat BPs.</s><s xml:id="_gz7GCbD">The tonometry method is vulnerable to physical movement, making it difficult to measure during daily activities.</s><s xml:id="_AJQRd7h">A recently developed beatby-beat BP monitoring device employing 46 tonometry sensors successfully captured BP surge during asleep <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> and during awake in the supine position at rest <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_H7nqHMe">Technical challenges remain in the 24-h beat-by-beat BP monitoring including during daytime activities.</s></p><p xml:id="_xVDuyRJ"><s xml:id="_9gmfb4j">As described above, each measurement method has its advantages and disadvantage (issues should be improved).</s><s xml:id="_pNJP5xH">Further development of device technology is warranted, and it is also important to consider how those novel devices can be applied for clinical practice.</s><s xml:id="_duZvDJt">Large amounts of data will be available from the long-term monitoring by the wearable device such as the Aktiia and the HeartGuide, and interpretation of these numerous BP data is also essential.</s><s xml:id="_F5RFAkS">The Aktiia and the HeartGuide provide the application which displays BP measurements on a smartphone <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_yPRwQS2">Such applications may improve patients' motivation for Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> Novel and conventional blood pressure monitoring methods to measure out-of-office blood pressure.</s><s xml:id="_C7NEGRv">Each dot represents an example of a BP measurement point during a time of day.</s><s xml:id="_nUqfW2P">Blue dots represent BP measurements using conventional BP monitoring methods and pink dots represent BP measurements using novel BP monitoring methods.</s><s xml:id="_JPeu5nf">BP blood pressure, PPG photo-plethysmography, BPM blood pressure monitoring, WBPM wearable blood pressure monitoring, ABPM ambulatory blood pressure monitoring, HBPM home blood pressure monitoring, OBPM office blood pressure monitoring hypertension treatment and BP control, and help physicians to provide optimal treatment toward "perfect 24-h BP control" for the patients by sharing the data with physicians.</s><s xml:id="_YPDeRGf">In order to achieve "perfect 24-h BP management", both the advances in BP monitoring devices that can measure BP accurately and continuously (or at high frequencies) and the progress in data analysis and feedback systems would be needed.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_vE7MvJR">Compliance with ethical standards</head></div>		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_cYwjW4r"><p xml:id="_GQCsn3v"><s xml:id="_b5yTeWk">Conflict of interest KK has received research grants from Omron Healthcare and A&amp;D Co.</s><s xml:id="_Qfgkarn">The other authors have no conflict of interest to declare.</s></p><p xml:id="_fG4chTW"><s xml:id="_vjAz5zw">Publisher's note Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_wU2T8TC">ACC/AHA/AAPA/ ABC/ACPM/AGS/APhA/ASH/ASPC/NMA/PCNA guideline for the prevention, detection, evaluation, and management of high blood pressure in adults: executive summary: a report of the American College of Cardiology/American Heart Association Task Force on Clinical Practice Guidelines</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Whelton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Carey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Aronow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Casey</forename><surname>De</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Collins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dennison</forename><surname>Himmelfarb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1161/hyp.0000000000000075</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_r6Kfxp4">J Am Coll Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2199" to="2269" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Whelton PK, Carey RM, Aronow WS, Casey DE Jr, Collins KJ, Dennison Himmelfarb C, et al. 2017 ACC/AHA/AAPA/ ABC/ACPM/AGS/APhA/ASH/ASPC/NMA/PCNA guideline for the prevention, detection, evaluation, and management of high blood pressure in adults: executive summary: a report of the American College of Cardiology/American Heart Association Task Force on Clinical Practice Guidelines. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2018;71:2199-269.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_5wk3h6p">ESC/ESH guidelines for the management of arterial hypertension</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mancia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Spiering</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Agabiti</forename><surname>Rosei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Azizi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Burnier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/hjh.0000000000001961</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_XUmvwv3">Eur Heart J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3021" to="3104" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Williams B, Mancia G, Spiering W, Agabiti Rosei E, Azizi M, Burnier M, et al. 2018 ESC/ESH guidelines for the management of arterial hypertension. Eur Heart J. 2018;39:3021-104.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_TYxvgsA">The Japanese Society of Hypertension guidelines for the management of hypertension (JSH 2019)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Umemura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Arima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Arima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Asayama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Dohi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hirooka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41440-019-0284-9</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_MUDU5by">Hypertens Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1235" to="1481" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Umemura S, Arima H, Arima S, Asayama K, Dohi Y, Hirooka Y, et al. The Japanese Society of Hypertension guidelines for the management of hypertension (JSH 2019). Hypertens Res. 2019; 42:1235-481.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_sMdkkft">Morning surge in blood pressure as a predictor of silent and clinical cerebrovascular disease in elderly hypertensives: a prospective study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kario</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Pickering</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Umeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hoshide</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hoshide</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Morinari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1161/01.cir.0000056521.67546.aa</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_vbzkFqZ">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1401" to="1406" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kario K, Pickering TG, Umeda Y, Hoshide S, Hoshide Y, Morinari M, et al. Morning surge in blood pressure as a predictor of silent and clinical cerebrovascular disease in elderly hyper- tensives: a prospective study. Circulation. 2003;107:1401-6.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_32SEvsc">Blood pressure variability and cardiovascular disease: systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Stevens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Koshiaris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Law</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Glasziou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Stevens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmj.i4098</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_6SwzsyG">BMJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">354</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4098</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Stevens SL, Wood S, Koshiaris C, Law K, Glasziou P, Stevens RJ, et al. Blood pressure variability and cardiovascular disease: systematic review and meta-analysis. BMJ. 2016;354:i4098.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_fVe8Q5P">Nighttime blood pressure phenotype and cardiovascular prognosis: practitioner-based nationwide JAMP study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kario</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hoshide</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Mizuno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kabutoya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nishizawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yoshida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1161/circulationaha.120.049730</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_FpDC5Bu">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1810" to="1820" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kario K, Hoshide S, Mizuno H, Kabutoya T, Nishizawa M, Yoshida T, et al. Nighttime blood pressure phenotype and cardi- ovascular prognosis: practitioner-based nationwide JAMP study. Circulation. 2020;142:1810-20.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_mYu26v4">Prognostic significance of visit-to-visit variability, maximum systolic blood pressure, and episodic hypertension</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rothwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Howard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Dolan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>'brien</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Dobson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Dahlof</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0140-6736(10)60308-x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_zqsWzeK">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">375</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="895" to="905" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rothwell PM, Howard SC, Dolan E, O&apos;Brien E, Dobson JE, Dahlof B, et al. Prognostic significance of visit-to-visit variability, maximum systolic blood pressure, and episodic hypertension. Lancet. 2010;375:895-905.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_TPNbmfD">Evidence and perspectives on the 24-hour management of hypertension: hemodynamic biomarker-initiated &apos;anticipation medicine&apos; for zero cardiovascular event</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kario</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.pcad.2016.04.001</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_QhuBqS7">Prog Cardiovasc Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="262" to="281" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kario K. Evidence and perspectives on the 24-hour management of hypertension: hemodynamic biomarker-initiated &apos;anticipation medicine&apos; for zero cardiovascular event. Prog Cardiovasc Dis. 2016;59:262-81.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_gSvR7JZ">Effective out-of-office BP monitoring to detect masked hypertension: perspectives for wearable BP monitoring</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Tomitani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hoshide</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kario</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41440-022-01080-2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_wwTkb3G">Hypertens Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="523" to="525" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Tomitani N, Hoshide S, Kario K. Effective out-of-office BP monitoring to detect masked hypertension: perspectives for wearable BP monitoring. Hypertens Res. 2023;46:523-5.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_SNXYU8a">Aktiia cuffless blood pressure monitor yields equivalent daytime blood pressure measurements compared to a 24-h ambulatory blood pressure monitor: preliminary results from a prospective single-centre study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Almeida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Cortes</forename><surname>Perruchoud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Alexandre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Vermare</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41440-023-01258-2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_wpQE3c6">Hypertens Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1456" to="1461" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Almeida T, Cortes Perruchoud D, Alexandre J, Vermare P, Sola J, et al. Aktiia cuffless blood pressure monitor yields equivalent daytime blood pressure measurements compared to a 24-h ambulatory blood pressure monitor: preliminary results from a prospective single-centre study. Hypertens Res. 2023; 46:1456-61.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_EJk9fmK">The first study comparing a wearable watch-type blood pressure monitor with a conventional ambulatory blood pressure monitor on in-office and out-of-office settings</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kario</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Shimbo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Tomitani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kanegae</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/jch.13799</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_KA9Tqda">J Clin Hypertens</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="135" to="141" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kario K, Shimbo D, Tomitani N, Kanegae H, Schwartz JE, Williams B. The first study comparing a wearable watch-type blood pressure monitor with a conventional ambulatory blood pressure monitor on in-office and out-of-office settings. J Clin Hypertens. 2020;22:135-41.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_SYRggQp">Simultaneous self-monitoring comparison of a supine algorithmequipped wrist nocturnal home blood pressure monitoring device with an upper arm device</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kario</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Tomitani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Iwashita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Shiga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kanegae</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/jch.14179</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_FvCWtWd">J Clin Hypertens</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="793" to="801" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kario K, Tomitani N, Iwashita C, Shiga T, Kanegae H. Simultaneous self-monitoring comparison of a supine algorithm- equipped wrist nocturnal home blood pressure monitoring device with an upper arm device. J Clin Hypertens. 2021;23: 793-801.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_kapuQxX">Nocturnal blood pressure surge in seconds is a new determinant of left ventricular mass index</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kokubo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kuwabara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ota</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Tomitani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yamashita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Shiga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/jch.14383</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_YjtKnGR">J Clin Hypertens</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="271" to="282" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kokubo A, Kuwabara M, Ota Y, Tomitani N, Yamashita S, Shiga T, et al. Nocturnal blood pressure surge in seconds is a new determinant of left ventricular mass index. J Clin Hypertens. 2022;24:271-82.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_4z7CscH">Relationship between blood pressure repeatedly measured by a wrist-cuff oscillometric wearable blood pressure monitoring device and left ventricular mass index in working hypertensive patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kario</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Tomitani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Morimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kanegae</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lacy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41440-021-00758-3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_TaKbeD5">Hypertens Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="96" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kario K, Tomitani N, Morimoto T, Kanegae H, Lacy P, Williams B. Relationship between blood pressure repeatedly measured by a wrist-cuff oscillometric wearable blood pressure monitoring device and left ventricular mass index in working hypertensive patients. Hypertens Res. 2022;45:87-96.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_H2QVWBA">Very short-term beat-by-beat blood pressure variability in the supine position at rest correlates well with the nocturnal blood pressure variability assessed by ambulatory blood pressure monitoring</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kinoshita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Saku</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Mannoji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kanaya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sunagawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41440-022-00911-6</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_xJqe5ek">Hypertens Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1008" to="1017" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kinoshita H, Saku K, Mano J, Mannoji H, Kanaya S, Sunagawa K. Very short-term beat-by-beat blood pressure varia- bility in the supine position at rest correlates well with the noc- turnal blood pressure variability assessed by ambulatory blood pressure monitoring. Hypertens Res. 2022;45:1008-17.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
