<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_J8DEAxy">Whither trial-based economic evaluation for health care decision making?</title>
				<funder ref="#_PN9Avnh">
					<orgName type="full">Health Services Research Collaboration</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Medical Research Council</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">MRC</orgName>
					<idno type="DOI" subtype="crossref">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100000265</idno>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
					<p type="raw">Copyright # 2006 John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. Copyright # 2006 John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. Copyright # 2006 John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. hec.1093 by University Of Iowa Libraries -Serials Acquisitions, Wiley Online Library on [14/08/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License Copyright # 2006 John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. Copyright # 2006 Copyright # 2006 Copyright # 2006 Copyright # 2006 Copyright # 2006</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2006-02-20">20 February 2006</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mark</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sculpher</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>a</label> Centre for Health Economics , University of York , UK</note>
								<orgName type="department">Centre for Health Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of York</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Karl</forename><surname>Claxton</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>a</label> Centre for Health Economics , University of York , UK</note>
								<orgName type="department">Centre for Health Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of York</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mike</forename><surname>Drummond</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>a</label> Centre for Health Economics , University of York , UK</note>
								<orgName type="department">Centre for Health Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of York</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Chris</forename><surname>Mccabe</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>b</label> ScHARR , University of Sheffield , UK</note>
								<orgName type="department">ScHARR</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Sheffield</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Centre for Health Economics , University of York , York , YO10 5DD , UK.</note>
								<orgName type="department">Centre for Health Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of York</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>YO10 5DD</postCode>
									<settlement>York</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_sVfxe3W">Whither trial-based economic evaluation for health care decision making?</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2006-02-20">20 February 2006</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">7E0360197B0AEF35CC0CD235F2D60331</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1002/hec.1093</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 10 May 2005 Accepted 24 November 2005</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T10:41+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term xml:id="_rymmhe6">economic evaluation</term>
					<term xml:id="_rMFftCS">randomised controlled trials</term>
					<term xml:id="_QbJ6r7C">decision analytical modelling</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_hSJwQyd"><p xml:id="_kmMUF4q"><s xml:id="_MGBBEU6">The randomised controlled trial (RCT) has developed a central role in applied cost-effectiveness studies in health care as the vehicle for analysis.</s><s xml:id="_dTKMr2C">This paper considers the role of trial-based economic evaluation in this era of explicit decision making.</s><s xml:id="_EYQmMs3">It is argued that any framework for economic analysis can only be judged insofar as it can inform two key decisions and be consistent with the objectives of a health care system subject to its resource constraints.</s><s xml:id="_VYw9vRd">The two decisions are, firstly, whether to adopt a health technology given existing evidence and, secondly, an assessment of whether more evidence is required to support this decision in the future.</s><s xml:id="_TdWX2J4">It is argued that a framework of economic analysis is needed which can estimate costs and effects, based on all the available evidence, relating to the full range of possible alternative interventions and clinical strategies, over an appropriate time horizon and for specific patient groups.</s><s xml:id="_fBDJFnR">It must also enable the accumulated evidence to be synthesised in an explicit and transparent way in order to fully represent the decision uncertainty.</s><s xml:id="_FzZUTaa">These requirements suggest that, in most circumstances, the use of a single RCT as a vehicle for economic analysis will be an inadequate and partial basis for decision making.</s><s xml:id="_NE3tX2X">It is argued that RCT evidence, with or without economic content, should be viewed as simply one of the sources of evidence, which must be placed in a broader framework of evidence synthesis and decision analysis.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="566.929" lry="737.008"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="566.929" lry="737.008"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="566.929" lry="737.008"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="566.929" lry="737.008"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="566.929" lry="737.008"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="566.929" lry="737.008"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="566.929" lry="737.008"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="566.929" lry="737.008"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="566.929" lry="737.008"/>
		<surface n="10" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="566.929" lry="737.008"/>
		<surface n="11" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="566.929" lry="737.008"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_WUnchBw">Introduction</head><p xml:id="_ydGtDfM"><s xml:id="_rmaz8m3">The randomised controlled trial (RCT) occupies a central role in the evaluation of health care interventions.</s><s xml:id="_UQYXJNf">In the field of clinical evaluation, the role of the RCT is principally to generate estimates of relative treatment effect (e.g.</s><s xml:id="_E3j4bGj">odds or hazard ratios) relating to the population of interest <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_9bbfnPP">In this context, appropriate randomisation minimises the risk of selection bias, although this will not ensure the generalisability of the estimates <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_8J4uMAf">In the context of economic evaluation, the role of the RCT has extended much further than being a source of estimates of relative treatment effects.</s><s xml:id="_8Mjtbvk">Since 1994, approximately 30% of published economic evaluations on the NHS Economic Evaluation Database have been based on data from a single RCT (<ref type="url" target="www.york.ac.uk/inst/crd">www.york.ac.uk/inst/crd</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_bzkDvzK">That is, the RCT was used as the vehicle for economic analysis, providing the sole source of data on resource use, baseline event rates and, where appropriate, health values as well as relative treatment effects.</s><s xml:id="_evAXJ5k">It would not be an overstatement to suggest that, amongst a large proportion of the clinical research community, this approach to economic evaluation is widely viewed as the entirety of what economic evaluation (even health economics!)</s><s xml:id="_MnGc24z">has to offer.</s></p><p xml:id="_6GNvXgr"><s xml:id="_epHuZ2j">Since the mid-1990s, many health care systems have made explicit use of economic evaluation to make decisions about which new technologies should be funded from collective resources.</s><s xml:id="_AaW6V5k">This formal requirement for economic analysis has largely related to the need for manufacturers to submit economic studies to decision makers in order for their new pharmaceutical products to be reimbursed <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_byUZJr9">In the UK, economic evaluation plays a key part in the technology appraisal process at the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) which makes decisions about a range of health technologies, and is a major element in the independent technology assessment, as well as manufacturer submissions, which inform appraisals <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_AwctzMF"><s xml:id="_B77TVud">Given that economic evaluation exists to inform decisions about resource allocation, the explicit use of these methods as a basis for actual decisions about coverage and reimbursement raises some important questions about appropriate methodology.</s><s xml:id="_J2UGnE5">One of these relates to the role of trial-based economic evaluation.</s><s xml:id="_sX7Ueuz">This paper discusses the requirements of economic evaluation for decision making and considers the extent to which the use of a single RCT as a vehicle for economic analysis is consistent with these requirements.</s><s xml:id="_cqwu8pM">It is argued that, in most cases, trial-based studies represent a partial and limited form of analysis.</s></p><p xml:id="_DbgBP3P"><s xml:id="_Cb4G27A">The paper is structured as follows.</s><s xml:id="_PSGYGkb">The next section considers the requirements for economic evaluation for explicit decisions about resource allocation.</s><s xml:id="_WMy4pjb">The following section considers the extent to which trial-based economic evaluation, compared with a framework of evidence synthesis and decision modelling, would be considered 'fit for purpose' given these requirements.</s><s xml:id="_sf2XBPQ">The penultimate section discusses the role played by RCTs in economic evaluation given existing funding arrangements for evaluative health services research.</s><s xml:id="_VvNuZuS">The last section offers some conclusions.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_fC8myf7">Requirements of economic evaluation for decision making</head><p xml:id="_ydtcVUC"><s xml:id="_mZekyFy">The formal use of economic evaluation as a basis for decision making about the reimbursement or coverage of health care technologies places particular demands on the analytical methods used.</s><s xml:id="_ENR6e9F">The requirements of economic evaluation for this purpose have been considered in detail elsewhere <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_dA7axqE">Here we present a brief summary of the arguments.</s></p><p xml:id="_xCXMgzs"><s xml:id="_TYyZxsw">There are two related questions which any health care system needs to address in making decisions about the cost-effectiveness of new technologies.</s><s xml:id="_tc5NmNe">The first is whether the new technology can be considered cost-effective based on existing evidence.</s><s xml:id="_YfdKTNC">Given its unavoidable nature, this adoption decision has to be taken on the basis of what is currently known about its costs and benefits relative to comparators.</s><s xml:id="_8ZjXGrC">The second question is, whatever the adoption decision, is it a cost-effective use of resources to demand additional evidence through research?</s><s xml:id="_VSRwc82">If the answer to this research decision is positive, further evidence will be used to review the adoption decision in the future.</s><s xml:id="_VC5vEap">Although the adoption decision is central to most reimbursement agencies, many also consider the issue of research priorities.</s></p><p xml:id="_gVeZJcX"><s xml:id="_5y4DzXk">Given these two fundamental questions, a series of requirements for economic evaluation emerges.</s></p><p xml:id="_MrUe3ST"><s xml:id="_Nycv7Mp">* Clear statement and measurement of the objective function.</s><s xml:id="_K8ysrgE">As decisions are typically being taken by budget-constrained health care systems, the analysis needed to inform the adoption and research decisions is essentially one of constrained optimisation in which an objective function is maximised subject to a budget constraint.</s><s xml:id="_3MYa7cz">A legitimate focus of the objective function is likely to be some measure of health gain.</s><s xml:id="_Ty6BZSF">This would not preclude the inclusion of other arguments, but their 'rate of substitution' with health gain would need to be defined.</s></p><p xml:id="_h5vuh46"><s xml:id="_Uk6wZtt">The quantification of the implications for the objective function in a given study is, of course, subject to much debate, but the quality-adjusted life-year (QALY) remains a widely used measure of health gain with well-understood strengths and weaknesses.</s><s xml:id="_QVN6MdG">A key requirement for decision making is the need for a consistent implementation of the measure of health gain in analyses informing decisions about different technologies.</s><s xml:id="_zfcxQvU">* A consistent perspective.</s><s xml:id="_wG6FyrR">The need for consistency in perspective across adoption decisions is also a requirement for decision making.</s><s xml:id="_MDYy2RZ">The appropriate cost and benefit perspective for a legitimate social decision maker would ideally be a broad societal one although, in reality, a somewhat constrained version might be the focus of actual decision makers.</s><s xml:id="_HqNUQRR">* Appropriate specification of the decision problem.</s><s xml:id="_hYQsgZS">Any economic analysis informing decisions needs to be clear about which patient population(s) are being considered.</s><s xml:id="_dTHtv6w">Once this is clear, all relevant options need to be defined.</s><s xml:id="_VSjbKKA">These are likely to include a range of possible existing interventions and programmes, as well as one or more new technologies.</s><s xml:id="_ASrcUZ3">The definition of 'alternative options' may also include the specification of alternative sequences of interventions or diagnostic tests and different stopping and starting rules for treatments.</s><s xml:id="_aFUBDMb">* Appropriate time horizon.</s><s xml:id="_R8sgTHd">A further requirement</s></p><p xml:id="_wRezaZy"><s xml:id="_aaFrnGX">for decision making is the need for an appropriate time horizon -that is, the time period over which costs and benefits are likely to differ between the alternative options being compared.</s><s xml:id="_Hwrfb36">A lifetime time horizon will be appropriate in many instances, particularly when an intervention impacts on mortality.</s><s xml:id="_bB8xruN">* All relevant evidence.</s><s xml:id="_hyZX7Du">In order to inform social decisions about resource allocation, all sources of evidence need to be used.</s><s xml:id="_G8wnHQX">Anything that falls short of this will be a partial analysis with potentially misleading results.</s><s xml:id="_a6hdpdd">This relates not only to measures of relative treatment effect, but also to the full range of other parameters in an economic analysis.</s><s xml:id="_PrQjvGJ">This requirement is consistent with the principles of evidence-based medicine <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_JgRs3rJ">* Relevant to the decision context.</s><s xml:id="_7qMUQNf">Decisions about new technologies are taken in specific contexts.</s><s xml:id="_7YbC8dX">This is defined by the jurisdiction of the specific decision-maker whom the economic evaluation is seeking to inform.</s><s xml:id="_rzBuMUY">* Appropriate characterisation of uncertainty.</s><s xml:id="_RqYr7aF">The imprecision with which parameters relevant to an economic evaluation are estimated needs to be quantified for two reasons.</s><s xml:id="_RJFSS3J">Firstly, if the relationships between those parameters and the measures of costs and effect are non-linear, then the correct estimate of expected cost-effectiveness can only be based on a probabilistic analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_JGJaA9a">Secondly, in order to assess whether or not additional research is required to inform a future decision about a technology, the uncertainty associated with the adoption decision needs to be quantified.</s><s xml:id="_fPfvAsD">That is, in reimbursing a new technology, what is the probability that a wrong decision is being made?</s><s xml:id="_aHaTUKP">It is also necessary to consider the implications of making a wrong decision in terms of wasted resources and opportunities for health gain forgone.</s><s xml:id="_WppvdT4">This is the foundation of value of information analysis which can establish the potential value of additional research which can remove the cost of uncertainty for the relevant patient population, and identify appropriate research designs by assessing the marginal cost and marginal value of alternative studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_DJp2sGE"><s xml:id="_nrCPZ3e">These requirements of economic evaluation for decision making are the starting point for considering an appropriate framework for analysis.</s></p><p xml:id="_KmWF5Z8"><s xml:id="_mWv5pMe">It is certainly true that, in their methods guidelines, many decision makers are not prescriptive about preferred methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_87TPZcT">However, unless these requirements are recognised and implemented, the value of formal economic evaluation for resource allocations decisions will be compromised.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_XHuwqXz">What analytical framework for economic evaluation?</head><p xml:id="_qjHAqh2"><s xml:id="_r7gbYbE">Trial-based economic evaluation Given the requirements for economic evaluation defined in the last section, to what extent can trialbased economic evaluation be considered 'fit for purpose'?</s><s xml:id="_fmQ9ZQu">An economic analysis based on a RCT will have the advantage of the relative effectiveness of the intervention being derived from a design, which should be free of selection bias.</s><s xml:id="_JcqrvWW">However, using a trial as a framework (vehicle) for economic analysis falls short in terms of many of the requirements described above.</s></p><p xml:id="_UryPweM"><s xml:id="_CFjjV59">A failure to compare all relevant options.</s><s xml:id="_Z8bbdY2">Given the costs of research and implications for patient numbers, few RCTs will include more than two options -typically a new technology plus one 'standard' intervention.</s><s xml:id="_QkASC2P">However, it is invariably the case that there is a range of existing interventions, which are used to varying degrees in routine practice.</s><s xml:id="_QBFqyGh">Furthermore, it will often be the case that new technologies for a given condition come in clusters -for example, classes of pharmaceuticals, or drugs in different but related classes.</s><s xml:id="_djZpCem">In a recent technology assessment of alternative therapies for different types of epilepsy in adults, between one and six newer anti-epileptic drugs were compared with two older therapies <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_kvGdf6T">Not surprisingly, no trial directly comparing all therapeutic options had been undertaken.</s><s xml:id="_ArhffYu">For many chronic diseases, therapies are used in sequence.</s><s xml:id="_UFU6Kcy">Although a few RCTs comparing alternative treatment sequences exist, this is typically a sub-set of all the possible sequences.</s><s xml:id="_Gf3JaSU">In looking at the cost-effectiveness of new biological therapies for rheumatoid arthritis, for example, NICE had to consider the appropriate point in a therapeutic sequence of two new biological therapies and eight existing disease-modifying anti-rheumatic drugs <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_C3ZPwX7"><s xml:id="_H6rztPU">The implication is that RCTs will usually only compare a sub-set of relevant options for a given patient population.</s><s xml:id="_5UaKNw5">Allowing a single trial to define the scope of an economic evaluation will, therefore, invariably produce a partial analysis.</s><s xml:id="_bWGWSeH">If one or more relevant options have not been included in an analysis, there is a clear risk of inappropriate adoption and research decisions.</s></p><p xml:id="_jTRyPJY"><s xml:id="_27ExuHd">A truncated time horizon.</s><s xml:id="_TbVamHR">For many trial-based economic evaluations, the maximum follow-up in the trial will be shorter than the appropriate time horizon for the economic analysis.</s><s xml:id="_eWYc5Sk">For trials concerned with the treatment of particular acute conditions or with alternative forms of management for terminally ill patients, this may not be the case.</s><s xml:id="_a9FCFUP">However, trial-based economic evaluations relating to interventions in many areas of health care will exhibit a gap between the costs and benefits which can be estimated in the trial, and those which are needed for decision making.</s></p><p xml:id="_Gq5cWjr"><s xml:id="_DkxNHCk">In some studies, simply providing a within-trial estimate of cost-effectiveness with a truncated time horizon can be misleading.</s><s xml:id="_zwe7tDc">For example, in Mark et al.'s cost-effectiveness analysis of alternative thrombolytic therapies following myocardial infarction, after one year's follow-up 91 and 89.9% of patients randomised to TPA and streptokinase, respectively, had survived, and mean costs were higher in the TPA group <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_XEKwPcM">Any within-trial estimate of cost per life-year (or QALY) gained would only allow for differences in survival duration until one year.</s><s xml:id="_Yn8bJCv">This fails to acknowledge that the additional patients surviving during follow-up in the TPA arm of the trial would have lived for some period beyond one year.</s><s xml:id="_CmHPfpb">Therefore, to provide a more reliable estimate of costeffectiveness, Mark et al., moved out of a trialbased paradigm and used decision modelling to extrapolate the survival curves over patients' lifetimes.</s></p><p xml:id="_TBz24kh"><s xml:id="_DwtHkK7">For some studies, the failure to estimate cost and benefits over the full time horizon may not be a major problem if the within-trial estimate of the incremental cost-effectiveness ratio is considered acceptable relative to a threshold, and longer follow-up would only further confirm the adoption decision.</s><s xml:id="_KFyQr4V">An example of such a study was a trialbased comparison of the cost-effectiveness of highdose versus low-dose ACE inhibitors in heart failure <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_7WY3TUA">Within the trial, high-dose therapy was observed, over four years of follow-up, to have a lower mortality risk and to result in lower mean costs.</s><s xml:id="_aqcKrZn">The fact that, within the trial, it was not possible to observe the survival durations of all patients may not have been a problem if it could be safely assumed that mortality rates with low-dose therapy would never fall below those with high dose.</s><s xml:id="_cBUrfBu">That is, life-years gained from high dose would only increase as follow-up continued, and its cost-effectiveness would only improve.</s><s xml:id="_kcxvhFv">However, this justification of within-trial estimates of cost-effectiveness has its limitations.</s><s xml:id="_dP9U98M">The first relates to the fact that patients living longer on one therapy are likely to incur additional costs relating to the disease in question and to diseases other than that for which the interventions are being evaluated.</s><s xml:id="_qXqQFrR">The second is that, although it may be possible to reach robust adoption decisions on the basis of a study with a truncated time horizon if further follow-up would be expected just to confirm the result, analysis to inform decisions about the value of further research cannot make such a simplification.</s><s xml:id="_36At3Uk">Value of information analysis involves the quantification of the costs of decision uncertainty in terms of forgone health and resource costs.</s><s xml:id="_4JYwNjp">These methods depend on all sources of parameter uncertainty being included in an analysis, including full life expectancy.</s><s xml:id="_4eyBeWe">Value of information methods based on a truncated time horizon could, therefore, generate misleading results.</s></p><p xml:id="_x9ST3Cg"><s xml:id="_kmEDX4g">Lack of relevance to the decision context.</s><s xml:id="_b472snc">A further problem with many RCTs as used as vehicles for economic evaluation is their lack of relevance to the specific jurisdiction in which the decisions are being made.</s><s xml:id="_YJnbr3n">This is often the case with trials undertaken by pharmaceutical and medical device manufacturers who focus their patient recruitment in countries, which represent important potential markets and/or where they can recruit quickly and inexpensively.</s><s xml:id="_MVrMNZe">Using such trials as a vehicle for economic analyses will mean that estimates of costs and benefits may reflect considerable variability in patient case-mix and routine clinical practice.</s><s xml:id="_chUqT2F">Although methods have recently been described to handle this variability in economic evaluation alongside multi-location trials <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[19]</ref>, they will not help if the jurisdiction making the decision has recruited relatively few patients or was not part of the study at all.</s><s xml:id="_8AEk2HM">This was the case with NICE's appraisal of the glycoprotein 2b/3a antagonists for non-ST-elevation acute coronary syndrome <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[20]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_hDeWU88">Although nearly 50 000 patients had been randomised to relevant trials of these therapies, these were predominately undertaken outside the UK, largely in continental Europe or north America where the management of heart disease has traditionally shown some important differences compared to that in the NHS <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[21]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_VMKyqyF">The economic analysis to support NICE's decision making required the use of a decision analytic framework to combine relative treatment effects from the trials with baseline event rates specific to the UK in an attempt to 'transfer' trial results to a NHS setting <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[22]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_8J6eaEE"><s xml:id="_cJ6gYGR">For publicly-funded RCTs supporting economic evaluation, it may be that patients and clinical practice are more representative of the jurisdiction in which the decision will be taken.</s><s xml:id="_mSrzsvm">With respect to NHS practice in the UK, for example, his might be expected to be the case in trials funded by the NHS Health Technology Assessment programme and the Medical Research Council.</s><s xml:id="_6sftmuw">However, centres are typically recruited into such studies because of their willingness to participate rather than whether they contribute to a representative picture of NHS patients and practice.</s><s xml:id="_BSXEQsg">For economic evaluation based on these trials, therefore, it may not be reasonable to assume generalisability with respect to the context of the decision.</s></p><p xml:id="_PMrUQV3"><s xml:id="_Dpva8Qr">Failure to incorporate all evidence.</s><s xml:id="_WGGAYju">Arguably the most damning criticism of trial-based economic evaluation is the fact that single trial is very unlikely to include all evidence relevant to a given evaluation.</s><s xml:id="_2wvtcav">One aspect of this problem is relatively trivial.</s><s xml:id="_KKvCE2K">In some trial-based economic studies not all the data necessary for cost-effectiveness analysis are collected.</s><s xml:id="_b97KTAS">For example, there may be an absence of resource utilisation data and measurements of health-related quality of life (HRQL).</s><s xml:id="_FakDY6z">This tends to be the case, for example, in RCTs undertaken to support pharmaceutical companies' applications for licences for new products, despite the fact that these studies are often the main source of evidence when the cost-effectiveness of these therapies is initially considered for reimbursement.</s><s xml:id="_8Vxn3SC">One approach in these cases is to limit the economic evaluation to those data that were included -for example, only to include those costs where resource use data were collected or that can be inferred.</s><s xml:id="_cXmaDmP">This sort of partial analysis can lead to wholly misleading results if important costs or effects are excluded.</s><s xml:id="_AJGWahJ">Another example is to report estimates of life-years, rather than QALYs, gained, when no HRQL data were collected.</s><s xml:id="_BuBWbFg">This was true of the two trial-based studies in cardiology described above <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_KSYXgNy">This, of course, implicitly assumes that all surviving patients are in full health.</s><s xml:id="_NBFbfgA">A second approach would be to augment the data collected in the trial with evidence from other sources, thereby moving away from trial-based economic evaluation towards synthesis and modelling.</s></p><p xml:id="_NErcbUQ"><s xml:id="_hyUdBVf">The fundamental problem is that single trials will invariably fail to reflect all the available evidence relating to a particular decision problem.</s><s xml:id="_DCJrguW">Trial-based studies have the advantage of reflecting an unbiased estimate of relative treatment effect.</s><s xml:id="_sRxyvv4">However, in many situations there will be other trials relating to the technology of interest and, even if they do not include resource use and HRQL data to sustain full trial-based analyses, ignoring their estimates of treatment effect will lead to partial and potentially misleading analyses.</s></p><p xml:id="_dFTU5X6"><s xml:id="_jxtcZAz">This principle also extends to other parameters such as baseline event rates, resource use and HRQL.</s><s xml:id="_x3ahSCC">Additional estimates of these parameters may be available (wholly or partially) in other trials.</s><s xml:id="_RbWWUhu">It is perhaps more likely, however, that estimates of these non-treatment effect parameters would be available in non-experimental studies such as longitudinal or cross-sectional studies.</s><s xml:id="_D58U5AE">These are important sources of evidence as these parameters are not susceptible to selection bias in the same way as treatment effects.</s><s xml:id="_qTcYvJ9">This is because they would usually reflect clinical events rather than treatment selection.</s><s xml:id="_9r6f4yX">For example, the rate of clinical events (e.g.</s><s xml:id="_UpRBU96">mortality) under a particular standard intervention (i.e.</s><s xml:id="_Yb5avXH">baseline event rate) or the resource use associated with a particular severity of myocardial infarction does not involve comparisons between treatments.</s><s xml:id="_fnuQKpT">Another way of presenting this point is that the only reason why resource use or utilities would be expected to differ between interventions would be as a result of clinical or health events, which should be reflected in the treatment effects.</s><s xml:id="_CBqY455">So there should be no risk of selection bias resulting from the use of non-trial sources for cost and utility parameters as long as all relevant clinical and health events are included in the model and cost and utility data are conditioned on those events.</s></p><p xml:id="_YTKWVHc"><s xml:id="_RZkRqdT">In principle, the need to bring to bear all available evidence does not stop there.</s><s xml:id="_CBEhq24">Sources additional to the single trial will probably be available to provide estimates functions of parameters within an economic analysis.</s><s xml:id="_sYFU8H2">For example, for a surgical intervention, some studies may present estimates of the risks of individual complications, and others may indicate the overall risk of any adverse event.</s><s xml:id="_nrQ2bsC">Ideally, the evidence presented in all studies would be incorporated into an economic analysis despite this inconstancy in reporting.</s><s xml:id="_gweBNJw">Although the rates of complications are presented differently, the mathematical relationship between them could be used to provide a full synthesis [Ades AE, Sculpher MJ, Sutton A et al.</s><s xml:id="_mrkJXT9">Bayesian methods for evidence synthesis in costeffectiveness analysis.</s><s xml:id="_EuPmcxW">Pharmacoeconomics, in press].</s></p><p xml:id="_gGh6sMx"><s xml:id="_fvNdncr">One response to the failure of trial-based economic evaluation to use all available evidence is that, once such a study has been published, it can be synthesised with other similar evidence in a more detailed analysis for decision making, thus providing some sort of weighted mean costeffectiveness across trials and assessing betweenand within-trial variability.</s><s xml:id="_eYav56m">This would be analogous to what happens with clinical measurements in RCTs: a single trial publishes its results and then meta-analysis is used to synthesis these estimates with those from other trials <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[23]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_z3RaWPh">However, although this makes sense in the context of individual clinical measurements, there can be no sense in meta-analysing estimates of cost-effectiveness such as an incremental cost-effectiveness ratio or expected net benefit.</s><s xml:id="_dbhWGKZ">This is because these costeffectiveness estimates are derived from a range of parameters, many of which would not be of relevance in all decision-making contexts.</s><s xml:id="_PPFuZKq">This would certainly apply to unit costs -for example, a cost-effectiveness ratio based on US unit costs would not be relevant to a decision in the UK.</s><s xml:id="_BhekFMn">This may also be true of other parameters such as resource use, utilities and baseline event rates.</s><s xml:id="_Kayj4nV">Standard meta-analysis for clinical measures typically focuses on relative treatment effects that are assumed exchangeable across different decision contexts.</s><s xml:id="_KaF6q5h">This assumption cannot be made with measures of cost-effectiveness and it would be essential to disaggregate a cost-effectiveness measure into its constituent parts; that is, to synthesise the evidence on each of the parameters in the decision problem and to model cost-effectiveness using the results of those analyses.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_RxREV77">Inadequate quantification of decision uncertainty.</head><p xml:id="_R3t67J4"><s xml:id="_7Rchm4R">As described above, to address the second key decision question -whether additional research is itself efficient to inform the adoption decision in the future -requires a full quantification of decision uncertainty.</s><s xml:id="_XWzvVMs">A failure fully to characterise the uncertainty in all parameters in an analysis can have a major influence on the expected value of perfect information and the expected value of sample information <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">24]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_QehCfUR">Characterising uncertainty is possible in a trial-based economic evaluation but only in relation to the evidence in that trial.</s><s xml:id="_xnXAHF4">As argued above, the use of a single trial as the sole basis for economic evaluation will usually ignore evidence from other trial and non-trial sources on relevant parameters and functions of parameters.</s><s xml:id="_YGkNu7Q">As well as a potential impact on expected cost-effectiveness (which may lead to an inappropriate adoption decision), failure to use all available evidence can lead to less precision in parameter estimates, which, all things being equal, will result in over-estimates of the expected value of perfect information.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_UNff8Xe">Evidence synthesis and decision modelling</head><p xml:id="_23Xum5F"><s xml:id="_qqkgAGS">If trial-based economic evaluation is a limited framework for cost-effectiveness analysis for decision making, what is the alternative?</s><s xml:id="_ePGzg4C">The use of decision analytic models, coupled with full evidence synthesis, is the only framework that has the potential to meet all the requirements for economic evaluation for decision making.</s><s xml:id="_QZUJxws">These methods provide a framework within which an appropriate structure for the underlying disease and the impact of all relevant options under evaluation can be developed, all existing evidence can be brought to bear and, through probabilistic sensitivity analysis, the joint implications of parameter uncertainty on the uncertainty in the decision (and the value of additional research) can be quantified.</s></p><p xml:id="_m8cRN2P"><s xml:id="_DUQtkeu">This role of decision models is contrary to how it has been portrayed in the literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[25]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_H7bpZHK">Models have sometimes been characterised as alternatives to trials <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[26]</ref>, but this is to misunderstand their respective roles.</s><s xml:id="_Da2puQK">The RCT provides estimates of particular parameters in a specific group of patients in a particular health care environment.</s><s xml:id="_gAKkgbx">Decision models provide a structure within which evidence from a range of sources can be directed at a specific decision problem for a defined population and context.</s><s xml:id="_ynvppMF">Being clear about this distinction between measurement (undertaken in trials and other primary studies) and decision making (which needs an analytical structure within which to direct the evidence at the decision problem being addressed) emphasises that models and trials are complements, not substitutes.</s><s xml:id="_BrYVz6M">Although they can generate measures of a range of parameters, RCTs are the key source of estimates of relative treatment effects, which should be free of selection bias.</s><s xml:id="_EPNFVWe">These are central to economic evaluation as they are the driver for differences between options in both costs and health effects.</s><s xml:id="_2hKaAng">However, trials should be seen as a source of inputs into, not as a vehicle for, economic evaluation.</s></p><p xml:id="_SCrBVKD"><s xml:id="_Nx5ckAD">Of course, there are numerous methodological challenges to be addressed in using decision models <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_gM8EKgc">These include the choice of an appropriate structure for a model, particularly for complex disease processes where future prognosis is dependent on a patient's past history <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[27]</ref>; how structural uncertainty in decision models is to be handled and reflected in decision uncertainty and value of information analysis; and various computational issues associated with the calculation of the expected value of perfect information for individual parameters, and of sample information <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[24]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_9Cxemwf"><s xml:id="_CU9kXyh">Other methodological challenges within the framework relate to evidence synthesis; that is, the process of bringing together all relevant evidence on parameters and functions of parameters [Ades AE, Sculpher MJ, Sutton A et al., in press].</s><s xml:id="_T7tEwFe">As soon as the primacy of using all available evidence in decision making is accepted, the analytical issues this throws up are clear.</s><s xml:id="_WfR56aP">These issues go well beyond standard meta-analysis, and are being addressed (usually within a Bayesian framework) more generally than just for purposes of economic evaluation <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_dTMK6QY">To date most methodological work in this area has focussed on complex synthesis problems relating to treatment effects.</s><s xml:id="_MxpRDcE">For example, obtaining absolute effectiveness measures for several interventions when these have not been compared head-to-head in trials <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">30]</ref>; synthesising data from trials with different points of follow-up with different endpoints <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[31]</ref>; and obtaining estimates of relative treatment effects from non-randomised studies.</s><s xml:id="_cmcjsM7">However, there are also important methodological questions to be considered in synthesising other parameters relevant to economic evaluation such as utilities and resource use <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[32]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_GthBcSa"><s xml:id="_FFU3fDY">The use of evidence synthesis to 'feed into' decision models also raises interesting questions.</s><s xml:id="_DrgKGU6">For example, multi-parameter synthesis relates to the methods used to bring together not just individual parameters, but also to include evidence on mathematical functions of those parameters <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[33]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_jf5Jxtg">Advanced methods of evidence synthesis, particularly undertaken using Bayesian methods, emphasise the importance of reflecting in models all available evidence and a complete picture of parameter uncertainty.</s><s xml:id="_Yp8Tqzq">In addition, they clearly show the importance of fully incorporating the correlations between parameters as these can affect estimates of expected cost-effectiveness and measures of decision uncertainty.</s><s xml:id="_Rq4zgMD">Further, the value of information will inevitably be sensitive to the degree of correlation.</s><s xml:id="_2tk7P6U">The importance of appropriately coupling decision models with evidence synthesis has resulted in a set of methods which have been termed 'comprehensive decision models', where these two stages are essentially undertaken jointly in order that all evidence, uncertainties and correlations are captured in the economic analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">35]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_HyvthrU"><s xml:id="_vz32eQF">What is the role for trials in economic evaluation?</s></p><p xml:id="_DGjzFMz"><s xml:id="_dZ3fRcv">The last section argued that the primary purpose of RCTs is to measure specific parameters in particular patients, and that these provide one source of parameter estimates for economic evaluations undertaken within the framework of evidence synthesis and decision modelling.</s><s xml:id="_2kwGzKB">Although this paper focuses on economic evaluation, very similar points can be made about clinical decisions for individual patients.</s><s xml:id="_MnEAq8K">Although it is generally accepted that clinical guidelines should be based on appropriate synthesis of evidence on treatment effects <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[36]</ref>, it is also important to use decision analysis as a framework to incorporate other parameter estimates including preferences <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[37]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_amRb2aG">This implies a radically different role for the trial in evaluative health services research than is currently the case, and this would be reflected in different funding arrangements for economic evaluation.</s></p><p xml:id="_Aq4qtJ4"><s xml:id="_wv2CuA9">Ideally, funders such as the UK Medical Research Council (MRC) would support the evaluation sequence illustrated in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> which is based on iterative approaches to health technology assessment suggested elsewhere <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[38,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">39]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_QDJR8CU">Firstly, identify potentially important decision problems relating to the management of particular populations and sub-populations of individuals.</s><s xml:id="_yw49w5E">These would typically be patients but would include others in the context, for example, of preventative services.</s><s xml:id="_GJAD9Dw">The second stage would be the funding of evidence synthesis and decision modelling to address the adoption and research questions.</s><s xml:id="_nRGQ28w">Thirdly, a formal process of research prioritisation would be undertaken based on the synthesis and modelling in the second stage.</s><s xml:id="_gSawvwV">Analysis of the expected value of perfect information would be used to establish the key interventions to evaluate and parameters to estimate <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">24]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_nfAtE9r">In particular, this would be used to determine the importance of collecting additional data on relative treatment effects (requiring an RCT) and other parameters (which may be estimated using an observational design).</s><s xml:id="_d5E2RUX">Value of sample information methods would be used to establish the optimal design of primary studies in terms, for example, of sample sizes and stopping rules.</s><s xml:id="_8KjC2Kc">In other words, the question of whether additional primary studies are required and, if so, their design is an analytical question informed by the second stage.</s></p><p xml:id="_hH6tKG3"><s xml:id="_7ev6j3C">In the fourth stage, one or more primary studies may be commissioned based on the results of the third stage.</s><s xml:id="_kP89AHw">A fifth stage is to update the evidence synthesis and decision modelling with data from the additional primary studies.</s></p><p xml:id="_s7YfuCw"><s xml:id="_Uc2EPDn">In Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, this preferred iterative evaluation process is shown as a full line across all five stages.</s><s xml:id="_pRYwp5a">There is an indication that some research funders recognise the strengths of this iterative framework.</s><s xml:id="_v53bASv">For example, the NHS Health Technology Assessment programme in the UK consists of secondary research (systematic reviews and decision modelling), which informs the selection and, to some extent, design of primary research studies (mainly RCTs).</s><s xml:id="_w4c4MHw">The Medical Research Council in the UK has also recognised the value of pre-trial modelling in the context of the evaluation of complex interventions <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[40]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_sT4GuQ8">It might be expected that, as formal use of economic evaluation in reimbursement decisions about new technologies becomes more widespread internationally, this will encourage greater use of an iterative framework to research sequencing and funding.</s><s xml:id="_azVvzTw">Of course, routinely adding stages 2, 3 and 5 into research will have cost implications for funders but this cost is likely to be a small proportion of the cost of any subsequent primary study and, arguably, a Copyright # 2006 John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd.</s><s xml:id="_rZkdeYf">Health Econ.</s><s xml:id="_hVHdpvZ">15: 677-687 (2006)</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_WTp28jt">Identify decision problems</head><p xml:id="_eSKSWVh"><s xml:id="_TJZXWQG">sensible investment to ensure appropriate primary studies are funded.</s><s xml:id="_9mdZDUw">The potential of this framework does not just apply to public sector research funders.</s><s xml:id="_CVeY9gu">Manufacturers of pharmaceuticals and other medical technologies stand to benefit from a similar approach to identifying which technologies to progress through the research and development process <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[41]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_FaGKAHc">Currently, however, to the extent that economic evaluation is seen as important by any research funder, it generally fits into their funding plan through RCTs.</s><s xml:id="_DQ5GN9D">Furthermore, the economic evaluation undertaken by pharmaceutical companies is focussed on having analyses available to inform reimbursement decisions at product launch.</s><s xml:id="_V4MQ2Wp">This puts the main emphasis on the collection of data for economic analysis within the products' regulatory trial programmes.</s><s xml:id="_63NhMZp">As things stand, therefore, the trial is central to how applied economic evaluation is funded.</s><s xml:id="_Vh63gX3">This can be seen in the second line in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> where the economic analysis relates only to the fourth stage of the broader evaluation process.</s><s xml:id="_ZwdDzQE">How can researchers within the field adopt an appropriate framework for economic evaluation whilst recognising that one of the few ways resources are going to be made available for economic analysis is as part of this trial?</s></p><p xml:id="_mzyK73a"><s xml:id="_zUU5F8F">It is possible to identify two scenarios regarding how an economic component might contribute to a trial.</s><s xml:id="_YCT6AxJ">The first is where a particular research question has been established, the decision to undertake a RCT has been made but the design of that trial (options compared, endpoints, follow-up, etc.) has yet to be determined.</s><s xml:id="_mN8acbk">In this situation, the ideal would be to be able to identify funds to undertake some initial synthesis and modelling to get a rough idea of the expected cost-effectiveness of all alternatives based on current evidence, the key uncertainties and the most appropriate primary research design.</s><s xml:id="_QqqJa9G">In essence, this might be seen as a constrained version of stage two and three in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_zhmPFwN">There may be an opportunity to undertake such work as part of a trial pilot study, but it is probably unlikely that it would be able to feed into trial design in an unconstrained manner.</s></p><p xml:id="_PGsD2pR"><s xml:id="_S3wASVx">A more likely situation is that there will be no opportunity for modelling, that the options being compared will have been selected and will be a sub-set of the relevant alternatives, and the size and follow-up period will be determined by the (anticipated) available budget.</s><s xml:id="_4N3K8eP">In these circumstances, one option would be for the economic evaluation researcher not to participate in the research given the absence of any coherent approach to its specification.</s><s xml:id="_rp58PxK">However, this would lose the opportunity to collect resource use or health-related quality of life data which may be expected to be important in establishing costeffectiveness, and miss the possibility of influencing trial analysis.</s><s xml:id="_M64VNYB">The marginal cost of such data collection may be quite modest given that the trial will be going ahead anyway.</s><s xml:id="_Dvydu8U">Furthermore, by remaining involved in the trial, it would hopefully be possible to secure a budget for economic analysis when the trial data emerge.</s><s xml:id="_KcYfetK">However, the purpose of this funding would not be to undertake a standard trial-based economic evaluation based only on the sample of trial patients.</s><s xml:id="_8CbwUsm">Rather, it would be to use the data collected in the trial as part of a wider trawl of available evidence, and to synthesise this within a decision-modelling framework based on a potentially broader specification of the decision problem.</s><s xml:id="_u6VpJw7">This is illustrated by the third line in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_aTqhVqQ">For large trials in clinical areas where primary studies are relatively rare, it is possible that the trial will provide a large proportion of the parameter estimates for the model.</s><s xml:id="_AtTGHXK">Clearly, this approach would require a carefully written proposal, which would have to emphasise the added value of this more comprehensive approach to economic evaluation.</s><s xml:id="_tV4X7de">Research funders will undoubtedly vary in their reaction to such methods, although it might be hoped that those who see their role as directly informing health service decision making (e.g. the NHS Health Technology Programme) are more likely to support the approach.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_nZDXRBN">Conclusions</head><p xml:id="_TUPv5P6"><s xml:id="_6fduFmk">For many years the RCT has been a convenient way of getting economic evaluation studies funded and undertaken.</s><s xml:id="_8fxD72M">However, for a large proportion of that period, once the study was published, it played little role in actual decisions about resource allocation.</s><s xml:id="_2gxmgNF">Many health care systems in developed countries now use economic evaluation as a formal input to decisions about whether to fund new interventions.</s><s xml:id="_By5tjje">This use of economic analysis for specific decisions raises a series of questions about appropriate methods.</s><s xml:id="_6mfAugU">It has been argued in this paper that the use of a single trial as a vehicle for economic analysis will, in most situations, lead to</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_qA7w56R"><s xml:id="_3wG73mv">Figure 1.</s><s xml:id="_JYeJBZE">Five stages in an iterative approach to the economic evaluation of health technologies</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p xml:id="_dTdS5Sf"><s xml:id="_3ukmthM">10991050, 2006, 7, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/hec.1093</s><s xml:id="_GYNFzzM">by University Of Iowa Libraries -Serials Acquisitions, Wiley Online Library on [14/08/2025].</s><s xml:id="_DhXDFc8">See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions)</s><s xml:id="_dNy8yqF">on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License</s></p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head xml:id="_mXaxw3N">Acknowledgements</head><p xml:id="_TTAeagC"><s xml:id="_5JKbcRJ">This study was undertaken as part of a programme of methodological research funded by the <rs type="funder">UK Medical Research Council</rs> through the <rs type="funder">Health Services Research Collaboration</rs>.</s><s xml:id="_f8YqZbc"><rs type="person">Mark Sculpher</rs> also receives funding via a <rs type="grantName">Career Award in Public Health</rs> funded by the <rs type="programName">NHS Research and Development Programme</rs>.</s><s xml:id="_A8cx3fu">The views expressed are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect those of the funders.</s><s xml:id="_kb9A75f">The authors are grateful for comments from <rs type="person">John Brazier</rs> and <rs type="person">Tony O'Hagan</rs>, as well as colleagues at the January 2005 meeting of the <rs type="institution">Health Economics Study Group</rs> meeting in Oxford and the July 2005 meeting of the <rs type="institution">International Health Economics Association in Barcelona</rs>.</s></p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_PN9Avnh">
					<orgName type="grant-name">Career Award in Public Health</orgName>
					<orgName type="program" subtype="full">NHS Research and Development Programme</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_dye8TSz"><p xml:id="_DUyXxfD"><s xml:id="_J6ARKGW">a partial and limited analysis with which to inform decision making.</s><s xml:id="_E9Ha6jV">The more appropriate framework for economic analysis is evidence synthesis and decision modelling where all available data are brought to bear on fully specified decision problems.</s><s xml:id="_XGzf44G">Given that a large proportion of funding for economic evaluation currently flows through the RCT, however, it will be necessary to use the trial as a key source of data collection, but also to ensure that analysis includes explicit evidence synthesis and a decision-modelling component.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_QrpgsEz">Clinical Epidemiology: A Basic Science for Clinical Medicine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Sackett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Haynes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Tugwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
			<publisher>Little, Brown and Co</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Toronto</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sackett DL, Haynes RB, Tugwell P. Clinical Epidemiology: A Basic Science for Clinical Medicine. Little, Brown and Co.: Toronto; 1985.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_YFGGnqu">Results of clinical trials and systematic trials: to whom do they apply? In The Advanced Handbook of Methods in Evidence Based Healthcare</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>O'connell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Glasziou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sarunac</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lowe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Stevens A, Abrams K, Brazier R, Fitzpatrick R, Lilford R</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
			<pubPlace>Sage; London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">O&apos;Connell D, Glasziou P, Hill S, Sarunac J, Lowe J, Henry D. Results of clinical trials and systematic trials: to whom do they apply? In The Advanced Handbook of Methods in Evidence Based Healthcare, Stevens A, Abrams K, Brazier R, Fitzpatrick R, Lilford R (eds). Sage: London; 2001.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_h2gJrgk">Health economic guidelines -similarities, differences and some implications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hjelmgren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Berggren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Andersson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1046/j.1524-4733.2001.43040.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_24ABxVQ">Value Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="225" to="250" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hjelmgren J, Berggren F, Andersson F. Health economic guidelines -similarities, differences and some implications. Value Health 2001; 4: 225-250.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_KYKcQyB">Guide to the Methods of Technology Appraisal</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-0-387-71996-2_3</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<pubPlace>NICE; London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>National Institute for Clinical Excellence (NICE</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">National Institute for Clinical Excellence (NICE). Guide to the Methods of Technology Appraisal. NICE: London; 2004.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_DJ7Adep">Guide to Technology Appraisal Process</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-0-387-71996-2_3</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<pubPlace>NICE; London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>National Institute for Clinical Excellence (NICE)</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">National Institute for Clinical Excellence (NICE). Guide to Technology Appraisal Process. NICE: London; 2004.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_k89b9WY">A rational framework for decision making by the National Institute for Clinical Excellence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Claxton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sculpher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Drummond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0140-6736(02)09832-x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_qXkyc6n">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">360</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="711" to="715" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Claxton K, Sculpher M, Drummond M. A rational framework for decision making by the National Institute for Clinical Excellence. Lancet 2002; 360: 711-715.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_nHRwrFz">It&apos;s just evaluation for decision making: recent developments in, and challenges for, cost-effectiveness research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sculpher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Claxton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Akehurst</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_mHE85Tz">Health Policy and Economics. Opportunities and Challenges</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ginnelly</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sculpher</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Maidenhead</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sculpher M, Claxton K, Akehurst R. It&apos;s just evaluation for decision making: recent develop- ments in, and challenges for, cost-effectiveness research. In Health Policy and Economics. Opportu- nities and Challenges, Smith PC, Ginnelly L, Sculpher M (eds). Open University Press: Maiden- head, 2005.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_YJu9PQR">Evidence-based medicine: what it is and what it isn&apos;t</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Sackett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wmc</forename><surname>Rosenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jam</forename><surname>Gray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Haynes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Richardson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_RGEZztb">Br Med J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">312</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="71" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sackett DL, Rosenberg WMC, Gray JAM, Haynes RB, Richardson WS. Evidence-based medicine: what it is and what it isn&apos;t. Br Med J 1996; 312: 71-72.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_4ZKYRWR">Probabilistic sensitivity analysis for NICE technology assessment: not an optional extra</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Claxton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sculpher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mccabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/hec.985</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_znBbpwp">Health Econ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="339" to="347" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Claxton K, Sculpher M, McCabe C et al. Probabil- istic sensitivity analysis for NICE technology assessment: not an optional extra. Health Econ 2005; 14: 339-347.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_UQYFRNc">The irrelevance of inference: a decisionmaking approach to the stochastic evaluation of heath care technologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Claxton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0167-6296(98)00039-3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_CfzKudq">J Health Econ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="341" to="364" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Claxton K. The irrelevance of inference: a decision- making approach to the stochastic evaluation of heath care technologies. J Health Econ 1999; 18: 341-364.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_TpYyDCF">An economic approach to clinical trial design and research priority-setting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Claxton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Posnett</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_gAEJ5eC">Health Econ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="513" to="524" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Claxton K, Posnett J. An economic approach to clinical trial design and research priority-setting. Health Econ 1996; 5: 513-524.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_pYjYKhk">A pilot study on the use of decision theory and value of information analysis as part of the National Health Service Health Technology Assessment Programme</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Claxton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ginnelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sculpher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Philips</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Palmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_j3bymR3">Health Technol Assess</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="132" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Claxton K, Ginnelly L, Sculpher M, Philips Z, Palmer S. A pilot study on the use of decision theory and value of information analysis as part of the National Health Service Health Technology Assess- ment Programme. Health Technol Assess 2004; 8(31): 1-132.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_nresCSH">A Rapid and Systematic Review of the Clinical Effectiveness, Tolerability and Cost Effectiveness of Newer Drugs for Epilepsy in Adults</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wilby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kainth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hawkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="www.nice.org.uk" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>National Institute for Clinical Excellence</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Wilby J, Kainth K, Hawkins N et al. A Rapid and Systematic Review of the Clinical Effectiveness, Tolerability and Cost Effectiveness of Newer Drugs for Epilepsy in Adults. National Institute for Clinical Excellence: London; 2003 (www.nice.org.uk).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Jobanputra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Barton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3310/hta6210</idno>
		<ptr target="http://www.nice.org.uk/pdf/RAAssessmentReport.pdf" />
		<title level="m" xml:id="_DnDSMrX">The Clinical Effectiveness and Cost-Effectiveness of New Drug Treatment for Rheumatoid Arthritis: Etenercept and Infliximab</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Birmingham University; Birmingham</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Jobanputra P, Barton P, Bryan S et al. The Clinical Effectiveness and Cost-Effectiveness of New Drug Treatment for Rheumatoid Arthritis: Etenercept and Infliximab. Birmingham University: Birmingham, 2004 (http://www.nice.org.uk/pdf/RAAssessment Report.pdf).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_kbnNbCC">Cost effectiveness of thrombolytic therapy with tissue plasminogen activator as compared with streptokinase for acute myocardial infarction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Mark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hlatky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Califf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1056/nejm199505253322106</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_KgPGAUw">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">332</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1418" to="1424" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mark DB, Hlatky MA, Califf RM et al. Cost effectiveness of thrombolytic therapy with tissue plasminogen activator as compared with streptoki- nase for acute myocardial infarction. N Engl J Med 1995; 332: 1418-1424.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_UgTsdbA">Low doses versus high doses of the angiotensin convertingenzyme inhibitor lisinopril in chronic heart failure: a cost-effectiveness analysis based on the Assessment of Treatment with Lisinopril and Survival (ATLAS) study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sculpher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Poole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jgf</forename><surname>Cleland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s1388-9842(00)00122-7</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Q4vzjQ7">Eur J Heart Failure</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="447" to="454" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sculpher MJ, Poole L, Cleland JGF et al. Low doses versus high doses of the angiotensin converting- enzyme inhibitor lisinopril in chronic heart failure: a cost-effectiveness analysis based on the Assessment of Treatment with Lisinopril and Survival (ATLAS) study. Eur J Heart Failure 2000; 2: 447-454.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ZcCbkEc">Assessing generalisability by location in trial based cost effectiveness analysis: the use of multilevel models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Manca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Rice</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sculpher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Briggs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/hec.914</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_TznmG7r">Health Econ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="471" to="485" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Manca A, Rice N, Sculpher MJ, Briggs AH. Assessing generalisability by location in trial based cost effectiveness analysis: the use of multilevel models. Health Econ 2005; 14: 471-485.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_fs9u7Zy">Country specific cost comparisons from multinational clinical trials using empirical Bayesian shrinkage estimation: the Canadian ASSENT-3 economic analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Willan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Pinto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O'</forename><surname>Brien</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_WgKuMWf">Health Econ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="327" to="338" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Willan AR, Pinto EM, O&apos;Brien BJ et al. Country specific cost comparisons from multinational clinical trials using empirical Bayesian shrinkage estimation: the Canadian ASSENT-3 economic analysis. Health Econ 2005; 14: 327-338.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_vtyPgd2">Copyright #</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/pds.1182</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_f6xhgJS">Ltd. Health Econ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="677" to="687" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006. 2006</date>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Copyright # 2006 John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. Health Econ. 15: 677-687 (2006)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_MTFGrxR">Using multilevel models for assessing the variability of multinational resource use and cost data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Grieve</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Nixon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Normand</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/hec.916</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_tS6Yw5W">Health Econ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="185" to="196" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Grieve R, Nixon R, Thompson S, Normand C. Using multilevel models for assessing the variability of multinational resource use and cost data. Health Econ 2005; 14: 185-196.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_9YyxEUM">Cost-effectiveness of alternative strategies for the initial medical management of non-ST elevation acute coronary syndrome: systematic review and decision analytic mdelling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Palmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sculpher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Philips</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ginnelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bowens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3310/hta9270</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_qg8McrZ">Health Technol Assess</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="172" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Robinson M, Palmer S, Sculpher MJ, Philips Z, Ginnelly L, Bowens A et al. Cost-effectiveness of alternative strategies for the initial medical manage- ment of non-ST elevation acute coronary syndrome: systematic review and decision analytic mdelling. Health Technol Assess 2005; 9: 1-172.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_kGyZq7n">Technological change around the world: evidence from heart attack care</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mcclellan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kessler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Saynina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Moreland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_27J8UsK">Health Affair</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="250" to="255" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">McClellan M, Kessler D, Saynina O, Moreland A. Technological change around the world: evidence from heart attack care. Health Affair 2001; 20(3): 250-255.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_eh4vY2M">Management of non-ST-elevation acute coronary syndromes: how cost-effective are glycoprotein IIb/IIIa antagonists in the UK National Health Service?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Palmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sculpher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Philips</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ijcard.2004.08.042</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_GxvE9wY">Int J Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="229" to="240" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Palmer S, Sculpher M, Philips Z et al. Management of non-ST-elevation acute coronary syndromes: how cost-effective are glycoprotein IIb/IIIa antago- nists in the UK National Health Service? Int J Cardiol 2005; 100: 229-240.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_665YyE6">Methods for Meta-Analysis in Medical Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sutton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Abrams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sheldon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<publisher>Chichester</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sutton AJ, Abrams KR, Jones DR, Sheldon TA, Song TA. Methods for Meta-Analysis in Medical Research. Wiley: Chichester, 2000.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_FtU6srw">Expected value of sample information in medical decision modelling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Ades</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Claxton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0272989x04263162</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_w2bQfGy">Med Decis Making</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="207" to="227" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ades AE, Lu G, Claxton K. Expected value of sample information in medical decision modelling. Med Decis Making 2003; 24: 207-227.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qAcUQtw">Problems of using modelling in the economic evaluation of health care</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sheldon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/(sici)1099-1050(199601)5:1&lt;1::aid-hec183&gt;3.0.co;2-k</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_u9vVmNw">Health Econ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sheldon TA. Problems of using modelling in the economic evaluation of health care. Health Econ 1996; 5: 1-11.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_yrc25xV">The Journal&apos;s policy on costeffectiveness analyses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Kassirer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Angell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_wHv2yke">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">331</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="669" to="670" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kassirer JP, Angell M. The Journal&apos;s policy on cost- effectiveness analyses. N Engl J Med 1994; 331(10): 669-670.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_RxyhVrS">Modelling in the economic evaluation of health care: selecting the appropriate approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Barton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_pFncjN5">J Health Serv Res Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="110" to="118" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Barton P, Bryan S, Robinson S. Modelling in the economic evaluation of health care: selecting the appropriate approach. J Health Serv Res Policy 2004; 9: 110-118.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_zHMeZar">Bayesian methods in metaanalysis and evidence synthesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sutton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Abrams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1191/096228001678227794</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_b7Hyy8k">Stat Method Med Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="277" to="303" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sutton AJ, Abrams KR. Bayesian methods in meta- analysis and evidence synthesis. Stat Method Med Res 2001; 10: 277-303.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_f8GGmh2">Borrowing strength from external trials in meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jpt</forename><surname>Higgins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Whitehead</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/(sici)1097-0258(19961230)15:24&lt;2733::aid-sim562&gt;3.0.co;2-0</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_mQQ53ct">Stat Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2733" to="2749" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Higgins JPT, Whitehead J. Borrowing strength from external trials in meta-analysis. Stat Med 1996; 15: 2733-2749.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_PHMCYys">A chain of evidence with mixed comparisons: models for multi-parameter evidence synthesis and consistency of evidence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Ades</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/sim.1566</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_CWSk5tj">Stat Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2995" to="3016" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ades AE. A chain of evidence with mixed compar- isons: models for multi-parameter evidence synth- esis and consistency of evidence. Stat Med 2003; 22: 2995-3016.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_sVNxvsh">Meta-analysis of multiple outcomes by regression with random effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Berkey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hoaglin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Antczak-Bouckoms</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mosteler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Colditz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/(sici)1097-0258(19981130)17:22&lt;2537::aid-sim953&gt;3.0.co;2-c</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_AqXykpu">Stat Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2537" to="2550" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Berkey CS, Hoaglin DC, Antczak-Bouckoms A, Mosteler F, Colditz GA. Meta-analysis of multiple outcomes by regression with random effects. Stat Med 1998; 17: 2537-2550.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_7D8Qfdw">A review of guidelines for good practice in decision-analytic modelling in health technol assessment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Philips</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ginnelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sculpher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3310/hta8360</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_4w9Msgq">Health Technol Assess</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="188" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Philips Z, Ginnelly L, Sculpher M et al. A review of guidelines for good practice in decision-analytic modelling in health technol assessment. Health Technol Assess 2004; 8(36): 1-188.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Cpk8KBf">Markov Chain Monte Carlo estimation of a multi-parameter decision model: consistency of evidence and the accurate assessment of uncertainty</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Ades</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cliffe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/027298902400448920</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_wNbHfmm">Med Decis Making</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="359" to="371" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ades AE, Cliffe S. Markov Chain Monte Carlo estimation of a multi-parameter decision model: consistency of evidence and the accurate assessment of uncertainty. Med Decis Making 2002; 22: 359-371.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_NCZh3W2">Performing cost-effectiveness analysis by integrating randomised trial data with a comprehensive decision model: application to treatment of ischemic stroke</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Samsa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Reutter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Parmigiani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0895-4356(98)00151-6</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_c9UKPZX">J Clin Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="259" to="271" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Samsa GP, Reutter RA, Parmigiani G et al. Performing cost-effectiveness analysis by integrating randomised trial data with a comprehensive decision model: application to treatment of ischemic stroke. J Clin Epidemiol 1999; 52: 259-271.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_P6keWym">Comprehensive decision analytical modelling in economic evaluation: a Bayesian approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sutton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Abrams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wailoo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/hec.804</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_SrwyCbr">Health Econ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="226" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Cooper NJ, Sutton AJ, Abrams KR, Turner D, Wailoo A. Comprehensive decision analytical mod- elling in economic evaluation: a Bayesian approach. Health Econ 2004; 13: 203-226.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_HaZm9nb">How to develop cost-conscious guidelines</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Eccles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mason</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3310/hta5160</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_dX8EgTS">Health Technol Assess</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Eccles M, Mason J. How to develop cost-con- scious guidelines. Health Technol Assess 2001; 5(16): 1-83.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_seDHBze">A normative analytic framework for development of practice guidelines for specific clinical populations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Owens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Nease</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0272989x9701700406</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_szprjMn">Med Decis Making</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="409" to="426" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Owens DK, Nease RF. A normative analytic framework for development of practice guidelines for specific clinical populations. Med Decis Making 1997; 17(4): 409-426.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_8y7RF4F">The iterative use of economic evaluation as part of the process of health technology assessment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sculpher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Drummond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Buxton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_EKyVc8e">J Health Serv Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="26" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sculpher M, Drummond M, Buxton M. The iterative use of economic evaluation as part of the process of health technology assessment. J Health Serv Policy 1997; 2(1): 26-30.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_UEvBn4Z">Improving the efficiency and relevance of health technology assessment: the role of decision analytic modelling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Fenwick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Claxton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sculpher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Briggs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.7748/nm.7.5.39.s13</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s" xml:id="_d47hRup">Centre for Health Economics Discussion Paper</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">179</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<pubPlace>York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Centre for Health Economics, University of York</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Fenwick E, Claxton K, Sculpher M, Briggs A. Improving the efficiency and relevance of health technology assessment: the role of decision analytic modelling. Centre for Health Economics Discussion Paper 179. Centre for Health Economics, University of York: York, 2000.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_B5AJckh">A Frame work for Development and Evaluation of RCTs for Complex Interventions to Improve Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>MRC Health Services and Public Health Research Board ; Medical Research Council</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">MRC Health Services and Public Health Research Board. A Frame work for Development and Evalua- tion of RCTs for Complex Interventions to Improve Health. Medical Research Council: London, 2000.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_GdKz69e">Optimal drug development programmes and efficient licensing and reimbursement rules: the role of value of information analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hawkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Claxton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s1098-3015(10)61624-5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_6gSY8Gz">Society of Medical Decision Making Conference</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Chicago</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>abstract</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hawkins N, Claxton K. Optimal drug development programmes and efficient licensing and reimburse- ment rules: the role of value of information analysis (abstract). Society of Medical Decision Making Conference, Chicago, 2003.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
