<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_YgfWA45">A reinforcement learning based algorithm for personalization of digital, just-in-time, adaptive interventions</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
					<p type="raw">© 2021 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</p>
				</availability>
				<date>2 April 2021 0933</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Suat</forename><surname>Gönül</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>a</label> SRDC Corp. , Silikon Blok Kat :</note>
								<orgName type="institution">SRDC Corp</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Silikon Blok Kat</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tuncay</forename><surname>Namlı</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>a</label> SRDC Corp. , Silikon Blok Kat :</note>
								<orgName type="institution">SRDC Corp</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Silikon Blok Kat</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ahmet</forename><surname>Cos ¸ar</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>b</label> Department of Computer Engineering , Middle East Technical University , Orta Dogu</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Middle East Technical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Orta Dogu</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hakkı</forename><surname>Toroslu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>b</label> Department of Computer Engineering , Middle East Technical University , Orta Dogu</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Middle East Technical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Orta Dogu</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>1</label> No:</note>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>16</label> SRDC Teknokent ODTÜ , Ankara , Turkey</note>
								<orgName type="institution">SRDC Teknokent ODTÜ</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Ankara</settlement>
									<country key="TR">Turkey</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Teknik Üniversitesi Universiteler Mah. Dumlupinar Blv. No:1 06800 , Ankara Turkey</note>
								<orgName type="institution">Teknik Üniversitesi Universiteler</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Mah. Dumlupinar Blv. No:1</addrLine>
									<postCode>06800</postCode>
									<settlement>Ankara</settlement>
									<country key="TR">Turkey</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_8E53Xn7">A reinforcement learning based algorithm for personalization of digital, just-in-time, adaptive interventions</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published">2 April 2021 0933</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">401058A33624570D2E1C64E6C629AC22</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.artmed.2021.102062</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 31 July 2020; Received in revised form 4 March 2021; Accepted 29 March 2021</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T10:53+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords xml:id="_yt7uCzH">Reinforcement learning Intervention delivery optimization Just-in-time adaptive interventions</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_RcAYfDu"><p xml:id="_e8C8Nx9"><s xml:id="_DftBqx5">A C T Suboptimal health related behaviors and habits; and resulting chronic diseases are responsible for majority of deaths globally.</s><s xml:id="_pgjFHVu">Studies show that providing personalized support to patients yield improved results by preventing and/or timely treatment of these problems.</s><s xml:id="_3yq5umz">Digital, just-in-time and adaptive interventions are mobile phone-based notifications that are being utilized to support people wherever and whenever necessary in coping with their health problems.</s><s xml:id="_4hzZaVB">In this research, we propose a reinforcement learning-based mechanism to personalize interventions in terms of timing, frequency and preferred type(s).</s><s xml:id="_kqbex6V">We simultaneously employ two reinforcement learning models, namely intervention-selection and opportune-moment-identification; capturing and exploiting changes in people's long-term and momentary contexts respectively.</s><s xml:id="_Q6T4qTa">While the intervention-selection model adapts the intervention delivery with respect to type and frequency, the opportune-moment-identification model tries to find the most opportune moments to deliver interventions throughout a day.</s><s xml:id="_bYtBCWG">We propose two accelerator techniques over the standard reinforcement learning algorithms to boost learning performance.</s><s xml:id="_3aTjcYp">First, we propose a customized version of eligibility traces for rewarding past actions throughout an agent's trajectory.</s><s xml:id="_ZNyzes6">Second, we utilize the transfer learning method to reuse knowledge across multiple learning environments.</s><s xml:id="_Ap3ars7">We validate the proposed approach in a simulated experiment where we simulate four personas differing in their daily activities, preferences on specific intervention types and attitudes towards the targeted behavior.</s><s xml:id="_C49sHCj">Our experiments show that the proposed approach yields better results compared to the standard reinforcement learning algorithms and successfully capture the simulated variations associated with the personas.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="10" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="11" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="12" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="13" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="14" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="15" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="16" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="17" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="18" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1." xml:id="_u3cm9Av">Introduction</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1." xml:id="_pNAkxdA">Motivation</head><p xml:id="_pXj24hE"><s xml:id="_fBTUDZZ">Suboptimal health behaviors and chronic diseases are responsible for approximately 40% of preventable deaths, in addition to their undesirable effects on quality of life and economy <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_pUt8agY">Chronic diseases are so prevalent nowadays that they cause deaths of approximately 40 million people yearly, corresponding to 70% of the deaths globally <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_EywFsE3">People's self-management abilities are of critical importance with regards to treatment of suboptimal health behaviors, habits; and chronic diseases.</s><s xml:id="_Vhq4Ryq">Some common self-management activities include, but not limited to, complying with dietary plans, adherence to prescribed medications or performing physical exercises <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_aJKvXfc">Supporting people in such activities necessitates consideration of individuals' unique lifestyles and priorities; their psychological and psychosocial contexts; and environmental factors <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_KjyzGrk">It is proven in many studies that providing personalized self-management support related to chronic diseases or common health problems yield better results compared to person-invariant approaches <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_7RhQqpp"><s xml:id="_jZrZY9w">Digital interventions are very suitable to support people in their selfmanagement activities.</s><s xml:id="_h5pBYGw">Recent technological advances in mobile and health sensors (wearable, implanted and digestible) areas <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> have provided means to deliver adaptive interventions via mobile devices momentarily, when required.</s><s xml:id="_BmQv79e">In this respect, the main objective of this work is to deliver an algorithm that learns personalized intervention delivery strategies with consideration to people's long-term and momentary contexts.</s><s xml:id="_xQCqmzs">The aim, in turn, as related to real-life care programs, 's to maximize adherence by preventing avoidable burden of these interventions and thus achieve better clinical outcomes eventually.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2." xml:id="_mm8v9mU">Reinforcement Learning (RL) for personalization of JITAIs</head><p xml:id="_zSZAFwm"><s xml:id="_En3eHqH">The just-in-time adaptive intervention (JITAI) concept is introduced by Nahum-Shani et al. to define momentary interventions via a number of components such as decision points or intervention options <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_vkRWeWS">We propose an RL <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> based algorithm for personalization of JITAI components.</s><s xml:id="_QXN9KGr">Using RL for this purpose is convenient for a number of reasons: Firstly, an RL agent learns through experience.</s><s xml:id="_xMwA9kz">Therefore, it does not require an initial data set, as used by other forms of learning methods to train an internal model or policy.</s><s xml:id="_xP9AP59">However, it is still possible to bootstrap the learning process to make sensible choices of interventions by configuring the policy based on external expert knowledge <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_gwawbTq"><s xml:id="_kXuWYwQ">The RL framework is convenient for modeling people's varying contexts (e.g.</s><s xml:id="_2vQ2hXj">environmental or psychosocial) and devising a learning algorithm based on each individual's continuously changing context values.</s><s xml:id="_kJWXHt3">Having an iterative nature, an RL agent performs actions based on its environment while continuously observing state changes of the environment; and updates its learning model based on the rewards.</s><s xml:id="_8zc6HMq">Similarly, in our case, the learning algorithm reacts to the changing contexts of an individual and updates its internal policy.</s><s xml:id="_kpkySau">By doing so, the algorithm is expected to construct a (near-) optimal personalized intervention delivery policy.</s></p><p xml:id="_e2vty4N"><s xml:id="_kzjk8aX">In principle, traditional RL already provides mechanisms to learn solutions for any task without the need of human supervision.</s><s xml:id="_ThrwhrS">However, if RL agents begin learning tabula rasa, i.e. no prior knowledge from a domain expert is available, the number of samples needed to learn a nearly optimal solution is often prohibitively large for real-world problems <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_JuAg8e5">So, learning a near-optimal policy is often slow or infeasible, especially if the experiment involves real-world subjects.</s><s xml:id="_upSV4Z5">In addition to long learning times, learning performance in a traditional RL system is usually asymptotic to a logarithmic curve, meaning that mostly random actions would be taken during the beginning phase of the learning process when the state space is scarcely explored <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_FRwKM4j">Addressing these challenges about the application of RL in problems with real subjects, our objective is to deliver an algorithm that learns a personalized policy quickly, which produces acceptible results even when the state space is scarcely explored.</s><s xml:id="_qq5xmD7">The algorithm is supposed to adapt its intervention delivery strategy dynamically and systematically based on people's ever-changing, unique momentary and long-term contexts.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.3." xml:id="_V6R8Nw7">Main contributions</head><p xml:id="_ERf6BU2"><s xml:id="_2XBVcNa">In our recent work <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, a single RL model was developed in order to optimize all aspects of JITAIs.</s><s xml:id="_JkqrMfm">Several extensions are built in this research based on this work.</s><s xml:id="_WM57UZR">Main contributions of this work are listed below:</s></p><p xml:id="_stX4qec"><s xml:id="_uFpQHN8">• Modeling the personalized JITAI delivery problem by simultaneously employing two RL models, namely intervention-selection and opportune-moment-identification.</s><s xml:id="_dvScpua">They learn personalized patterns with respect to two intrinsic characterics of JITAIs: adaptiveness and justin-timeness respectively.</s><s xml:id="_gf3Mr7E">The intervention-selection model adapts intervention delivery considering that a person still needs to be supported towards forming habit on a targeted behavior.</s><s xml:id="_Jgy2dRy">The model learns personal preferences on intervention types and frequency throughout the learning process.</s><s xml:id="_ZUBarRf">The opportune-moment-identification model, learns personalized patterns to deliver interventions at the most opportune moments during the day.</s><s xml:id="_3RGtdw5">• Integration of an empirically validated habit formation model <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> for realistic simulation of habit related parameters included in people's long terms contexts.</s><s xml:id="_FKyu9xC">• Mathematical background for the main RL models as well as the optimization techniques utilized by these models.</s><s xml:id="_eK4RgUR">The interventionselection model utilizes habit formation model in order to simulate people's habitual behaviors and habit formation processes; the opportune-moment-identification model utilizes selective eligibility traces and transfer learning techniques to accelerate the learning process to learn personalized patterns and devise tailored intervention delivery strategies.</s><s xml:id="_RCGE9SC">• Simulation-based validation where personas are simulated with variations in their daily activities, preferences on specific intervention types and attitudes towards a targeted behavior.</s><s xml:id="_5TAqVFP">• Analysis of the performance of the two RL-models individually and validation of their hyperparameter configurations.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.4." xml:id="_7wyHkYk">Organization of the paper</head><p xml:id="_79q2jVb"><s xml:id="_z6N3XYM">In the rest of the manuscript, Section 2 presents related works related to personalized intervention delivery and methods beyond the traditional RL.</s><s xml:id="_wdwrDGb">Section 3 includes the main concepts and approach.</s><s xml:id="_z8EWXut">Section 4 presents the learning algorithm after elaborating accelerator techniques applied on the standard methods.</s><s xml:id="_F82kBJH">Section 5 presents an instantiation of the conceptual approach by elaborating two Markov Decision Process (MDP)-based RL models.</s><s xml:id="_mJeesKQ">Section 6 presents the simulation-based validation approach by giving details about the variations of the simulated personas.</s><s xml:id="_287KnxZ">After presenting the results of the validation approach and discussing their alignment with the simulation configurations in Section 7, we conclude the paper.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2." xml:id="_Yk3SkF7">Related work</head><p xml:id="_N9bmKza"><s xml:id="_En7G7S7">We investigate related works from two main perspectives.</s><s xml:id="_FwqRFSM">We first analyze studies providing personalized support (in the form of mobile phone-based interventions) to people suffering from chronic diseases or health problems.</s><s xml:id="_K4bzUu8">We are specifically interested in their system design and personalization methods.</s><s xml:id="_PN84FHC">Second, we present studies proposing alternative ways of rewarding past actions and applying transfer learning between learning environments.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_VkAtxsd">Personalization of interventions via adaptivity and just-in-timeness.:</head><p xml:id="_U6FwppZ"><s xml:id="_FXz74Jy">Personalized guidance to people suffering from health problems have been studied in many studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_QxFZprM">Gustafson et al. developed a framework with several self-management support modules for overcoming alcohol addiction <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_3bKvBeC">GPS monitoring module, one of the modules of their system, warns people when they are close to a pre-defined place.</s><s xml:id="_avuNCZV">The work proposed by Waki et al. processes patients' inputs about food and physical exercise, collected twice a day, and generates an intervention accordingly <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_R9aajCQ">Personalization via RL is applied in other domains such as personalized medicine <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref> in critical care or education <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_2VVbbDY">We consider such systems as static considering their decision making methods on delivering interventions.</s><s xml:id="_cR2BJhj">In contrary to such approaches, our approach keeps a dynamic set of decision rules inside the RL algorithm's policy.</s><s xml:id="_YHNtfZz">This provides a systematic way to improve/adapt intervention delivery dynamically in time according to the changing person contexts.</s></p><p xml:id="_BsjYZss"><s xml:id="_GZEbeYG">Optimization of intervention delivery with respect to just-intimeness and adaptivity were investigated by many studies in the literature.</s><s xml:id="_MKSwPhh">Some of them tackle specific health problems.</s><s xml:id="_jwsTAx2">For example, the agent-based model developed by Chih et al. discovers the predictors of food choice and obesity <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_jyzE4AJ">Similarly, the system proposed by Goldstein et al. predicts dietary lapses and delivers interventions tailored for individuals <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_yVqmYGY">Their system uses supervised machine learning techniques working on physiological context variables and identifies strong predictors of potential lapses.</s><s xml:id="_gVdQj3G">On the other hand, there are also studies devising more generic systems that optimize JITAI components dynamically.</s><s xml:id="_Q6buW9e">These systems implement mathematical models of existing behavior change theories by capturing long-term changes in the model parameters and adapting the intervention parameters accordingly <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_FQNMDCW">For instance, the system proposed by Navarro-Barrientos et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref> realizes the Theory of Planned Behavior <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_fXbsu4T">The system targets adaptation of intervention parameters so that users of the system can lose weight.</s><s xml:id="_48USgv9">Martin et al.'s system benefits from the Social Cognitive Theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> in supporting people with their physical activity tasks <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_DqgQXXr">Spruitz et al. introduce a generic conceptual approach to devise data-driven mathematical models for JITAIs <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_jeVxyRd"><s xml:id="_9QacHyg">The study conducted by Lei et al. is closest to ours in terms of utilization of RL for optimization of JITAI parameters <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_Rc97CgY">They reduce the intervention delivery problem into a contextual bandit problem by modelling the states of the RL environment with various momentary context parameters.</s><s xml:id="_Arbp8ZB">As the learning algorithm, the referred study benefits from a native actor-critic approach while ours employs an actor-only approach learning in an online setting.</s><s xml:id="_Z5Z6kkQ">They also present a simulation-based validation approach to investigate the performance of their approach.</s><s xml:id="_WSFXVYX">They assume a person context composed of i.i.d.</s><s xml:id="_fVYEWrG">variables.</s><s xml:id="_wQ62Wns">As described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>, we utilize a template-based context simulation where contexts are composed of individual variables that are randomized with Gaussian distribution.</s><s xml:id="_Db9BgX8">Like us, Lei et al. also considers intervention burden on people where the burden effect is reflected to the reward function of the RL setup.</s><s xml:id="_DxrKf6r">Our simulation approach also includes the habit concept and incorporates the habit formation model to simulate relevant parameters.</s></p><p xml:id="_m5SEbJT"><s xml:id="_Gsp7Vx8">Rewarding past actions.: Eligibility traces are one of the basic mechanisms for rewarding past actions.</s><s xml:id="_97m4txb">Basic eligibility tracing has two variations, namely accumulating traces and replacing traces.</s><s xml:id="_H6ehzxv">In the accumulating traces, eligibility value of a revisited state is increased by 1, which allows eligibility values larger than 1.</s><s xml:id="_A5vaBmz">In the replacing traces case, though, eligibility values of revisited states are reset to 1.</s><s xml:id="_u9b63xG">This means that frequency and recency are primary heuristics in accumulating and replacing traces respectively.</s><s xml:id="_6BrwQPD">In our approach, we utilize accumulating traces as we want a fast learning rate for frequently visited states.</s></p><p xml:id="_cmPjppX"><s xml:id="_aGF3Fx7">Some studies are similar to ours in terms of selective, postponed rewarding of past actions considering that some of the actions taken could be suboptimal.</s><s xml:id="_mZChYRZ">For example, Bloch et al. propose the Temporal Second Difference Traces method so that trace updates can be performed after apparently suboptimal actions are taken <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_rkFArMd">In addition to keeping track of a single eligibility value for visited states, the method keeps track of all updates on the eligilibility values.</s><s xml:id="_u35tSzB">Using this information, it is able to optimize the updates as more information becomes available.</s><s xml:id="_MkmdRxR">Other relevant rewarding mechanisms include postponing the update of a visited state by recording the agents' recent experiences until the the state is visited again.</s><s xml:id="_VUXdBPS">The aim is to improve the quality of the update with more accurate information <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_5CpXCXs"><ref type="bibr">Kormushev et al.</ref> propose a concept, called Time Hopping, to prevent failures (i.e.</s><s xml:id="_bYAvacV">taking wrong actions) in scarcely explored states <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_8MzjeWy">The approach, though, is only applicable for simulation-based studies as setting the environment state as desired in real-life is not feasible.</s></p><p xml:id="_rYRyqQW"><s xml:id="_a6CAAhw">Transfer learning strategies between learning environments.: From a pure RL perspective, the survey study conducted by Taylor et al. provides a comprehensive summary about application of transfer learning in the RL domain <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_cBbAcFU">The survey classifies related studies into groups based on similarities and differences between environments among which knowledge to be transferred.</s><s xml:id="_rsqH66E">Referring to this survey, our study is classified into the group where state and action spaces of the environments are the same.</s><s xml:id="_n48xEPz">Studies in this group that also transfer whole policies among tasks either learn from easy missions or break down the task to easier missions.</s><s xml:id="_S3YWVdp">However, the JITAI personalization problem does not have a modular structure.</s><s xml:id="_VV4r3yB">So, approaches working on hierarchical or modular tasks would not work on our problem.</s><s xml:id="_rNGky5q">Lazaric follows a similar approach with us where state transitions are saved as tuples of source state, taken action, target state and emitted reward.</s><s xml:id="_eKa4TyE">His method checks similarity of information collected in an environment with information obtained in other environments to decide transfer the knowledge or not <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_UsAAfHk">In our study, only state and action pairs are stored at each transition.</s><s xml:id="_kmNryvp">Such pairs are aggregated in a single common policy indicating the action to be selected in the corresponding state.</s><s xml:id="_mAfDqAZ">Nevertheless, partial policy transfers or criteria-based knowledge transfer as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref> might be appropriate for our case as well.</s><s xml:id="_uTJewEZ">Source environments might have certain regions with relatively higher similarities with the other policies.</s></p><p xml:id="_fZg86Je"><s xml:id="_W6HkZJb">Data associated with a single person is deemed insufficient when it comes to devise an intervention delivery policy tailored to an individual via RL methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_kRWeh2Z">In this sense, Tabatabaei et al. propose a narrowing reinforcement learning approach to overcome the cold-start problem <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_2cRP6B4">They use a neighborhood function to group similar users and generated suitable policies based on the reactions of the users to the delivered interventions.</s><s xml:id="_Q8nuzz8">The size of the neighborhood is inversely proportional with the collected experiences.</s><s xml:id="_MnSSSav">This means that the policy becomes more individualized as the amount of the collected experience increases.</s><s xml:id="_aKC3MCx">Similarly, Zhu et al. introduce a group-driven RL for personalized intervention delivery <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_rc38B7D">K-means clustering is utilized to group users based on similarity of activity trajectories and learn a shared RL policy for each group.</s><s xml:id="_utJeQjR">Yürüten applies timeseries analysis on activity data to recognize common behavioral profiles <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_avnMYgc">In addition to daily activity patterns, his system tries to group users based on their reactions to the delivered interventions.</s><s xml:id="_8aVTYBB">In our approach, we seek similarity between states across environments i.e. persons.</s><s xml:id="_yZf62Q3">We use random forests for classifying states that are composed of contextual variables where the states are labeled with the actions as described previously.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3." xml:id="_Q2f8RpT">Problem formulation</head><p xml:id="_7UuQEBM"><s xml:id="_VYanCrA">The main challenge targeted by the study is to discover optimal values for intervention parameters such as type, timing or frequency that can change per individual.</s><s xml:id="_kUqE3Aj">As the real-life experiment opportunities are limited, we propose a mechanism for simulating personas having different characteristics.</s><s xml:id="_tYZG5SZ">The simulation mechanism accepts a set of inputs, such as daily action plans or personal preferences, as tailoring factors for the proposed learning algorithm.</s><s xml:id="_D7cJJ5m">In addition, a mathematical habit formation model is used to simulate personas' habit formation process in a realistic way in terms of the duration of habit formation.</s></p><p xml:id="_B73HBzJ"><s xml:id="_3tY2srn">The proposed learning algorithm generates signals for necessity and timing the intervention by tracking and processing the simulated data.</s><s xml:id="_PvhQzyJ">An intervention along with its metadata like timing or content is represented with the JITAI concept.</s><s xml:id="_Fz9kEwc">Informally, a JITAI is defined as a method to capture a person's changing contextual state and provide an appropriate type of intervention wherever and whenever necessary.</s><s xml:id="_NRPrZhJ">In our context, JITAI parameters (frequency, type and timing) are optimized via the two RL models.</s></p><p xml:id="_J2gYXTc"><s xml:id="_W5UAcyX">Overall, the proposed algorithm is an RL-based, iterative algorithm that aims to select the best action at each iteration.</s><s xml:id="_SxPwDj4">The algorithm runs in sync with people's self-management action plans and momentary contexts where each iteration of the RL models correspond to a decision point as described below:</s></p><p xml:id="_8FgPMgg"><s xml:id="_qXx2fM8">The intervention-selection and opportune-moment-identification models have their own set of points to evaluate the relevant person context and take corresponding action.</s><s xml:id="_w72KqdQ">Decision point sets (DP AP and DP RW of the intervention-selection and opportune-momentidentification models respectively) are driven by action plans as described below:</s></p><p xml:id="_bBdMWaW"><s xml:id="_QwVJydY">An action plan contains a list of planned activities to be performed by the person for achieving the targeted behavior change and associated clinical outcomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_tGNQR2s">An action plan partitions a day, as depicted in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>, into time frames.</s><s xml:id="_u67BYfT">Each activity is associated with two sequential time frames.</s><s xml:id="_yT4fc9w">The first time frame is the period through which the activity is supposed to be performed.</s><s xml:id="_3HShtbh">Only certain types of interventions can be delivered at each frame e.g.</s><s xml:id="_ETvwDRF">reminders in the first one and motivation or warning interventions in the second.</s></p><p xml:id="_BhxsEED"><s xml:id="_FsCK8y6">Definition 1 (DP AP ): An action plan yields a set of points in time where a decision is made for delivering an intervention.</s><s xml:id="_3GatdHa">Let AP be the set of activities such that a ∈ AP.</s><s xml:id="_ZFEFfQN">Then, the set of the points generated for the action plan, DP AP , can be represented as,</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">DP AP = {dp 2i-1 , dp 2i | ∀i a i ∈ AP, i &gt; 0} S. Gönül et al.</formula><p xml:id="_bHJQ68K"><s xml:id="_hchjfqW">The set definition above implies that there would be a corresponding decision point for both time frames [dp i ,dp i+1 ] associated with a planned activity.</s></p><p xml:id="_67v5knZ"><s xml:id="_jZz9srX">Opportune moments for engagement with an intervention are affected by a person's contextual states throughout the daily life.</s><s xml:id="_udyNyJf">For instance, a state change from physical activeness to sedentary state might be an indicator of an opportune moment.</s></p><p xml:id="_X3TsPdm"><s xml:id="_KsuqFB4">Definition 2 (DP RW ): The set, DP RW contains all time points where a contextual change occurs in a person's real world.</s><s xml:id="_Y7weP5Y">Therefore, this set differs for each person; even for each day of a particular person.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_hHDxJXZ">Definition 3 (JITAI):</head><p xml:id="_hdQt7ym"><s xml:id="_B4yBfbk">A JITAI is represented with two mappings.</s><s xml:id="_aaBpacK">For the intervention selection, it is a mapping from a state (is s n ) representing the person's long-term context to a decision (i.e.</s><s xml:id="_WRvEwfK">action) (is a n ) on whether to generate an intervention (for simplicity no intervention decision can also be considered as a type of intervention with no action) and its type.</s><s xml:id="_ebpJFrb">For the opportune-moment-identification case, the mapping is from a state (omi s n ) representing the person's momentary context to a decision (omi a n ) on when exactly to deliver the intervention.</s></p><p xml:id="_wBDbpTW"><s xml:id="_PcrEAY5">Definition 4 (JITAI using RL): Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref> shows how the execution of the RL models are projected onto the time frames of an action plan.</s><s xml:id="_QmPcgKx">∀dp, dp ∈ DP AP , i.e. for all decision points of the intervention selection model, a state transition occurs such that the learning agent travels from is s 1 to is s n .</s><s xml:id="_rRtdnTg">At each decision point, the intervention selection model selects an intervention type for delivery.</s><s xml:id="_YPpVdnx">Similarly, ∀dp,dp ∈ DP RW , the opportunemoment-identification model makes state transitions starting from omi s 1 to omi s n .</s><s xml:id="_DDJJdUP">A state transition occurs when there is a change in the momentary context of the person.</s><s xml:id="_ppHUwd8">However, the opportune-momentidentification is disabled in cases no particular intervention type is selected by the intervention-selection model.</s><s xml:id="_JNG5Yd5">For example, considering Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>, no intervention type is selected in is s 2 .</s><s xml:id="_7ASPtDF">Therefore, there is no state transition of the opportune-moment-identification model throughout the second time frame.</s><s xml:id="_DTWGFaz">When it is active, the opportunemoment-identification model decides to deliver the selected intervention or not at each decision point.</s></p><p xml:id="_trb2h4W"><s xml:id="_Cx7g8xP">RL models learn tailored intervention delivery strategies aiming maximum engagement with interventions, to achieve the expected behavior change and improved clinical indicators eventually.</s><s xml:id="_tCBPvNb">Considering that suboptimal support via interventions would lead to undesired results, our aim in this work is to achieve a near-optimal delivery strategy for an individual as soon as possible by maximizing the rewards collected by each model.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4." xml:id="_KFVpq87">Proposed approach</head><p xml:id="_Upt5Sbb"><s xml:id="_y755RKd">In this section, following a schematic diagram describing the overall approach, we present the accelerator techniques as an expansion on the base RL algorithms to boost the learning performance.</s><s xml:id="_zsAsXvu">Then, the overall algorithm shows how the two RL models interact with each other and these two techniques.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1." xml:id="_gAu7Y6g">Overall structure of the approach</head><p xml:id="_9Jr7DJj"><s xml:id="_yqJpfWB">As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref>, the approach is composed of two main steps.</s><s xml:id="_eKZHyEy">Basically, in the first step i.e. the training phase, the algorithm trains a State Classifier to be used in the actual experiment to be able to reduce the number of random actions that are taken in unknown states, i.e. states that are not visited previously.</s><s xml:id="_DUY8sEf">As mentioned earlier, the core algorithm contains two RL models that run simultaneously as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. The opportune-moment-identification model monitors the momentary changes of the simulated persona and take actions accordingly.</s><s xml:id="_TGxjU2H">In this phase, the opportune-moment-identification model utilizes only the selective eligibility traces method as the State Classifier is not available yet.</s><s xml:id="_fhMmUDN">On the other hand, the intervention-selection model monitors the habitual context of the persona via the habit formation model.</s><s xml:id="_aD53mZE">As a result of the training phase, the State Classifier becomes available for the actual experiment where the opportune-momentidentification model uses this technique also for further improving the learning process.</s><s xml:id="_3sjqywY">Fig. 2. Execution of the intervention-selection and opportune-moment-identification models in sync with the time frames associated to action plan activities.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2." xml:id="_qHpRGfF">Selective eligibility traces</head><p xml:id="_G5ZqEcb"><s xml:id="_pUpXuDf">Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">4</ref> depicts how the environment and agent interact with each other concerning the opportune-moment-identification-model.</s><s xml:id="_BhDHzBw">a i denotes the action taken when the environment is in state s i and r i is the reward received for a i .</s><s xml:id="_Szrd3Wc">The boxes labeled with j indicate that an intervention is delivered to the person as an action i.e.</s><s xml:id="_63BcG5b">Deliver_Intervention has been taken; otherwise means that the Deliver_Nothing action has been taken.</s><s xml:id="_uCKt5bg">∀dp, dp ∈ DP RW , i.e. for each decision point of the opportunemoment-identification model, the algorithm makes a decision on delivering the intervention (i.e. the one selected by the interventionselection model) or not at each step until the behavior is performed or the person engages with the intervention.</s><s xml:id="_g65UpZe">As seen in the figure, throughout a learning episode, the algorithm might deliver an intervention several times.</s><s xml:id="_vn6Rkpw">However, the person might not see or engage with interventions immediately.</s><s xml:id="_B4hCbm6">One or more interventions might be processed or discarded after a certain amount of time by the person when s/ he interacts with the delivered interventions.</s><s xml:id="_2re2bDZ">In the example, there would be two notifications on the mobile phone, i.e. j 1 and j 2 , at state s 7 .</s></p><p xml:id="_CUwrjbc"><s xml:id="_9KyfbJt">Delayed response to the delivered intervention necessitates rewarding past actions.</s><s xml:id="_RCgyrzA">The RL literature has a solution for such cases: eligibility traces.</s><s xml:id="_UfwnuyA">However, the standard eligibility trace approach is not suitable for the problem we target.</s><s xml:id="_MWDAFup">For example, assume that the person would only engage with j 2 and discards j 1 .</s><s xml:id="_ZYr4Hx6">r 7 would be a positive reward as the person has seen/engaged with j 2 .</s><s xml:id="_bAD3f6m">In this case, the standard eligibility tracing mechanism gives credit to all previous actions, including a 1 , a 3 and a 5 .</s><s xml:id="_ahsXWHC">However, rewarding a 1 and a 3 is an inconsistency.</s><s xml:id="_EaXJjBE">Because, those actions are suboptimal as interventions were sent in inappropriate moments without any engagement.</s></p><p xml:id="_ampv5CT"><s xml:id="_VPu4avA">We address this inconsistency by customizing the eligibility criteria of retrospective rewarding.</s><s xml:id="_kya38jG">Instead of rewarding all past state-action pairs in the agent's trajectory, only the actions resulting with engaged interventions are positively rewarded.</s><s xml:id="_zPhMeBz">Complementary to this modification, we ensure that the action before the engagement with the intervention would be Deliver_Action even if it were originally Deliv-er_Nothing action.</s><s xml:id="_AbKE3QS">For example, in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">4</ref>, although a 7 is a Deliver_Nothing action originally, it was indeed an opportune moment for engaging with the intervention.</s><s xml:id="_mrNCBWH">So, we modify the eligibility trace as if a  Deliver_Intervention action were taken in s 7 .</s><s xml:id="_cYSzAwy">This modification favors taking the Delivery_Intervention action in future visits to s 7 .</s><s xml:id="_nBcgRrE">The algorithm described in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">5</ref> shows the two modifications we perform on the standard eligibility trace mechanism.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3." xml:id="_xCVfHT8">Transfer learning across opportune-moment-identification environments</head><p xml:id="_qNhsMam"><s xml:id="_xKrN3V4">To be able to apply transfer learning in an RL setup, we first analyze similarities and differences between the environments among which knowledge to be shared.</s><s xml:id="_xjZ7GEx">We apply transfer learning in the opportunemoment-identification model.</s><s xml:id="_JK5aCDJ">In this respect, while the state space, action space and reward functions have the same configuration, only the transition functions differ, which is obvious as they reflect people's unique contexts.</s></p><p xml:id="_cGRgqwg"><s xml:id="_a8pZcX5">Having these similarities and differences, we decided to have complete policies as the knowledge to be transferred.</s><s xml:id="_tcmHMsC">Having the policy of others, a learning agent could perform better in new states.</s><s xml:id="_uNyqM8U">It may benefit from the other agents' experiences that visited the same or similar state previously, instead of choosing a random action.</s><s xml:id="_6hV7rBu">Fewer random actions provide a warm-start for the learning agent which does a jump-start in terms of learning performance.</s><s xml:id="_DJY5jrR">However, this requires identification of other agents, whose policies to be transferred to the current agent.</s><s xml:id="_MbC5edv">To deal with this problem, we decided to keep a common policy (CP) that accumulates successful experiences of all agents.</s><s xml:id="_v4qFrSM">In this way, we build a case repository accumulating the transitions happening in any available environment <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_DSvacN6">Definition 5 (Common Policy -CP):</head><formula xml:id="formula_1">CP: S OMI → {(a, n) | a ∈ A OMI , n ∈ℕ+}</formula><p xml:id="_yecMSH2"><s xml:id="_jzm828U">where CP is a function that maps states to action-number tuples.</s><s xml:id="_qSxndRG">Each tuple includes the action along with the number of agents taking that action in the given state with a successful outcome.</s><s xml:id="_zehBFpx">We do not transfer CP as it is but use it as raw data to train a supervised-learning based State Classifier (SC).</s></p><p xml:id="_JVB2m9E"><s xml:id="_vmjCArR">Definition 6 (State Classifier -SC): SC: S OMI → A OMI , where SC is a function from the state space to the action space.</s><s xml:id="_9AfQH24">SC provides classification capability for states that have not been discovered by the current agent.</s><s xml:id="_vgk6m7s">It might even be the case that a state might have not been discovered by any of the agents.</s><s xml:id="_esN6xQS">Even so, the classifier might predict the action considering the similarity of the states that were previously discovered.</s></p><p xml:id="_xdq4CSt"><s xml:id="_QDch69W">CP is updated after each episode, based on the activities of the agent throughout the episode.</s><s xml:id="_eSsNR5q">The algorithm to update CP is explained in Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_GParS54">SC is trained with the data accumulated in CP.</s><s xml:id="_2acGMFm">Each training data item is a tuple with a state and label as follows: data_item = &lt; s, l&gt;, where s ∈ S OMI and l ∈ A OMI .</s><s xml:id="_974zCQc">The label of each data item is determined by the total number of times of actions being selected by the agents.</s><s xml:id="_nNfy2eK">Simply, the action with the highest number of selection for the given state is set as the label.</s></p><p xml:id="_swqUWvV"><s xml:id="_aMfA7Vb">As presented before, the state parameters of the opportune-momentidentification model are enumerated values, which makes decision trees an appropriate method to perform classification on the data items.</s><s xml:id="_9yp4x6M">Specifically, we decided to use the Random Forests <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref> as they are more suitable to realize customized transfer learning approaches, such as transferring partial policies, by modifying the tree generation accordingly.</s><s xml:id="_FHjMjrZ">In this study, though, we used the default tree generation and classification mechanism provided by the Apache Spark library <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4." xml:id="_C29aba3">Overall algorithm</head><p xml:id="_v5bqy3e"><s xml:id="_Q796RaY">In this section, we present the overall learning algorithm.</s><s xml:id="_wWvCn2A">As depicted in Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref>, the algorithm describes the execution of a single learning episode, which corresponds to a simulated day in the trials.</s><s xml:id="_qfkCx7D">S. Gönül et al.</s><s xml:id="_pkMQ2vP">Fig. 7. Overall learning algorithm.</s></p><p xml:id="_yVx7Q5s"><s xml:id="_RCAkWDu">First, we present inputs, which are complex data structures encompassing specific data elements used in the algorithm.</s><s xml:id="_JQk7U92">The first four inputs are the main components of the RL environments, namely environment and agent objects of the intervention-selection and opportune-moment-identification models.</s><s xml:id="_U6XV3ME">The environment objects keep track of the current state of the environment and transition history.</s><s xml:id="_wkF75UD">Next, an action plan includes daily planned activities for the person.</s><s xml:id="_6ThpDqZ">Lastly, while the Common Policy (CP) contains the accumulated selection counts of actions along with the states, the State Classifier(SC) is the trained model that is used to predict actions to be taken in unknown states.</s></p><p xml:id="_NbssHkz"><s xml:id="_NuraSB9">The actual procedure starts with the first phase, initiating the outermost loop of the algorithm.</s><s xml:id="_UZsfQwN">This loop runs for each decision point of the intervention-selection model throughout a learning episode, i.e. ∀ dp,dp ∈ DP AP .</s><s xml:id="_tGzKac4">The first step is to determine the action (is_a t ) to be taken in the current state (is_s t ) of the intervention-selection model, by the learning agent of the intervention-selection model.</s><s xml:id="_Heryhmc">Internally, we use a greedy policy such that the action leading to the highest long-term reward is selected.</s><s xml:id="_sjZgwZR">The policy selects the action from EA DP , i.e. the eligible set of interventions as defined in Section 5.2.</s></p><p xml:id="_935qxtv"><s xml:id="_ZpP4bme">In the second phase, the opportune-moment-identification model runs only if a certain intervention type is selected (is a t ∕ = No I ntervention).</s><s xml:id="_K978KRz">The first operation performed by the opportune-moment-identification model is to determine the action (omi_a t ) based on the current state (omi_s t ).</s><s xml:id="_wySrfvc">Greedy logic is used by this model also.</s><s xml:id="_q7Ushnd">However, the learning algorithm utilizes SC in case it has to select a random action (omi a s .selectMode</s><s xml:id="_Rj8dqEE">= RANDOM) in an unknown state.</s><s xml:id="_t6uYhdq">In other cases, it utilizes the greedy policy and selects the action with the highest q-value.</s><s xml:id="_pkReEuk">Following action selection, the environment makes transition from the current state to the next state by taking the selected action.</s></p><p xml:id="_UYtgGFX"><s xml:id="_fUE84ym">In the third phase, two simulations take place.</s><s xml:id="_a58DvJM">If an intervention is delivered (omi a t = Deliver I ntervention), the person's reaction to the delivered intervention is simulated.</s><s xml:id="_5VnAhJg">The result of the simulation is either to discard the intervention or engage with it.</s><s xml:id="_k4Uwtkm">The second simulation is about performing the targeted behavior.</s><s xml:id="_2uebTWa">Whether the behaviour will be performed or not is determined by the habit formation model.</s><s xml:id="_wpNBVd2">Details about the two simulation activities will be given in the next section.</s></p><p xml:id="_Sfgr3PH"><s xml:id="_rqrY8xC">The fourth phase starts with obtaining the reward (omi_r t ) for the action taken by the opportune-moment-identification model via Eq.</s><s xml:id="_TwnWE3T">(1) and Eq.</s><s xml:id="_9PnVkSd">(2).</s><s xml:id="_xfxQcDm">Then, eligibility traces are updated (Algorithm1), and the transition is recorded into the episode analysis object.</s><s xml:id="_keSuPWb">For each selected intervention, the opportune-moment-identification model runs through all the time frames associated with the current planned activity of the action plan (context c hange occurs within action p lan a ctivity.time</s><s xml:id="_pWCxDyK">f rame).</s></p><p xml:id="_67qAkbG"><s xml:id="_ezUzFww">Finally, execution context switches back to the interventionselection model by advancing the habit formation model one step.</s><s xml:id="_mxU6Ebd">The next step for the intervention-selection model (is s t+1 ) is obtained using the updated parameters of the habit formation model and the reward (is r t ) is generated (Eq.</s><s xml:id="_EmVVhN7">( <ref type="formula">3</ref>)).</s><s xml:id="_yAaHjcm">The loop is iterated for all time frames generated by the action plan.</s><s xml:id="_CemPxXa">Once the episode is over, CP is updated with the collected data for the episode (Algorithm2).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5." xml:id="_TzHPpsc">RL models</head><p xml:id="_yMsSruZ"><s xml:id="_xZaYyMC">In this section, we instantiate the intervention-selection and opportune-moment-identification models by providing formal definitions for each of them.</s><s xml:id="_qnjeapN">We assume that people are fully observable thanks to the directly sensed or inferred contextual parameters required by the learning models.</s><s xml:id="_UfNqdFS">This makes using MDPs appropriate to formally describe the RL environments.</s><s xml:id="_QtWYbJn">An MDP M is characterized with a tuple consisting of four parameters: state set, action set, probability matrix and reward function, which is represented as M = &lt; S, A, P, R&gt;.</s><s xml:id="_tJajv95">We present MDP configurations for the intervention-selection and opportunemoment-identification models in the following sections.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1." xml:id="_B6Eccyw">The opportune-moment-identification model</head><p xml:id="_XXQDwU8"><s xml:id="_ZuH3mXv">The MDP instantiated for the opportune-moment-identification model is represented with: M OMI = &lt; S OMI , A OMI , P OMI , R OMI &gt;.</s></p><p xml:id="_UwkH45e"><s xml:id="_9qzSzz3">Considering that the opportune-moment-identification model aims to capture person-specific patterns over momentary context, the person state includes parameters pertaining to physiological, psychological or environmental context of the person.</s><s xml:id="_kkZDn9T">Each state s OMI ∈ S OMI is composed of six parameters as defined below:</s></p><p xml:id="_5UQwnHq"><s xml:id="_FkENSC6">s OMI = &lt; time, location, physical_activity_status, phone_screen_status, emotional_status, number_of_interventions_sent_for_planned_activity&gt;</s></p><p xml:id="_tg28Xjq"><s xml:id="_ncZdXBv">The time required to reach a (near) optimal policy with an RL solution is inversely proportional with the size of state and action sets.</s><s xml:id="_raNF4Yf">Therefore, we avoid state parameters with continuous values and modeled them as discrete parameters as described below:• time= {x: x &gt;= 0 and x &lt; 95, x ∈ℕ}.</s><s xml:id="_9ZAatcJ">This parameter is used to represent the time during a day.</s><s xml:id="_DPv4AHc">The action set of the opportune-moment-identification model includes two elements: Deliver_Intervention and Deliver_Nothing that are respectively used for delivering the selected intervention or not.</s><s xml:id="_j2ypq8x">The action set is formally described as follows:</s></p><p xml:id="_KCd2Mbn"><s xml:id="_xZnmvNE">A OMI = {Deliver_Intervention, Deliver_Nothing} Reward function of the opportune-moment-identification model, R OMI , first considers the action taken at step t (omi a t ).</s><s xml:id="_aApTKhu">The algorithm generates a relatively small negative reward (-1) as shown in Eq. ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) for cases where no intervention is delivered (omi a t = Deliver N othing).</s><s xml:id="_ftSaB7k">Although choosing 0 reward seems reasonable for such cases, this setting leads to getting stuck in a local minima as not sending any intervention is favored throughout the whole learning process.</s></p><p xml:id="_4AZPeJE"><s xml:id="_h4GBsWt">In cases where an intervention is delivered (omi a t = Deliver I ntervention), the algorithm initiates the reward by considering the person's reaction to the intervention.</s><s xml:id="_HKUwPrx">The reward is initially set to 1000 and -2 for reacting (reacted t = true) and not-reacting (reacted t = false) cases respectively.</s><s xml:id="_4FXncYJ">These initial values reflect the higher importance given to an action leading to engagement.</s><s xml:id="_5b6XqNk">Consecutive notreacting cases generate multiplied negative rewards in proportion with the number of cases.</s><s xml:id="_nguGT5M">If the intervention was reacted, the reward is updated according to the temporal proximity of the intervention delivery to the actual engagement time with the intervention (difference t ).</s><s xml:id="_ykgdK8r">Three ranges are defined into which the temporal difference (td) of delivery and engagement can fall.</s><s xml:id="_eQ5qhdP">These ranges can be represented as: 0 &lt;= td &lt;= 30, 30 &lt; td &lt;= 60 and td &gt; 60.</s><s xml:id="_CTd7Fh6">The lower the temporal difference, the higher the reward.</s><s xml:id="_BY9nbuz">While Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">2</ref>) shows calcuation of the reward generated for the temporal proximity, Eq. ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) shows calculation of the eventual reward generated at each step of the opportune-momentidentification model.</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_2">temporal reward t = ⎧ ⎨ ⎩ -2, if difference t &gt; 60 -1, if 30 ≥ difference t &gt; 60 2, if difference t &lt; 30<label>(2)</label></formula><p xml:id="_snfpJZw"><s xml:id="_8Tc3Nr9">The opportune-moment-identification model is a stochastic environment considering the way state transitions occur.</s><s xml:id="_zE3pV9a">As presented earlier, S OMI is mainly composed of parameters pertaining to people's varying momentary contexts.</s><s xml:id="_53ybac8">Therefore, concerning transitions from state omi s t to omi s t+1 , the values of omi s t+1 are observed from people's daily activities.</s><s xml:id="_guNHs9T">This means that this model does not have a well-defined transition probability matrix.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2." xml:id="_24MQXNQ">The intervention-selection model</head><p xml:id="_YZGgCQu"><s xml:id="_hmBdDN9">The MDP for the intervention-selection model is represented with:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_3">M IS = &lt; S IS , A IS , P IS , R IS &gt;.</formula><p xml:id="_qk3gszs"><s xml:id="_Tqgehuc">S IS is the state set, where each state s IS ∈ S IS is represented with a tuple composed of four parameters as follows:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_4">s IS = &lt; habit_strength, behavior_frequency, day_type, remember_behavior&gt;</formula><p xml:id="_apRGW5A"><s xml:id="_hNCGBsK">As in the opportune-moment-identification case, we avoided state parameters with continuous values for this model as described below:• habit_strength= {x: x &gt;= 0 and x &lt; 10, x ∈ℕ}.</s><s xml:id="_EqmKqNT">Habit strength represents the strength of automaticity of the behavior without occupying the mind to remember to perform the behavior.</s><s xml:id="_Kj7X7bu">In other words, the higher the habit strength is, the less need is required for providing cues in the form of interventions for reminding the behavior.•</s><s xml:id="_AvWbmwf">behavior_frequency= {x: x &gt;= 0 and x &lt; 10, x ∈ℕ}.</s><s xml:id="_hJuANpj">Behavior frequency is the ratio of number of times executing the behavior to the total number of opportunities to perform a behavior, within a certain time frame in the past.•</s><s xml:id="_jPkJZGn">day_type: Day type is an enumeration that can take either weekend or weekday values.</s><s xml:id="_c5M5mFs">Its value is extracted from the date of the active learning episode i.e. the simulated day.•</s><s xml:id="_bkunCPe">remember_behavior:Remembering behavior is also an enumeration that can take either true or false values.</s><s xml:id="_h6ZYVPv">The specific value of this parameter indicates whether the person would remember performing the behavior as planned in the action plan.</s></p><p xml:id="_HMyvXUU"><s xml:id="_DfSnFsX">The action set of the intervention selection model is defined as follows:</s></p><p xml:id="_PnsJfjb"><s xml:id="_SkTgQAq">A IS = {J 1 , J 2 ,..., J n , No_Intervention} The set of intervention types include J 1 ,..., J n that are supposed to be identified by domain experts addressing a particular disease/health problem <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_4WVZUJc">In addition to the specific intervention types, not delivering any intervention, represented with No_Intervention label, is also a possible action.</s><s xml:id="_Tmf8hwN">An internal mapping (M) keeps an association between each activity (a ∈ AP) defined in an action plan and an eligible set of interventions (EA a ) such that:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_5">M : A→EA a , a ∈ AP, EA a ⊂A IS</formula><p xml:id="_ANqtqPB"><s xml:id="_k6FNz9k">EA a is further narrowed considering the intervention types eligible for the decision points.</s><s xml:id="_G6BcVkx">For decision points prior to the planned activity, only the reminder interventions are considered.</s><s xml:id="_t7YFKuR">Otherwise, only the motivation interventions are eligible.</s><s xml:id="_aDDEySr">We define the final set of eligibile actions at a decision point as EA DP .</s><s xml:id="_4sSTkDy">At each decision point of the intervention-selection model, an action is a t is selected from this set i.e. is a t ∈ EA DP .</s></p><p xml:id="_tBvTkZR"><s xml:id="_vjwr2e4">R IS function is conditioned on 3 variables: remembering the behavior, delivering an intervention or not and engagement with the delivered intervention, if any.</s><s xml:id="_9m8APPt">The reward is calculated based on these variables at each state change (is s t ), step t.</s><s xml:id="_hyN3pvV">Varying combinations of conditions on these variables form the reward function as presented in Eq. ( <ref type="formula">3</ref>).</s></p><p xml:id="_zDW7BJs"><s xml:id="_2KaZVSS">The values for the six respective cases in the equation are instantiated as -50, -10, -5, -3, -1 and 10.</s><s xml:id="_97PGQEr">The reasoning behind such an instantiation is to generate relatively higher rewards in cases when the person does not remember performing the behavior and an intervention type is selected as a counter action (remember b ehavior = false and is a ∕ = No I ntervention).</s><s xml:id="_VKtHNS6">Engaging with the intervention is rewarded positively (reacted = true) so that the interventions that are not engaged by the person would be selected less.</s><s xml:id="_wFQJABy">The worst decision of the algorithm would be not to select any intervention even if the person would not remember performing the behavior (remember b ehavior = false and is a = No I ntervention).</s><s xml:id="_pBBx4Mw">So, this is the case where the largest reward in magnitude, but a negative one, is generated.</s><s xml:id="_pPpvbrz">(3)</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_6">is r t = ⎧ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎨ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎩</formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">omi r t = ⎧ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎨ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎩ not s ent(-</formula><p xml:id="_k69BdFr"><s xml:id="_Cq3XNSA">1), if omi a t = Deliver N othing, reacted t = false sent n ot r eacted(-2) * number o f a ttempts , if omi a t = Deliver I ntervention, reacted t = false sent r eacted(1000) +temporal r eward &lt; ce : inf &gt; t &lt; /ce : inf &gt; , if omi a t = Deliver I ntervention, reacted t = true (1)</s></p><p xml:id="_QMQZUJD"><s xml:id="_sVgzmb5">P IS is a matrix of probabilities, P(is s t+1 |is s, is a t ), indicating the probability of transition from state is s to state is s t+1 by taking the action is a t .</s><s xml:id="_vASWksp">The intervention-selection model follows an episodic learning approach such that each day corresponds to an episode.</s><s xml:id="_twt6nsY">State transitions throughout an episode, i.e. a day, is laid out by the action plan associated to the person.</s><s xml:id="_qTdct6u">Subsequent state parameters are calculated by the habit formation model embedded into the intervention-selection model.</s><s xml:id="_pRS5Say">Therefore, state Transition dynamics from state is s t to is s t+1 are deterministic.</s><s xml:id="_hWErCmd">We provide details about state transition and calculation of parameters of next state in Appendix A.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6." xml:id="_6sZEhZd">Experiment and validation setup</head><p xml:id="_4gz3XEx"><s xml:id="_n4b22ka">This section presents the simulation-based validation approach.</s><s xml:id="_Jnb6Cev">First, we provide details about the simulated concepts, which are the action plan and personas, by elaborating the differentiating factors of these concepts.</s><s xml:id="_SX8BJez">We introduce a set of hypotheses, capturing the personas' differentiating factors, against which the proposed approach is validated.</s><s xml:id="_2znFXTC">The validation approach continues with the metrics that are being used to validate the two accelerator methods.</s><s xml:id="_4RRRAxb">Afterwards, we describe a benchmarking methodology on the reward function parameters.</s><s xml:id="_CWcEhgw">Lastly, we provide details about the experiments of which results are discussed in the results section.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1." xml:id="_xc3GzDS">Simulations</head><p xml:id="_YxBr9K5"><s xml:id="_5VvMVxt">As briefly mentioned in the introduction, we simulate a number of concepts as distinguishing characteristics of people that should be captured by the proposed learning algorithm.</s><s xml:id="_cdSWKTW">The overall simulation approach has already been discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_8UtcsF6">Thus, we only summarize the simulation set up and provide details about the expansions on the initial approach.</s><s xml:id="_bWRBATH">For more details, please see the Simulation Testbed section of the referred study.</s><s xml:id="_k2tYyVM">In summary, the simulation setup can be explained under two main topics: the action plan and personas.</s></p><p xml:id="_CYA6pJF"><s xml:id="_2yq9yRY">Simulating Action Plan.</s><s xml:id="_ayAawrD">We assume a simple action plan with 3 predefined decision points (morning, noon and evening) at which 2 types of reminder and one type of motivational interventions can be sent.</s></p><p xml:id="_YevzVwz"><s xml:id="_fehFj8b">Simulating Personas.</s><s xml:id="_VQy9pDv">We consider four distinguishing factors for four simulated personas.</s><s xml:id="_jRNCCjd">The first one is habit formation, which is an indicator of strength of automaticity of performing the targeted behavior without external cues.</s><s xml:id="_Ttd4xge">To simulate habit-related concepts in a realistic way, we use the habit formation model <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_KuJqXmF">The main parameter of the model that we are interested in is commitment intensity, which is an indicator of the time required to turn a behaviour into habit.</s><s xml:id="_gkcRN2R">Considering the parameter can take values between 0 and 1, we assign 0.2, 0.4, 0.6 and 0.8 values to Person -1, Person -2, Person -3 and Person -4 respectively.</s><s xml:id="_9ntyY5s">Having a relatively higher commitment intensity shows more appreciation or having more desire for the targeted behavior by the person.</s></p><p xml:id="_sJcwyBd"><s xml:id="_ENGNpZb">The second factor is daily activities of people.</s><s xml:id="_sBn5XRJ">Daily activities vary for each individual.</s><s xml:id="_sM4vRtH">We introduce a concept called activity timeline to represent all daily activities of a person during the day from wake up to sleep.</s><s xml:id="_fd6xYqY">The aim of having such timelines is to simulate states that are (or not) suitable for engaging with interventions and for performing the activities described in action plans.</s><s xml:id="_eMD2zw4">A timeline is a placeholder for a sequence of activities to be performed throughout the day.</s></p><p xml:id="_quQ6aJc"><s xml:id="_jj3kHzt">We populate timelines with predefined activities that can be semi-randomized for each person for each learning episode i.e. simulated day.</s><s xml:id="_n8ExNZQ">This semi-randomization is realized in the following way: First, a subset of the activities are selected among the complete set of activities.</s></p><p xml:id="_3GyC2UJ"><s xml:id="_SggDw5Y">Then, each activity is associated with a start time and duration.</s><s xml:id="_sE2p4rU">The sequence, start time and duration of activities differ for each learning episode and for each person.</s><s xml:id="_kUDMEwq">Randomization of activity selection, start time identification and duration calculation are achieved with a Gaussion distribution within predefined limits relevant for the randomized variable.</s><s xml:id="_UX8cYxs">For instance, duration of an activity might be randomized between 30 and 60 minutes.</s><s xml:id="_dQHW8z8">The third factor is simulation of reactions to the delivered interventions.</s><s xml:id="_PaEkNDG">Reaction to an intervention has two prerequisites: the person should be favoring that type of intervention and the daily activity should be suitable for engaging the intervention.</s><s xml:id="_jB3rm8H">We represent personal preferences on intervention types simply with a percentage that is used as a probability of reacting to an intervention.</s><s xml:id="_BM4Mvpp">Persona-specific preferences on intervention types are given in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_U5kSHVU">Note that the preferences on the intervention types are not disjoint.</s><s xml:id="_xCZwZAG">So, the sum of the preference probabilities do not necessarily sum up to 1.</s></p><p xml:id="_dvrVAdj"><s xml:id="_3aajqRH">The last factor is simulation of the actual behavior performance.</s><s xml:id="_zCsMKvw">It is determined by the prediction on remembering the behavior by the habit formation model and suitability of the daily activity for performing the behavior.</s><s xml:id="_ytwZgRv">If the prediction of the model is positive, we assume that the person would perform the behavior during the activity if the activity is set as suitable for performing the activity in the scope of corresponding activity timeline.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2." xml:id="_x7xjYqk">Validation methodology 6.2.1. Hypotheses for the simulated personas</head><p xml:id="_yyHfshd"><s xml:id="_5zpVCX9">The proposed algorithm is supposed to adapt the intervention delivery respecting to factors that differ for each person.</s><s xml:id="_99Dqyuv">We introduce a set of hypotheses driven by these factors against which the algorithm is validated.</s><s xml:id="_Yn3xZgX">Specifically, we introduce the following four human factors, each of which has a corresponding hypothesis:</s></p><p xml:id="_f8YfgQU"><s xml:id="_7Pb6PrK">• Commitment intensity to adopt a targeted lifestyle behavior • Habit strength facilitating the performance of the targeted behavior • Preference on intervention types • Daily activities Respective hypotheses corresponding to these factors are as follows:• Hypothesis 1: The habit formation model implies that the higher commitment intensity of a person is, the less time s/he requires to reach the maximum habit strength.</s><s xml:id="_jDjX9gQ">Therefore, duration of the simulated care process through which interventions are sent should increase as the commitment intensity decreases.•</s><s xml:id="_FvaG2XN">Hypothesis 2: A high habit strength indicates that the person would perform the behavior without a need for external cues.</s><s xml:id="_mmpjFdh">Therefore, the number of delivered interventions should be inversely proportional with the perceived habit strength and become more and more intermittent throughout the simulated care process.•</s><s xml:id="_yNNHtPk">Hypothesis 3: The ratio of selected interventions should be consistent with the preferences of the persons.•</s><s xml:id="_uaSfu8F">Hypothesis 4: Daily activities differ for each simulated person as they have different activity timelines.</s><s xml:id="_vWaU2SW">Even, the activities change for the same person at each simulated day since the activities are selected in a semi-random manner.</s><s xml:id="_cMxZzZa">Therefore, the proposed approach should deliver interventions respecting to people's daily life patterns by respecting the timing and suitability of activities for engaging with the intervention and performing the behavior.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.2." xml:id="_DpPRZPx">Metrics for validating the accelerator techniques</head><p xml:id="_VxYNEt3"><s xml:id="_K6NuvAM">In order to validate the effectiveness of the accelerator techniques, we use performance metrics introduced by the transfer learning methodology, namely: jump-start, asymptotic performance, total reward, transfer ratio and time-to-threshold <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>.•</s><s xml:id="_QCAMU57">Jump-startrepresents the improved performance of a learning agent at the beginning of the learning process</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_eT8vSaw">Table 1</head><p xml:id="_vX4kWGB"><s xml:id="_XAh8wkg">Preferences associated to simulated personas on intervention types.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_G7ESDKp">Reminder-1</head><p xml:id="_En9Zbgn"><s xml:id="_ZqbqAaG">Reminder-</s></p><p xml:id="_GaXVV4A"><s xml:id="_5eWvmnX">2 Motivation Person 1 0% 50% 10% Person 2 20% 80% 80% Person 3 80% 10% 80% Person 4 50% 50% 50% S. Gönül et al.</s></p><p xml:id="_fd93DWT"><s xml:id="_3pDVj8w">compared to the base algorithm without using transferred knowledge.•</s><s xml:id="_Qq8WxDc">Asymptotic performanceis the maximum performance that is achieved by the base algorithm and the algorithm utilizing transferred knowledge.•</s><s xml:id="_qWYsxa9">Total rewardis the amount of reward collected throughout the learning process.•</s><s xml:id="_4WFnpEq">Transfer ratiois the total amount of rewards accumulated thanks to the transferred knowledge divided by the total amount of rewards gathered with the base algorithm without any transferred knowledge.•</s><s xml:id="_FKWHf3V">Time to thresholdindicates the number of steps to reach a pre-defined performance level.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.3." xml:id="_CQ4vdQP">Baseline delivery strategy</head><p xml:id="_uNQHbVH"><s xml:id="_93SxcPx">Fixed intervention delivery policy (FP): A fixed intervention delivery strategy is defined as a baseline method in addition to the dynamic and adaptive intervention delivery policies as aimed by the proposed approach.</s><s xml:id="_VXNNr7F">This fixed policy is used as a baseline algorithm against which the results of the opportune-moment-identification model will be compared.</s><s xml:id="_NXRnzR3">Intervention delivery schedule of FP is as follows: Interventions are sent at 3 fixed time frames as long as the person has not engaged with the intervention and has not performed the behavior yet.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.4." xml:id="_PkmHk6N">Fine-tuning the reward functions parameters</head><p xml:id="_Z5phYBX"><s xml:id="_TGTB4An">The reward functions of the RL models are critical as they guide the learning agent in the correct direction by generating a proper reward representing the appropriateness of the taken action.</s><s xml:id="_BaMtEZK">Initial values for the reward function parameters are set heuristically considering the relative importance of the factor being rewarded towards achieving the ultimate goal.</s><s xml:id="_HGQnN8X">We validate the parameters by benchmarking alternative values and observing them leading to sub-optimal results.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.3." xml:id="_7jd9JWT">Experiments</head><p xml:id="_8atx6Th"><s xml:id="_n3GaFJn">We conduct two experiments such that each experiment contains 100 trials and each trial contains 100 learning episodes.</s><s xml:id="_XV3PZFH">The first experiment does not utilize the State Classifier as it has not been trained yet.</s><s xml:id="_FVmpNHb">The data generated by the first experiment are used to train the State Classifier.</s><s xml:id="_A3zpQ4C">The second experiment utilizes the State Classifier for selecting actions.</s><s xml:id="_a36jrR7">The results presented in the next section are obtained in the second experiment.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7." xml:id="_JvCgNjH">Results</head><p xml:id="_kwpBFkt"><s xml:id="_pWpavCN">In the light of the experimental setup presented in the previous section, we first show how the obtained results validate the hypotheses.</s></p><p xml:id="_HKKY8wa"><s xml:id="_R6H6KgF">Then, we analyze the results with respect to the transfer learning-based metrics.</s><s xml:id="_HFP4pyd">Finally, we present the results of benchmarking on the reward function parameters.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1." xml:id="_54evd2m">Validation of the hypotheses Overall duration of intervention delivery (Hypothesis 1):</head><p xml:id="_j427FRy"><s xml:id="_FvasFBu">We have set commitment intensities in an increasing manner from Person-1 to Person-4.</s><s xml:id="_ZhMNnFh">This implies that the time required to form habit for the targeted behavior should be the shortest for Person-4 and the longest for Person-1.</s><s xml:id="_xzwbYnv">The left-y versus x-axis of Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref>  Right-y axis versus x-axis of Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref> represents the habit strength per episode as simulated by the habit formation model.</s><s xml:id="_wzYgNYU">Time elapsed to reach the maximum habit strength for each person is also consistent with the commitment intensities set for the personas.</s><s xml:id="_NBHSaX6">According to the model, the person with highest commitment intensity should reach to the maximum habit strength first.</s><s xml:id="_q2JCuek">In line with this relationship, Person-1 ranked last and Person-4 ranked first in reaching the maximum habit strength.</s><s xml:id="_2A3hdfb">Considering the length of the duration to reach the maximum habit strength, the values obtained in our study are consistent also with the results obtained by Lally et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_9f38fg5">They have developed a habit formation model on empirical data regarding performance of the targeted behavior and habit strength perceived by subjects.</s><s xml:id="_xTavgkQ">Their model outputs duration for forming habit on daily behaviors where the behaviors are classified with a set of difficulty classes.</s><s xml:id="_BqyqaqQ">According to Lally et al., the duration for forming habit varies from almost a month to a few months where difficulty of behavior is the main determinant.</s><s xml:id="_45mtNYk">In our study, we consider only one behavior type.</s><s xml:id="_tTFCjtX">However, studies show that the perceived difficulty for the same behavior might differ for different people <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_52duSQG">Considering all these factors, we argue that the simulation is realistic in terms of generation of habit strength values i.e. performing the targeted behavior without a need to extrinsic reminders.</s></p><p xml:id="_4mMp6Xa"><s xml:id="_eaPytgX">Total number of delivered interventions (Hypothesis 2): Looking again at the dappled lines of Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref> showing the number of delivered interventions, the averages are relatively high in the starting phase of the Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref>. Episode vs. intervention count vs. habit strength plot.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_fuuMWat">S. Gönül et al.</head><p xml:id="_9XH4X5m"><s xml:id="_4emHUnE">simulations for each persona where the habit strength is relatively low especially for Person-1 and Person-2.</s><s xml:id="_G4Nj3zH">According to the habit formation model, lower commitment intensity implies lower habit strength.</s><s xml:id="_G967Bch">Considering this fact, during the beginning phase, it can be observed that the average numbers of delivered interventions for Person-1, the dapped blue line, are higher than the others most of the time.</s><s xml:id="_a34aF4W">That is, Person-1 who has the lowest commitment intensity receives the highest number of interventions.</s><s xml:id="_HC7j5qS">As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">9</ref>(a), the total number of interventions delivered for Person-1 is higher than the rest.</s><s xml:id="_eTgT77V">This is expected as Person-1 is supposed to be reminded more to perform the behavior throughout the whole process.</s><s xml:id="_6aTMuPQ">After a while, though, the number of delivered interventions gets closer to zero.</s><s xml:id="_cqnvbDA">The number of delivered interventions reacts to the changing habit strength such that as the habit strength increases the number of delivered interventions decreases and become more and more intermittent throughout the trial.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_5dDmMdD">Number of delivered interventions per type (Hypothesis 3):</head><p xml:id="_R3mPBJ5"><s xml:id="_vhEqFHJ">The three simulated intervention types are clustered into two disjoint sets according to their categories.</s><s xml:id="_6BwZ2Sd">That is, only the interventions of the same set can be alternatives to each other.</s><s xml:id="_N2CERR4">Therefore, the results should be evaluated independently for each set.</s><s xml:id="_p8GPHqa">Being reminder interventions, Reminder-1 and Reminder-2 belongs to the reminder set, whereas Motivation belongs the motivation set.</s><s xml:id="_eNdFdcu">As stated earlier, each specific preference value is used as a probability of engagement when the user is presented with the corresponding intervention type.</s><s xml:id="_AWKXxZM">For example, Person-1 never reacts to Reminder-1; Person-2 reacts to Reminder-2 or Motivation with an 80% chance when s/he is presented with a Reminder-2 or Motivation.</s><s xml:id="_5XVxcte">Because of the disjoint preference probabilities, we cannot expect a linear correlation across individuals for a particular intervention type and delivery ratios.</s><s xml:id="_vZRRH43">Even, ratios for the same person may not be correlated even if the corresponding preference probabilities are the same.</s><s xml:id="_wffC2vH">For example, for Person-4, Reminder-2 and Motivation have the same percentages but it is not expected to get the same ratio for these two interventions since Reminder-1 can also be sent as a reminder intervention.</s></p><p xml:id="_87RwDTy"><s xml:id="_fTPDgvp">We compare intervention ratios among each distinct set per individual basis in Fig. <ref type="figure">9(b</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_jf8R7Tt">Ratios of Reminder-1 and Reminder-2 reflect the initial prefences per person basis.</s><s xml:id="_VKRB8nm">For example, the ratio of Reminder-1 is higher than the ratio of Reminder-2 for Person-3, considering that preferences of Person-3 is 80% and 10% for Reminder-1 and Reminder-2 respectively.</s><s xml:id="_dRkGCFg">The ratios of Reminder-1 and Reminder-2 are almost equal each other.</s></p><p xml:id="_xWd3c5r"><s xml:id="_VBQwyNr">At the first glance, though, it can still be said that there are inconsistencies between preferences and the obtained results.</s><s xml:id="_5BkGg8j">For example, Person-1 has no interest at all for Reminder-1 and little interest for Motivation.</s><s xml:id="_uvV882N">But, the results show that the ratios for Reminder-1 and Motivation are 15% and 40% respectively.</s><s xml:id="_QgHeg5z">In case of Reminder-1, the main reason of this inconsistency is random selection of interventions in unexplored states i.e. the states that have not encountered previously by the learning agent.</s><s xml:id="_CEZZh9n">That is, the learning agent makes random decisions on selecting Reminder-1 or Reminder-2.</s><s xml:id="_SjpAM73">This problem applies also to Motivation.</s><s xml:id="_7fs4gpb">In addition to that, the algorithm favors intervention delivery regardless of its type, in case the person is predicted not to perform the behavior.</s><s xml:id="_aSrWgHz">In such cases, any type of intervention is considered as a reminder.</s></p><p xml:id="_3PFk6Nf"><s xml:id="_Vrh9aT7">Temporal proximity of intervention delivery and behaviour performance (Hypothesis 4): According to the design of the simulation, intervention delivery and behavior performance do not necessarily happen at the same time.</s><s xml:id="_rvyvWMD">Most of the time, there is a temporal difference between the two.</s><s xml:id="_XDJPqRz">The desired behavior is to send a reminder as close as possible to a time point when the conditions are suitable to perform the behavior so that the effect of the reminder is maximized.</s><s xml:id="_EkF9ekG">Fig. <ref type="figure">10</ref> shows the ratio of interventions that fall into the pre-defined ranges of temporal differences.</s><s xml:id="_vJ65mNc">Each range is represented with a bar in the chart.</s><s xml:id="_48QWCvg">In general, the ratio of delivered interventions decreases as the time difference Fig. 10.</s><s xml:id="_2hyKwMD">Difference between JITAI delivery and behavior performance times.</s></p><p xml:id="_urXJQTu"><s xml:id="_FDvWBmT">increases.</s><s xml:id="_vAZwp8Z">The pattern is only violated at the second bar, i.e. the 31-60 minute bar.</s><s xml:id="_VWVabRW">The reason is that daily activities generated at that time slot are not suitable for engaging with the intervention.</s><s xml:id="_PEfEaM9">This is an indicator of the algorithm's capability on learning the personalized patterns as it does not deliver interventions in states that are not suitable for engagement.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2." xml:id="_VVD2uRq">Validation of the accelerator techniques</head><p xml:id="_g3XnFNT"><s xml:id="_ErbFWwY">The metrics that are used for validation of the accelerator techniques were introduced in Section 6.2.2.</s><s xml:id="_q8nbs9U">Fig. <ref type="figure">11</ref> addresses all these metrics simultaneously.</s><s xml:id="_qsXJJ5J">The figure shows the rewards aggregated per episode.</s><s xml:id="_tn9F2ju">We present rewards obtained with 3 versions of the learning algorithm.</s><s xml:id="_9VUnfwH">The green, blue and red lines show the results obtained with the base Q-Learning (QL) algorithm, the base algorithm expanded with the selective eligibility traces (QL-SET) and the base algorithm expanded with both the selective eligibility traces and transfer learning techniques (QL-SET-TL).</s></p><p xml:id="_9r7vNzQ"><s xml:id="_gXUyFTv">The blue line laying over the green one, indicates a better jump-start achieved by the selective eligibility traces compared to the base algorithm.</s><s xml:id="_H9wJpq8">Nevertheless, the red line outperforms the other two with a notable highest jump start at the beginning of the simulation.</s><s xml:id="_w8JUcTz">The areas under the lines correspond to the total rewards collected by the respective algorithm.</s><s xml:id="_V9D4Z2H">According to the figure, QL-SET-TL collects more reward than the others throughout the experiment.</s><s xml:id="_gZXpCXm">This also implies that QL-SET-TL is more effective than the others considering the ratio of number of engaged interventions to the total of number interventions sent.</s><s xml:id="_4YqqKAE">With respect to the asymptotic performance, QL-SET-TL has a higher course than the other two during the active intervention delivery periods.</s><s xml:id="_uHvs5aK">Concerning the time-to-threshold metric, we do not introduce a predefined threshold.</s><s xml:id="_x8dTfJd">However, it can be said that all versions stabilize almost at the same time.</s><s xml:id="_SKrjXsy">Lastly, the area between the red line (QL-SET-TL) and blue line (QL-SET) correspond to the additional rewards that were collected thanks to the transfer learning.</s><s xml:id="_NEn5w7f">In this respect, considering the active intervention delivery period, the area between the blue and red lines indicate a notable contribution of transfer learning on the collected rewards.</s><s xml:id="_ZCETbHY">QL-SET-TL performs better than FP for each metric.</s></p><p xml:id="_pRAPbxq"><s xml:id="_2RNhCtc">The results presented in Fig. <ref type="figure">11</ref> shows that QL-SET-TL performs the best at the beginning of the simulation.</s><s xml:id="_eEcHYv3">In this respect, Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">12</ref> shows the ratio of actions determined by the State Classifier (SC) versus the agent's internal policy.</s><s xml:id="_NeWkKyr">SC selects most of the actions at the beginning of trials.</s><s xml:id="_jMB9Ftn">The number of actions selected by the agent's internal policy increases gradually as the agent itself learns more and more about its environment.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3." xml:id="_GeFr4KQ">Validation of the reward function parameters</head><p xml:id="_pP3bNm6"><s xml:id="_mUZ9hZe">While specifying reward values for each condition, zero (0) has been accepted as the neutral point and the magnitude of the rewards have been determined according to their perceived benefit.</s><s xml:id="_FZRD83N">In the two subsequent sections, we present details about this approach along with experimental results obtained for benchmarked reward values.</s><s xml:id="_BRgMbnx">Fig. 12. Ratio of actions per action selection mechanism.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.1." xml:id="_hDPnVgJ">Validation of the opportune-moment-identification reward function</head><p xml:id="_E6u2R93"><s xml:id="_dysRPFb">The reward function of the opportune-moment-identification model includes two equations (Eq.</s><s xml:id="_ZQMPuXN">( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) and Eq.( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">2</ref>)).</s><s xml:id="_6vZrjcq">Eq. ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) is conditioned on two variables namely the action taken (omi a t ) and reaction to the delivered intervention (reacted t ).</s><s xml:id="_VVVTPQY">Its main aim is to produce a reward indicating whether the state, where an intervention is delivered, is an appropriate state for engaging with the intervention or not.</s><s xml:id="_3YtpGDA">Thus, the most desired case is the case where an intervention is delivered and the person engages with the intervention i.e. (omi a t = Deliver I ntervention and reaction t = true).</s><s xml:id="_r843nDu">Therefore, in case an intervention is delivered but the reaction is negative i.e. (omi a t = Deliver I ntervention and reaction t = true), a relatively smaller reward should be generated.</s><s xml:id="_GvMTThE">Difference in magnitudes of these two rewards shows that discovering a state that is appropriate for engaging with an intervention is more critical.</s><s xml:id="_XsNEbus">However, there might be cases that are appropriate for engagement but no engagement occurs because of the randomization factors.</s><s xml:id="_qy2fX4y">Such cases might be observed successively.</s><s xml:id="_xTeSQ99">The negative reward is multiplied in proportion to the length of such cases.</s><s xml:id="_Ek7YJEe">Thus, to neutralize or even revert the incorrect knowledge  learnt in such situations quickly, we chose a relatively higher value (1000) for the sent r eacted case.</s><s xml:id="_8ERTgFU">Nevertheless, different values result in a similar performance as long as the value for this parameter would be the largest one among the other cases of the equation.</s><s xml:id="_s83bK27">Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">13</ref>, in (a), (b), (c) and (d) parts, show the rewards obtained for Person-1 when sent_reacted is set to 50, 500, 2500 and 10000 respectively while the other reward values are fixed.</s><s xml:id="_tcfMZKV">The results obtained for 500 and 2500 provide similar results with the original value i.e. 1000.</s><s xml:id="_Np6GnYR">The pattern changes towards to the edge cases.</s><s xml:id="_CpTtp2w">In case an even larger reward is specified, the learning performances of QL-SET and QL-SET-TL overlap since the effect of negative cases become negligible.</s><s xml:id="_DSRgGwA">On the other side, setting a smaller value for sent r eacted weakens its effect.</s><s xml:id="_kWGhhTg">As a result, performance plots of these two algorithms diverge considering also that the number of desired actions taken by QL-SET is fewer compared to QL-SET-TL.</s></p><p xml:id="_TEYGxeE"><s xml:id="_hQaft2k">The intiutive choice for the not s ent reward specified for the cases with no intervention delivery would be 0 since there is no feedback available from the person.</s><s xml:id="_X9hfQjh">However, in this case, the learning agent gets stuck at a local minima by always selecting the Deliver N othing action.</s><s xml:id="_vs6e9Rj">In order to prevent this, a relatively small negative reward is generated to force the agent take the Deliver I ntervention after some time.</s></p><p xml:id="_GnP5tuU"><s xml:id="_gdwgwUb">The second equation, i.e.</s><s xml:id="_fYgUPjv">Eq.( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">2</ref>), generates a value to fine-tune the reward generated for the sent_reacted case.</s><s xml:id="_VxgTvDU">In this equation, the temporal difference between intervention delivery and behavior performance is considered.</s><s xml:id="_dWM4GU5">The aim is to have this difference as small as possible to increase the effectiveness of the intervention.</s><s xml:id="_reSqDaT">Therefore, we set rewards in a decreasing manner as the temporal difference increases.</s><s xml:id="_cqAQTvq">Preserving this pattern while specifying reward values did not affect the performance of QL-SET-TL, QL-SET and QL.</s><s xml:id="_xDjR5J9">Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">14</ref>, in (a), (b), (c) and (d) parts, show the results obtained when the reward values are multiplied by 10, 25, 50 and 125.</s><s xml:id="_HKCaDZW">As can be seen from the figure, the results obtained for the first three scales reflect the initial patterns, even though the lines get closer as the scaling increases.</s><s xml:id="_nRGyEcE">However, increasing the scale even further causes all the results to overlap.</s><s xml:id="_qysyGJd">This is because the rewards generated in Eq.( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">2</ref>)) become negligible.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.2." xml:id="_dXUc6qf">Validation of the intervention-selection reward function</head><p xml:id="_3F8J5Y3"><s xml:id="_YSZR99S">Similarly, the reward function of the intervention-selection model is also a conditional equation (Eq.</s><s xml:id="_vctVNXv">( <ref type="formula">3</ref>)) depending on 3 variables namely, delivered action (is a t ), remembering the behavior (remember behavior t ) and reaction to the delivered intervention (reacted t ).</s></p><p xml:id="_Fv8j7mv"><s xml:id="_CTVwAqh">Considering the habit formation model, situational cues should be provided to people if they forget performing the behavior.</s><s xml:id="_gSx6BBv">Thus, the cases where the person does not remember performing the behavior i.e. (remember behavior t = false) is critical.</s><s xml:id="_9k8GsBG">Among the cases satisfying this primary condition, the case where no intervention is delivered (is a t = No I ntervention) should be avoided because it leads to non-performance of the behavior at all.</s><s xml:id="_jkJnSVH">Therefore, a relatively large, negative reward is set for this case (-50).</s><s xml:id="_6BnFErN">When the person does not remember performing the behavior but an intervention is sent i.e. (remember behavior t = false and is a t ∕ = No I ntervention), engagement may or may not occur.</s><s xml:id="_rRTy8Es">The case where an engagement occurs is a desired case.</s><s xml:id="_3YZSw9w">So, a positive reward <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> is set for this case.</s><s xml:id="_f2GnVWw">Since the non-engagement cases are considered as burden on the person, they are negatively rewarded.</s><s xml:id="_b37D3W4">Despite non-engagement, sending an intervention can still be seen as a desired behavior.</s><s xml:id="_dJ3zsPt">Therefore, we set the reward to -5 for this case.</s><s xml:id="_VbUsf2m">Cases where behavior is not remembered and no intervention is sent are the most undesirable cases (remember behavior t = false and is a t = No I nterventio).</s><s xml:id="_MVc9Fqh">Therefore, the reward for this case is -10.</s></p><p xml:id="_zqUkYvU"><s xml:id="_vnnG7wr">The person might remember the behavior and also react to the delivered intervention as well(remember behavior t = true and reacted t = true).</s><s xml:id="_UHWb4XT">However, this is still accepted as a burden on the person since s/he does not need to be reminded.</s><s xml:id="_6Sv8msn">Therefore, the reward is specified as 3 for this case.</s></p><p xml:id="_jdS36Tx"><s xml:id="_sHn9d4m">Lastly, -1 reward is specified for the case where the person remembers the behavior and no intervention is delivered (remember behavior t = true and is a t = No I ntervention).</s><s xml:id="_Abm8wYP">Although choosing 0 reward for such cases seems reasonable, we chose -1 to prevent getting stuck at a local minima as in the case of opportunemoment-identification model.</s></p><p xml:id="_s2HFS3F"><s xml:id="_XkhRZrd">Scaling the reward values all together does not change the algorithm results.</s><s xml:id="_KUxzBfA">Also, similar performance plots are obtained when the reward settings are changed by preserving the magnitudes and signs of rewards across Eq. (3).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8." xml:id="_pgyvZZJ">Discussion</head><p xml:id="_TxYbpxB"><s xml:id="_KmdZCPW">Even though the results capture the rules and conditions associated with the simulated parameters, there is still room for potential improvements e.g.</s><s xml:id="_CT7D2yP">selection of intervention types.</s><s xml:id="_ZZzSAWU">Specifically, the intervention-selection model could be improved further.</s><s xml:id="_qb4aBBV">Although we currently follow a model-free approach, the intervention-selection model can be designed as a model-based system.</s><s xml:id="_Rw6QPFP">This enables training of the value-function of the RL environment via intermediate simulations before taking an action.</s><s xml:id="_mejAWft">Such simulations could still run on the habit formation model.</s><s xml:id="_D5yNpFW">In such a structure, the intervention-selection model could even be split into two separate models that would adjust the type and frequency factors separately.</s></p><p xml:id="_fEjS8yZ"><s xml:id="_5c69ACu">We believe that the proposed learning mechanism is an innovative approach, modeling the momentary and long-term contexts of people utilizing the RL methodology, where the eventual aim is to personalize different JITAI components; namely type, frequency and timing.</s><s xml:id="_gB6bnu4">However, we provided only an initial basis concerning the model parameters that are utilized to capture the personalized patterns in relative contexts and we do not claim that those are the necessary/sufficient set of parameters.</s><s xml:id="_PkVr5XG">On the contrary, the models could be enriched with additional context parameters pertaining to environment, mobile phone or person him/herself.</s><s xml:id="_Kzqyzdh">Such an improvement would in turn require further optimization of the algorithm e.g. by better state generalization.</s><s xml:id="_a9xJwAF">In such a case deep reinforcement learning methods might be utilized as function approximators mapping the state space to the action space <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_fbkGGgE"><s xml:id="_KmWmHhV">State space and action space sizes determine the complexity of the approach such that the complexity increases as the state or action space gets larger.</s><s xml:id="_C2AZJba">Although the algorithm runs through sequential episodes where only a small portion of the overall state space is visited, the whole state space is usually much larger.</s><s xml:id="_EzwPryk">For instance, while the state space of the opportune-moment-identification model contains all combinations of time of day, physical status, phone status and so on, a person encounters only some specific states during a single episode i.e. a day.</s><s xml:id="_Xg9zyCR">Furthermore, complexity of the actual experiment phase of the approach could be seen relatively lower considering a human subject can be involved in the experiment for a limited time.</s><s xml:id="_CrQ5xdK">So, the complexity of the approach is not driven by the real experiment phase but the training phase.</s><s xml:id="_fDRTQ2S">Number of episodes to train the classifier increases as the state spaces get larger.</s><s xml:id="_Vwg4S6Y">The selective eligibility traces and transfer learning techniques that we integrated into the learning process reduce the learning time both in live and simulation compared to the existing algorithms by enabling the reuse of the learnt knowledge.</s></p><p xml:id="_D5qMarQ"><s xml:id="_cyTRbkm">In relation to the healthcare domain, we argue that the proposed approach would lead to improved care programs.</s><s xml:id="_sctCFJU">The evidence is overwhelming that healthy lifestyle behaviors like perfoming physical activity or dieting can reduce the risk of developing numerous chronic diseases and in many cases even reverse the existing disease <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_dvfkrpg">Therefore, we can argue that the proposed approach would improve the effectiveness of behavior change programs and contribute people's health via a smart intervention delivery strategy tailored to individuals.</s></p><p xml:id="_vbVEZep"><s xml:id="_7Z9vMyb">We think the scope of the proposed simulation approach can be expanded.</s><s xml:id="_PMyBv9A">In this work, we consider preferences on intervention types, commitment intensities and daily activities as differentiating factors in the persona simulation at the moment.</s><s xml:id="_fZwRxTf">However, a more realistic simulation could be achieved by also considering factors like selfefficacy, motivation, prior experience changing the behavior or outcome expectancies.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9." xml:id="_mt6uMSF">Conclusion</head><p xml:id="_Ne5XQvQ"><s xml:id="_T2dTdBM">In this study, a reinforcement learning (RL)-based algorithm is presented for personalization of intervention delivery in terms of timing, frequency and type of interventions.</s><s xml:id="_PuMAfB9">The algorithm optimizes these parameters by employing two dedicated RL models.</s><s xml:id="_cDzcnSc">The standard eligibility tracing mechanism is customized for selective rewarding of past actions as well as manipulation of the trajectory of actions considering suitability of the states for engaging with interventions.</s><s xml:id="_MDUpyz3">Furthermore, transfer learning technique is integrated with the algorithm in order to reuse knowledge across learning environments.</s></p><p xml:id="_MexaesY"><s xml:id="_YxJQqbe">The proposed approach is validated by using a simulation-based approach since human experiments are costly, risky and timeconsuming and unreliable.</s><s xml:id="_PKvBGA3">During the validation, simulated personas are provided with tailored interventions aiming to promote forming habit on a targeted health-related behavior.</s><s xml:id="_TMBW2SR">Four personas are simulated with differences in their daily activities, preferences on specific intervention types and attitude towards the targeted health behavior.</s><s xml:id="_5UvcTpa">An empirically validated habit formation model is used for realistic simulation of people's intrinsic habit-related parameters and their engagement with interventions.</s></p><p xml:id="_6hg4C6P"><s xml:id="_ZTF3wQv">The proposed algorithm is able to capture the rules and conditions associated with the simulated concepts.</s><s xml:id="_Ped398W">Also better results are obtained in comparison to the standard RL algorithms.</s></p><p xml:id="_HD3XaND"><s xml:id="_QASr7fs">As a future work, the proposed approach will be validated on a realworld case study in the scope of an ongoing multi-national project, POWER2DM <ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref> aiming to develop a self-management support system to support diabetes patients in their daily lives.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .Fig. 2 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_wdd9kvr"><s xml:id="_4JkGnch">Fig. 1.</s><s xml:id="_Jjgch4H">Partitioning of the daily time frame according to an action plan.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,141.62,55.43,312.05,72.86" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_XK6fmN9"><s xml:id="_u93bXWE">Fig. 3. Schematic diagram of the overall approach.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,117.69,55.43,359.86,286.99" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_cbV2DGj"><s xml:id="_ydQKhs2">Fig. 4. Agent-environment interactions within the opportune-moment-identification model.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,117.64,589.15,360.00,137.09" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_wTU6R5Z"><s xml:id="_P2JZ2PE">Fig. 5. Modifications on the standard eligibility traces.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="6,117.64,403.68,360.00,322.56" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 6 .Fig. 7 .</head><label>67</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_AsBQ9ke"><s xml:id="_tBsVKA2">Fig. 6.</s><s xml:id="_vp3ttVD">The algorithm for updating CP after each episode.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,117.64,55.41,360.00,236.16" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_YEByjff"><s xml:id="_YNsMPga">The time value is generalized to represent only the quarter hour periods.</s><s xml:id="_AAkEEVq">Its value is calculated with the following equation: time = h*4 + ⌊m / 15⌋, where hour h is defined as h = {h: h &gt;= 0 and h &lt; 24, h ∈ℕ} and minute m is defined as m = {m: m &gt;= 0 and h &lt; 60, m ∈ℕ}.• location: Location represents whereabouts of a person with three enumerated values namely Home, Office and Other.•</s><s xml:id="_VYFwM98">physical_activity_status: This parameter is used to enumerate physical activity of a person with Sedentary, Indoor_Activity, Walking, Running and Driving alternatives.•</s><s xml:id="_ZSFRjjM">phone_screen_status: Enumerated value of phone screen status that can be On or Off.• emotional_status: Enumerated value representing the emotions that a person may have including Neutral, Happy, Excited, Relaxed, Angry and Stressed alternatives.•</s><s xml:id="_jqaDdeq">number_of_interventions_sent_for_planned_activity: Number of delivered interventions for the active activity defined in the action plan.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_PXjyD7y"><s xml:id="_qtbry46">not s ent n ot r emembered(-50), if is a = No I ntervention, remember b ehavior = true sent r emembered n ot r eacted(-10), if is a ∕ = No I ntervention, remember b ehavior = true, reacted = false sent n ot r emembered n ot r eacted(-5), if is a ∕ = No I ntervention, remember b ehavior = false, reacted = false sent r emembered r eacted(-3), if is a ∕ = No I ntervention, remember b ehavior = true, reacted = true not s ent r emembered(-1), if is a = No I ntervention, remember b ehavior = true sent n ot r emembered r eacted(10), if is a ∕ = No I ntervention, remember b ehavior = false, reacted = true</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_XeQWfGV"><s xml:id="_Qe3XwpN">represents the number of interventions delivered in each episode.</s><s xml:id="_Z4xq8Wx">The dappled lines with square shapes show the values obtained for this metric.</s><s xml:id="_jUtaGSa">As implied by the habit formation model, the number of interventions gets closer to zero last for Person-1, i.e. the algorithm delivers interventions for a longer time for Person-1 compared to the other persons.</s><s xml:id="_qpJYyFP">In general, the length of intervention delivery period decreases for each person inversely proportional to the commitment intensity values set for the associated personas.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 9 .Fig. 10 .</head><label>910</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_QH52ta7"><s xml:id="_zAj5ExE">Fig. 9. Person vs. intervention type ratio plot.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="12,81.64,55.41,432.00,155.38" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 11 .Fig. 12 .</head><label>1112</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_EjfZgUn"><s xml:id="_sK3Rq9v">Fig. 11.</s><s xml:id="_CSg5tj8">Rewards collected per episode in the opportune-moment-identification model.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="13,81.69,55.42,431.86,307.87" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 13 .</head><label>13</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_Hgs3qSY"><s xml:id="_HEfyhVZ">Fig. 13.</s><s xml:id="_K7F2Wc9">Rewards obtained with the modified the sent-reacted variable in Eq. (1).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="14,117.92,55.42,359.42,244.37" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 14 .</head><label>14</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_K2m3why"><s xml:id="_sbYNKvW">Fig. 14.</s><s xml:id="_7CfzXcW">Rewards obtained with varying scales of temporal rewards.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="14,82.26,444.72,430.70,281.52" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p xml:id="_bJXjK4x"><s xml:id="_DV4XvWq">https://cordis.europa.eu/project/id/689444</s></p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_vP2EkMJ">Conflict of interest</head><p xml:id="_ASvy7uv"><s xml:id="_RNrh6Qj">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_h2Tgeju">Appendix A. Integration of the habit formation model with the intervention-selection model</head><p xml:id="_eYaRqJG"><s xml:id="_mchWtCQ">Similar to the RL models, the habit formation model is also an iterative model and has its own internal dynamics.</s><s xml:id="_gcTuN8y">It runs in parallel with the intervention-selection model.</s><s xml:id="_y8pBmrR">At each state transition of the intervention-selection model, we also iterate the habit formation model by updating its internal parameters.</s><s xml:id="_9a8semQ">Four parameters are updated at each step of the habit formation model, namely habit strength, behavior frequency, accessibility and salience of reminders (corresponding to interventions in our case) <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_r8CA5Cg">Although accessibility and salience of reminder concepts are not directly included in the laid-out RL model, they are essential parameters for predicting the remembering of the behavior.</s><s xml:id="_kRVmPQn">In the rest of this section, iterative updating procedure of these four parameters are presented via a set of equations that are adopted from the habit-formation model.</s><s xml:id="_qhVpxhF">Then, Eq. (A.10) and Eq.</s><s xml:id="_zr5jrSz">(A.11) shows the prediction methodology on remembering the behavior.</s><s xml:id="_rNPHqFp">All these equations are solved at each step of the intervention-selection model in order to calculate the parameters of the next state.</s></p><p xml:id="_mrmCq6f"><s xml:id="_bEH4xVu">The subsequent three equations show calculation of the next habit strength value (hs t+1 ).</s><s xml:id="_DRFJBxA">In Eq. (A.1), the decay amount on the habit strength arising from not performing the behavior (bp t = false) is obtained.</s><s xml:id="_4V9NjQH">If the person performs the behavior (bp t = true), the habit strength does not decrease.</s><s xml:id="_GZpkcpE">Then, in Eq. (A.2), increase amount of the habit strength is calculated in case the person performs the behavior.</s><s xml:id="_Xq9wr5M">Finally, the final value of the habit strength for the next step (hs t+1 ) is obtained in Eq. (A.3) by subtracting the decay amount and adding the increase amount to the value at the previous step (hs t ).</s><s xml:id="_bCsH5ve">In these equations, hs t , bf t and bp t are the habit strength, behavior frequency and behavior performance at step t. bf t indicates whether the behavior is performed or not after taking the action a t .</s><s xml:id="_SdGzGyG">HDC, i.e. the habit decay constant, is the constant introduced by the habit formation model, adjusting the decay amount at each step.</s><s xml:id="_VzjNS9V">Eq. (A.4) shows the calculation of the next value of behavior_frequency (bf t+1 ).</s><s xml:id="_e9wpC8V">A sliding window is maintained to keep a record for each opportunity to perform the behavior within a particular period in the past.</s><s xml:id="_mJC2EYS">As a result of discussion with cognitive behavior psychologists, it is decided to have the history size as 14 days, as records of past 2 weeks might reveal patterns about the behaviors of people about their self-management activities.</s><s xml:id="_36vCYTH">The window is implemented as a queue such that each of its items is a binary value indicating whether the behavior has been performed or not.</s><s xml:id="_UgTSYhH">At each step, the oldest item (bp oldest ) of the window is removed from the queue, and the latest behavior performance indicator (bp newest ) is pushed into the queue.</s><s xml:id="_P6M2jv8">The behavior frequency is the ratio of the number of the behavior performances to the total opportunity count, as calculated in Eq. (A.4).</s><s xml:id="_seRxkJg">People get bored of seeing the same type of notifications on their mobile phones.</s><s xml:id="_c3bqYfR">Then, they become unresponsive to such notifications or discard them <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_tcmJ6nf">In the scope of this study, intervention types are grouped according to their categories (e.g.</s><s xml:id="_xuGguzy">reminders and motivations as mentioned earlier).</s><s xml:id="_aSBM6yK">A specific category might be associated with several intervention types.</s><s xml:id="_bhp7Z7W">For example, two reminder intervention types might be using different behavior change techniques to remind a behavior.</s></p><p xml:id="_UfKAtut"><s xml:id="_eZwjKk7">Our method maintains one salience indicator for each intervention type (i).</s><s xml:id="_huU45mh">Eq. (A.5) shows calculation of the next value of intervention salience indicator(sal i,t+1 ).</s><s xml:id="_8x4fBfn">Indicators of only the interventions having the same category with the selected action (category i = category sat ) are updated at each step.</s><s xml:id="_7WGGA6b">Salience indicator of the selected intervention type (is a t ) decreases in proportion to the current salience amount.</s><s xml:id="_FRHaU6A">The amount is calculated by using the SC constant of the habit formation model.</s><s xml:id="_fGxt4y5">Indicators of other interventions having the same category with the current intervention (i ∕ = is a t and category(i) = category(is a t )) are increased as the person is not exposed to them.</s><s xml:id="_pxDzBCF">The same constant is applied in the opposite direction to increase the salience amount.</s><s xml:id="_Jr4UkXQ">∀i(i ∈ A IS and i ∕ = No I ntervention and category(i) = category(is a t )),</s></p><p xml:id="_qe62X9D"><s xml:id="_zq2deZ9">Accessibility is defined as likelihood of performing the behavior by the habit formation model.</s><s xml:id="_ehVcupE">According to the model, accessibility decreases at each step, in proportion to its current amount (Eq.</s><s xml:id="_E7nDKKP">(A.6)).</s><s xml:id="_7heCmyw">On the other hand, it increases in presence of a reminder (Eq.</s><s xml:id="_zKGjPnD">(A.7)) and when the targeted behavior is performed (Eq.</s><s xml:id="_JqsqHKf">(A.8)).</s><s xml:id="_DaJkwwE">So, if an intervention is selected at step t, accessibility is increased accordingly.</s><s xml:id="_EeqhaVJ">The updated value of accessibility is obtained by subtracting the decay amount and adding the increase amounts to the previous value (Eq.</s><s xml:id="_CrxpuZF">(A.9)).</s></p><p xml:id="_52arwzy"><s xml:id="_K7Yzs8N">acc t+1 = acc tacc decay t + acc g ain pb t + acc g ain rem t (A.9)</s></p><p xml:id="_MVm7pjT"><s xml:id="_q2rNmr7">In these equations, acc t , bp t , bf t , is a t and sal t represent respectively accessibility value, whether the behavior performed, behavior frequency, intervention selection action and salience of the selected intervention at step t. ci represent the commitment intensity of the person indicating the strength of any form of internal pressure by the person to perform the behavior.</s><s xml:id="_fjqKnfJ">Furthermore, ADC, AGC P B, AGC R and WCI R EM are the constants obtained from the habit formation model.</s><s xml:id="_NkFgS9z">They respectively represent the constants for accessibility decay, accessibility gain by performing the behavior, accessibility gain by reminders and weight of the commitment intensity in accessibility gain by reminders.</s><s xml:id="_ZN7M3vg">The last step regarding the iteration of the habit formation model is to predict whether the person would remember to perform the behavior or not.</s><s xml:id="_BN86k4Z">The prediction is simply done by comparing the current accessibility value and the accessibility threshold value.</s><s xml:id="_UYRQDpv">Accessibility threshold depends on the habit strength and behavior frequency parameters.</s><s xml:id="_V7faT3R">Based on these values, the threshold value is obtained using Eq.</s><s xml:id="_Uv9GBWS">(A.10).</s><s xml:id="_GyxgeNA">Getting accessibility greater than the threshold indicates that the person would remember to perform the behavior (Eq.</s><s xml:id="_XnhS9hd">(A.</s><s xml:id="_zhM5m97">In this equation, acc t , hs t and bf t represents accessibility, habit strenght and behavior frequency values at step t.</s><s xml:id="_7pm66e4">ATC, ATH, ATBF and DTH are the constants representing accessibility threshold, weight of habit strength in accessibility threshold, weight of the behavior frequency in accessability threshold and weight of distraction due to habits.</s><s xml:id="_Xk48fPD">Please refer to the original study for more details about these constants and the habit formation model itself <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_mw5dv6e">Building new computational models to support health behavior change and maintenance: new opportunities in behavioral research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Spruijt-Metz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hekler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Saranummi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Intille</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Korhonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Nilsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s13142-015-0324-1</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_d4APG8J">Transl Behav Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="335" to="346" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Spruijt-Metz D, Hekler E, Saranummi N, Intille S, Korhonen I, Nilsen W, et al. Building new computational models to support health behavior change and maintenance: new opportunities in behavioral research. Transl Behav Med 2015;5 (3):335-46.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_grM2kYE">Noncommunicable diseases</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2471/b09509</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/noncommunicable-diseases" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018-06">2018 June. March 4, 2021</date>
			<publisher>World Health Organization</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">World Health Organization. Noncommunicable diseases. 2018 June (accessed March 4, 2021), https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/nonco mmunicable-diseases.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_mgukAJH">Effects of low-energy diet or exercise on cardiovascular function in working-age adults with type 2 diabetes: a prospective, randomized, open-label, blinded end point trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Gulsin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Swarbrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Athithan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Brady</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Henson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Baldry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2337/dc20-0129</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Pq3TjTd">Diabetes Care</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1300" to="1310" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Gulsin GS, Swarbrick DJ, Athithan L, Brady EM, Henson J, Baldry E, et al. Effects of low-energy diet or exercise on cardiovascular function in working-age adults with type 2 diabetes: a prospective, randomized, open-label, blinded end point trial. Diabetes Care 2020;43(6):1300-10.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_adShxGn">Success rates in smoking cessation: psychological preparation plays a critical role and interacts with other factors such as psychoactive substances</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Joly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Perriot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Athis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Chazard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Brousse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Quantin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ZBRYGv5">Plos one</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">184800</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Joly B, Perriot J, d&apos;Athis P, Chazard E, Brousse G, Quantin C. Success rates in smoking cessation: psychological preparation plays a critical role and interacts with other factors such as psychoactive substances. Plos one 2017;12(10): e0184800.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_s2xGAgs">Effectiveness of mobile phone messaging in prevention of type 2 diabetes by lifestyle modification in men in India: a prospective, parallel-group, randomised controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ramachandran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Snehalatha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Selvam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nanditha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s2213-8587(13)70067-6</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_9HXXuYT">Lancet Diabetes Endocrinol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="198" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ramachandran A, Snehalatha C, Ram J, Selvam S, Simon M, Nanditha A, et al. Effectiveness of mobile phone messaging in prevention of type 2 diabetes by lifestyle modification in men in India: a prospective, parallel-group, randomised controlled trial. Lancet Diabetes Endocrinol 2013;1(3):191-8.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_CDgVpaN">A randomized clinical trial of a tailored lifestyle intervention for obese, sedentary, primary care patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Eaton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hartman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Perzanowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Risica</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_rvBYpgp">Ann Fam Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="311" to="319" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Eaton CB, Hartman SJ, Perzanowski E, Pan G, Roberts MB, Risica PM, et al. A randomized clinical trial of a tailored lifestyle intervention for obese, sedentary, primary care patients. Ann Fam Med 2016;14(4):311-9.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Bzx9yjb">Near-optimal insulin treatment for diabetes patients: a machine learning approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Shifrin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Siegelmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.artmed.2020.101917</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_2YwuFdm">Artif Intell Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">101917</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Shifrin M, Siegelmann H. Near-optimal insulin treatment for diabetes patients: a machine learning approach. Artif Intell Med 2020:101917.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_rtedqWq">Reinforcement learning application in diabetes blood glucose control: a systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tejedor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Woldaregay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Godtliebsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_YbBSMts">Artif Intell Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">101836</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Tejedor M, Woldaregay AZ, Godtliebsen F. Reinforcement learning application in diabetes blood glucose control: a systematic review. Artif Intell Med 2020:101836.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_yXs4sfX">A comprehensive overview of smart wearables: the state of the art literature, recent advances, and future challenges</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Niknejad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ismail</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mardani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Liao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ghani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.engappai.2020.103529</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Fjg2d65">Eng Appl Artif Intell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">103529</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Niknejad N, Ismail WB, Mardani A, Liao H, Ghani I. A comprehensive overview of smart wearables: the state of the art literature, recent advances, and future challenges. Eng Appl Artif Intell 2020;90:103529.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_KEtU2r3">Just-in-time adaptive interventions (JITAIs) in mobile health: key components and design principles for ongoing health behavior support</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nahum-Shani I</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Spring</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Collins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Witkiewitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tewari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_CYSwSUr">Ann Behav Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="446" to="462" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nahum-Shani I, Smith SN, Spring BJ, Collins LM, Witkiewitz K, Tewari A, et al. Just-in-time adaptive interventions (JITAIs) in mobile health: key components and design principles for ongoing health behavior support. Ann Behav Med 2017;52(6): 446-62.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_kEb5ZkN">Reinforcement learning: an introduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Sutton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Barto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<publisher>MIT press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sutton RS, Barto AG. Reinforcement learning: an introduction. MIT press.; 1998.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_8Zz7xVF">Anticipatory mobile computing for behaviour change interventions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Pejovic</forename><surname>Veljko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Musolesi</forename><surname>Mirco</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_tbjFZFy">Proceedings of the 2014 ACM international joint conference on pervasive and ubiquitous computing: adjunct publication</title>
		<meeting>the 2014 ACM international joint conference on pervasive and ubiquitous computing: adjunct publication</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-09-13">2014 September 13-17</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Pejovic Veljko, Musolesi Mirco. Anticipatory mobile computing for behaviour change interventions. In: Proceedings of the 2014 ACM international joint conference on pervasive and ubiquitous computing: adjunct publication; 2014 September 13-17.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_d88zYfG">Scalable inverse reinforcement learning through multifidelity bayesian optimization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Imani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Ghoreishi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_RbAaTT3">Ieee Trans Neural Netw Learn Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Imani M, Ghoreishi SF. Scalable inverse reinforcement learning through multifidelity bayesian optimization. Ieee Trans Neural Netw Learn Syst 2021.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_d7HTdGX">Transfer in reinforcement learning: a framework and a survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lazaric</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_pAC4N88">Reinforcement learning</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin, Heidelberg</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="173" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lazaric A. Transfer in reinforcement learning: a framework and a survey. Reinforcement learning. Berlin, Heidelberg: Springer; 2012. p. 143-73.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_XqcdhVV">Transfer learning via inter-task mappings for temporal difference learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1145/1329125.1329170</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_RBJ8MQ4">J Mach Learn Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2125" to="2167" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-09">2007. Sep</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Taylor ME, Stone P, Liu Y. Transfer learning via inter-task mappings for temporal difference learning. J Mach Learn Res 2007;8(Sep):2125-67.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_PhZtG6k">Time hopping technique for faster reinforcement learning in simulations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kormushev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Nomoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hirota</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.20965/jaciii.2009.p0600</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Evrmrcr">Cybern Inf Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kormushev P, Nomoto K, Dong F, Hirota K. Time hopping technique for faster reinforcement learning in simulations. Cybern Inf Technol 2011;11(3).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qzApUWC">Optimization of justin-time adaptive interventions using reinforcement learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gonul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Namli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Baskaya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sinaci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cosar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Toroslu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-3-319-92058-0_32</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_2wxFJXk">Recent trends and future technology in applied intelligence. IEA/AIE 2018</title>
		<title level="s" xml:id="_DqbUwg4">lecture notes in computer science</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mouhoub</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sadaoui</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ait</forename><surname>Mohamed</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Ali</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cham</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10868</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Gonul S, Namli T, Baskaya M, Sinaci AA, Cosar A, Toroslu IH. Optimization of just- in-time adaptive interventions using reinforcement learning. In: Mouhoub M, Sadaoui S, Ait Mohamed O, Ali M, editors. Recent trends and future technology in applied intelligence. IEA/AIE 2018. lecture notes in computer science, vol 10868. Cham: Springer; 2018.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_JH9aj93">Changing behavior by memory aids: a social psychological model of prospective memory and habit development tested with dynamic field data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Tobias</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_7RzYGJy">Psychol Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">408</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Tobias R. Changing behavior by memory aids: a social psychological model of prospective memory and habit development tested with dynamic field data. Psychol Rev 2009;116(2):408.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_M65XdcZ">Feasibility, acceptability, and preliminary efficacy of a smartphone intervention for schizophrenia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ben-Zeev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Brenner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Begale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Duffecy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Mohr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Mueser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/schbul/sbu033</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_3ARhGbu">Schizophr Bull</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1244" to="1253" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ben-Zeev D, Brenner CJ, Begale M, Duffecy J, Mohr DC, Mueser KT. Feasibility, acceptability, and preliminary efficacy of a smartphone intervention for schizophrenia. Schizophr Bull 2014;40(6):1244-53.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_NhsUdsA">Automatic messaging for improving patients engagement in diabetes management: an exploratory study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fioravanti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Fico</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Salvi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>García-Betances</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Arredondo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_zkhudCD">Med Biol Eng Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1285" to="1294" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Fioravanti A, Fico G, Salvi D, García-Betances RI, Arredondo MT. Automatic messaging for improving patients engagement in diabetes management: an exploratory study. Med Biol Eng Comput 2015;53(12):1285-94.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_m2YXwck">Effectiveness of a smartphone application for weight loss compared with usual care in overweight primary care patients: a randomized controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Laing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mangione</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Tseng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Leng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Vaisberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mahida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.7326/m13-3005</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_5ffbu6p">Ann Inter Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">161</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10_Supplement</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Laing BY, Mangione CM, Tseng CH, Leng M, Vaisberg E, Mahida M, et al. Effectiveness of a smartphone application for weight loss compared with usual care in overweight primary care patients: a randomized controlled trial. Ann Inter Med 2014;161(10_Supplement):S5-12.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_4gTquzj">A smartphone application to support recovery from alcoholism: a randomized clinical trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Gustafson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mctavish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chih</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Atwood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Boyle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Dux84RZ">JAMA Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="566" to="572" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Gustafson DH, McTavish FM, Chih MY, Atwood AK, Johnson RA, Boyle MG, et al. A smartphone application to support recovery from alcoholism: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA Psychiatry 2014;71(5):566-72.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ZFt3Zr2">DialBetics: a novel smartphone-based self-management support system for type 2 diabetes patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Waki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fujita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Uchimura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Omae</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Aramaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kato</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_WDhk85z">J Diabetes Sci Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="209" to="215" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Waki K, Fujita H, Uchimura Y, Omae K, Aramaki E, Kato S, et al. DialBetics: a novel smartphone-based self-management support system for type 2 diabetes patients. J Diabetes Sci Technol 2014;8(2):209-15.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_wutgmDX">Personalised medicine in critical care using Bayesian reinforcement learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Utomo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kurniawati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pokharel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-3-030-35231-8_47</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_T22k2Kb">International conference on advanced data mining and applications</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cham</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2019-11">2019 November</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="648" to="657" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Utomo CP, Kurniawati H, Li X, Pokharel S. Personalised medicine in critical care using Bayesian reinforcement learning. International conference on advanced data mining and applications. Cham: Springer; 2019 November. p. 648-57.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_CpjjGft">A model-free affective reinforcement learning approach to personalization of an autonomous social robot companion for early literacy education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Grover</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Spaulding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gomez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Breazeal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1609/aaai.v33i01.3301687</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_6Muy9Vy">proceedings of the AAAI conference on artificial intelligence</title>
		<meeting>the AAAI conference on artificial intelligence</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019-07">2019 July</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="687" to="694" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Park HW, Grover I, Spaulding S, Gomez L, Breazeal C. A model-free affective reinforcement learning approach to personalization of an autonomous social robot companion for early literacy education. In proceedings of the AAAI conference on artificial intelligence (vol. 33, no. 01) 2019 July:687-94.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_uqN25wa">Predictive modeling of addiction lapses in a mobile health application</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chih</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Patton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mctavish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Isham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Judkins-Fisher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Atwood</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_FvCJwRF">J Subst Abuse Treat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Chih MY, Patton T, McTavish FM, Isham AJ, Judkins-Fisher CL, Atwood AK, et al. Predictive modeling of addiction lapses in a mobile health application. J Subst Abuse Treat 2014;46(1):29-35.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_YYNQBK3">Return of the JITAI: applying a just-in-time adaptive intervention framework to the development of m-health solutions for addictive behaviors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Goldstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Evans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Flack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Juarascio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Manasse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s12529-016-9627-y</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_BtMrwHJ">Int J Behav Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="673" to="682" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Goldstein SP, Evans BC, Flack D, Juarascio A, Manasse S, Zhang F, et al. Return of the JITAI: applying a just-in-time adaptive intervention framework to the development of m-health solutions for addictive behaviors. Int J Behav Med 2017; 24(5):673-82.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_euGQFxh">The importance of behavior theory in control system modeling of physical activity sensor data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Riley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Cesar</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rivera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/embc.2014.6945209</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_HgEUQDF">Engineering in medicine and biology society</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>EMBC</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014-08">2014. 2014 August</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6880" to="6883" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Riley WT, Cesar A, Rivera DE. The importance of behavior theory in control system modeling of physical activity sensor data. Engineering in medicine and biology society (EMBC), 2014 36th annual international conference of the IEEE 2014 August:6880-3.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_DpTtVUR">A dynamical model for describing behavioural interventions for weight loss and body composition change</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Navarro-Barrientos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Rivera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Collins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_xN83Cwj">Math Comput Model Dyn Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="183" to="203" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Navarro-Barrientos JE, Rivera DE, Collins LM. A dynamical model for describing behavioural interventions for weight loss and body composition change. Math Comput Model Dyn Syst 2011;17(2):183-203.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_k9S7UTs">From intentions to actions: a theory of planned behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ajzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_qSQCnzw">Action control</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin Heidelberg</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="39" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ajzen I. From intentions to actions: a theory of planned behavior. Action control. Springer Berlin Heidelberg; 1985. p. 11-39.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_a4PBcSZ">Social foundations of thought and action: a social cognitive theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bandura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall, Inc</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Englewood Cliffs, NJ, US</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bandura A. Social foundations of thought and action: a social cognitive theory. Englewood Cliffs, NJ, US: Prentice-Hall, Inc; 1986.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_bJQPdCQ">A dynamical systems model of social cognitive theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Rivera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Riley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Hekler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Buman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Adams</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_cu8veXf">American control conference</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACC</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014-06">2014 June. 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2407" to="2412" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Martin CA, Rivera DE, Riley WT, Hekler EB, Buman MP, Adams MA, et al. A dynamical systems model of social cognitive theory. American control conference (ACC) 2014 June:2407-12. 2014.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_eWgbKeN">Dynamic models of behavior for just-in-time adaptive interventions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Spruijt-Metz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Nilsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_WrNRJDT">IEEE Pervasive Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="17" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Spruijt-Metz D, Nilsen W. Dynamic models of behavior for just-in-time adaptive interventions. IEEE Pervasive Comput 2014;13(3):13-7.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Q8EbGzn">An actor-critic contextual bandit algorithm for personalized interventions using mobile devices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tewari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_azvgtMU">Adv Neural Inf Process Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lei H, Tewari A, Murphy S. An actor-critic contextual bandit algorithm for personalized interventions using mobile devices. Adv Neural Inf Process Syst 2014; 27.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_xTce56C">An expandable approach for design and personalization of digital, just-in-time adaptive interventions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gonul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Namli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Huisman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laleci</forename><surname>Erturkmen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Toroslu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Cosar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_wFZxrnW">J Am Med Inform Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="198" to="210" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Gonul S, Namli T, Huisman S, Laleci Erturkmen GB, Toroslu IH, Cosar A. An expandable approach for design and personalization of digital, just-in-time adaptive interventions. J Am Med Inform Assoc 2019;26(3):198-210.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_e9rWKxK">Temporal second difference traces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Bloch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1104.4664</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bloch MK. Temporal second difference traces. 2011. arXiv preprint arXiv: 1104.4664.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_U5qJ8Yf">Postponed updates for temporal-difference reinforcement learning. Intelligent systems design and applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Van Seijen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Whiteson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/isda.2009.76</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009-11">2009. 2009 November</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="665" to="672" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ISDA&apos;09. ninth international conference</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">van Seijen H, Whiteson S. Postponed updates for temporal-difference reinforcement learning. Intelligent systems design and applications, 2009. ISDA&apos;09. ninth international conference on 2009 November:665-72.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_xTNp5vh">Transfer learning for reinforcement learning domains: a survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-3-642-01882-4_7</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_wzTtSZR">J Mach Learn Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1633" to="1685" />
			<date type="published" when="2009-07">2009. Jul</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Taylor ME, Stone P. Transfer learning for reinforcement learning domains: a survey. J Mach Learn Res 2009;10(Jul):1633-85.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_bcuZcsT">Knowledge transfer in reinforcement learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lazaric</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.58286/29685</idno>
		<ptr target="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-00772626/document" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<pubPlace>Milano)</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Politecnico di Milano</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD thesis</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lazaric A. Knowledge transfer in reinforcement learning (Doctoral dissertation, PhD thesis, Politecnico di Milano, Milano). 2008. Retrieved from https://hal.inria. fr/hal-00772626/document.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_TXxzeQN">Multi-criteria expertness based cooperative method for SARSA and eligibility trace algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Pakizeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Pedram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Palhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_CEnDwDs">Appl Intell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="487" to="498" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Pakizeh E, Pedram MM, Palhang M. Multi-criteria expertness based cooperative method for SARSA and eligibility trace algorithms. Appl Intell 2015;43(3):487-98.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_PuJCX2A">Group-driven reinforcement learning for personalized mhealth intervention</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Liao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-3-030-00928-1_67</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_7W4VFWm">International conference on medical image computing and computer-assisted intervention</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cham</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2018-09">2018 September</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="590" to="598" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Zhu F, Guo J, Xu Z, Liao P, Yang L, Huang J. Group-driven reinforcement learning for personalized mhealth intervention. International conference on medical image computing and computer-assisted intervention. Cham: Springer; 2018 September. p. 590-8.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ZEGNQw7">Narrowing reinforcement learning: overcoming the cold start problem for personalized health interventions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tabatabaei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hoogendoorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Van Halteren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-3-030-03098-8_19</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_MXbJnRw">International conference on principles and practice of multi-agent systems</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cham</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2018-10">2018 October</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="312" to="327" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Tabatabaei SA, Hoogendoorn M, van Halteren A. Narrowing reinforcement learning: overcoming the cold start problem for personalized health interventions. International conference on principles and practice of multi-agent systems. Cham: Springer; 2018 October. p. 312-27.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_cpPVuaq">Recommender systems for healthy behavior change</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Yürüten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3940/rina.innovsail.2010.14</idno>
		<ptr target="https://infoscience.epfl.ch/record/231155" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<pubPlace>Lausanne</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Doctoral dissertation</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Yürüten O. Recommender systems for healthy behavior change. 2017 (Doctoral dissertation, École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne, Lausanne). Retrieved from https://infoscience.epfl.ch/record/231155.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_fsCqzV3">Care plans and care planning in long term conditions: a conceptual model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Burt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Blakeman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Protheroe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Roland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bower</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1017/S1463423613000327</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1017/S1463423613000327" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_MmMWrc3">Prim Health Care Res Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="342" to="354" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Burt J, Rick J, Blakeman T, Protheroe J, Roland M, Bower P. Care plans and care planning in long term conditions: a conceptual model. Prim Health Care Res Dev 2014;15(4):342-54. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1463423613000327.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ZgkVUmq">Supplemental observation acquisition for learning by observation agents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Floyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Esfandiari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10489-018-1191-5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_zQ3VCMx">Appl Intell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="17" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Floyd MW, Esfandiari B. Supplemental observation acquisition for learning by observation agents. Appl Intell 2018:1-17.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_4BDfmx9">Random forests</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Breiman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1023/a:1010933404324</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_TXEtsaN">Mach Learn</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="32" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Breiman L. Random forests. Mach Learn 2001;45(1):5-32.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_UatnV4r">Mllib: machine learning in apache spark</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bradley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Yavuz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sparks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Venkataraman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_TNJdBAZ">J Mach Learn Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1235" to="1241" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Meng X, Bradley J, Yavuz B, Sparks E, Venkataraman S, Liu D, et al. Mllib: machine learning in apache spark. J Mach Learn Res 2016;17(1):1235-41.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_wQueAGw">How are habits formed: modelling habit formation in the real world</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lally</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Van Jaarsveld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Potts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wardle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/ejsp.674</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_fjbCfsG">Eur J Soc Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="998" to="1009" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lally P, Van Jaarsveld CH, Potts HW, Wardle J. How are habits formed: modelling habit formation in the real world. Eur J Soc Psychol 2010;40(6):998-1009.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_a6a8QXP">Self-efficacy in activities of daily living and symptom management in people with dizziness: a focus group study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fridberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Gustavsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_uNUtARN">Disabil Rehabil</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="705" to="713" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Fridberg H, Gustavsson C. Self-efficacy in activities of daily living and symptom management in people with dizziness: a focus group study. Disabil Rehabil 2019; 41(6):705-13.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_2kxNCVD">Perceived difficulty with physical tasks, lifestyle, and physical performance in obese children</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Valerio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Gallarato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>'amico</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Sticco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tortorelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Zito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_29F49TU">BioMed Res Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Valerio G, Gallarato V, D&apos;Amico O, Sticco M, Tortorelli P, Zito E, et al. Perceived difficulty with physical tasks, lifestyle, and physical performance in obese children. BioMed Res Int 2014;2014.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_tmQFVPB">Deep reinforcement learning: an overview</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1701.07274</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Li Y. Deep reinforcement learning: an overview. 2017. arXiv preprint arXiv: 1701.07274.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_e9zphT4">Mobile intervention design in diabetes: review and recommendations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mulvaney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ritterband</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bosslet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11892-011-0230-y</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_4dVX97y">Curr Diabetes Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">486</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mulvaney SA, Ritterband LM, Bosslet L. Mobile intervention design in diabetes: review and recommendations. Curr Diabetes Rep 2011;11(6):486.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
