<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_NQFrhg9">Digital therapeutics in Japan: Present and future directions</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Enago&apos;s English Editing</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
					<p type="raw">© 2024 Japanese College of Cardiology. Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). 0914-5087/© 2024 Japanese College of Cardiology. Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2024-11-28">28 November 2024</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>MD, PhD) ⁎</roleName><forename type="first">Akihiro</forename><surname>Nomura</surname></persName>
							<email>anomura@med.kanazawa-u.ac.jp</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">⁎ College of Transdisciplinary Sciences for Innovation , Kanazawa University , Kakuma- machi , Kanazawa , Ishikawa , 9201192 , Japan.</note>
								<orgName type="department">College of Transdisciplinary Sciences for Innovation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Kanazawa University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Kakuma- machi</addrLine>
									<postCode>9201192</postCode>
									<settlement>Kanazawa</settlement>
									<region>Ishikawa</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">College of Transdisciplinary Sciences for Innovation , Kanazawa University , Kanazawa , Japan</note>
								<orgName type="department">College of Transdisciplinary Sciences for Innovation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Kanazawa University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Kanazawa</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Department of Cardiovascular Medicine , Kanazawa University Graduate School of Medical Sciences , Kanazawa , Japan</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiovascular Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Kanazawa University Graduate School of Medical Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Kanazawa</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Frontier Institute of Tourism Sciences , Kanazawa University , Kanazawa , Japan</note>
								<orgName type="department">Frontier Institute of Tourism Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Kanazawa University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Kanazawa</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">CureApp Institute , Karuizawa , Japan</note>
								<orgName type="institution">CureApp Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Karuizawa</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_DAAzUVu">Digital therapeutics in Japan: Present and future directions</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2024-11-28">28 November 2024</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">DF11B0461E77A31D6E7732A6CE80926B</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jjcc.2024.11.005</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 3 October 2024 Received in revised form 4 November 2024 Accepted 11 November 2024</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T10:59+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords xml:id="_ZNGuReB">mHealth SaMD Digital medicine Digital therapeutics</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_YHhRWjz"><p xml:id="_ZAXUPCH"><s xml:id="_g6J4HMN">s u m m a r y Digital therapeutics (DTx) represent an innovative approach to healthcare, leveraging software applications (apps) delivered through digital devices to treat medical conditions.</s><s xml:id="_frAgnvx">This review focuses on three DTx apps approved in Japan, targeting nicotine dependence, hypertension, and insomnia.</s><s xml:id="_WnCZkr8">CureApp SC, the DTx system for nicotine dependence, comprises a patient smartphone app, an Internet of Things device for exhaled carbon monoxide measurement, and a Web-based physician app.</s><s xml:id="_aH6vJYf">A clinical trial demonstrated significantly higher rates of continuous abstinence in the intervention group than in the controls (63.9 % vs. 50.5 %, p = 0.001) at 24 weeks, with effects persisting through 52 weeks.</s><s xml:id="_xM8hhA6">For hypertension management, CureApp HT focuses on lifestyle modifications with daily home blood pressure monitoring.</s><s xml:id="_SqFzvRU">The HERB-DH1 trial showed a significant reduction in 24-h systolic blood pressure (between-group difference, -2.4 mmHg; p = 0.024) and morning home blood pressure (between-group difference, -4.3 mmHg; p &lt; 0.001) in the intervention group compared with those in the controls.</s><s xml:id="_8gUJqUe">This hypertension DTx app also exhibits potential lifetime cost-effectiveness.</s><s xml:id="_q55xuq5">Regarding insomnia management, SUSMED MedCBT-i supports physician-delivered cognitive behavioral therapy for insomnia.</s><s xml:id="_t4B7kfU">In a randomized controlled trial, Athens Insomnia Scale scores significantly improved in the intervention group compared with those in the controls (between-group difference, -3.4 point; p &lt; 0.001) at 8 weeks.</s><s xml:id="_VQVEYhy">These DTx apps represent a significant advancement in managing chronic conditions, offering scalable and accessible methods for delivering evidence-based interventions.</s><s xml:id="_uRJ2uux">They also address the challenges in implementing lifestyle modifications and behavioral therapies in traditional healthcare settings.</s><s xml:id="_wkddWKK">As DTx become more integrated into routine clinical practice, ongoing research is crucial to evaluate their long-term efficacy, safety, and cost-effectiveness.</s><s xml:id="_vsudwSE">The success of these initial DTx apps in Japan paves the way for more comprehensive digital health solutions, potentially improving individual patient outcomes and contributing to larger-scale public health improvements in managing chronic conditions.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="793.701"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_xNp37ty">Introduction</head><p xml:id="_D9zBe5z"><s xml:id="_9QaSmn4">Digital therapeutics (DTx) represent a novel therapeutic approach leveraging software applications (apps) delivered through digital devices to treat medical conditions <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_QADq2Dv">Unlike conventional digital health solutions, DTx have rigorous clinical evidence demonstrating efficacy and safety, leading to regulatory approval as medical devices in various regulatory bodies <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_TSt4YdS">Its recognition has gradually expanded, particularly following the 2014 revision of Japan's Pharmaceutical Affairs Law to the Pharmaceuticals and Medical Devices Act, which classifies software programs as medical devices (also known as SaMD) even in the absence of physical components <ref type="bibr">[3]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_3vb2E93"><s xml:id="_PTpsmFJ">While smartphones currently dominate as the primary platform for DTx delivery, a growing trend exists toward treatment programs utilizing virtual reality through head-mounted displays.</s><s xml:id="_n8crpSE">DTx apps installed on digital devices for therapeutic purposes are often called "treatment apps" or "prescription digital therapeutics (PDT)," reflecting their prescription-like nature akin to traditional pharmacological interventions.</s><s xml:id="_VDgDtFp">A key advantage of DTx over conventional hospital or clinic-based care is that it provides seamless therapeutic interventions in patients' daily lives via mobile devices.</s><s xml:id="_eedSNeB">Recently, DTx have also been engaged in disease diagnosis and preventio n <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_xRUufWF"><s xml:id="_Q7tdKhZ">As of September 2024, three DTx apps for nicotine dependence, hypertension management, and insomnia have received regulatory approval.</s><s xml:id="_97eewFk">Of those, the apps for nicotine dependence and hypertension management have also obtained national health insurance coverage in Japan.</s><s xml:id="_uHHRBY3">This review provides a comprehensive overview of the three therapeutic apps, integrating the current evidence.</s></p><p xml:id="_ZRXX5GR"><s xml:id="_VRyqTfr">Digital therapeutics for nicotine dependence CureApp SC, the DTx system for smoking cessation, is designed to address psychological nicotine dependence in patients' daily lives between clinical visits during the standard 12-week, five-session smoking cessation program covered by Japanese health insurance <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[4]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_9bKUX8T">This system comprises three components: a patient smartphone app, an Internet of Things device [portable exhaled carbon monoxide (CO) checker] that synchronizes with the patient app via Bluetooth, and a Web-based physician app for information review and guideline reference (Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>) <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[5]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_jM4KBPE">The patient app provides personalized behavioral therapy and smoking cessation guidance content to reinforce treatment for psychological nicotine dependence.</s><s xml:id="_JTvqxXH">Patients can monitor their progress by measuring and recording daily exhaled CO levels using the portable checker, with results accessible through both patient and physician apps.</s></p><p xml:id="_HQ89s45"><s xml:id="_fJ4FwzF">A clinical trial evaluated the efficacy of this DTx system when added to the standard smoking cessation program <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[6]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_ajPKZKg">Nicotine-dependent patients were randomized to either the intervention group (n = 285), which used the app system in addition to standard care, or the control group (n = 287), which used a sham app alongside standard care.</s><s xml:id="_Q5p7HzQ">The primary outcome, continuous abstinence rate from weeks 9 to 24, was significantly higher in the intervention group than in the control group [63.9 % vs. 50.5 %; odds ratio (OR), 1.73; 95 % confidence interval (CI), 1.24-2.42;</s><s xml:id="_bnBx2rc">p = 0.001], with effects persisting through at least 52 weeks (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_QfAYYKb">Thus, the system significantly improved patients' continuous abstinence rates when added to their standard smoking cessation treatment.</s><s xml:id="_8ZWNEz5">On the basis of these findings, this smoking cessation support system became Asia's first DTx to receive regulatory approval and insurance reimbursement in Japan in 2020, thereby prescribed in Japanese clinical settings.</s><s xml:id="_CAgP5Q3">The Tobacco Control Medical-Dental Research Network in Japan has published guidelines for its appropriate use <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[7]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_j5Vgp2v"><s xml:id="_BPDksS5">In the field of nicotine dependence treatment, the utility of online standard smoking cessation programs using information and communication technology has been explored, predating the widespread adoption of telemedicine.</s><s xml:id="_AtunrsU">A 2019 noninferiority trial compared the success rates of continuous abstinence between patients who used the app system and received the second through five consultations of the standard smoking cessation program via telemedicine, and those who received all five consultations in person <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[8]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_VBWQ2Qy">The telemedicine group was noninferior to the in-person group in terms of 9-12-week continuous abstinence rates (telemedicine group, 81.0 %; in-person group, 78.9 %).</s><s xml:id="_YHj9gFz">Similar results were observed for the 9-24-week continuous abstinence rates.</s><s xml:id="_8d5nYVA">Therefore, telemedicine combined with treatment apps can potentially maintain therapeutic efficacy while improving patient convenience.</s></p><p xml:id="_7vwJxEV"><s xml:id="_BgGYydD">Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_pMZQTvs">Digital therapeutics system for nicotine dependence.</s><s xml:id="_YWpy2J3">The system includes a patient app downloaded and used on the patients' smartphone, a portable exhaled carbon monoxide checker that can be connected to the patient app via Bluetooth, and a Web-based physician app.</s><s xml:id="_m7nBxCV">Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. Pivotal trial results of the DTx system for nicotine dependence.</s><s xml:id="_hEddgCb">The intervention group using the DTx app system showed a significantly higher continuous abstinence rate than the control group for the primary outcome of continuous abstinence for 9-24 weeks.</s><s xml:id="_JQkRHe9">Furthermore, the therapeutic effect was maintained even at 52 weeks.</s><s xml:id="_zgJUvST">DTx, digital therapeutics.</s></p><p xml:id="_sjryEVr"><s xml:id="_THgq7yY">Beyond the medical setting, several smartphone app-assisted smoking cessation services exist.</s><s xml:id="_883Px7g">The ascure smoking cessation program is a 24-week fully online program that provides smoking cessation guidance by combining an app based on the patient app features of the aforementioned nicotine dependence treatment support system, support from nonphysician smoking cessation guidance assistants, and over-the-counter nicotine replacement therapy <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">10]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_7tPrvGA">Studies examining the effectiveness of this app-assisted online smoking cessation guidance program have shown continuous abstinence rates of 48.6 %-61 % at weeks 9-12 and 47.5 %-56.4 % at weeks 21-24 <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">10]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_EbxZbCF">Another service is the Linkage online smoking cessation program.</s><s xml:id="_EypPBZY">It is a 12month program consisting of 2 months of physician-led online consultations and 10 months of aftercare by support staff, using a dedicated app with telemedicine capabilities and prescription of smoking cessation aids.</s><s xml:id="_fQRtYWE">A retrospective observational study of this program reported continuous abstinence rates of 55.8 % at weeks 9-12 and 42.4 % at weeks 9-52 <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[11]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_FskCjnB">Both programs have also investigated the effectiveness of their online smoking cessation programs for users of heated tobacco products (HTPs), which are an emerging concern.</s><s xml:id="_mqQNJq8">Results indicated that participants who exclusively used HTPs before program enrollment had achieved significantly higher continuous abstinence rates than those who only used conventional cigarettes <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">11]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_8pnSvMH">Thus, such online smoking cessation programs may be valuable tools for smokers seeking to quit, not only for conventional cigarette users but also for HTP users.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_ZVrX4Kn">Digital therapeutics for hypertension</head><p xml:id="_X9KU5TC"><s xml:id="_gmPnAbP">In 2022, the DTx app for hypertension management, CureApp HT, received regulatory approval and insurance reimbursement in Japan.</s><s xml:id="_eCyfCPv">It is a novel therapeutic option that incorporates app usage in outpatient hypertension management.</s><s xml:id="_4ysmehj">This "novel" approach does not provide patients with extraordinary treatments via the app and is not a freely downloadable health app prescribed without follow-up.</s><s xml:id="_RjPtJM7">Rather, it is a physician-guided DTx that focuses on "lifestyle modifications," which are long emphasized as a crucial nonpharmacological intervention in hypertension treatmen t <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[12]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_6fzQkne">This app aims to maximize the antihypertensive effects of lifestyle modifications through daily app usage, home blood pressure measurements, and regular progress reviews with physicians during outpatient visits <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[13]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_mFVW2uc">This section provides an overview of the hypertension treatment support app and its implementation in clinical practice, along with scientific evidence.</s></p><p xml:id="_V8hnqks"><s xml:id="_ypUZUd9">Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref> illustrates the overview of CureApp HT.</s><s xml:id="_kTdp79C">This therapeutic app provides comprehensive and continuous support for hypertension treatment by promoting lifestyle modifications not only during outpatient visits but also in patients' daily lives between clinic visits <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[13]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_zUaZqeT">Its primary objective is to maximize the antihypertensive performance of lifestyle modifications, which are recommended for all patients with hypertension according to hypertension treatment guidelines <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">15]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_S4UgnJw">This objective is achieved by providing patients with knowledge about their hypertension and its complications, encouraging the practice of lifestyle modifications (nonpharmacological treatment) related to blood pressure reduction, and monitoring daily blood pressure values using home blood pressure monitors.</s><s xml:id="_YCNDw8a">Lifestyle modifications consist of the following six components that have shown certain antihypertensive effects in clinical studies: 1) dietary therapy including salt reduction, 2) weight loss, 3) regular exercise, 4) alcohol consumption moderation, 5) quality sleep, and 6) stress management <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[13]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_DgZNPw3">The specific program content provided by the patient app during the 6-month insurance coverage period is as follows: First, knowledge and practical methods regarding hypertension and the aforementioned six lifestyle modification items are provided to the app user (Step 1: input and education stage).</s><s xml:id="_EGtzSsm">Next, lifestyle modifications are implemented with app support according to the knowledge gained in Step 1 (Step 2: app-supported interventions stage).</s><s xml:id="_AdV9Mtu">Finally, patients set their own goals for lifestyle modifications, aiming to truly habituate the modified lifestyle and behavioral patterns through voluntary and continuous practice (Step 3: self-planning and evaluation stag e) <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">16]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_HkwHmkR">Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>. Overview of the DTx app for hypertension management.</s><s xml:id="_KyKUDez">This DTx app aims to address the treatment gap between outpatient clinic visits for hypertension management.</s><s xml:id="_2HqHarz">This app promotes awareness of hypertension and its complications through connection with home blood pressure monitoring.</s><s xml:id="_C2J92mV">With the goal of efficiently supporting lifestyle modification, which is recommended for all patients with hypertension in the guidelines, this DTx app can potentially maximize the effect of this nonpharmacological treatment in 6 months.</s><s xml:id="_uM9Yrfr">Furthermore, healthcare providers can access the gathered information via a Web application and provide medical advice to patients during their regular clinic visits according to the data collected.</s><s xml:id="_kBm3Q6n">DTx, digital therapeutics.</s></p><p xml:id="_UUYEGRG"><s xml:id="_amuph5k">While the patient app incorporates various programs designed to maximize the lifestyle modification effects, including the elements of cognitive behavioral therapy, the foundation is daily home blood pressure monitoring <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">17]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_NPMZqXf">Patients measure their home blood pressure daily and then input the values into the app or automatically transfer them via Bluetooth, allowing them to monitor their home blood pressure trends.</s><s xml:id="_9676Qdv">Additionally, recording daily reflections in an electronic diary (digital diary) is actively promoted to improve daily app usage rates.</s><s xml:id="_cCfvR4v">Data from the patient app are clearly visualized for easy use by primary care physicians during outpatient consultations.</s><s xml:id="_rhp8TRV">Then, changes in blood pressure values, measurement rates, diary content, and program progress are summarized in a single sheet for printing and explanation.</s><s xml:id="_AVEdPCx">During the first post-prescription consultation (after 1 month), physicians review the home blood pressure measurement rates and app program progress.</s><s xml:id="_7DYHyP5">Ideally, at 1 month, the patient should be able to complete all 14 knowledge acquisition content items in Step 1, the first step toward lifestyle modifications, and transition to Step 2. However, if the home blood pressure measurement rate falls below the insurance calculation criterion of 71.4 % (measuring blood pressure on at least 5 out of 7 days on average) or if little progress has been made in Step 1 content, the physician needs to thoroughly discuss the reasons with the patient.</s><s xml:id="_AGpvDTr">Specifically, they need to re-explain the necessity and expected effects of this app in hypertension treatment, provide guidance on its use, and agree with the patient on continued app usage.</s><s xml:id="_ybmFQU7">Ideally, by the third month, the program should progress to the middle of Step 3, and patients should continue using the app until the sixth month (the insurance calculation limit) wherein they can already practice and habituate lifestyle modifications daily even without app support.</s><s xml:id="_Gg52wRh">As of September 2024, once the 6-month insurance calculation period for this app expires, the use of the hypertension DTx app (patient app) is terminated.</s><s xml:id="_WJ32Ae8">Subsequently, users can access the Smart Blood Pressure Record app, a personal health record (PHR) app focused on home blood pressure measurements; this app is available only to those who have used CureApp HT (without insurance coverage and free of charge) <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[18]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_Zb3c73n">While this app requires a new download, users can continue with the same account used for CureApp HT.</s><s xml:id="_yfWpJn8">The PHR app retains the previous 6 months of blood pressure records.</s><s xml:id="_gMmDran">Moreover, given that blood pressure records can be viewed in the physician app under the same patient account, the PHR app is useful for sharing home blood pressure data between physicians and patients in routine clinical practice, making it ideal for long-term electronic blood pressure diary use after CureApp HT.</s></p><p xml:id="_xkDnG8C"><s xml:id="_3c4FggP">Clinical evidence regarding the DTx app for hypertension management has been reported.</s><s xml:id="_TyXQR9T">For instance, the HERB-DH1 validation trial examined the antihypertensive effect of this app in patients with hypertension <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[16]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_8ssxY99">A total of 390 patients with essential hypertension aged 65 years or younger who were not taking antihypertensive medications were randomized into two groups: the therapeutic app intervention group and the control group.</s><s xml:id="_TxVG6u4">The former used the hypertension treatment support app in addition to lifestyle modification guidance based on the 2019 Guidelines for the Management of Hypertension issued by the Japanese Society of Hypertension, whereas the latter received only guideline-based lifestyle modification guidance in outpatient settings.</s><s xml:id="_t3a96Zx">The primary endpoint that is, the between-group difference in 24-h systolic blood pressure measured by ambulatory blood pressure monitoring at 12 weeks, was -2.4 mmHg (95 % confidence interval, -4.5 to -0.3; p = 0.024), showing a significantly greater blood pressure reduction in the therapeutic app intervention group than in the control group.</s><s xml:id="_rjYsXpj">Similarly, for morning home blood pressure, the between-group difference was -4.3 mmHg (p &lt; 0.001), again demonstrating a significantly greater blood pressure reduction in the therapeutic app intervention group, with this antihypertensive effect persisting for at least 24 weeks (Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_AX6us42">These results validate the antihypertensive effect of the hypertension treatment support app when added to guidelinebased lifestyle modification guidance in patients with essential hypertension not taking antihypertensive medications.</s><s xml:id="_pe4uJnW">Furthermore, studies identifying the effective components of the DTx app revealed key factors associated with systolic blood pressure reduction: decreased salt intake, weight loss, and increased frequency of self-reported behavioral efficacy records <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">20]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_a7WAcAY">Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>. HERB-DH1 pivotal trial results of the DTx app for hypertension management.</s><s xml:id="_5tanSc9">The primary endpoint that is, the mean change in 24-h systolic blood pressure (SBP) from baseline to week 12, was significantly greater in the DTx intervention group than in the control group.</s><s xml:id="_3n994ez">Regarding key secondary endpoints, the DTx intervention group clearly showed significantly greater reduction from baseline in morning home and office SBPs than the control group.</s><s xml:id="_qd67nVB">DTx, digital therapeutics.</s></p><p xml:id="_6MHVB2p"><s xml:id="_eQ6GM9X">Additionally, a study evaluated the long-term health economic effects of this app according to the clinical data from the abovementioned validation trial <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[21]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_u9Y33HG">Under the model used in this study, the lifetime difference in medical costs between the therapeutic app intervention group and the control group was 110,717 yen (higher in the therapeutic app intervention group), whereas the difference in quality-adjusted life years (QALYs) was 0.092 (longer in the therapeutic app intervention group).</s><s xml:id="_Q3zj2sg">The incremental cost-effectiveness ratio (ICER) was 1,199,880 yen/QALY.</s><s xml:id="_r75VBpF">This ICER value is below the 5,000,000 yen/QALY threshold often used in Japan as a standard for "willingness-to-pay for one QALY gain."</s><s xml:id="_RUUrQdQ">Therefore, according to this criterion, using this app may be cost-effective over a lifetime .</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_7Zsy9ER">Digital therapeutics for insomnia</head><p xml:id="_TGKHkCU"><s xml:id="_bZ8ghGG">The SUSMED MedCBT-i app is a medical software developed to support physician-delivered cognitive behavioral therapy for insomnia (CBT-I) in treating insomnia disorder <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[22]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_qr5rT8w">This approach, known as Digital CBT-I, is a treatment program based on face-to-face CBT-I, focusing on three core elements: behavioral, cognitive, and educational components.</s><s xml:id="_bB2yYUK">The content primarily includes sleep hygiene guidance, sleep logs (sleep diaries), sleep restriction therapy, stimulus control therapy, and cognitive therapy <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[23]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_WkCRFPp">In practice, patients use the app to implement sleep hygiene guidance and input sleep logs during the first week, followed by an 8-week Digital CBT-I program.</s><s xml:id="_xDdZ5z4">Throughout this period, target bedtimes and wake times are set while concurrently evaluating insomnia status using the Athens Insomnia Scale (AIS) <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">25]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_9b5ZWSC"><s xml:id="_2HbhHdc">A randomized controlled trial examined the clinical efficacy of this insomnia treatment app <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[22]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_6NXKUAU">In this validation study, 175 patients aged 20 years or older diagnosed with insomnia disorder were randomized into two groups: an app treatment group (underwent Digital CBT-I via the insomnia treatment app; n = 87) and a control group (used a sham app without CBT-I functionality; n = 88).</s><s xml:id="_8TcpF8d">The primary endpoint that is, the between-group difference in AIS change from baseline at 8 weeks after initiating Digital CBT-I, was -3.4 (95 % CI, -4.7 to -2.2; p &lt; 0.001), showing a significantly greater improvement in AIS in the app treatment group than in the control group.</s><s xml:id="_EqRPZE6">Consequently, this insomnia treatment app received regulatory approval in Japan in February 2023.</s><s xml:id="_CKkVxsM">Currently, procedures are underway to seek insurance coverage for the app.</s><s xml:id="_aprMDKW">This DTx approach to insomnia represents a significant advancement in the field of sleep medicine, offering a scalable and accessible method for delivering evidence-based CBT-I <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[23]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_eTTC5tZ">The positive results from the clinical trial suggest that such digital interventions are important in addressing the growing prevalence of insomnia, particularly in settings where access to face-to-face CBT-I is limited.</s><s xml:id="_qkC9sTY">As with other DTx apps, ongoing research is crucial to further establish its long-term efficacy, optimal integration into clinical practice, and potential costeffectiveness in various healthcare systems.</s></p><p xml:id="_tMvCG8B"><s xml:id="_hxMmGjJ">Conclusions and future perspective This paper presents an overview of DTx used for managing nicotine dependence treatment, hypertension management, and insomnia therapy that have been approved in Japan.</s><s xml:id="_dHxNNJg">I have outlined their implementation procedures and tips for clinical practice, along with scientific evidence and cost-effectiveness analysis results.</s><s xml:id="_nf3sk8E">Lifestyle modification has long been recognized as crucial in managing conditions such as hypertension.</s><s xml:id="_EnXpDGR">However, its effective implementation has been hindered by time constraints in outpatient settings, difficulties in providing personalized guidance tailored to patients' lifestyles, challenges in monitoring adherence, and the need for active engagement from patients and healthcare providers.</s><s xml:id="_TpQ2988">By introducing DTx delivered through mobile devices in healthcare, these aspects of treatment can be efficiently supported.</s><s xml:id="_Ywyaqd3">Given that these digital tools assist both patients and healthcare providers in managing hypertension and other conditions, many of the traditional barriers to lifestyle modification have been overcome.</s></p><p xml:id="_Mnjc4Vh"><s xml:id="_7RAPB7Y">The success of these initial DTx apps in Japan paves the way for more comprehensive and sophisticated digital health solutions.</s><s xml:id="_3h3eKfx">As technology advances and our understanding of these apps in healthcare deepens, more targeted, personalized, and effective digital interventions may be developed.</s><s xml:id="_Js4F8kG">These developments may not only improve individual patient outcomes but also contribute to larger-scale improvements in public health, particularly in the management of chronic conditions such as nicotine dependence and hypertension.</s><s xml:id="_bCfJy3r">However, successful implementation of DTx apps requires careful consideration of regional factors, including dietary and physical activity patterns, cultural norms, socioeconomic disparities, religious practices, smartphone adoption rate, and region-specific regulatory and reimbursement frameworks.</s><s xml:id="_kvyy9zS">One notable example is the expansion strategy of the hypertension management DTx, which is currently being adapted for the US healthcare environment through the development of "Komorebi", a culturally optimized app designed to improve blood pressure control on a global scale <ref type="bibr">[26]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_yszmAc6"><s xml:id="_GyBqVEf">As we move forward, we anticipate continued development and expansion of DTx in the management of cardiac and related diseases.</s><s xml:id="_GwYspQM">In Japan alone, &gt;30 DTx apps are currently under development, with target indications expanding beyond cardiometabolic diseases to include neuropsychological, gastrointestinal, and oncological conditions <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_Vz5x2CV">These innovative approaches hold great promise for enhancing patient care, improving treatment outcomes, and potentially reducing healthcare system burdens.</s><s xml:id="_c47REgT">Future research and clinical application of DTx in cardiology and related fields will likely focus on refining existing tools, developing new apps for other conditions, and further integrating these technologies into standard care practices.</s></p><p xml:id="_SuuZrdk"><s xml:id="_JqpK3dJ">In conclusion, while DTx represent a significant step forward in patient care, rigorous evaluation of their long-term efficacy, safety, and cost-effectiveness should be continued.</s><s xml:id="_J9xUkpj">As these technologies become more integrated into routine clinical practice, ongoing research and real-world evidence is crucial in optimizing their use and ensuring that they meet the evolving needs of both patients and healthcare providers in the field of cardiovascular medicine.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_w396rVa">Disclosures</head><p xml:id="_tvkgDEs"><s xml:id="_FxCDmaQ">Akihiro Nomura received honoraria and joint research grant from CureApp, Inc.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="2,126.20,505.76,342.82,211.75" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="2,317.27,53.27,228.15,239.55" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="3,112.03,464.94,371.17,226.89" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="4,97.85,474.24,399.52,226.15" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head xml:id="_JubakRT">Acknowledgments</head><p xml:id="_9y9kpnv"><s xml:id="_bQhdBVG">I would like to express my gratitude to all colleagues involved in the research and development of DTx.</s><s xml:id="_bqg7pv7">I also send cheers to everyone who continues to dedicate their efforts to the advancement and promotion of DTx, whose contributions are invaluable to the progress of this emerging field in healthcare.</s><s xml:id="_aCbJVYk">English language editing was supported by the <rs type="funder">Enago's English Editing</rs> service.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Cy75rzc">Funding</head><p xml:id="_PPWmWfj"><s xml:id="_mmUQQn7">None.</s></p></div>
			</div>


			<listOrg type="funding">
			</listOrg>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_QURVNMF">Data availability</head><p xml:id="_pK2EgfW"><s xml:id="_Sgnzmbu">Data availability is not applicable as no new data were analyzed in this review article.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_tZP7HBG">Author contributions</head><p xml:id="_X8jqaux"><s xml:id="_QytPW9x">A.N. conceptualized, researched, wrote, and edited all content in this review article.</s><s xml:id="_EzYZcxc">A.N. is responsible for the integrity of the work as a whole.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_C8VsJ4J">Declaration of generative AI and AI-assisted technologies in the writing process</head><p xml:id="_haSrEs5"><s xml:id="_yFcgg4H">During the preparation of this manuscript, the author used Claude 3.5 Sonnet (text generation AI) for supporting English language editing.</s><s xml:id="_ryfmXRH">After using this tool, the author reviewed and edited generated contents as needed and takes full responsibility for the contents of the publication.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<idno type="DOI">10.17816/eid677915-4363932</idno>
		<ptr target="https://dtxalliance.org/)" />
		<title level="m" xml:id="_JG3Wb9f">Industry overview</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Digital Therapeutics Alliance</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Digital Therapeutics Alliance. Industry overview. (URL from: https://dtxalliance.org/).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_yabgwTq">Digital health, digital medicine, and digital therapeutics in cardiology: current evidence and future perspective in Japan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nomura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41440-023-01317-8</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_egSVjxA">Hypertens Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2126" to="2134" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nomura A. Digital health, digital medicine, and digital therapeutics in cardiology: current evidence and future perspective in Japan. Hypertens Res 2023;46:2126-34.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1253/circj.cj-66-0062</idno>
		<ptr target="http://j-circ.or.jp/kinen/anti_smoke_std/pdf/anti_smoke_std_rev8_.pdf" />
		<title level="m" xml:id="_cbGkpGB">The standard procedure manual for smoking cessation</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>The Japanese Respiratory Society</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>8th edition</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">The Japanese Circulation Society, The Japan Lung Cancer Society, The Japanese Cancer Society, The Japanese Respiratory Society. The standard procedure manual for smoking cessation, 8th edition. 2021. (URL from: http://j-circ.or.jp/kinen/anti_ smoke_std/pdf/anti_smoke_std_rev8_.pdf).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_n6Me4tB">A novel smoking cessation smartphone app integrated with a mobile carbon monoxide checker for smoking cessation treatment: protocol for a randomized controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nomura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Tateno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Masaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Muto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Suzuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Satake</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/12252</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_tNheDGK">JMIR Res Protoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e12252</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nomura A, Tateno H, Masaki K, Muto T, Suzuki S, Satake K, et al. A novel smoking cessation smartphone app integrated with a mobile carbon monoxide checker for smoking cessation treatment: protocol for a randomized controlled trial. JMIR Res Protoc 2019;8:e12252.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_rpZQrWW">A randomized controlled trial of a smoking cessation smartphone application with a carbon monoxide checker</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Masaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Tateno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nomura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Muto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Suzuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Satake</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41746-020-0243-5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_bfRqZEk">NPJ Digit Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">35</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Masaki K, Tateno H, Nomura A, Muto T, Suzuki S, Satake K, et al. A randomized con- trolled trial of a smoking cessation smartphone application with a carbon monoxide checker. NPJ Digit Med 2020;3:35.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/tc.5.1.1</idno>
		<ptr target="https://tobacco-control-research-net.jp/media/20220628-154855-558.pdf" />
		<title level="m" xml:id="_GDgketz">Guidelines for the appropriate use of the digital therapeutics for nicotine dependence (CureApp-SCⓇ)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Tobacco Control Medical-Dental Research Network</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Tobacco Control Medical-Dental Research Network. Guidelines for the appropriate use of the digital therapeutics for nicotine dependence (CureApp-SCⓇ). 2021. (URL from: https://tobacco-control-research-net.jp/media/20220628-154855-558.pdf).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Aq2AVrM">Clinical efficacy of telemedicine compared to face-to-face clinic visits for smoking cessation: multicenter open-label randomized controlled noninferiority trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nomura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Tanigawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Muto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Oga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Fukushima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kiyosue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/13520</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_48EY8Pc">J Med Internet Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">13520</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nomura A, Tanigawa T, Muto T, Oga T, Fukushima Y, Kiyosue A, et al. Clinical efficacy of telemedicine compared to face-to-face clinic visits for smoking cessation: multi- center open-label randomized controlled noninferiority trial. J Med Internet Res 2019;21:e13520.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_tnQdZJk">Efficacy of the ascure smoking cessation program: retrospective study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Tanigawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Satake</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nomura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/17270</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_pCS9MKV">JMIR Mhealth Uhealth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e17270</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kato A, Tanigawa T, Satake K, Nomura A. Efficacy of the ascure smoking cessation program: retrospective study. JMIR Mhealth Uhealth 2020;8:e17270.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_hr8ayv6">The usefulness of a smartphone appbased smoking cessation program for conventional cigarette users, heated tobacco product users, and dual users: retrospective study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Noda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>So</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sonoda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Tabuchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nomura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/42776</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_rzky2ep">J Med Internet Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">42776</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Noda Y, So R, Sonoda M, Tabuchi T, Nomura A. The usefulness of a smartphone app- based smoking cessation program for conventional cigarette users, heated tobacco product users, and dual users: retrospective study. J Med Internet Res 2023;25:e42776.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_6RAMYfd">Outcomes of a telemedicine smoking cessation programme for heated tobacco product users in Japan: a retrospective cohort study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nomura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ikeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Fujimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Morita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Taniguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ishizawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmjopen-2022-063489</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_2yYjD69">BMJ Open</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">63489</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nomura A, Ikeda T, Fujimoto T, Morita Y, Taniguchi C, Ishizawa T, et al. Outcomes of a telemedicine smoking cessation programme for heated tobacco product users in Japan: a retrospective cohort study. BMJ Open 2022;12:e063489.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_eY6z5Z6">The Japanese Society of Hypertension guidelines for the management of hypertension (JSH 2019)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Umemura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Arima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Arima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Asayama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Dohi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hirooka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41440-019-0284-9</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_7tF7Dja">Hypertens Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1235" to="1481" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Umemura S, Arima H, Arima S, Asayama K, Dohi Y, Hirooka Y, et al. The Japanese Society of Hypertension guidelines for the management of hypertension (JSH 2019). Hypertens Res 2019;42:1235-481.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_UdP3xVG">A multicenter clinical trial to assess the efficacy of the digital therapeutics for essential hypertension: rationale and design of the HERB-DH1 trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kario</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nomura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Harada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Tanigawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>So</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Nakagawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/jch.13993</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Pm4Fshe">J Clin Hypertens</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1713" to="1722" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<pubPlace>Greenwich</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kario K, Nomura A, Harada N, Tanigawa T, So R, Nakagawa K, et al. A multicenter clinical trial to assess the efficacy of the digital therapeutics for essential hypertension: rationale and design of the HERB-DH1 trial. J Clin Hypertens (Greenwich) 2020;22: 1713-22.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_3pZVxMu">International Society of Hypertension global hypertension practice guidelines</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Unger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Borghi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Charchar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Poulter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Prabhakaran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1161/hypertensionaha.120.15026</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_kNMfsSa">Hypertension</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1334" to="1357" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020. 2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Unger T, Borghi C, Charchar F, Khan NA, Poulter NR, Prabhakaran D, et al. 2020 International Society of Hypertension global hypertension practice guidelines. Hypertension 2020;75:1334-57.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_VnWm5GU">ESH guidelines for the management of arterial hypertension the task force for the management of arterial hypertension of the European Society of Hypertension: endorsed by the International Society of Hypertension (ISH) and the European renal association (ERA)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mancia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kreutz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Brunstrom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Burnier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Grassi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Januszewicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/hjh.0000000000003621</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_KEY4Tp6">J Hypertens</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1874" to="2071" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023. 2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mancia G, Kreutz R, Brunstrom M, Burnier M, Grassi G, Januszewicz A, et al. 2023 ESH guidelines for the management of arterial hypertension the task force for the management of arterial hypertension of the European Society of Hypertension: endorsed by the International Society of Hypertension (ISH) and the European renal association (ERA). J Hypertens 2023;41:1874-2071.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_z4BSZmB">Efficacy of a digital therapeutics system in the management of essential hypertension: the HERB-DH1 pivotal trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kario</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nomura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Harada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Okura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Nakagawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Tanigawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/eurheartj/ehab559</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_mQqm3GF">Eur Heart J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4111" to="4122" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kario K, Nomura A, Harada N, Okura A, Nakagawa K, Tanigawa T, et al. Efficacy of a digital therapeutics system in the management of essential hypertension: the HERB- DH1 pivotal trial. Eur Heart J 2021;42:4111-22.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_m2A4Xbr">ESC guidelines for the management of elevated blood pressure and hypertension</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Mcevoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mccarthy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bruno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Brouwers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Canavan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ceconi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_2qQKMYx">Eur Heart J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3912" to="4018" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024. 2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">McEvoy JW, McCarthy CP, Bruno RM, Brouwers S, Canavan MD, Ceconi C, et al. 2024 ESC guidelines for the management of elevated blood pressure and hypertension. Eur Heart J 2024;45:3912-4018.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_gNAuGtv">%BC%E3%83%88%E8%A1%80%E5%9C%A7%E8%A8%98%E9% 8C%B2%E3%81%AE%E3%81%AF%E3%81%98%E3%82%81%E6%96%B9)</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.29073/e3.v10i2.947</idno>
		<ptr target="https://help.ht.cureapp.com/hc/ja/articles/22986971545881-CureApp-%E3%82%B9%E3%83%9E%E3%83" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_AZJCacX">How to start the CureApp Smart Blood Pressure Record app</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>CureApp Inc</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">CureApp Inc. How to start the CureApp Smart Blood Pressure Record app. (URL from: https://help.ht.cureapp.com/hc/ja/articles/22986971545881-CureApp-%E3% 82%B9%E3%83%9E%E3%83%BC%E3%83%88%E8%A1%80%E5%9C%A7%E8%A8%98%E9% 8C%B2%E3%81%AE%E3%81%AF%E3%81%98%E3%82%81%E6%96%B9).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_huBDpRv">Home blood pressure-lowering effect of digital therapeutics in hypertension: impact of body weight and salt intake</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kario</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Tomitani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Harada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Okura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Hisaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Tanigawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41440-023-01245-7</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_HUpQPDa">Hypertens Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1181" to="1187" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kario K, Tomitani N, Harada N, Okura A, Hisaki F, Tanigawa T, et al. Home blood pressure-lowering effect of digital therapeutics in hypertension: impact of body weight and salt intake. Hypertens Res 2023;46:1181-7.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Mmyjdkv">Daily self-reported behavioural efficacy records on hypertension digital therapeutics as digital metrics associated with the reduction in morning home blood pressure: post-hoc analysis of HERB-DH1 trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Hisaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Aga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Tomitani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Okawara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Harada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kario</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41440-023-01434-4</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Va8CQ7T">Hypertens Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="120" to="127" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hisaki F, Aga M, Tomitani N, Okawara Y, Harada N, Kario K. Daily self-reported behavioural efficacy records on hypertension digital therapeutics as digital metrics associated with the reduction in morning home blood pressure: post-hoc analysis of HERB-DH1 trial. Hypertens Res 2024;47:120-7.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_nEGatgm">Cost-effectiveness of digital therapeutics for essential hypertension</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nomura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Tanigawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kario</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Igarashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41440-022-00952-x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_jTH3k5e">Hypertens Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1538" to="1548" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nomura A, Tanigawa T, Kario K, Igarashi A. Cost-effectiveness of digital therapeutics for essential hypertension. Hypertens Res 2022;45:1538-48.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_V5XmEJA">Effect of smartphone-based cognitive behavioral therapy app on insomnia: a randomized, double-blind study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Watanabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kuroki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ichikawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ozone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Uchimura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ueno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/sleep/zsac270</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_e6bVfas">Sleep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">270</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Watanabe Y, Kuroki T, Ichikawa D, Ozone M, Uchimura N, Ueno T. Effect of smartphone-based cognitive behavioral therapy app on insomnia: a randomized, double-blind study. Sleep 2023;46:zsac270.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_pzKzDNJ">Clinical guidelines Committee of the American College of physicians. Management of chronic insomnia disorder in adults: a clinical practice guideline from the American College of Physicians</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Qaseem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kansagara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Forciea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cooke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Denberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.7326/m15-2175</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_EQszFUy">Ann Intern Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">165</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="133" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Qaseem A, Kansagara D, Forciea MA, Cooke M, Denberg TD. Clinical guidelines Committee of the American College of physicians. Management of chronic insomnia disorder in adults: a clinical practice guideline from the American College of Physicians. Ann Intern Med 2016;165:125-33.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_RGdkQCG">Recommendations for a standard research assessment of insomnia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Buysse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ancoli-Israel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Edinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lichstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Morin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/sleep/29.9.1155</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_jEenBAQ">Sleep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1155" to="1173" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Buysse DJ, Ancoli-Israel S, Edinger JD, Lichstein KL, Morin CM. Recommendations for a standard research assessment of insomnia. Sleep 2006;29:1155-73.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_HCneChr">Guidelines for the appropriate use of the digital therapeutics for insomnia (SUSMED MedCBT-i)</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/jsr.14084</idno>
		<ptr target="https://jssr.jp/files/guideline/20240315.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>The Japanese Society of Sleep Research</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">The Japanese Society of Sleep Research. Guidelines for the appropriate use of the digital therapeutics for insomnia (SUSMED MedCBT-i). 2024. (URL from: https:// jssr.jp/files/guideline/20240315.pdf).</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
