<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_hBmxZHv">What is User Engagement? A Conceptual Framework for Defining User Engagement with Technology</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>1</label> Centre for Management Informatics , Dalhousie University , 6100 University Avenue , Halifax , Nova Scotia , Canada B3H 3J5 .</note>
								<orgName type="department">Centre for Management Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Dalhousie University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>6100 University Avenue</addrLine>
									<postCode>B3H 3J5</postCode>
									<settlement>Halifax</settlement>
									<region>Nova Scotia</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ZNGtCRJ">What is User Engagement? A Conceptual Framework for Defining User Engagement with Technology</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">36ADE1BFEED674F070F7A500AAFBDACF</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1002/asi.20801</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T11:03+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_ys6kGcJ"><p xml:id="_PYszaTR"><s xml:id="_xCH3gJX">The purpose of this article is to critically deconstruct the term engagement as it applies to peoples' experiences with technology.</s><s xml:id="_GBBgT5q">Through an extensive, critical multidisciplinary literature review and exploratory study of users of Web searching, online shopping, Webcasting, and gaming applications, we conceptually and operationally defined engagement.</s><s xml:id="_3YM3MBK">Building on past research, we conducted semistructured interviews with the users of four applications to explore their perception of being engaged with the technology.</s><s xml:id="_2a69Wsw">Results indicate that engagement is a process comprised of four distinct stages: point of engagement, period of sustained engagement, disengagement, and reengagement.</s><s xml:id="_7bTrVkt">Furthermore, the process is characterized by attributes of engagement that pertain to the user, the system, and user-system interaction.</s><s xml:id="_BHDDH38">We also found evidence of the factors that contribute to nonengagement.</s><s xml:id="_W2m7M9U">Emerging from this research is a definition of engagement a term not defined consistently in past work as a quality of user experience characterized by attributes of challenge, positive affect, endurability, aesthetic and sensory appeal, attention, feedback, variety/novelty, interactivity, and perceived user control.</s><s xml:id="_g9ZcVGt">This exploratory work provides the foundation for future work to test the conceptual model in various application areas, and to develop methods to measure engaging user experiences.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="10" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="11" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="12" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="13" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="14" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="15" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="16" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="17" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="18" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="19" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="20" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="21" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="22" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="23" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="24" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="25" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="26" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="27" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="28" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="29" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="30" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="31" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="32" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="33" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="34" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="35" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="36" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="37" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="38" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_9YgDQCd">INTRODUCTION</head><p xml:id="_ynBmTDG"><s xml:id="_zY4G7De">In the past few decades, human-computer interaction studies have emphasized the need to move beyond usability to understand and design for more engaging experiences <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Hassenzahl &amp; Tractinsky, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Jacques, Preece, &amp; Carey, 1995;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Laurel, 1993)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_YEr4QdR">A Web interface that is boring, a multimedia presentation that does not captivate users' attention, or an online forum that fails to engender a sense of community are quickly dismissed with a simple mouse click.</s><s xml:id="_Mc3bcQd">Failing to engage users equates with no sale on an electronic commerce site and no transmission of information from a Web site; people go elsewhere to perform their tasks and communicate with colleagues and friends.</s><s xml:id="_mP7cqqz">Successful technologies are not just usable; they engage users.</s><s xml:id="_hdfRKPn">Despite the need to engage users and create engaging technologies, there is no agreed upon definition of the construct.</s><s xml:id="_gE8z7J3"><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Chapman (1997)</ref> stated emphasizes playfulness and sensory integration in engagement, which she also refers - <ref type="bibr">(2003)</ref> proposed that engagement is a dimension of usability, and is influenced by users' first impression of an application and the enjoyment they derive from using it.</s><s xml:id="_vMtv8xr">Multiple studies of engagement have described it according to different characteristics, such as media presentation, perceived user control, choice, challenge, feedback, and variety <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Jacques et al., 1995;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Said, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b63">Webster &amp; Ho, 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Chapman, 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Chapman, Selvarajah, &amp; Webster, 1999)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_zt9XZ7W">Cumulatively, these attributes demonstrate the physical, cognitive, and affective components of user experiences.</s></p><p xml:id="_E8U2EZS"><s xml:id="_dmeq6Em">The objective of this study is to develop an operational definition of engagement and to identify the key components that make up engagement.</s><s xml:id="_k3Rdqr3">To do so, we first reviewed and analyzed previous research on engagement, including its use in various application areas and its relationship to other established theories of human-computer interaction.</s><s xml:id="_4As4guz">Next we conducted an exploratory study of first-person accounts of engagement with four computer applications: online shopping, Web searching, Webcasting, and video games.</s><s xml:id="_B5dquem">We conclude with a model of user engagement.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_znFY9Th">LITERATURE REVIEW</head><p xml:id="_3gGPSSY"><s xml:id="_aYmD8aH">even essential human response to computer-</s></p><p xml:id="_fKanfrW"><s xml:id="_23w3GaR">).</s><s xml:id="_CTFqDGn">For learning to take place, multimedia presentations should engage their audiences <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">(Webster &amp; Ho, 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Jacques et al., 1995)</ref> and educators should critically engage students with technology in the applications.</s><s xml:id="_g8eXKP5">The fervor of discussion about engagement suggests that engaging interactions are sought after by both users and developers of computer systems and applications.</s><s xml:id="_7b9WhqN">Just as we have worked to identify users' perceptions, actions, and attitudes about how to make a system functional and intuitive to use, we must concentrate on understanding how to make systems more engaging.</s><s xml:id="_yY2dvYm">Given the increased emphasis on user experience, it is no longer sufficient to ensure that a system is merely usable <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Blythe, Overbeeke, Monk, &amp; Wright, 2003)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_QFK6tjv">Theoretical Underpinnings</head><p xml:id="_tSbMxuM"><s xml:id="_KmuUVgn">Prior research has suggested that engagement consists of users' activities, attitudes, <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Kappelman, 1995)</ref>, goals and mental models, and motor skills <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Said, 2004)</ref>, and that it manifests itself in the form of attention, intrinsic interest, curiosity, and motivation <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Chapman, 1997)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_m5kg7SH"><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Jacques et al. (1995)</ref> looked at a limited number of cognitive and affective variables in relation to the format and display of a specific multimedia system.</s><s xml:id="_p4UnN6x">Said's approach was based on children's interactions with video games, and Chapman's research examined university students' reactions to presentation software.</s><s xml:id="_fu8dfq5">Thus existing frameworks are based on research conducted in specific domains and with particular user groups and applications, with little or no attempt to generalize beyond the individual work and without theoretical foundations to support that work.</s><s xml:id="_3329M3U">The exception to this is Chapman and colleagues <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Chapman, 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Chapman et al., 1999)</ref> who related engagement to flow theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Csikszentmihalyi, 1990)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_nByyYVa">In addition to flow theory, other theories emerged from our analysis of previous research of user experiences in humancomputer interaction: aesthetic theory <ref type="bibr">(Beardsley, 1982)</ref> play theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">(Stephenson, 1967)</ref>, and information interaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">(Toms, 2002)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_BSXCATq">We examine all of these theories flow, play, aesthetics, and information interaction to inform our understanding of user experiences.</s><s xml:id="_UrgCvyT">seems to matter; the experience itself is so enjoyable that people will do it even at great <ref type="bibr">mihalyi, 1990, p. 4)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_Ru8RF64">Flow theory has been used to explore situational and personality variables associated with computer-based tasks <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">(Woszczynski, Roth, &amp; Segars, 2002)</ref>, to predict and design for flow experiences <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Finneran &amp; Zhang, 2003)</ref>, and to understand users' reactions to and motivations for using applications <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Ghani &amp; Deshpande, 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Konradt &amp; Sulz, 2001)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_mC9wECH">Engagement has that engagement may share some attributes with flow, such as focused attention, feedback, control, activity orientation (i.e., interactivity), and intrinsic motivation <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Csikszentmihalyi, 1990)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_cGCcdN8">Previous studies indicate that engagement consists of system feedback, user control <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Brown &amp; Cairns, 2004)</ref>, attention, motivation <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Chapman, 1997)</ref>, and the ability of the system to challenge individuals at levels appropriate to their knowledge and skills <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Skelly, Fries, Linnett, Nass, &amp; Reeves, 1994)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_mZZeZrq">Despite the common threads between engagement and flow, we propose that there are differences.</s><s xml:id="_byySHuM">Specifically, flow involves intrinsic motivation, yet engaging experiences may come about as well during the nonvoluntary use of a system.</s><s xml:id="_gSqXzn6">Further, flow requires sustained, long-term focus and loss of awareness of the outside world; engagement should still occur in the midst of today's multitasking and dynamic computer environments.</s><s xml:id="_y4h5dGH"><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Jennings (2000)</ref> suggested that aesthetic experiences are intrinsically motivating, require focused attention, stimulate curiosity, and are interesting and pleasurable.</s><s xml:id="_8jtKdvG">Some of these attributes, including interest, as well as aesthetics itself, have been associated with engagement <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Chapman, 1997)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_Fc7NQYc">Aesthetics is the visual appearance of the interface as it conforms to design principles <ref type="bibr">(i.e., symmetry, balance, emphasis, harmony, proportion, rhythm, and unity;</ref><ref type="bibr">Beardsley, 1982)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_U5D35Jg">Aesthetic theory has been applied by software developers in interface design <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Skelly et al., 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Lavie &amp; Tractinsky, 2004)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_AFMyv3m">Aesthetics has been linked to usability and users' skills and needs, as well as to the sensory aspects or format of the application <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Laurel, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr">Hummels, 2000</ref><ref type="bibr">, as cited in Overbeeke, Djajadiningrat, Hummels, Wensveen, &amp; Frens, 2003)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_YmVKD2g">As a result, aesthetics is important to engagement, but clearly is only one aspect of engagement.</s></p><p xml:id="_yjQ96sP"><s xml:id="_fsGygmS">Play is the physical activity that encourages learning and creativity, develops and satisfies psychological and social needs, and involves aspects of competition and collaboration <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Rieber, 1996)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_6bv8KNy">Play has also been associated with having an experience, such as news reading <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">(Stephenson, 1967)</ref> and browsing <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">(Toms, 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr">2000)</ref>, and has recently been examined in the context of educational technologies <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Rieber, 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Said, 2004)</ref>, video games <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Pausch, Gold, Skelly, &amp; Thiel, 1994)</ref>, and decision making on the Web <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Atkinson &amp; Kydd, 1997)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_VBz9agj">Play has been associated with increased frequency and satisfaction of system use <ref type="bibr">(Atkinson &amp; Kydd)</ref>, and has been attributed to increased motivation, challenge, and affect <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">(Woszczynski et al., 2002)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_eUEdT6p">Thus elements of play are intrinsic to engagement.</s></p><p xml:id="_EfGbU2X"><s xml:id="_cwKxbpu">Interaction pertains to the communication between the user and the computer interface <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(Schneiderman, 1997)</ref>, where the interface is the medium enabling user experiences.</s><s xml:id="_wyZvX9w">The interface represents the union of information design (i.e., how data is categorized, presented, and made meaningful to the user), interaction design (i.e., how the information tells a story), and sensorial design (i.e., the techniques employed to stimulate and utilize the five senses; <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Shedroff, 1994)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_KtcqHjw">Information interaction is <ref type="bibr">(Toms, 2002, p. 855 )</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_YBFfpYs">For the user, this sequence of events or activities occurs when people use systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">(Wright, McCarthy, &amp; Meekison, 2003)</ref> and is contingent upon attributes of the user (e.g., motivations, expectations), system (e.g., usability), and contextual or environmental (e.g., organizational culture) characteri-stics <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Hassenzahl &amp; Tractinsky, 2006)</ref>, in addition to task <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Marchionini, 1995)</ref> and content <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">(Toms, 2002)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_33JAYGd">Information interaction provides the connectivity for engagement.</s><s xml:id="_xfQCS9C">The computer system may be aesthetically appealing with design elements that promote play.</s><s xml:id="_zJtajU7">The user may be susceptible to the state of flow.</s><s xml:id="_vUTyq37">However, it is the interaction between users and systems operating within a specific context that facilitates an engaging experience.</s></p><p xml:id="_wCrX4sw"><s xml:id="_AsjeW9Q">Table <ref type="table">1</ref> maps the characteristics that emerge from the literature for flow, aesthetics, play, and information interaction theories.</s><s xml:id="_6rnB6JV">In the final column, we hypothesize which of these attributes may be intrinsic to engagement.</s><s xml:id="_HQwthV6">Concurrent with these theories, an engaging experience is encouraged by the sensory appeal of the system and the level of feedback and challenge the user receives from the system.</s><s xml:id="_EynT3BH">Engaged users are affectively involved, motivated, and perceive themselves to be in control over the interaction.</s><s xml:id="_j3GqxfU">However, there are other characteristics inherent in flow, play, aesthetic, and information interaction theories that are unlikely to be present in engagement.</s><s xml:id="_pXCgH9K">Engaging experiences have the attention of the user, but, unlike experiences in flow and aesthetic theories, do not require users to become so focused that they lose their awareness of physical reality.</s><s xml:id="_vNSQc4d">In contrast to flow and play, engagement may not be dependent on the user forming specific goals for the interaction.</s><s xml:id="_guCedVE">Users may use an application without any specific purpose or desirable outcome and have an engaging experience.</s><s xml:id="_Tatt2VM">While information interaction focuses on the user experience with content, engagement is an expression of that interactivity.</s><s xml:id="_cM36kBw">While some of the other frameworks stress the meaningfulness of the experience (i.e., aesthetics and flow), an engaging experience may make a lasting impression but have no more meaning than that the experience was enjoyable or challenging.</s></p><p xml:id="_JEJuMyk"><s xml:id="_ptBFRrK">TABLE 1. Attributes of flow, aesthetic, play, and information interaction theories, and proposed relevancy to engagement.</s><s xml:id="_RSpmGjN">Theories Flow Aesthtic Play Information Attribute of Attributes from the theories theory theory theory interaction engagement?</s><s xml:id="_HRnqsm3">Aesthetics Yes Affective appeal Yes Attention Maybe Challenge Yes Feedback Yes Goal-directed Maybe Meaningfulness Maybe Motivation Yes</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_K9jNvYj">Perceived control Maybe</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_54vRG2H">Sensory appeal Yes</head><p xml:id="_GZTw2xf"><s xml:id="_hNHjMAW">Based on our exploration of these four theoretical frameworks and previous research on engagement, an understanding of engagement emerges.</s><s xml:id="_StDpBv7">Like flow, play, aesthetics, and information interaction, engagement builds upon the foundation of a usable system that is effective, efficient, and satisfying.</s><s xml:id="_TjxmJcG">The theoretical framework that informs engagement integrates system attributes (i.e., feedback, challenge, sensory appeal) with the affective propensities of the user.</s><s xml:id="_27kaD6r">Thus engagement is conceptually a holistic framework for understanding the integration of user and system variables, and how they combine to push the boundaries of user experience from merely perfunctory to pleasurable and memorable.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_q6BhMZQ">Application Areas</head><p xml:id="_TcwQczs"><s xml:id="_WMjHgpW">We chose to explore engagement in four application areas: online shopping, Web searching, educational Webcasting, and video games.</s><s xml:id="_WUc6XwV">Our rationale for this was that studies of engagement exist predominantly in education and video games, while there is sparse research about engagement in online shopping and Web searching.</s><s xml:id="_PCpzFtv">By looking at these four applications, we intended to confirm past findings in the areas of video gaming and education applications, and to see what the areas of Web searching and online shopping would contribute to the understanding of engagement.</s></p><p xml:id="_VDmk833"><s xml:id="_CGgGwfF">Education researchers have emphasized that engagement should be a pleasurable experience that involves intellectual challenge or stimulation <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Douglas &amp; Hargadon, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Read, MacFarlane, &amp; Casey, 2002)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_8eJHPXv">Read, MacFarlane, and Casey observed children's facial expressions to identify instances of engagement and fun, and linked remembering enjoyable situations and intending to perform them again.</s><s xml:id="_EtJQXYA">In addition to fun, researchers have explored the impact of specific technologies, including educational multimedia <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Jacques et al., 1995)</ref>, presentation software <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">(Webster &amp; Ho, 1997)</ref>, computer-based versus video-based training applications <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Chapman et al., 1999)</ref>, and film and hypertext <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Laarni, Ravaja, Kallinen, &amp; Saari, 2004</ref>) on engagement.</s><s xml:id="_64JTyfF">The characteristics of engaging systems that emerge from these studies have included ease of use, aesthetic appeal, and choice <ref type="bibr">(Jacques et al.)</ref>; feedback, challenge, and variety <ref type="bibr">(Webster &amp; Ho)</ref>; interactivity <ref type="bibr">(Chapman et al.; Laarni et al.)</ref>; and sensory appeal through the use of different multimedia components including text, graphics, and sound <ref type="bibr">(Laarni, et al.)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_6mEzBbg"><s xml:id="_6r4wf7Z">A number of these same attributes (e.g., feedback, intrinsic motivation, fun, user control, and interactivity) have been studied in video games <ref type="bibr">(Carroll &amp; Thomas, 1988;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b61">Vorderer, Hartmann, &amp; Klimmt, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Choi &amp; Kim, 2004)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_EA3NDvU"><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Said (2004)</ref> varied the amount of control participants had over a video game, i.e., some children took on the role of characters, some manipulated the characters' world, and others watched the game unfold without being able to intervene.</s><s xml:id="_nVgsT37">Results indicated that immediate feedback from the system, well-defined goals, prior experience, and increasing challenge in proportion to gameplaying skills were essential attributes of engagement.</s><s xml:id="_vXsPZPP">Physiological arousal <ref type="bibr">(Ravaja et al., 2004)</ref>, as well as players' sense of social presence <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Champion, 2003)</ref> and sensation seeking <ref type="bibr">(Ravaja et al.)</ref>, were all factors of engagement with video games.</s></p><p xml:id="_R9JTfXZ"><s xml:id="_PXwdJmN">Engagement has rarely been examined in online shopping and search applications.</s><s xml:id="_hSRmn8t">However, given the role of affect in both of these contexts (see, e.g., <ref type="bibr">Nahl &amp; Bilal, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Arnold &amp; Reynolds, 2003)</ref>, we can extrapolate that engagement in these areas will be not only purposeful but pleasurable, and that this emotional component will make people more likely to return to a specific product or company Web site <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">(Webster &amp; Ahuja, 2004)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_EwDEK2j">Qualities of Web sites, such as novelty <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">(Toms, 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr">2000)</ref> and aesthetics <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Lavie &amp; Tractinsky, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Skelly et al., 1994)</ref>, as well as feedback, navigability, control, and interactivity <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Huang, 2003)</ref>, have demonstrated that users' needs for both information and entertainment must be satisfied when it comes to engaging searching and shopping experiences.</s><s xml:id="_ApQacSC">Poor Web site design and usability may Web searching is hampered by a Web site's poor navigational structure, users are left feeling disoriented and frustrated <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Atkinson &amp; Kydd, 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">Webster &amp; Ahuja, 2004)</ref>, and that they lack control over the interaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Rozell &amp; Gardner, 2000)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_Ezuxf64"><s xml:id="_usp8nJZ">An examination of these application areas reveals what qualities of video games and educational applications make for an engaging experience; studies in the areas of usability and user affect suggest what factors will predict engagement in searching and online shopping environments.</s><s xml:id="_R7FVMHJ">Table <ref type="table">2</ref> summarizes the attributes of engagement that emerge from reviewing research in the areas of education, video games, online shopping, and searching.</s><s xml:id="_9DZunYU">Of note is that some of these characteristics differ from the earlier theoretical discussion (compare Tables <ref type="table">1</ref> and <ref type="table">2</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_uWatYXY">Our definition of an engagement attribute is a characteristic of the user-computer interaction that influences or is a component of the engagement.</s><s xml:id="_cmz2EyJ">Engagement attributes are products of users' interactions with the technology, since they depend on what the user finds innately compelling.</s><s xml:id="_td4zD9d">Previous research across the four applications areas suggests that challenge, pleasure, endurability, attention, aesthetic and sensory appeal, feedback, variety/novelty, interactivity, and perceived user control are attributes of engagement.</s><s xml:id="_MR3nSg7">We predict that an engaging experience is characterized by these attributes.</s></p><p xml:id="_mwZv9Am"><s xml:id="_GgtZNZP">TABLE 2. Attributes of engagement suggested by previous research in four areas of application.</s><s xml:id="_RwzUsWj">Applications Attributes of Video Educational Online Web engagement games applications shopping searching Aesthetics appeal a Attention a Challenge a Endurability Feedback a Interactivity Perceived user control a Pleasure b Sensory appeal a Variety/Novelty a Indicates that these attributes also appear in Table 1 as characteristics of flow, aesthetic, play,and information interaction theories.</s><s xml:id="_HST395g">b</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_qrZgnFS">RESEARCH DESIGN</head><p xml:id="_NePQZrD"><s xml:id="_9WMWC5N">Based on our synthesis of aesthetic, flow, play, and information interaction theories, and on previous work in the application areas of video games, online shopping, Web searching, and educational software, we propose a definition of engagement:</s></p><p xml:id="_tsbZzHg"><s xml:id="_Ke7Y8p8">Engagement is a category of user experience characterized by attributes of challenge, positive affect, endurability, aesthetic and sensory appeal, attention, feedback, variety/novelty, interactivity, and perceived user control.</s></p><p xml:id="_ZNyBMPW"><s xml:id="_vyRVmdB">As a result, the research question that guided the design of this study is: Is this definition of engagement complete?</s><s xml:id="_rv7QmnD">In other words, has previous research identified all of the possible attributes of engagement, or are there others that have yet to be recognized?</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_rsTcwVs">METHODOLOGY</head><p xml:id="_UAnTQdJ"><s xml:id="_J4zFE4F">There are a variety of methods that we might have employed to study this construct, including surveys, participant observation, and so forth.</s><s xml:id="_WRD664Y">However, due to the exploratory nature of our research, we could not be confident in creating questionnaire items or classifying observed behaviors.</s><s xml:id="_r7krHvV">Nor could we be certain that studying this phenomenon while participants were actively engaged would not interfere with their experiences.</s><s xml:id="_NtZqYAm">In addition, it was our belief that there is more to engagement than we could garner by studying the activity itself.</s></p><p xml:id="_P99Vdvn"><s xml:id="_mq4jEu3">We concluded that conducting semistructured interviews was the best method, because it enabled us to delve into the thoughts, behaviors, and feelings of our participants and to allow them to recount a real-life experience.</s><s xml:id="_shBgjyb">A drawback to this methodology is that <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Wright, 2004)</ref>, a conclusion reached by <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Ericsson and Simon (1993)</ref> in their analysis of retrospective verbal protocols.</s><s xml:id="_UUqzkZJ">As such, it may be biased by users' reflections of events as they relate to other experiences; some details may be withheld or changed since this method relies on accurate recall and depends on what participants deem important or memorable.</s><s xml:id="_cVERZzq">On the other hand, if an experience was truly memorable, then participants likely remember the details of the experience.</s><s xml:id="_zNUcDGE">Ericsson and Simon further acknowledged that situations of intense cognitive activity, such as that required for the applications we were investigating, tend not to produce useful data when done concurrently with real-time data collection in the form of think-alouds.</s><s xml:id="_bG7T4FC">Given the methodological research in this area, the method we chose was the best given this set of circumstances.</s><s xml:id="_ymhC4JJ">Thus, we acknowledge that our interview data is part recall and part interpretation on the part of our participants, but we believe that participants' reflections of their experiences communicate memorable information about the nature of their engagement.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_bMzn7jh">Participants</head><p xml:id="_ngRtXVW"><s xml:id="_Vc8pst2">Participants (n = 17; 10 female, 7 male) were recruited in two Canadian cities.</s><s xml:id="_9tUZzUf">Recruitment notices were sent via listservs that solicited interviewees who were online shoppers, searchers, video game players, and distance learners of a specific webcast application.</s><s xml:id="_wZ9DCMM">Thus, this was a purposive sample with individuals chosen on the basis of their interaction with the applications of interest to this study.</s><s xml:id="_sZ7urCu">Recruitment continued until the researchers felt there were no new ideas emerging from the interviews <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Oppenheim, 1992)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_nzj967r">Our intention was not to saturate each application area, but to examine engagement in general using a variety of applications.</s></p><p xml:id="_G2eS4Aq"><s xml:id="_he86NTd">As a group, the 10 females and 7 males were educated and technologically savvy.</s><s xml:id="_8apGD2p">All used e-mail on a daily basis and searched the Web daily (95%) or weekly (5%).</s><s xml:id="_UxMhpPF">All had a high school diploma; 88% had some undergraduate education, and 30% held college diplomas; 71% had completed or were currently enrolled in a masters program.</s><s xml:id="_xdDMpux">Fortyone percent were currently students.</s><s xml:id="_5MbtzWU">Most of the participants were under age 35 (n = 13), while the remainder were between 36 and 45 (n = 3) and over 55 (n = 1).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_GTbdEjk">Interview Protocol</head><p xml:id="_7Cc6Gf3"><s xml:id="_pg38Jwt">Appendix A consists of the interview questions.</s><s xml:id="_KeqVFnb">Based upon our conjecture that engagement is a quality of user experience, we used McCarthy and <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Wright's (2004)</ref> framework for interpreting our results.</s><s xml:id="_yyBnEvw">The four threads of experience are (a) compositional (i.e., beginning, middle, and end); (b) spatiotemporal (i.e., the subtasks being performed as part of participants' application use, such as searching, browsing, comparing information, and communicating with others, as well as their awareness of themselves and their environments, and characteristics of the technology); (c) emotional, (e.g., pleasure, fatigue); (d) sensual (i.e., cognitive [e.g., problem solving], and behavioral [e.g., interactivity] components of the experience).</s><s xml:id="_nRtYaMY">The interview was designed to elicit participants' reactions to each of these components of experience.</s></p><p xml:id="_jXVU84F"><s xml:id="_WhHy4Ew">Specifically we asked them to recount their affective responses, sensory impressions of their environments and the interface, and perceptions of how much time they spent on the computer-based activity.</s><s xml:id="_Njrmy7Z">In accordance with the compositional thread, we allowed our participants to tell us a story.</s></p><p xml:id="_R6qM8nN"><s xml:id="_cpWQ5DK">The same interview questions were used for all applications, with slight modifications made to reflect the specific application.</s><s xml:id="_sE48mna">For example, one question for online shopping uestions were included throughout the protocol, but were used only if participants had difficulty articulating the experience.</s><s xml:id="_hf3SKuJ">The interview ended when all of these semistructured questions had been addressed.</s><s xml:id="_UGUJvpH">The order of the questions was allowed to vary so that the interview flowed more like a conversation between the participant and the researcher.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_GhaKpXE">Procedure</head><p xml:id="_umYYzpk"><s xml:id="_ZmxDS4f">In-person interviews were carried out with 15 of the 17 participants in their homes or the researchers' office; two interviews were conducted over the telephone.</s><s xml:id="_v5Xb8nj">After they completed the demographics and consent form, individuals were asked to recall a time in recent memory when they felt engaged while using the application they chose to discuss in the interview.</s><s xml:id="_yE7mzRs">The interviews lasted 30 45 minutes.</s><s xml:id="_fGqRnHK">At the end of the interview, participants were thanked for their participation and paid an honorarium of $15 Canadian.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_ya4UnBF">Data Analysis</head><p xml:id="_AHpRySR"><s xml:id="_meHKSBY">We practiced theoretical sampling in that we decided to interview users of four different applications.</s><s xml:id="_PDyr8kM">Our goal was to generate a strong theoretical foundation for the construct of engagement; as such our coding scheme was theoretically sensitive and concerned with validating or refuting past research.</s><s xml:id="_fHppGkG">Interviews were audio recorded, transcribed, and analyzed using a qualitative software package, Qualrus.</s><s xml:id="_6tXwBCZ">Fifty-two codes (see Appendix B) were generated from the data using Strauss' grounded theory, which is systematic in its approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(Strauss &amp; Corbin, 1990)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_TCjkWCb">As such, we acknowledge that we approached the data with preconceived ideas based on our review of the research, and that our reading of previous research may have influenced some of our coding categories.</s></p><p xml:id="_XBPZNrZ"><s xml:id="_75jCW4k">The interview transcripts went through five iterative examinations.</s><s xml:id="_aVz5Xqf">We used McCarthy and <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Wright's (2004)</ref> threads of experience to organize the data.</s><s xml:id="_ZzRgd98">The first pass through the data focused on emotional representations in the data and incidences of positive, negative, or neutral affect.</s><s xml:id="_yw8McCV">The sensual thread examined the qualities of the system, such as its appearance and the interactivity of the technology.</s><s xml:id="_DnQugEG">Lastly, the spatiotemporal thread described what the participant was doing (e.g., browsing, comparing products, etc.) and their perceptions and awareness of their physical environments.</s><s xml:id="_8PmJABh">The compositional thread was woven around these other threads and identified the beginning, middle, and end of the experience.</s><s xml:id="_QCzrakS">In addition, we also coded the data for the attributes of engagement suggested by previous research, and for the new attributes that emerged in this analysis.</s></p><p xml:id="_hZu5GY9"><s xml:id="_U65j4qH">The coded segments were subjected to interrater reliability by an independent coder.</s><s xml:id="_QYebFwH">The coder was provided with the complete list of codes and their definitions, as well as the interviews.</s><s xml:id="_T6T9TJp">The coder was asked to apply the codes to all of the interviews, or to create new codes if none were appropriate.</s><s xml:id="_RgVxG6A">Once this was complete, the primary researcher compared the codes assigned by the coder with her own, noting discrepancies in the assignment of codes and any new codes that the independent coder had created.</s><s xml:id="_XE7Reh5">The researcher then met with the independent coder to discuss the analyses, focusing on the missed and disputed codes.</s><s xml:id="_KPFCPK2">The result of this process was a 92% agreement.</s><s xml:id="_qZqTGH9">For the coded segments in which an agreement was not reached between the researcher and the independent coder, the second researcher was asked to weigh in.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_4ygmn5G">RESULTS</head><p xml:id="_SRTwvKx"><s xml:id="_2embZUp">To reiterate, these are: (a) compositional (i.e., narrative structure); (b) spatiotemporal (i.e., time and space); (c) emotional; and (d) sensual (i.e., cognition and behavior).</s><s xml:id="_dnYrRfB">Because the findings indicated a common trajectory for engaging experiences, we start our discussion with this path as a process with distinct stages.</s><s xml:id="_usHs8Ef">Subsequently, we describe the findings according to the threads of experience.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_3fWpQRQ">The Process of Engagement</head><p xml:id="_mfhZmVd"><s xml:id="_ZYF4XuU">From the systematic analysis approach, engagement emerged as a process with distinguishable attributes inherent at each stage in that process.</s><s xml:id="_TxMzeGe">The steps in this process are the point of engagement (engagement is initiated), period of engagement, disengagement, and reengagement.</s><s xml:id="_3jRjexs">In this section we describe each of these stages and indicate the attributes and manifestations of the experiential threads present during each stage</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_7aR9DZr">Point of engagement.</head><p xml:id="_hwqWPDz"><s xml:id="_KpefFTu">Participants described how engaging experiences began.</s><s xml:id="_tN8pCap">In some cases, they had a webcast viewers tuned in to hear a particular speaker or about a topic that resonated with their research interests.</s></p><p xml:id="_8Tz6dvz"><s xml:id="_Z9Y7KR6">Web searchers talked about wanting to stay up-to-date with favorite television shows or local/world news items.</s><s xml:id="_R4YJMqn">Video gamers played games based on the recommendations of others or the genre of the game (P12).</s><s xml:id="_Ry6VfMd">In other cases participants' objectives were less s released to advertise games.</s><s xml:id="_JjNAduY">game's got to be amazing cause if you spend a lot of time in this game, the graphics, animation, sound are so enthralled that [you Interviewees also described social motivations for initiating interactions or tasks with know I consulted other people, both friends and anonymous reviewers, to select a product that best suited their needs.</s><s xml:id="_Xk7zPYS">Web searchers described browsing news, technology, and television network Web sites to share information with others at a later time.</s><s xml:id="_AgtbyUB">In fact, one searcher discussed searching for information explicitly for others.</s></p><p xml:id="_GfeaREu"><s xml:id="_Dd5Hr8E">Some participants became engaged by the layout or aesthetics of the interface.</s><s xml:id="_NQFycUv">They talked about being attracted to images and features that first caught their attention, like homing in on the search box on the screen (P2).</s><s xml:id="_Jh6VpE2">Shoppers and searchers discussed being carried away from their original task to look for a specific product or Web site.</s><s xml:id="_aAb8tkN">This was sometimes int Sometimes a news story was a launching pad for further browsing of online and I find it interesting, I will use that as a basis to were watching temporarily to look for more information on the Web pertaining to the content of the presentation.</s></p><p xml:id="_hcTCGtA"><s xml:id="_WtATkQ2">The point of engagement was often triggered when something resonated with participants' interests.</s><s xml:id="_KUck3k6">For some video gamers, the engagement was built up through in a</s></p><p xml:id="_QppEvec"><s xml:id="_6A7hVdk">Webcast viewers talked about becoming engaged by something the speaker said that was relevant to their interests or captured their attention, or by the use of multimedia.</s><s xml:id="_qwwT9r7">One webcast viewer described watching an archived webcast while tidying her office something int (P17).</s></p><p xml:id="_9NzH3W9"><s xml:id="_EJ7J4X8">In summary, the engagement process was initiated by the resonance of the aesthetic or informational composition of the system interface with users'.</s><s xml:id="_dfBwkR7">These elements captured participants' attention and interest and moved them forward into engagement.</s><s xml:id="_EatwQXv">In some cases, interviewees were motivated for social reasons, while at other times they were looking to satisfy a specific goal (i.e., buy a product) or simply open themselves up to having an engaging experience.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_zHrer2y">Period of engagement.</head><p xml:id="_VFcmJBb"><s xml:id="_pJ9VrUn">After discussing the point at which they became engaged, participants described what was taking place and what they felt and thought while engaged.</s><s xml:id="_6M7mSUC">This stage was marked by the attention interviewees were able to focus on their task and the application, the novelty of the experience, their level of interest, and their perceptions of challenge, feedback, and user control inherent in the interaction.</s></p><p xml:id="_PJaTMuw"><s xml:id="_Bpqpcnn">Attention, the concentration of mental activity <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Matlin, 1994)</ref>, was evident during this stage.</s><s xml:id="_qEFasZx">At times participants were highly focused and remarked that they were frequently the broadcast, as what maintained their attention.</s><s xml:id="_93hF9HD">One interviewee described a speaker Novelty is the tendency to seek out elements that are new, interesting, or unusual in one's environment <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Huang, 2003)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_4QhQycx">It is also defined as sudden and unexpected changes that occur on the interface that evoke a reaction from the user (</s></p><p xml:id="_kkRKVcf"><s xml:id="_4Nfesu8">Aboulafia &amp; Bannon, (P11, P13) by items for which they did not originally search.</s><s xml:id="_anEqNWy">One Web searcher (e.g., h Engagement continued when interviewees' interest was sustained.</s><s xml:id="_W45rVr9">Shoppers indicated that looking at one product led to looking at others and comparing items across different he found inte (P2).</s><s xml:id="_wTAfNEj">A webcast viewer emphasized maintaining intellectual interest in the presentation, know or what you have heard from other people [and] you can decide whether you</s></p><p xml:id="_sYA6YMQ"><s xml:id="_kUwkdF2">Challenge pertains to the amount of effort users perceive they are expending <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">(Webster &amp; Ahuja, 2004)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_TTRKvED">Shoppers, searchers, and Webcast viewers preferred computer (P10).</s><s xml:id="_cFHa3sD">Shoppers talked about online stores that were well organized and enabled them straightforward.</s><s xml:id="_7jAzpPr">Though webcast viewers preferred less functional challenge in their use of the application, they did want to be intellectually challenged by the content.</s><s xml:id="_phpzmV4">Video do one s challenge and satisfaction from overcoming the challenge that it makes you feel good almost, and as you get better, the game gets difficult, probably at abo (P5).</s></p><p xml:id="_FtzE3y6"><s xml:id="_vFdxQMs">Feedback is the information communicated to users about actions that have occurred and results that have been achieved.</s><s xml:id="_kkZsWuz">Feedback may be visual, auditory, or tactile <ref type="bibr">(Stone, Jarratt, Woodroffe, &amp; Minocha, 2005)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_q2rjrDj">For webcast participants, feedback was through the text-sort of at the nd to keep track of background elements of the game that were separate from the ones currently on the screen and in focus, but that required attention from time to time (P8).</s></p><p xml:id="_ttckuDu"><s xml:id="_NUkQvFt">Participants expressed the desire to perceive they were in control of the interaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Schneiderman &amp; Plaisant, 2005)</ref> and to assert that they had the skills and abilities to meet the challenges of particular circumstances <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Mandel, 1997)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_WmwHMW8">According to one -it-d not relying on salespeople that was appealling.</s><s xml:id="_EeDakha">The need for control was embedded in the I'm looking at to a certain degree.</s><s xml:id="_SF2NUgt">I am aware of the fact that [the online store] is was driving in a race game, but not of other things that were part of the game such as they are certainly way out of your control and that's the whole point.</s><s xml:id="_FKwhaxy">It seems to mimic r Another talked about the games he played as controlling some aspects, and leaving the entified as a reason to disengage these interviewees.</s></p><p xml:id="_XUAJxkA"><s xml:id="_pA7FXYt">In summary, the period of sustained engagement was marked by participants' attention and interest being maintained in the interaction.</s><s xml:id="_avNSjZQ">This was achieved by the presentation of feedback and novel information and features on the interface.</s><s xml:id="_BASHBkU">Interviewees were also more likely to stay in the engagement when they perceived that they were in charge of the interaction and appropriately challenged.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_QmnKEcc">Disengagement.</head><p xml:id="_nTKW6Gw"><s xml:id="_gDzAcTg">Disengagement occurred when participants made an internal decision to stop the activity, or when factors in the participants' external environment caused them to cease being engaged.</s></p><p xml:id="_cvpAwXd"><s xml:id="_jRDHahh">(P13).</s><s xml:id="_zy4fjGN">At other times, the fact that the task was not urgent precipitated the disengagement.</s><s xml:id="_rshjJPp">One shopper indicated that she had not put a great deal of energy into wasn't a timeline or anything really stren viewers also indicated they simply were not able to sustain their attention over the course of a threethen you sort of lose interest; other things within your own mind do interfere so you start stopped because other things came into their minds, such as having to turn their attention to their job or school work.</s><s xml:id="_RykkYCf">Interviewees also discussed physiological circumstances that brought about their disengagement, such as eye fatigue, or needing to eat/drink or use the washroom.</s></p><p xml:id="_9vrWXYu"><s xml:id="_PUpPJK2">At other times, disengagement was the result of external factors, such as being interrupted.</s><s xml:id="_YB56usu">The source of interruptions was from environmental factors, such as a kitchen timer going off, e-mail alerts, or other people who were sometimes there in person.</s><s xml:id="_mUynWab">For instance, interviewees mentioned contending with coworkers' questions, the phone ringing, or the presence of others in their physical space.</s><s xml:id="_qZ4tVE9">Disengagement was also brought about by technological issues.</s><s xml:id="_AnKa7AG">A webcast viewer stated that broadcasts couple of it, but at the same time it doesn't offer anything new.</s><s xml:id="_Vupzttf">It's still the same old stuff, there's To summarize, disengagement was precipitated by internal and external factors.</s><s xml:id="_ETuj7mr">Interviewees sometimes made a conscious decision to stop their activity because they lost interest or felt pressures associated with the opinions of others, time, or other tasks.</s><s xml:id="_F5k26YS">External issues, such as distractions and interruptions, lack of novelty in the application, and usability issues with the technology, also made participants disengage.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_2QxmFf8">Reengagement.</head><p xml:id="_YADZ5pm"><s xml:id="_yCKeAA2">Interviewees indicated that disengaging from a task or interface was not necessarily the end of their engagement.</s><s xml:id="_gvqEMbP">Shopping, fo because it was temporarily dropped or stretched out over an extended period of time.</s><s xml:id="_yRsqyWu">Even when shoppers and searchers were engaged, they did not remain on one Web and features.</s><s xml:id="_ZMf4Nv6">Webcast viewers indicated that they checked out of broadcasts from time to time to pursue other activities, such as checking erd something interesting (P15).</s><s xml:id="_W5FnuMR">Video gamers drink, or adjust the lighting and temperature in the room.</s></p><p xml:id="_tVXrcGW"><s xml:id="_8jGyf7B">At times, the computer application brought about the reengagement because participants were disengaged before they were ready.</s><s xml:id="_sc6v8me">For example, a video game player described several attempts to get through a stage of a game successfully where to the Web searcher frequently interrupted by elements in her environment indicated that she otes on a piece of paper too in case something happens and I end up losing the search screen, or I log Participants talked about their likelihood of returning to use an application.</s><s xml:id="_ftFxpYg">Positive past experiences were indicative of reengagement.</s><s xml:id="_3xB7YS2">One video gamer said he was (P5).</s><s xml:id="_3NrX3Fh">Shoppers discussed browsing online shopping sites for pleasure (P13) or Convenience is a really big thing.</s><s xml:id="_gUBATCm">Who's got time to go down to the [box office] in the an online store that sent her news about sale items and coupons as incentives to ike 'go to [online store] and receive $5 off -mails from them in the content/topic of the broadcasts that encouraged them to tune in again.</s><s xml:id="_Zb99yyF">This was also the case for a Web searcher who returned each week to network Web sites to see e novelty of seeing both what she could accomplish in her next session with the game, but also what it had done in her absence.</s></p><p xml:id="_Dc9Yyts"><s xml:id="_2VcpSau">Thus reengagement with these applications occurred in both the short-and long-term.</s><s xml:id="_eaBRqWp">Participants reengaged if the system disengaged them before they were truly ready.</s><s xml:id="_Qm5D2Wc">They also reengaged after they had abandoned their tasks to see to personal needs, take time to consider and compare information, or switch tasks.</s><s xml:id="_pqssZR4">Returning to an application in future was the result of positive past experience with that application.</s><s xml:id="_PWtuFKj">These motivations were about having fun, being rewarded with convenience and incentives, and learning or discovering something new.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_WR344yp">Nonengagement.</head><p xml:id="_bd4pnmk"><s xml:id="_CqvUw6b">There was evidence in the interviews that participants were not always engaged or encountered barriers to becoming engaged.</s><s xml:id="_PRqW4Fd">In some cases, this was because the online experience was not as enjoyable as the realted the t they did not allow themselves to become engaged because they did not feel that had enough time to take in the experience.</s><s xml:id="_yfqtkhD">At times, multitasking or being interrupted during a computer-based task prevented engagement with a primary task.</s><s xml:id="_nujm3Yx">For example, interviewees said they checked e-mail, communicated with others in the same room or online, searched for information, and dealt with interruptions, and that these activities prevented them from becoming engaged (P4).</s></p><p xml:id="_PCnkCCp"><s xml:id="_CdzpFGq">The content of the application was also cited as a reason for not engaging.</s><s xml:id="_S6XZjaa">For shoppers and searchers, the abundance of information available to peruse was out there, a lot of different product information, you can't go through it all, so you have to -ups, important.</s><s xml:id="_V5rBaWW">Really, if it's that much work for me to get to see it, then it's not worth it.</s></p><p xml:id="_zgyBtmd"><s xml:id="_s9hGscs">Poor usability was a barrier to shopping (P2).</s><s xml:id="_f7ykXcY">Webcast viewers experienced frustration when they attempted to use communication technology to chat with other viewers or the speaker, citing the delay in transmitting their message, since their comments were tied to specific points in time.</s><s xml:id="_pJTsdzv">Two other interviewees remarked that viewing a webcast lessened their awareness of to the size of the vid says something funny then you are going to laugh and you are going to see other people laughing.</s><s xml:id="_4XUPs8B">And you are going to be looking at them laughing.</s><s xml:id="_vBQsqjC">Or if there is something on the chalkboard as well you might glance over there.</s><s xml:id="_2fSvQ9r">Even if it was Therefore, engagement was not always part of users' experiences with the applications.</s><s xml:id="_8FBq6r3">At times it was because participants would have preferred to shop in a physical store or sit in real classroom.</s><s xml:id="_2vZnUJC">At other times lack of time or having to multitask deterred engagement.</s><s xml:id="_wmsPZwd">Content that overwhelmed or failed to interest users and usability issues with the technology were barriers to engagement.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_BqNnvDg">Experience Threads</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_tT6YEbN">Compositional thread.</head><p xml:id="_rQXxZxu"><s xml:id="_9etFj9c">In following the compositional thread of experience, engagement as a process emerged from the data.</s><s xml:id="_FGN5XZA">As previously discussed, engaging experiences consist of a point of engagement, a period of sustained engagement, disengagement, and, sometimes reengagement.</s><s xml:id="_YW8dVmm">In addition, we discovered that engagement did not always take place.</s><s xml:id="_dySTKmR">As a result, engagement is a quality of user experience and it may be embedded in a larger event or experience.</s><s xml:id="_5fyd8bv">The other threads of experience, sensual, emotional, and spatiotemporal, were present in the engagement experience.</s><s xml:id="_GsCcDyf">Although some examples of these threads are embedded in our discussion of the engagement process, we summarize them in the following sections.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_XKJ4C6N">The sensual thread.</head><p xml:id="_93QR8dR"><s xml:id="_DArXWQw">The sensual thread pertains to the visual, auditory, and interactive components of the users' experiences with the application.</s><s xml:id="_pW6e7kT">Applications used aesthetics (as defined by <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Jennings (2000)</ref>) and multimedia to engage users' senses.</s><s xml:id="_dTqYmkX">Online shoppers talked about the importance of viewing products from multiple perspectives (P12), while graphics were also essential to video gamers for evoking realism in the game (P5, P9).</s><s xml:id="_S4wHAp9">Searchers and webcast viewers focused their attention on the salient attributes of the interface (P6, P17).</s><s xml:id="_7me2eup">For example, presentation materials were deemed more engaging if cases.</s><s xml:id="_22WUhQ5">visual incorporated other media such as videos.</s><s xml:id="_yNyrYA4">The auditory aspects of video games, such as gamers.</s></p><p xml:id="_m9N2NMf"><s xml:id="_7R5Du5H">Interactivity was also part of the engagement.</s><s xml:id="_3fEzhd8">Video game players customized features whether as a member of a war campaign in a strategy game, or as a race car driver.</s><s xml:id="_6CuCWrJ">Another gamer described playing a simulation game in which she created characters and their environments and manipulated both of these through game play.</s><s xml:id="_g2EbAae">The many features of the webcast interface video, presentation slides, and chat failed to engage some of the webcast viewers (P15, P16).</s><s xml:id="_KJurMrs">One participant wanted to be able to manipulate the size and placement of the features, which were fixed (P15); another commented part due to the time lapse in communication tools that prevented truly synchronous feedback between the learners and the speaker.</s><s xml:id="_Mn9SrqY">Thus, for the webcast viewers, some of the interaction was of a social nature.</s><s xml:id="_pfXfZsA">Lastly, Web users experienced interactivity in their ability to select information.</s><s xml:id="_9Wb6fh9">Shoppers talked about zooming in on and rotating products (P10).</s></p><p xml:id="_JAajyM7"><s xml:id="_7q3M79Z">In summary, interviewees' visual, auditory, and tactile senses were engaged during their interactions with the applications.</s><s xml:id="_6k3kENW">At times the application facilitated the engagement with its presentation of information or graphics and multimedia features; at other times it deterred engagement with its inability to meet the customization and communicative needs of participants.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_MC8W6dF">The emotional thread.</head><p xml:id="_cqAGS3t"><s xml:id="_YfpY6mE">The emotional thread accounts for the affective experiences of users' interactions, as well as the motivations that influenced and maintained their use of the application.</s></p><p xml:id="_jSQNh2J"><s xml:id="_vMXpV5z">Participants expressed a range of positive emotions, including enjoyment, satisfaction, and fun.</s><s xml:id="_t2mxfjT">Web searchers, shoppers, webcast viewers, and video gamers all expressed their enjoyment of their tasks be it browsing for information (P6) or products (P13), interacting with others during an online class (P17), or playing games (P5, P8, P12).</s><s xml:id="_Cguvp6g">One gamer related his physiological response during the gaming experience to his ge There were also a number of negative emotional reports from interviewees.</s><s xml:id="_mM7qFQJ">Participants made them wonder if they had made the best decisions about purchases (P11) or information (P4).</s><s xml:id="_sgAHFR8">Participants also felt frustration towards the technology (P4, P16) and anxiety about how much time they had spent on their tasks (P17, P4).</s><s xml:id="_UF43BHa">Boredom was mentioned by the gamers as a reason to disengage (P12).</s><s xml:id="_RSf7xrP">There was also an interesting facet of guilt across interviewees; participants described feeling guilty about having put other things off to use an application (P13, P6, P8, P9).</s></p><p xml:id="_tWPs5W2"><s xml:id="_7g6mhQQ">Interviewees described their motivations for using the applications.</s><s xml:id="_n956CxV">Getting what one wanted made interviewees reflect on their experience as a success.</s><s xml:id="_qqGxaV4">For instance, a ordered a single ticket to go to [a play] and I got a great deal, got a great seat, had the participants talked about receiving purchases in the mail, finding information they had been looking for, learning, and accomplishing specific levels in a video game.</s><s xml:id="_rNa3EKt">Another factor for perceived success pertained to doing one's homework and arriving at a</s></p><p xml:id="_QUq5jkC"><s xml:id="_zzyjCVP">The spatiotemporal thread.</s></p><p xml:id="_U9BSUQU"><s xml:id="_pggqrDm">The spatiotemporal thread pertains to the time and space of the interaction.</s><s xml:id="_GsARAN6">Included in this thread are participants' perceptions of time, their internal states, and their external environments.</s></p><p xml:id="_zUWPqmY"><s xml:id="_rEUnvsu">Interviewees remarked about the passage of time during their interactions, including their impression that it took a lot of time to decide on products (P11), make contact with by quickly and part P6).</s></p><p xml:id="_SC8KXqZ"><s xml:id="_kSJpXfd">Emerging from the data was the concept of awareness.</s><s xml:id="_CmnEyhd">Awareness is defined as cognizance of one's environment (self) or concentration on particular (external) stimuli (Merriam- <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Webster Online, 2006)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_kMyBqNj">Examples of both of these types of awareness were found in the data.</s><s xml:id="_DJfFEV8">During the engagement, participants indicated losing consciousness of their physical surroundings much like the flow state.</s><s xml:id="_g84q4pa">A searcher stated that she was concentrating on what they were doing while using the application.</s><s xml:id="_sK2jUPS">A webcast viewer described herself Others were responsive to their real and virtual environments and the people in them.</s><s xml:id="_ubyws5B">Webcast viewers mentioned their awareness of other people, both those on camera at</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_zc5r6dh">Summary.</head><p xml:id="_KbGtSXv"><s xml:id="_puvBUrT">The threads of experience framework <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(McCarthy &amp; Wright, 2004)</ref> provides an effective means of organizing the findings of this study.</s><s xml:id="_FWyqu9J">Table <ref type="table">3</ref> shows the attributes that emerged during each stage of the engagement process; the compositional thread reflects the process and is used to structure the attributes according to the emotional, spatiotemporal, and sensual threads of experience.</s><s xml:id="_CX2KxnX">Reengagement was not included in this table because this part of the process shares the same attributes as the point of engagement.</s></p><p xml:id="_dMdMNxQ"><s xml:id="_W6nED3d">TABLE 3. Summary of the engagement attributes according to the threads of experience.</s><s xml:id="_UBV2zmn">Compositional thread Process of Engagement Threads of Point of engagement experience (and Reengagement) Engagement Disengagement Aesthetic elements are Graphics that keep attention Inability to interact with Sensual pleasing or attention and interest to evoke realism features of the technology or getting manipulate inteface features "Rich" interfaces that (usability) Novel presentation of promote awareness of others information or customized views of Lack of too much challenge information Emotional Motivation to accomplish Positive affect: enjoyment, Negative affect: Uncertainty a task or to have an fun, physiological arousal information overload, experience frustration with technology, boredom, guilt Interest Positive affect: Feelings of success and accomplishment Spatiotemporal Becoming situationed in Perception that time passed Not having sufficient time to the "story" of the very quickly interact with or time to devote application to the application Lack of awareness of others Ability to take one's when the engagement Interruptions and distractions time in using the revolved around social in physical environment application interaction Feedback and control</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_sR8SdV4">A PROPOSED MODEL OF ENGAGEMENT</head><p xml:id="_ZStPYXm"><s xml:id="_ngfxgzu">The outcome of this exploratory study is the identification of four distinct stages of engagement and the attributes that characterize each stage.</s><s xml:id="_3UzG43N">The point of engagement is initiated by the aesthetic appeal or novel presentation of the interface, the users' motivations and interests, and users' ability and desire to be situated in the interaction and to perceive that there is sufficient time to use the application.</s><s xml:id="_5Mky5uA">Engagement is sustained when users are able to maintain their attention and interest in the application, and is characterized by positive emotions.</s><s xml:id="_EzKhSKH">Users want to customize the interface to meet their needs and receive appropriate and timely feedback from the application.</s><s xml:id="_wg3Rk6q">In addition, they want to lose their perception of time and others during some interactions, but keep their awareness of others in cases where engagement is enhanced by social interaction.</s><s xml:id="_MunVW4F">Users disengage for many reasons such as the usability of the technology (i.e., challenge and interactivity), and distractions in their environments.</s><s xml:id="_kxMvmnC">This stage, depending on the outcome, resulted in either positive or negative emotions.</s><s xml:id="_7gR8Vrn">Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> illustrates the model.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_6XURqDC">FIGURE 1. Proposed model of engagement and its attributes.</head><p xml:id="_C2w2BUN"><s xml:id="_7xVY9K4">The fact that our participants were not always engaged, and that they described disengaging and reengaging in the same session, indicates that a single session contains a range of engaging experiences that vary in intensity.</s><s xml:id="_jxkd2xm">Users may be engaged or not engaged, but engagement itself operates on a continuum.</s><s xml:id="_mMRykNh">In this way it is similar to the construct of usability in that it may be poor, average, or high.</s></p><p xml:id="_hXrNvwK"><s xml:id="_uvnpqgH">The point of engagement may occur at any point during the interaction when users delve beyond the mechanistic or routine level <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Norman, Ortony, &amp; Russel, 2003)</ref> and invest themselves in the interaction.</s><s xml:id="_mzGwmZv">We propose that, at this stage, the interface must present information in a novel or aesthetically pleasing way in order to capture users' motivation and interest and situate them in the interaction.</s></p><p xml:id="_whc8caQ"><s xml:id="_uWWEuN3">Our research suggests that once engaged, users' attention and interest must be maintained.</s><s xml:id="_HYA538F">Users must be made to feel part of the interaction through an awareness of what the system is doing (feedback) and feeling connected to the technology (interactivity) or to other people (social awareness), and in control over what is happening.</s><s xml:id="_PD3Z2F8">The richness of the application generates positive emotions in users.</s><s xml:id="_wTPn5PE">A representation of attributes during this stage is depicted in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> to convey the dynamic interaction that is taking place during this period.</s><s xml:id="_bSGBgGB">The intensity of these attributes may vary depending on the users' expectations of and experience with the technology, the type of interaction, and the nature of the technology itself.</s></p><p xml:id="_WRe6CZT"><s xml:id="_KaDabhr">d, or to stop using the system altogether.</s><s xml:id="_QVKQJfJ">In this case the user slips back into a mechanistic interaction with the system, devoid of affective or cognitive stimulation.</s><s xml:id="_Zjscr5d">Disengagement is associated with positive emotions (users' needs and motivations are satisfied and they feel successful) or with negative feelings of frustration, uncertainty, being overwhelmed by challenges or information, loss of interest or motivation, and lack of novelty or challenge.</s></p><p xml:id="_832Az59"><s xml:id="_9hfj4Uh">Users may cycle through the stages of engagement several times during a single session; thus reengagement is intrinsic to the model.</s><s xml:id="_kQRN3Kt">Reengagement may be shortterm.</s><s xml:id="_HkMPc7Z">During Web searching, a user may engage with a particular page, disengage, and then return to the same or a different page.</s><s xml:id="_7Q9hZSw">Web searching illustrates that engagement may continue with a topic, but not with a website; likewise, a website may be so engaging that the user abandons their original task.</s><s xml:id="_2Barcu9">Reengagement may also be longterm, for example, when a search is extended over time.</s></p><p xml:id="_wFe8YFZ"><s xml:id="_D4DCfsx">Previous frameworks of engagement have emphasized what users are doing and thinking (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Said, 2004)</ref> or feeling <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Kappelman, 1995)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_RHN9ghn">The first contribution of our model is that it is holistic and presents the behaviors, cognitions, and emotions of users in the context of content, design, and interactive features of the application.</s><s xml:id="_zndHgTU">In addition, engagement has not been explicitly identified as a process.</s><s xml:id="_YFZUntt"><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Chapman (1997)</ref> examined which may equate with our point of engagement stage but most researchers have not articulated engagement as having a beginning, middle, and end, nor what attributes might characterize each of these stages.</s><s xml:id="_cawTfma">The idea of reengagement that may occur during the same session with an application or at a future time is novel.</s><s xml:id="_KGAKRP3">The second contribution of this model is that we have linked attributes of engagement to each stage of the process.</s><s xml:id="_n7CpzCt">We have considered all of the disparate engagement attributes, and we have identified which attributes are most significant to particular stages of the engagement process.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_qcvPuzW">DISCUSSION</head><p xml:id="_sA7yXsa"><s xml:id="_WJ52EQT">The research objectives of this study were to conceptually and operationally define engagement.</s><s xml:id="_VYpBpKA">We proposed that engaging systems extend beyond usability of the application.</s><s xml:id="_PaQ3mWa">Using flow, aesthetic, play and information interaction theories as our foundation, we discovered that the attributes of engagement challenge, affect, endurability, aesthetic and sensory appeal, attention, feedback, variety/novelty, perceived control, and interactivity are products of the user-system interaction.</s><s xml:id="_fUSFGPU">Previous work suggested that challenge, pleasure, endurability, attention, aesthetic and sensory appeal, feedback, variety/novelty, interest, interactivity, and perceived user control were attributes of engagement.</s><s xml:id="_J9ZZrs8">We confirmed the presence of these attributes in the engagement process.</s><s xml:id="_Dsg3SKM">In addition, we discovered that awareness of others and one's environment, and perception of time, were also part of engaging experiences.</s><s xml:id="_B5zYK9C">Thus, we have expanded our original definition of engagement to include these additional attributes:</s></p><p xml:id="_mVN84Fv"><s xml:id="_AyDbMQw">Engagement is a quality of user experiences with technology that is characterized by challenge, aesthetic and sensory appeal, feedback, novelty, interactivity, perceived control and time, awareness, motivation, interest, and affect.</s></p><p xml:id="_RMFXsnR"><s xml:id="_t2kD4Hm">In the midst of conceptually and operationally defining engagement, we have articulated a process model of engagement.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_2ccfCEc">Process Model of Engagement</head><p xml:id="_EK3hMQj"><s xml:id="_79uzYv6">The experience threads, in particular the compositional thread, clearly delineated a systematic process that depicts engaging experiences.</s><s xml:id="_4YTWebn">Engagement consists of a point of engagement, a period of sustained engagement, disengagement, and (possibly) reengagement.</s><s xml:id="_72s5rqZ">In prior research, engagement was associated with a variety of attributes: feedback, control, focused attention, motivation, challenge, aesthetic and affective appeal, and novelty <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Jacques et al., 1995;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Said, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b63">Webster &amp; Ho, 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Chapman, 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Chapman et al., 1999)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_3xpYTNH">Previous models of engagement have viewed engagement as a process (defined as a task) or product of information-system development <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Kappelman, 1995)</ref>, rather than a quality of users' experience with technology.</s><s xml:id="_WgRkZr5"><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Chapman (1997)</ref> investigated engagement influences and outcomes, but his results are limited to a specific educational software package and user group.</s><s xml:id="_AVszeq9">In addition, he concluded that some of the measurement items could have been improved in order to ensure that they measured what they were intended to (p. 123).</s><s xml:id="_KBbftnB">In addition, both <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Kappelman (1995)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Chapman (1997)</ref> look at dimensions of engagement (i.e., product versus task, influences versus outcomes), but they do not define engagement as a process with a beginning, middle, and end, or state that there is an iterative component to engagement.</s></p><p xml:id="_yQ5yARq"><s xml:id="_QpV4DJz">Participants indicated that interest in and attention to the content and aesthetics of the computer application were present during the point of engagement, and that they typically had a goal (sometimes well-defined, sometimes social, and sometimes to have an experience) in mind when initiating an interaction with a computer application.</s><s xml:id="_34efae9">Goal setting was put forward by <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Said (2004)</ref> as an untapped variable to consider for engagement.</s><s xml:id="_AdCV7Ax">Whereas this study identified interest, attention, motivation, and aesthetics as attributes at the point of engagement, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Chapman (1997)</ref> found that feedback and control were influences on engagement.</s><s xml:id="_MDjQPFV">These latter variables were more prominent in this study during the engagement phase.</s><s xml:id="_MVz6K9K">The experience of being engaged was perpetuated by the interactivity of the computer environment sometimes physical, social, or cognitive and the usability of the interface as they matched the users' attention, motivation, interest, and need for aesthetic and sensory appeal, novelty, control, and challenge.</s><s xml:id="_ghspygZ">Like <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Said (2004)</ref>, we found behavioral and cognitive manifestations of engagement during this phase, as demonstrated in users' appraisals of the challenge, novelty, and control afforded to them by the system, and their actions, mediated by the system's ability to provide feedback and customization options.</s><s xml:id="_RMZWTpV">However, we also saw the role of affect in positive and negative emotions, a finding similar to <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Kappelman (1995)</ref>, who identified attitude as a major component of his product/process matrix of system involvement.</s><s xml:id="_5KjyYEe">However, unlike Kappelman, our interest was in engagement as an experience; he studied it as an outcome of participants' level of involvement in software development.</s></p><p xml:id="_7VwYwNP"><s xml:id="_gpTrwjg">Interviewees disengaged for internal reasons that were physiological or based on time pressures and their inner voices to move on to other activities.</s><s xml:id="_b9Maqfw">External reasons for disengaging included interruptions in the environment and technology issues.</s><s xml:id="_JEqkuDp">During this phase, there was a mixture of positive and negative emotions expressed; at the same time, some participants mentioned that their emotions were dependent upon the situation and influenced by the interaction.</s></p><p xml:id="_RDSbhvb"><s xml:id="_m6SQzTP">Original to this study is the concept of reengagement.</s><s xml:id="_SSQSfjC">Participants described reengagement as both a short-term and long-term activity.</s><s xml:id="_dgh2Mff">Short-term reengagements were precipitated by interviewees' decisions to pause the activity to attend to other needs or stretch the task out over time, and by the technology or environmental factors disengaging them before they were ready.</s><s xml:id="_RxzVnZ9">With regard to reengagement, attributes such as convenience and ease of use, the need for information, and novelty were most salient.</s><s xml:id="_T7Ws9f4">Users returned to the application because they had past success with it, or it offered them something new (a product or an experience) that could not be obtained elsewhere, and was able to provide adequate levels of control, challenge, and feedback to ensure interviewees were neither bored nor frustrated.</s><s xml:id="_9UuhZWg">Overall, positive experiences influenced participants' likelihood of returning to an application <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Rozell &amp; Gardner, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">Webster &amp; Ahuja, 2004)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_UtgPHwM"><s xml:id="_k4jxQsP">Participants described several factors that prevented engagement from taking place, or caused their engagement to lapse; nonengagement has not been addressed in previous studies.</s><s xml:id="_fNdaYg4">These included the inability of the online experience to emulate a real-life encounter, technology issues such as information overload and pop-ups, communication tools that delayed feedback, and being required to multitask or manage interruptions.</s><s xml:id="_Jd7dXdH">Although <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">Webster and Ho (1997)</ref> found evidence for higher levels of engagement with more interactive applications, the amount of interactivity was not indicative of engagement in this study.</s><s xml:id="_H7my2hx">Rather, it was the quality and appropriateness of the interactivity to the user's task that precipitated engagement.</s><s xml:id="_Te2vzfE">This is supported by <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Jacques et al. (1995)</ref>, who found that students' preferences for visual-or text-based educational multimedia depended on the task they needed to perform, and by <ref type="bibr">Skelly et al. (1994)</ref>, who warned that more interface features and choices do not necessarily lead to engagement.</s></p><p xml:id="_DndZCxj"><s xml:id="_4NPeNxv">Overall, when engagement occurred, participants described cycling through a dynamic process of initiating and sustaining their engagement until internal or external circumstances disengaged them.</s><s xml:id="_RS9Dxn6">However, they often experienced multiple engaging episodes during the same session, or returned to the application in subsequent sessions.</s><s xml:id="_e9JJQb5">This likelihood of return is a strong predictor of systems success <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(DeLone &amp; McLean, 1992)</ref>, and likely of whether systems are engaging.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_8Fs5vtG">Attributes of engagement.</head><p xml:id="_8a7ruxw"><s xml:id="_PXRGdAf">Central to this research was identifying the attributes of engagement.</s><s xml:id="_N4uz8fK">Interwoven throughout the engagement process were a variety of attributes: attention, novelty, interest, control, feedback, and challenge.</s><s xml:id="_fcdfME3">In addition, we found evidence for emotional (affect and motivation), sensory (aesthetics and interactivity), and spatiotemporal (perception of time, and self-and external awareness) threads of experience.</s><s xml:id="_KpQbQuA">These findings both confirm and dispute previous research.</s><s xml:id="_6QfxzhV">We found evidence for more attributes during the engagement phase than Webster and colleagues <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">(Webster &amp; Ahuja, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b63">Webster &amp; Ho, 1997)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Jacques et al. (1995)</ref>, who concluded that engagement was composed of three elements: attention focus, curiosity, and intrinsic interest.</s><s xml:id="_gDy6Gnp"><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Skelly et al. (1994)</ref> suggested that engaging experiences were comprised of curiosity, feedback, and challenge, while <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">Webster and Ho (1997)</ref> concluded that feedback, challenge, and novelty, but not perceived control were attributes of engaging presentation software.</s><s xml:id="_SJYSZBH">However, we found evidence to suggest that users do need to perceive they are in control of the interaction (see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Said, 2004)</ref>, though some of our participants were comfortable with some unpredictability, which likely is applicationspecific.</s></p><p xml:id="_pH5SJVr"><s xml:id="_KY2evza">Our findings are inline with other research that has emphasised self-directed, meaningful involvement with materials or applications based on cognitive challenge and motivation <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Kearsley &amp; Schneiderman, 1999)</ref> because participants across applications needed personal (e.g., interest) or external incentives (e.g., tangible product, rewards in a game) to continue their tasks and adequate levels of physical or cognitive challenge.</s><s xml:id="_z7uBywc">Like <ref type="bibr">Carroll and Thomas (1988)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Pausch et al. (1994)</ref>, our study found that engagement failed to begin or was curtailed when systems were perceived by the user as either too difficult or too easy to use.</s><s xml:id="_TVG82EB"><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">Wells and Matthews (1994)</ref> state that attention may be based on the cognitive judgements people make about the relevance of specific stimuli to themselves or their tasks.</s><s xml:id="_uwnzTh2">This was the case with our participants who attended to interface features that would enable them to efficiently complete a task or to content on the interface that resonated with their personal interests.</s></p><p xml:id="_u3szVCB"><s xml:id="_5NFDdvr">Novelty played an important role in this study in sustaining users' engagements with the applications.</s><s xml:id="_HamX89T">For video gamers, this took the form of unexpected auditory or visual stimuli <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Aboulafia &amp; Bannon, 2004)</ref>; shoppers were interested in seeing new products, and webcast viewers and Web searchers sought new content.</s><s xml:id="_X2JjDbw">However, there was a ceiling for novelty <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">(Webster &amp; Ho, 1997)</ref>, because participants did not wish for so much Feedback was shown to be an essential component for inciting and maintaining engagement.</s><s xml:id="_n8GZx4x">Feedback is inextricably linked to communication whether between a human and an artefact, or between several humans using the technology and awareness of others.</s><s xml:id="_BZagUbM">In the webcast environment, for example, participants underscored their ability to interact with other remote viewers and individuals at the host institution.</s><s xml:id="_Gq4xuE9">This is not surprising given people's strong bias for socialization <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Picard, 1997)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_WgGaQcf">Participants also demonstrated a need for tangible feedback (e.g., textual, visual, or aural) <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Pausch et al., 1994)</ref> that allowed them to orient themselves in a Web search or game, gauge their success in completing a shopping transaction, and see that their messages were received by others in the Webcasting environment.</s><s xml:id="_QXMkqws">However, it is apparent that the attributes of engagement identified in this study interest, motivation, affect, attention, challenge, feedback, aesthetics and sensory appeal, awareness, novelty, perceived control, perceived time, and interactivity are products of the user-system interaction.</s><s xml:id="_AFHeNYA">Some of these attributes are associated with usability variables of effectiveness, efficiency, and satisfaction.</s><s xml:id="_UkybjdY">This demonstrates that usability is intricately woven into the experience of engagement; while an application may be usable, it may not be engaging, but engaging applications do appear to have an inherent baseline of usability.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Dn5APNJ">Limitations</head><p xml:id="_XzdpvY3"><s xml:id="_usaQ4p4">The current findings are based on a selected sample of individuals at a specific point in time.</s><s xml:id="_6AC6jtM">As in most exploratory research, we cannot make absolute conclusions.</s><s xml:id="_8RzAyba">However, the findings are, for the most part, in accordance with previous literature, leading one to speculate about the potential for generalization.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_GTZSnwZ">Future Work</head><p xml:id="_zeMxVyr"><s xml:id="_c9PyVtz">The purpose of this study was not to compare engagement across the four applications, and we make no attempts, given our sample size per application, to do so.</s><s xml:id="_gy5QtvK">We observed all participants moving through the engagement process on much the same trajectory, and being impacted upon by the same attributes.</s><s xml:id="_hD4PqJR">However, we noted some differences among the groups.</s><s xml:id="_8NuqxRT">For example, video gamers seemed to have more difficulty disengaging than users of other applications, and were more likely to want more challenging experiences.</s><s xml:id="_w6GHpxn">One area of future research is examining the model more systematically within each of the application domains.</s><s xml:id="_Z8qk2Ad">Potentially, for example, the intensity of an attribute may vary with the application.</s><s xml:id="_tuApDUv">In addition, the specific notion of disengagement is also of interest and pertains to computer addiction <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Charlton (2002)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_QSk7k4z">When, if ever, does intense engagement cross the line into addiction?</s></p><p xml:id="_EfNKTk9"><s xml:id="_UpZkAYK">There are attributes (e.g., challenge, feedback, perceived control) that are components of not only engagement, but also usability.</s><s xml:id="_uTZt5UB">Future work will examine the relationship between these two constructs.</s><s xml:id="_tY5dGu6"><ref type="bibr">Quesenbury (2003)</ref> suggests that engagement, along with effectiveness, efficiency, ease of learning, and error tolerance, are dimensions of usability.</s><s xml:id="_PjcVfs6">It is our conjecture that usability facilitates engagement, but a usable system may not be engaging.</s><s xml:id="_JhnxP8k">Thus we view engagement as a higher order experience that encompasses more than usability.</s><s xml:id="_BWUj9Kc">The fact that our participants described aesthetics, novelty, endurability, and so forth supports this.</s></p><p xml:id="_8qpqWW9"><s xml:id="_eJVvGHP">One of the major gaps in the literature on engagement is in empirical evidence about how it should be measured <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">(Webster &amp; Ho, 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Jacques et al., 1995)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_vBZRRU9">Thus far attempts have been incomplete, nongeneralizable, or one-dimensional.</s><s xml:id="_cr4Hzmp">Our future goals are to develop and rigorously test an instrument to assess users' perceived engagement.</s><s xml:id="_XNKE7k9">In addition, we intend to triangulate this subjective measure with behavioral and physiological (e.g., heart rate, galvanic skin response) methods.</s><s xml:id="_WF3nqV6">Studies have been conducted to explore entertainment and emotion (cf.</s><s xml:id="_Pr8ebPU"><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Mandryk, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Mandryk, Atkins, &amp; Inkpen, 2006</ref>) using these techniques.</s><s xml:id="_qVgDhaF">This will provide a holistic view of engagement that encompasses all of the threads of user experience.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_F82NYUD">CONCLUSION</head><p xml:id="_cAWqNys"><s xml:id="_xMcgGWn">This research provides insights into the phenomenon of engagement and is a foundation for further research.</s><s xml:id="_KcM3h5b">We have confirmed and expounded a conceptual model that views engagement as a process in which computer users initiate and sustain engagement, disengage with the application or task, and potentially reengage several times during a single interaction with an application.</s><s xml:id="_bCnkJAx">The process is defined by the presence of multiple attributes that vary in intensity depending on a combination of user and system attributes that emerge during the interaction.</s><s xml:id="_hxRfZE3">We have put forward a model that defines which attributes of engagement are most prominent during each phase in the process.</s><s xml:id="_sHVsRS6">We have highlighted attributes including attention, aesthetics, interest, challenge, control, motivation, novelty, and feedback as the user, system, and interaction components of the compositional, emotional, sensual, and spatiotemporal aspects of users' experience that predict and facilitate engagement.</s><s xml:id="_3M96rkj">Our work has acknowledged the derivation of engagement from other constructs, such as flow, aesthetic experience, play, and information interaction and concluded that, while it shares attributes with these other frameworks, its combination and expression of components is unique.</s><s xml:id="_VywUguB">We have also demonstrated that engagement is consistent across different types of applications in terms of the attributes present and the trajectory followed by users through the process.</s></p></div>		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_dauB5Dc">APPENDIX A: SEMISTRUCTURED INTERVIEW QUESTIONS</head><p xml:id="_zMmMYzc"><s xml:id="_UFMBv37">Note: These questions were used for the Web searching interviews and were modified slightly to accommodate users of the other three applications.</s></p><p xml:id="_nJrqTHX"><s xml:id="_axpvtHf">There are times when we become so involved surfing the Web that nothing else seems to matter; we lose track of time and our surroundings because we become so focused on the search experience.</s></p><p xml:id="_fGEAQdU"><s xml:id="_b2NQApt">1. Can you recall a time when you felt this way while using the Web? Probes: a) What topic were you searching?</s><s xml:id="_DxuVqYZ">b) What Web site were you looking at? c) Where were you when you were using the Web? d) Can you estimate how long you were on the Web for?</s><s xml:id="_HxkfTPD">2.In this particular situation, was looking for information on the Web a voluntary or mandatory activity for you?</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_TW345wB">Problem solving</head><p xml:id="_tZ6Bkcf"><s xml:id="_am2YDkU">The participant employs analytical thinking in using the technology.</s></p><p xml:id="_zaTNkgC"><s xml:id="_CZ7Uppk">Relevance ability (as of an information-retrieval system) to retrieve -Webster Online)</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_NzqfEQr">Time</head><p xml:id="_9bCTqT3"><s xml:id="_FQRz4Ma">Estimated time spent on task; may also refer to having sufficient or insufficient time to complete a task</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_znTSm3w">Predictable</head><p xml:id="_tfbRhCp"><s xml:id="_V6zEEEG">The participant asserts or estimates that something will occur based on past experience.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_rbfUPzh">Serendipity</head><p xml:id="_TMqB8kR"><s xml:id="_xxXV6Sc">The participant makes an unexpected discovery while using the technology.</s></p><p xml:id="_QN6gDJ6"><s xml:id="_SpcPzbu">Ease of use The participant describes the technology as being usable or easy to use.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_URmga9k">Fantasy (Merriam-Webster Online)</head><p xml:id="_raYRxBh"><s xml:id="_nVEg2Rv">Immersion enveloped by, included in, and interacting with an environment <ref type="bibr">(Witmer &amp; Singer, 1998, p. 227</ref>)</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_gnxfj9s">Interactivity</head><p xml:id="_VGYYYpu"><s xml:id="_qFzsUUK">The degree of information exchange between systems and users <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Huang, 2003)</ref> Social</s></p><p xml:id="_bkynVRF"><s xml:id="_5FWdqst">The participant describes social or community aspects of using interface or performing task.</s><s xml:id="_QbwyUfp">Disengagement (external)</s></p><p xml:id="_2QZvqph"><s xml:id="_knqswxj">The participant stops task due to an event in the external environment.</s><s xml:id="_U2ZXYBR">Disengagement (self)</s></p><p xml:id="_fy5AREP"><s xml:id="_zGWz7r6">The participant stops a task voluntarily or for internal reasons.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_PDCcRGY">Engagement</head><p xml:id="_3XWkmXh"><s xml:id="_VpUjUkK">The participant describes being engaged or involved with the interface or task.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_endHP9d">Likelihood of return</head><p xml:id="_vfsX7cS"><s xml:id="_JZ6BQ4J">The participant indicates they would use the technology in future.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_KEZ9pFh">Point of engagement</head><p xml:id="_U5CFfGb"><s xml:id="_Qyqk5D9">The point at which the participant experienced becoming engaged in a task or interface attributes Genre Acategory of technology composition characterized by a particular style, form, or content; e.g., newspaper as a form of document</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_2vmBxwC">Organization</head><p xml:id="_F5dUegZ"><s xml:id="_qN736Y3">The participant comments on the arrangement and structure of the technology.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_C3BqYZY">Affect (negative)</head><p xml:id="_A4kmHxH"><s xml:id="_5JvuS2w">Affect is the emotional investment a user makes in order to be immersed in an environment and sustain their involvement in the environment; this variable describes a negative response.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_jSxECsF">Affect (neutral)</head><p xml:id="_HGUJerp"><s xml:id="_s3SM74w">Affect is the emotional investment a user makes in order to be immersed in an environment and sustain their involvement in the environment; this variable describes a neutral response.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Hf3hxke">Affect (positive)</head><p xml:id="_Pjxjx6N"><s xml:id="_nXMFGFA">Affect is the emotional investment a user makes in order to be immersed in an environment and sustain their involvement in the environment; this variable describes a positive response.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_dMVJqwK">Fatigue</head><p xml:id="_hSgZXbK"><s xml:id="_C4dfvB5">Weariness, exhaustion</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_HxVKCn2">Interruptibility</head><p xml:id="_gPWY5dw"><s xml:id="_UbkuMDP">The participant describes him/herself as being susceptible to distraction.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_fG86NP8">Learning preference</head><p xml:id="_FcterXu"><s xml:id="_x6Hy6zt">The participant points out something about the technology that fits or does not fit the way they prefer to process information.</s><s xml:id="_hk9PwR4">Pleasure Delight, joy, gratification (Merriam-Webster Online)</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_gC7a7rU">Understanding affect in design: An outline conceptual framework</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Aboulafia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bannon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/1463922031000086708</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_b4gWndx">Theoretical Issues in Ergonomic Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Aboulafia, A., &amp; Bannon, L.J. (2004). Understanding affect in design: An outline conceptual framework. Theoretical Issues in Ergonomic Science, 5(1), 4</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_wRAjMQM">Hedonic shopping motivations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Arnold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Reynolds</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0022-4359(03)00007-1</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_fMupypq">Journal of Retailing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">77</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Arnold, M. J., &amp; Reynolds, K.E. (2003). Hedonic shopping motivations. Journal of Retailing, 79, 77</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_HBnD4PX">Individual characteristics associated with World Wide Web user: An empirical study of playfulness and motivation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Atkinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kydd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1145/264701.264705</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_4URVkRH">The DATA BASE for Advances in Information Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">53</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Atkinson, M., &amp; Kydd, C. (1997). Individual characteristics associated with World Wide Web user: An empirical study of playfulness and motivation. The DATA BASE for Advances in Information Systems, 28(2), 53</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Beardsely</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_9Zh8f7Y">The aesthetic point of view</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Ithaca, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cornell University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Beardsely, M. (1982). The aesthetic point of view. Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_PujDDmr">Funology: From usability to enjoyment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Blythe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Overbeeke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Monk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<publisher>Kluwer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Dordrecht, The Netherlands</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Blythe, M., Overbeeke, K., Monk, A.F., &amp; Wright, P.C. (2003). Funology: From usability to enjoyment (Vol. 3). Dordrecht, The Netherlands: Kluwer.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_XyJBNTh">A grounded investigation of game immersion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Cairns</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1145/985921.986048</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_N6fDEtt">Proceedings of the Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>
		<meeting>the Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems<address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004. 1297 1300</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Brown, E., &amp; Cairns, P. (2004). A grounded investigation of game immersion. In Proceedings of the Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (pp. 1297 1300). New York: ACM.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Caroll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_tFBjEVc">Fun. SIGCHI Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Caroll, J.M., &amp; Thomas, J.C. (1988). Fun. SIGCHI Bulletin, 19(3), 21</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_9bFKZfF">Applying game design theory to virtual heritage environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Champion</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1145/604471.604532</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_x8Muesx">Proceedings of the First International Conference on Computer Graphics and Interactive Techniques</title>
		<meeting>the First International Conference on Computer Graphics and Interactive Techniques<address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="273" to="274" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Champion, E. (2003). Applying game design theory to virtual heritage environments. In Proceedings of the First International Conference on Computer Graphics and Interactive Techniques (pp. 273 274). New York: ACM.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_feU6wXe">Models of engagement: Intrinsically motivated interaction with multimedia learning software</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Chapman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<pubPlace>Waterloo, Canada</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Waterloo</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Unpublished master&apos;s thesis</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Chapman, P. (1997). Models of engagement: Intrinsically motivated interaction with multimedia learning software. Unpublished master&apos;s thesis, University of Waterloo, Waterloo, Canada.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_p6M6Qft">Engagement in multimedia training systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Chapman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Selvarajah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Webster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/hicss.1999.772808</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_cMUe6hU">Proceedings of the 32nd Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences</title>
		<meeting>the 32nd Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences<address><addrLine>Washington, DC</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1084">1999. 1084</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Chapman, P., Selvarajah, S., &amp; Webster, J. (1999). Engagement in multimedia training systems. In Proceedings of the 32nd Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences (p. 1084). Washington, DC: IEEE.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_sTRfKPZ">A factor-and engagement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Charlton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_HhekmbH">British Journal of Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="329" to="344" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Charlton, J.P. (2002). A factor- and engagement. British Journal of Psychology, 93(3), 329 344.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_7bTEV9A">Why people continue to play online games: In search of critical design factors to increase customer loyalty to online contests</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_fHyS8mb">Cyber Psychology and Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="24" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Choi, D., &amp; Kim, J. (2004). Why people continue to play online games: In search of critical design factors to increase customer loyalty to online contests. Cyber Psychology and Behavior, 7(1), 11 24</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_PWU8WgM">Flow: The psychology of optimal experience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Csikszentmihalyi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<publisher>Harper &amp; Row</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Csikszentmihalyi, M. (1990). Flow: The psychology of optimal experience. New York: Harper &amp; Row.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_2cbG7bv">Information systems success: The quest for the dependent variable</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Delone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mclean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1287/isre.3.1.60</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_RJ8usTe">Information Systems Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="60" to="95" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">DeLone, W.H., &amp; McLean, E.R. (1992). Information systems success: The quest for the dependent variable. Information Systems Research, 3(1), 60 95</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_dt5Bf5r">The pleasure principle: Immersion, engagement, flow</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Douglas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hargadon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_ekT7sCZ">Proceedings of ACM Hypertext 2000</title>
		<meeting>ACM Hypertext 2000<address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="153" to="160" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Douglas, Y., &amp; Hargadon, A. (2000). The pleasure principle: Immersion, engagement, flow. In Proceedings of ACM Hypertext 2000 (pp. 153 160). New York: ACM.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_4tDA3YC">Protocol analysis: Verbal reports as data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ericsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Rev. Ed.</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ericsson, K.A., &amp; Simon, H.A. (1993). Protocol analysis: Verbal reports as data. (Rev. Ed.). London: MIT Press.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_NcPyfu6">person-artefact-task (PAT) model of flow antecedents in computer-mediated environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Finneran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_T9fSZ4U">International Journal of Human-Computer Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="475" to="496" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Finneran, C.M., &amp; Zhang, P. (2003). person-artefact-task (PAT) model of flow antecedents in computer-mediated environments. International Journal of Human-Computer Studies, 59(4), 475 496.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ufdYCfu">Task characteristics and the experience of optimal flow in human-computer interaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ghani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Deshpande</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/00223980.1994.9712742</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_gU3fz5z">The Journal of Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="381" to="391" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ghani, J.A., &amp; Deshpande, S.P. (1994). Task characteristics and the experience of optimal flow in human-computer interaction. The Journal of Psychology, 128(4), 381 391.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_zNjVSut">User experience: A research agenda</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hassenzahl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Tractinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/01449290500330331</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_hyJjC8q">Behaviour and Information Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">91</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hassenzahl, M., &amp; Tractinsky, N. (2006). User experience: A research agenda. Behaviour and Information Technology, 25(2), 91</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_xQvu6wX">Designing Web site attributes to induce experiential encounters</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0747-5632(02)00080-8</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_F4padfD">Computers in Human Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="425" to="442" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Huang, M. (2003). Designing Web site attributes to induce experiential encounters. Computers in Human Behavior, 19(4), 425 442.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_gwAr8Uf">Designing engaging experiences with children and artists</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hull</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Reid</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_9VqWEZH">Funology: From usability to enjoyment</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Blythe</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Monk</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Overbeeke</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Dordrecht, The Netherlands</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Kluwer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="179" to="187" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hull, R., &amp; Reid, J. (2003). Designing engaging experiences with children and artists. In M.A.Blythe, A.F.Monk, K.Overbeeke, &amp; P.C.Wright (Eds.), Funology: From usability to enjoyment (pp. 179 187). Dordrecht, The Netherlands: Kluwer.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_cWzNuvY">Engagement as a design concept for multimedia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Jacques</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Preece</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Carey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_pG2seBu">Canadian Journal of Educational Communication</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="59" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Jacques, R., Preece, J., &amp; Carey, T. (1995). Engagement as a design concept for multimedia. Canadian Journal of Educational Communication, 24(1), 49 59</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_b6FNagN">Theory and models for creating engaging and immersive ecommerce Web sites</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jennings</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1145/333334.333358</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_3WDFACP">Proceedings of the 2000 ACM SIGCPR Conference on Computer Personnel Research</title>
		<meeting>the 2000 ACM SIGCPR Conference on Computer Personnel Research<address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="85" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Jennings, M. (2000). Theory and models for creating engaging and immersive ecommerce Web sites. In Proceedings of the 2000 ACM SIGCPR Conference on Computer Personnel Research (pp. 77 85). New York: ACM.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_xAnAYDP">Measuring user involvement: A diffusion of innovation perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kappelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_we79xyv">Database Advances</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2/3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">65</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kappelman, L.A. (1995). Measuring user involvement: A diffusion of innovation perspective. Database Advances, 26(2/3), 65</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_KAXpaDF">Engagement theory: A framework for technologybased teaching and learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kearsley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Schneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999-02-15">1999. 5 April, 1999. Retrieved 15 February, 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kearsley, G., &amp; Schneiderman, B. (1999). Engagement theory: A framework for technology- based teaching and learning. 5 April, 1999. Retrieved 15 February, 2005, from</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_HKasT7r">The experience of flow in interacting with a hypermedia learning environment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Konradt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sulz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_7qRnDHm">Journal of Educational Multimedia and Hypermedia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="69" to="84" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Konradt, U., &amp; Sulz, K. (2001). The experience of flow in interacting with a hypermedia learning environment. Journal of Educational Multimedia and Hypermedia, 10(1), 69 84</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_psHJMnk">Transcendent experience in the use of computer-based media</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Laarni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ravaja</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kallinen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Saari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_5GeANDC">Proceedings of the Third Nordic Conference on Human-Computer Interaction</title>
		<meeting>the Third Nordic Conference on Human-Computer Interaction<address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="409" to="412" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Laarni, J., Ravaja, N., Kallinen, K., &amp; Saari, T. (2004). Transcendent experience in the use of computer-based media. In Proceedings of the Third Nordic Conference on Human-Computer Interaction (pp. 409 412). New York: ACM.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_BMGW5Db">Computers as theatre</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Laurel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Reading, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Laurel, B. (1993). Computers as theatre. Reading, MA: Addison-Wesley.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_FcC8mXw">Assessing dimensions of pervieved visual aesthetics of Web sites</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lavie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Tractinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_jRQjHsj">International Journal of Human-Computer Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="269" to="298" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lavie, T., &amp; Tractinsky, N. (2004). Assessing dimensions of pervieved visual aesthetics of Web sites. International Journal of Human-Computer Studies, 60(3), 269 298.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Q5WNZne">Does collaborative hypertext support better engagement in learning the basics of informatics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Makkonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_dC9anzH">SIGCSE Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="130" to="132" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Makkonen, P. (1997). Does collaborative hypertext support better engagement in learning the basics of informatics? SIGCSE Bulletin, 29(3), 130 132.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mandel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_wNxypJv">The elements of user interface design</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mandel, T. (1997). The elements of user interface design. New York: Wiley.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_XwQctba">Objectively evaluating entertainment technology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mandryk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1145/985921.985977</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_nHpuECb">Proceedings of the Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>
		<meeting>the Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems<address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1057" to="1058" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mandryk, R.L. (2004). Objectively evaluating entertainment technology. In Proceedings of the Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (pp. 1057 1058). New York: ACM.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_G452j6V">A continuous and objective evaluation of emotional experience with interactive play environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mandryk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Atkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Inkpen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_A8QCWWV">Proceedings of the Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>
		<meeting>the Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems<address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1027" to="1036" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mandryk, R.L., Atkins, M.S., &amp; Inkpen, K. (2006). A continuous and objective evaluation of emotional experience with interactive play environments. In Proceedings of the Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (pp. 1027 1036). New York: ACM.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_HcYmRzf">Information seeking in electronic environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Marchionini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1017/cbo9780511626388</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Marchionini, G. (1995). Information seeking in electronic environments. New York: Cambridge University Press.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Matlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_t3U9zex">Cognition</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Orlando, Florida</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Harcourt Brace</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>3rd ed.</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Matlin, M.W. (1994). Cognition (3rd ed.). Orlando, Florida: Harcourt Brace.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_t42gjA2">Technology as experience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mccarthy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.7551/mitpress/6687.001.0001</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, Massachusetts</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">McCarthy, J., &amp; Wright, P. (2004). Technology as experience. Cambridge, Massachusetts: MIT Press.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Miriam-Webster</forename><surname>Online</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.m-w.com/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006-05-20">2006. May 20, 2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Miriam-Webster Online (2006). Retrieved May 20, 2006 from http://www.m-w.com/</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_fJ4jXmq">Information and emotion: The emergent affective paradigm in information behavior research and theory</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/03615260802418922</idno>
		<editor>Nahl, D., &amp; Bilal, D.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<publisher>Information Today</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Medford, NJ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nahl, D., &amp; Bilal, D. (Eds.). (2007). Information and emotion: The emergent affective paradigm in information behavior research and theory. Medford, NJ: Information Today</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_bwgTuKk">Cognitive engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Norman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1201/b15703-3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_SfnqrW3">User centred system design</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Norman</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Draper</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Hillsdale, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="61" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Norman, D.A. (1986). Cognitive engineering. In D.A.Norman &amp; S.W.Draper (Eds.), User centred system design (pp. 31 61). Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ujzXxqe">Affect and machine design: Lessons for the development of anourmous machines</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Norman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ortony</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Russel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_BcrrtAq">IBM Systems Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">421</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">38</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Norman, D.A., Ortony, A., &amp; Russel, S M. (2003). Affect and machine design: Lessons for the development of anourmous machines. IBM Systems Journal, 421(1), 38</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Oppenheim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_Ax6Vv24">Questionnaire design, interviewing, and attitude measurement</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Printer Publishers</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Oppenheim, A.N. (1992). Questionnaire design, interviewing, and attitude measurement. London: Printer Publishers.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_acv69tA">Let&apos;s make things engaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Overbeeke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Djajadiningrat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hummels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wensveen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Frens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_T3z7bm7">Funology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Blythe</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Monk</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Overbeeke</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Dordrecht, The Netherlands</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Kluwer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="17" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Overbeeke, K., Djajadiningrat, T., Hummels, C., Wensveen, S., &amp; Frens, J. (2003). Let&apos;s make things engaging. In M.A.Blythe, A.F.Monk, K.Overbeeke, &amp; P.C.Wright (Eds.), Funology ( pp. 7 17). Dordrecht, The Netherlands: Kluwer.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_hFyRCwZ">What HCI designers can learn from video game designers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Pausch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Skelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Thiel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1145/259963.260220</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_KgwgUtw">Proceedings of the Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Plaisant</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting>the Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems<address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="178" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Pausch, R., Gold, R., Skelly, T.C., &amp; Thiel, D. (1994). What HCI designers can learn from video game designers. In C.Plaisant (Ed.), Proceedings of the Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (pp. 177 178). New York: ACM.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_YyjtPrW">Affective computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Picard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<publisher>The MIT Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Picard, R.W. (1997). Affective computing. Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_EDXvVSh">Dimensions of usability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Quesenbery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4324/9781410607409</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_vhTVW9K">Content and complexity: Information design in technical communications</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Albers</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mazur</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Mahwah, N.J.</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81" to="102" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Quesenbery, W. (2003). Dimensions of usability. In M.Albers &amp; B.Mazur (Eds.), Content and complexity: Information design in technical communications (pp. 81 102). Mahwah, N.J.: Lawrence Erlbaum.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_5Kn2zBr">Emotional response patterns and sense of presence during video games: Potential criterion variables for game design</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ravaja</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Salminen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Saari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Laarni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Holopainen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jarvinen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1145/1028014.1028068</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_GrFutUE">Proceedings of the Third Nordic Conference on Human-Computer Interaction</title>
		<meeting>the Third Nordic Conference on Human-Computer Interaction<address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="339" to="347" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ravaja, N., Salminen, M., Saari, T., Laarni, J., Holopainen, J., &amp; Jarvinen, A. (2004). Emotional response patterns and sense of presence during video games: Potential criterion variables for game design. In Proceedings of the Third Nordic Conference on Human-Computer Interaction (pp. 339 347). New York: ACM.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_5adMA4V">Endurability, engagement and expectations: Measuring children&apos;s fun</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Read</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Macfarlane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Casey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_UcWz4Zg">Proceedings of the International Workshop on</title>
		<meeting>the International Workshop on<address><addrLine>Eindhoven, The Netherlands</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Shaker Publishing</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002-08">2002, August 28 29</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="189" to="198" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Read, J., MacFarlane, S., &amp; Casey, C. (2002, August 28 29). Endurability, engagement and expectations: Measuring children&apos;s fun. In Proceedings of the International Workshop on (pp. 189 198). Eindhoven, The Netherlands: Shaker Publishing.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_mG3fX7Q">Seriously considering play: Designing interactive learning environments based on the blending of microworlds, simulations, and games</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Rieber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_38WVt4G">Educational Technology Research and Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">45</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rieber, L.P. (1996). Seriously considering play: Designing interactive learning environments based on the blending of microworlds, simulations, and games. Educational Technology Research and Development, 44(2), 45</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_c7Zszn7">Cognitive, motivation, and affective processes associated with computer related performance: A path analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rozell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gardner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0747-5632(99)00054-0</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_8JQC8Mm">Computers in Human Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="222" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rozell, E.J., &amp; Gardner, W.L. (2000). Cognitive, motivation, and affective processes associated with computer related performance: A path analysis. Computers in Human Behavior, 16(2), 199 222.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_NTwcfmD">An engaging multimedia design model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Said</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_KunNupf">Proceedings of the 2004 Conference on Interaction Design and Children</title>
		<meeting>the 2004 Conference on Interaction Design and Children<address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="169" to="172" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Said, N.S. (2004). An engaging multimedia design model. In Proceedings of the 2004 Conference on Interaction Design and Children (pp. 169 172). New York: ACM.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_hFQtjTZ">Critical engagement with technology in the computer classroom</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Salvo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_fBxKvHR">Technical Communication Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="317" to="337" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Salvo, M.J. (2002). Critical engagement with technology in the computer classroom. Technical Communication Quarterly, 11(3), 317 337.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_xMHTmv9">Direct manipulation for comprehensible, predictable and controllable user interfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Schneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1145/238218.238281</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_BCdmDZc">Designing the user interface</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Reading, MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="39" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>3rd ed.</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Schneiderman, B. (1997). Direct manipulation for comprehensible, predictable and controllable user interfaces. In Designing the user interface (3rd ed., pp. 33 39). Reading, MA: Addison- Wesley.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Schneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Plaisant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_XMBxFR5">Designing the user interface</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Boston, MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Pearson</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>4th ed.</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Schneiderman, B., &amp; Plaisant, C. (2005). Designing the user interface (4th ed.). Boston, MA: Pearson.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_cWkMDhc">Information interaction design: A unified field theory of design</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Shedroff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.nathan.com/thoughts/unified/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994-09-12">1994. 12 September, 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Shedroff, N. (1994). Information interaction design: A unified field theory of design. Retrieved 12 September, 2005 from http://www.nathan.com/thoughts/unified/</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_XqwD4dG">Seductive interfaces: Satisfying a mass audience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Skelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Fries</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Linnett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Nass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Reeves</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1145/259963.260452</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_x8RMMZZ">Proceedings of the Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Plaisant</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting>the Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems<address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="359" to="360" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Skelly, T.C., Fries, K., Linnett, B., Nass, C., &amp; Reeves, B. (1994). Seductive interfaces: Satisfying a mass audience. In C.Plaisant (Ed.), Proceedings of the Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (pp. 359 360). New York: ACM.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_VwsPeEt">Play theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Stephenson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_RQQwvJh">The play theory of mass communication</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Chicago</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1967">1967</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="65" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Stephenson, W. (1967). Play theory. In The play theory of mass communication (pp. 45 65). Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_ht9Gqpq">User interface design and evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Jarrett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Woodroffe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Minocha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufman</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Stone, D., Jarrett, C., Woodroffe, M., &amp; Minocha, S. (2005). User interface design and evaluation. London: Morgan Kaufman.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_eZ5eZYw">Basics of qualitative research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Strauss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Corbin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<publisher>Sage</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Thousand Oaks, CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Strauss, A.L., &amp; Corbin, J. (1990). Basics of qualitative research. Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_f3h7rg4">What motivates browsing?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Toms</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1046/j.1365-2532.1999.00240-8.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_9vhuye8">Exploring the contexts of information behaviour</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Allen</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Taylor Graham</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="208" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Toms, E.G. (1998). What motivates browsing? In T.D.Wilson &amp; D.K.Allen (Eds.), Exploring the contexts of information behaviour (pp. 191 208). London: Taylor Graham.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_YyGM24x">Understanding and facilitating the browsing of electronic text</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Toms</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_hu7dMCy">International Journal of Human Computer Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="423" to="452" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Toms, E.G. (2000). Understanding and facilitating the browsing of electronic text. International Journal of Human Computer Studies, 52(3), 423 452.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_uFSdrWD">Information interaction: Providing a framework for information architecture</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Toms</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_tFHQtkb">Journal of the American Society for Information Science and Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="855" to="862" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Toms, E.G. (2002). Information interaction: Providing a framework for information architecture. Journal of the American Society for Information Science and Technology, 53(10), 855 862.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_KW2gjQe">Explaining the enjoyment of playing video games: The role of competition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Vorderer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hartmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Klimmt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_UksQFkZ">Proceedings of the Second International Conference on Entertainment Computing</title>
		<meeting>the Second International Conference on Entertainment Computing<address><addrLine>Pittsburgh, PA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="9" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Carnegie Mellon University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Vorderer, P., Hartmann, T., &amp; Klimmt, C. (2003). Explaining the enjoyment of playing video games: The role of competition. In Proceedings of the Second International Conference on Entertainment Computing (pp. 1 9). Pittsburgh, PA: Carnegie Mellon University.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_EH7ApKk">Enhancing the design of Web navigation systems: The influence of user disorientation on engagement and performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Webster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ahuja</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Unpublished manuscript</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Webster, J., &amp; Ahuja, J.S. (2004). Enhancing the design of Web navigation systems: The influence of user disorientation on engagement and performance. Unpublished manuscript.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_kC3MvDK">Audience engagement in multimedia presentations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Webster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1145/264701.264706</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Guz4sFa">The DATA BASE for Advances in Information Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">63</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Webster, J., &amp; Ho, H. (1997). Audience engagement in multimedia presentations. The DATA BASE for Advances in Information Systems, 28(2), 63</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_yzA8kCV">Attention: Selection of complex, personally significant and emotional stimuli</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wells</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Matthews</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_FyPnn5q">Attention and Emotion: A Clinical Perspective</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Hove, UK</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="60" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Wells, A., &amp; Matthews, G. (1994). Attention: Selection of complex, personally significant and emotional stimuli. In Attention and Emotion: A Clinical Perspective (pp. 45 60). Hove, UK: Lawrence Erlbaum.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_e3zXqPY">Measuring presence in vitual environments: A presence questionnaire</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Witmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Singer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_QNJgjQj">Presence</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="225" to="240" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Witmer, B.G. &amp; Singer, M.J. (1998). Measuring presence in vitual environments: A presence questionnaire. Presence, 7(3), 225 240.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Ax6MFKe">Exploring the theoretical foundations of playfulness in computer interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Woszczynski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Roth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Segars</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_w3WgZnE">Computers in Human Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="369" to="388" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Woszczynski, A.B., Roth, P.L., &amp; Segars, A.H. (2002). Exploring the theoretical foundations of playfulness in computer interactions. Computers in Human Behavior, 18(4), 369 388.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_73cqm8e">Making sense of experience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mccarthy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Meekison</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_KYvBhRy">Funology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Blythe</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Monk</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Overbeeke</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Dordrecht, The Netherlands</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Kluwer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="53" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Wright, P.C., McCarthy, J., &amp; Meekison, L. (2003). Making sense of experience. In M.A.Blythe, A.F.Monk, K.Overbeeke, &amp; P.C.Wright (Eds.), Funology (pp. 43 53). Dordrecht, The Netherlands: Kluwer.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
