<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Y6SqVK9">Post-discharge follow-up using text messaging within an enhanced recovery program after colorectal surgery ଝ</title>
				<funder ref="#_HQjPWZ5">
					<orgName type="full">unknown</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Prix</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
					<p type="raw">© 2016 Elsevier Masson SAS. All rights reserved. © 2016 Elsevier Masson SAS. All rights reserved.</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2016-08-08">8 August 2016</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Carrier</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>a</label> Service de chirurgie digestive , CHU Estaing , 63003 Clermont-Ferrand , France</note>
								<orgName type="department">Service de chirurgie digestive</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CHU Estaing</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>63003</postCode>
									<settlement>Clermont-Ferrand</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cotte</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>b</label> Service de chirurgie digestive , Hôpitaux Sud , 69310 Lyon , France</note>
								<orgName type="department">Service de chirurgie digestive</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hôpitaux Sud</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>69310</postCode>
									<settlement>Lyon</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Beyer-Berjot</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>c</label> Service de chirurgie , Hôpital Nord , 13915 Marseille , France</note>
								<orgName type="department">Service de chirurgie</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hôpital Nord</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13915</postCode>
									<settlement>Marseille</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Faucheron</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>d</label> Service de chirurgie digestive , CHU de Grenoble , 38700 Grenoble , France</note>
								<orgName type="department">Service de chirurgie digestive</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CHU de Grenoble</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>38700</postCode>
									<settlement>Grenoble</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Joris</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>e</label> Service d&apos;anesthésie , CHU de Liège , 4000 Liège , Belgium</note>
								<orgName type="department">Service d&apos;anesthésie</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CHU de Liège</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>4000</postCode>
									<settlement>Liège</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Slim</surname></persName>
							<email>kslim@chu-clermontferrand.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation"><label>a</label> Service de chirurgie digestive , CHU Estaing , 63003 Clermont-Ferrand , France</note>
								<orgName type="department">Service de chirurgie digestive</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CHU Estaing</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>63003</postCode>
									<settlement>Clermont-Ferrand</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Francophone de Réhabilitation Améliorée après Chirurgie (GRACE)</note>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Francophone de Réhabilitation Améliorée après Chirurgie (GRACE)</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Service de chirurgie digestive , unité de chirurgie ambulatoire , CHU Estaing , 1 , place Lucie-Aubrac , 63003 Clermont-Ferrand , France.</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Service de chirurgie digestive</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">unité de chirurgie ambulatoire</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CHU Estaing</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1 place Lucie-Aubrac</addrLine>
									<postCode>63003</postCode>
									<settlement>Clermont-Ferrand</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qcNaETy">Post-discharge follow-up using text messaging within an enhanced recovery program after colorectal surgery ଝ</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2016-08-08">8 August 2016</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">FAC2780F6179514503A3895F8096BCA5</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jviscsurg.2016.05.016</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T11:31+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term xml:id="_B3aPk2u">message</term>
					<term xml:id="_MBy5NwS">Colorectal surgery</term>
					<term xml:id="_8yN9qT4">Enhanced recovery after surgery</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_3taaEuQ"><p xml:id="_WEjDTMh"><s xml:id="_ta8rGGB">Introduction: Enhanced recovery after surgery programs (ERP) often lead to early discharge and return to home.</s><s xml:id="_8BH4GBC">In terms of risk management, extended surveillance is recommended.</s><s xml:id="_Z2Eejhm">Surveillance using text messages (TM) has been validated for minor operations in ambulatory surgery.</s><s xml:id="_GnEZqNj">The goal of this study was to evaluate the feasibility of home surveillance by TM after colorectal surgery within an ERP.</s><s xml:id="_aNpnEJr">Methods: This prospective multicenter study involved the University hospitals of Clermont-Ferrand, Grenoble, Marseille and Lyon Sud between November 2014 and September 2015.</s><s xml:id="_kZnMA3U">All patients underwent colorectal surgery within an ERP.</s><s xml:id="_pzrZPCK">Post-discharge, patients received TM (4 simple questions with regard to pain, bowel movements, temperature and phlebitis) on days 1, 3 and 5.</s><s xml:id="_zP9TMBe">If there was abnormal or lack of response, an automatic alert was sent to the attending physician via Internet and the patient was contacted immediately.</s><s xml:id="_gKFP2bJ">Results: One hundred and eleven patients were included.</s><s xml:id="_bJVKyjY">Responses were obtained within a median of 12 (1-422) minutes, and 90% of patients answered all TM.</s><s xml:id="_nnuP3Pk">There were 48 alerts: 56% because of pain and 40% due to absence of response to the TM.</s><s xml:id="_SE6cRT2">Alerts led to in-hospital care for</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.27" lry="841.88"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.27" lry="841.88"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.27" lry="841.88"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.27" lry="841.88"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_9v3BChg">Introduction</head><p xml:id="_BZCaJaU"><s xml:id="_AzUWQrB">The enhanced recovery after surgery program (ERP) is a set of common everyday perioperative care elements, formerly referred to as ''fast track surgery'' <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_yZ9RyPJ">ERP management focuses on reduced morbidity and better-quality convalescence.</s><s xml:id="_6KpczGq">In addition to these advantages <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, ERP most often leads to shortened hospital stay, and raises the question of postoperative surveillance at home, within the framework of post-surgical risk management.</s><s xml:id="_V5PqVBz">Just as for ambulatory surgery where patients are contacted the day after surgery by a nurse, it is important to set up a system for postoperative surveillance in this setting as well.</s></p><p xml:id="_VjpczQY"><s xml:id="_XFECrfY">Text messaging a simple and rapid means for close and repeated postoperative contact.</s><s xml:id="_cduYMn8">According to the French Regulatory Authority of electronic and postal communications [Autorité de Régulation des Communications électroniques et des Postes (ARCEP)], 79.9 million subscriber identity module (SIM) cards were in service in France late 2014 [3]: i.e. since the population of France was 66.259 million, this penetration rate of over 100% attests to the wide accessibility of mobile telephones today.</s><s xml:id="_tWzrwHK">There are several examples in medicine where TM have proven their utility.</s><s xml:id="_CMEQkTC">Text messages (TM) are used for therapy education for chronic diseases such as diabetes <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[4]</ref>, improved observance of antiretroviral treatments <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[5]</ref> as well as efficient reminders for medical appointments <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">7]</ref>, or, again, to encourage smoking cessation <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[8]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_4H5wxbH">Use of TM is regarded as an alternative to telephone calls for surveillance after ambulatory surgery and short-stay surgery by the Fédération de Chirurgie Viscérale et Digestive (FCVD) and the Groupe Francophone de Réhabilitation Améliorée après Chirurgie (GRACE) <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[9]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_rDawmuQ">Within the framework of postoperative followup, studies have shown promising results for minor <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[10]</ref> and ENT surgery (evaluation of post-tonsillectomy pain) <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[11]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_Kgr6mgJ">To the best of our knowledge, there are currently no studies that have evaluated an at-home TM surveillance system after major surgery.</s></p><p xml:id="_yNNGbBT"><s xml:id="_t7tgaWY">The goal of this study was to evaluate the feasibility of home surveillance by TM after colorectal surgery within the framework of an ERP.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_m3qW9P4">Materiel and methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_9xf9Bxf">Study design</head><p xml:id="_bh6EMbB"><s xml:id="_v7w7MC8">This was a prospective multicenter study, performed in the University Hospitals of Clermont-Ferrand, Grenoble, Marseille and Lyon Sud between November 2014 and September 2015.</s><s xml:id="_228PfwF">Patients were included if they underwent colorectal surgery (colonic or rectal cancer, chronic inflammatory disease, endometriosis or complicated sigmoid diverticular disease), had access to a mobile telephone, and were familiar with the use of TM.</s><s xml:id="_zpuWhFe">There was no age limit as long as the patients accepted inclusion in the study.</s><s xml:id="_MgCSnJb">All patients were in an ERP according to the recommendations published by GRACE (available on line at: <ref type="url" target="http://www.grace-asso.fr">http://www.grace-asso.fr</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_FmRp9Dw">Study protocol</head><p xml:id="_KCZ3hPf"><s xml:id="_j4ahf6t">Before discharge (decided based on objective criteria according to enhanced recovery programs), all patient were given oral and written instructions explaining the followup program in detail.</s><s xml:id="_6m3Z4TV">Inclusion to the study was decided on the day of discharge: the patient's telephone number was entered on a protected page on the Internet site (<ref type="url" target="https://www.memoquest.com/">https://www.memoquest.com/</ref>)</s><s xml:id="_9a94qNc">managed by the Calmedica Society, Paris.</s><s xml:id="_t7B9ewj">Patients were then followed at-home by TM.</s><s xml:id="_CBgyMMY">Five questions were sent out at 10 AM the day after discharge (D + 1), then at D + 3 and D + 5.</s><s xml:id="_93f8dzx">The five questions were explained in detail orally to the patients as well as on the information sheet.</s><s xml:id="_YgXyKYw">The appropriate answers based on patient symptomatology were also fully explained (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_2nFVbjs">The TM questions concerned:</s></p><p xml:id="_WZ2DTbW"><s xml:id="_sMq6zXA">• body temperature;</s></p><p xml:id="_zyWBG5T"><s xml:id="_xHKtYvV">• pain (scored on a scale of 0 to 10); • signs of clinical bowel obstruction;</s></p><p xml:id="_jpBAAEJ"><s xml:id="_3Ez7h9G">• signs/symptoms of venous thromboembolic disease (VTED); • the absence of all these symptoms.</s><s xml:id="_Z8ycKN2">A final message was sent out to patient on D + 7 after discharge where they were asked to evaluate their satisfaction on a score ranging from 1 to 5 (5 being the best).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_8aE7Jfd">Study data</head><p xml:id="_HPFugdP"><s xml:id="_qFHnQUa">The first step was to gather all the TM responses for a comprehensive survey.</s><s xml:id="_Y2atHf2">With actions or management were adapted to symptoms according to risk management principles, alerts were sent directly to the responsible surgeon in case of abnormal responses.</s><s xml:id="_7hmqUyr">Thus, a predetermined boundary for each of the questions triggered the alarm: temperature above 37.8 • C, pain score of 4/10 or greater, presence of signs of intestinal obstruction or VTED.</s><s xml:id="_N9FMuV2">The failure to respond within four minutes after the TM question was sent also triggered an alert.</s><s xml:id="_wDwBA5E">The alert was sent automatically by the digital platform to the e-mail of the person responsible for the study at each of the four centers.</s><s xml:id="_Jb8pnhf">For the sake of clarity, we recorded the number of ''alerts-patients'' because, in practice, this corresponds to the e-mails received by the responsible surgeon.</s><s xml:id="_kkmhGBx">Once alerted, the surgeon or paramedical personnel organized further enquiry and actions: first by a telephone call to the patient to gather more details on the symptoms triggering the alert, and then to set up a management plan (medication prescription, laboratory tests, appointment for a follow-up examination, or direct admission to a surgical service, without going through the emergency department).</s></p><p xml:id="_FGvVN9n"><s xml:id="_SfTWCss">Analyses included the causes, the number of alerts, the rapidity of response(s) to the TM ''question'' (median delay between the TM ''question'' and the TM ''response''), the pertinence of the alerts, the number of re-admissions, of surgical re-operations, visits to the emergency department, in order to assess the organizational fallout of such a followup scheme.</s><s xml:id="_8taNXYQ">Results were expressed as medians and ranges.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_vbneXpX">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_pPbwVdu">Population</head><p xml:id="_wz5Ts35"><s xml:id="_rcrHcJC">In all, 111 patients were prospectively included from the four University Hospitals: Clermont-Ferrand (n = 55), Lyon Sud (n = 26), Grenoble (n = 20) and Marseille (n = 10) during the study period.</s><s xml:id="_RxGghZn">Median age of patients was 57 (25-82) years.</s><s xml:id="_V7XyvP9">All patients had undergone colorectal surgery within an ERP allowing the patient to return home early.</s><s xml:id="_HTwkSbd">The median postoperative hospital stay was six (4-10) days.</s><s xml:id="_uarhrBt">One patient with postoperative anastomotic disruption after rectal surgery was included according to intention to treat analysis.</s><s xml:id="_xpCGnQT">A total of 16 questions were sent to each of the 111 patients according to the preestablished protocol (5X3 for surveillance and one for evaluation of satisfaction).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_VufK2KX">Responses</head><p xml:id="_2cjR3JY"><s xml:id="_v85c5bQ">The rate of non-responses to the TM served to evaluate the feasibility of the TM follow-up system.</s><s xml:id="_MHrFJCG">Non-response was relatively low: 10% on D + 1, 7% on D + 3 and 10% on D + 5.</s><s xml:id="_qDjcURT">In all cases, an alert was triggered and communicated to the responsible surgeon.</s><s xml:id="_SbyDR6W">The response rate for the satisfaction questionnaire (D + 7) was 85%.</s></p><p xml:id="_gDrB7WX"><s xml:id="_Sn5szbS">The median time to TM response was 12 minutes (1-422) on D + 1, 5 minutes (1-452) on D + 3, 4 minutes (1-293) on D + 5 and 8 minutes (1-403) on D + 7 for the satisfaction questionnaire.</s><s xml:id="_KaADSP8">For the 85% patients responding to the satisfaction questionnaire, the median score was 5 <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref><ref type="bibr">(3)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(4)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(5)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_WmnhVCN">Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> summarizes the percentages of responses for each grade of satisfaction.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_5FJe9Jf">Analysis of the alerts</head><p xml:id="_mQzPgaw"><s xml:id="_hXy3yse">A total of 48 ''alerts-patients'' were registered by the digital platform.</s><s xml:id="_FA9yQDQ">The causes of these alerts were as follows: pain rated 4/10 or greater (n = 27, i.e. 56.2% of the alerts), absence of response to the TM (n = 19, i.e. 39.5%), signs of VTED (n = 1), and intestinal function disorder (n = 1).</s><s xml:id="_F7t7Rrk">Two alerts concerned combined temperature over 37.8 • C and substantial pain.</s><s xml:id="_MmV4jmq">Most of the alerts were related to poor observance of antalgic medication, banal symptoms without any relation to a surgical complication, or either forgetting to or an error in responding to the TM.</s></p><p xml:id="_h2dNWVN"><s xml:id="_XSMYV8d">The TM reminders led to two surgical re-operations (1.8% of patients in this series): one patient with fascial dehiscence was diagnosed early because of isolated abdominal pain scaled above 4/10; when the patient was seen, she underwent immediate re-operation with an unremarkable postoperative course.</s><s xml:id="_6MF8DVN">The second re-operation concerned a 24 year-old female who had undergone laparoscopic left colectomy for pelvic endometriosis.</s><s xml:id="_zt8dwrJ">The operation and postoperative hospital stay were unremarkable and the patient was discharged on D7.</s><s xml:id="_XZBSg75">However, she did not respond to the first D + 1 reminder.</s><s xml:id="_zN6BTex">The alert led the health care team to discover that the patient had been hospitalized in a peripheral hospital for acute peritonitis.</s><s xml:id="_f8nA73X">This patient had a colorectal anastomotic disunion and was transferred back to the original University Hospital where she underwent re-operative laparoscopic repair.</s></p><p xml:id="_uydqAGf"><s xml:id="_aG7Bp7J">Three patients were re-hospitalized (i.e. a re-admission rate of 2.7%): the two patients who underwent re-do surgery and one patient who had postoperative intestinal symptoms, were successfully managed by symptomatic treatment.</s></p><p xml:id="_HN2cRRu"><s xml:id="_ZgYKHFV">Last, of note in our series, no postoperative complication requiring re-hospitalization or re-operation was observed in the absence of an alert.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_mWprQk2">Discussion</head><p xml:id="_Wq5XnZf"><s xml:id="_E2v6KND">This study has clearly shown that home surveillance by TM for patients undergoing colorectal surgery within an ERP was feasible.</s><s xml:id="_EQbJQ99">Moreover, TM surveillance with automatic alerts led to early, timely detection of postoperative complications (once because of abdominal pain, the other because of failure to respond).</s><s xml:id="_eNDA5kS">In this preliminary series, no postoperative complication went un-recognized or was diagnosed tardily: the sensitivity and efficacy of the system are reassuring.</s><s xml:id="_GUcx5Wk">This method of surveillance could possibly be considered as an alternative to and replace of the classical postoperative follow-up (telephone calls, typically performed in ambulatory surgery and short-stay hospitalization, or early medical or paramedical follow-up visits).</s><s xml:id="_Yvtw5fF">One of the advantages of this method is that it frees caretaker time.</s><s xml:id="_eU3YdFM">Moreover, of the 111 patients, only one (0.9%) went through the emergency department, underscoring the value of this follow-up system, in that it does not increase congestion in the emergency department.</s><s xml:id="_HpP2bPA">TM surveillance by the original health care team also alleviates additional work and charges for family physicians.</s></p><p xml:id="_UrXynty"><s xml:id="_esqMPeE">Orr and King, in their meta-analysis of randomized studies, highlighted the overall role of TM in improving patient-healthy behavior, thus improving health care <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[12]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_VbT9rJG">The high level of satisfaction recorded on D + 7 questionnaires attests to the desire of patients to become involved as an active actor in their care, as advocated by the French High Authority of Health Care (<ref type="url" target="http://www.has-sante.fr/">http://www.has-sante.fr/</ref>) and probably corresponds to a feeling of comfort, security and confidence in enhanced recovery programs thanks to this simple and extended home surveillance.</s><s xml:id="_zMkMxnz">Patient behavior patterns and their adhesion to care can only be improved.</s></p><p xml:id="_83Uucf6"><s xml:id="_TDtnJ9k">The principal limitation of this study is selection bias: only those patients who had access and were knowledgeable with regard to TM were included.</s><s xml:id="_m7NeWPD">Obviously, this may have excluded the use of the system by the elderly or those not capable of using this mode of communication or patients without access to mobile phones.</s><s xml:id="_u4mgxYW">While the maximal age in this series was 82 years, the median age (57 years) was less than the median age of 67 (25-91) years of patients in the GRACE-AUDIT database (<ref type="url" target="http://www.grace-asso.fr/">http://www.grace-asso.fr/</ref>,</s><s xml:id="_Ffp5a9Q">consulted December 30, 2015 for 400 records; unpublished data).</s></p><p xml:id="_3F5YyX5"><s xml:id="_rHbXFaT">At first view, this method may seem time-consuming for the caregivers who have to manage the alerts, call the patients and then set up the new management plan.</s><s xml:id="_BW5cgHa">In reality, this direct contact between the patient and the original health care service deepens knowledge of patient status, and ensures better risk management thanks to enhanced reactivity in the setting with potential for mismanagement of postoperative complications or failure to rescue <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[13]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_FHY2JeV"><s xml:id="_kU2YrDK">Last, this study was not designed to be a medicoeconomic analysis comparing surveillance by TM to traditional surveillance (telephone call to patients and early return visit, surveillance by home health nurse, etc.).</s><s xml:id="_7aCm6y2">However, it is important to keep in mind the minimal cost of TM (20 centimes) compared to the hourly cost of a secretary or nurse.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_PAbVb79">Conclusion</head><p xml:id="_D6ae5wu"><s xml:id="_vHdhwYK">The feasibility of surveillance by TM, as shown in this preliminary study, leads us to recommend this program and suggests extension of the indications from short-stay surgery to other surgical procedures performed within ERP.</s><s xml:id="_yT5bUr3">More studies are necessary to confirm and give further strength to these results.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_ESXCrvB"><s xml:id="_z4GfFes">Figure 1.</s><s xml:id="_38NHKs6">Percentage of satisfaction on a 1 to 5 scale.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,302.64,62.87,238.80,159.26" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_Br4Z5KN"><s xml:id="_Gfuh6HB">Details of TM.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>If your temperature is above</cell><cell>TEM (upper or lower) or</cell></row><row><cell>37 • C simply answer the 3</cell><cell>no answer</cell></row><row><cell>letters TEM</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Do you have a stomachache</cell><cell>A number between 0</cell></row><row><cell>or sore scar? Measure your</cell><cell>and 10</cell></row><row><cell>pain on a scale of 0 to 10</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>and just answer a number</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Do you have vomiting or a gas</cell><cell>DIG (upper or lower) or</cell></row><row><cell>barrier? If yes, simply</cell><cell>no answer</cell></row><row><cell>answer the 3 letters DIG</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Do you have pain in the calf</cell><cell>PHP (upper or lower) or</cell></row><row><cell>or chest, palpitations, or</cell><cell>no answer</cell></row><row><cell>dizziness? If yes, simply</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>answer the 3 PHP letters</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>If you have any of these</cell><cell>NO (upper or lower) or</cell></row><row><cell>symptoms, simply answer</cell><cell>no answer if you</cell></row><row><cell>NO</cell><cell>answered TEM, DIG,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PHP or TEM in one of</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>the previous TM</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head xml:id="_jD2YEtj">Disclosure of interest</head><p xml:id="_HkPJ3Ar"><s xml:id="_5hK8ZfS">The authors declare that they have no competing interest.</s></p><p xml:id="_CpukpjP"><s xml:id="_aaMs8aP">The <rs type="projectName">Start-Up Calmedica</rs> provided free access to the TM outbox platform.</s></p></div>
			</div>
			<div type="funding">
<div xml:id="_v6cNHNB"><p xml:id="_qTXapBG"><s xml:id="_C3JMjZe">).</s><s xml:id="_5rmnpQD">The work was awarded ''<rs type="funder">Prix</rs></s></p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_HQjPWZ5">
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">Start-Up Calmedica</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_PDTxQCk">Anaesthesia, surgery, and challenges in postoperative recovery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kehlet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Dahl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0140-6736(03)14966-5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_KPeQFdC">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">362</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1921" to="1928" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kehlet H, Dahl JB. Anaesthesia, surgery, and challenges in post- operative recovery. Lancet 2003;362:1921-8.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_WMssAQV">Systematic review and meta-analysis of enhanced recovery programmes in surgical patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nicholson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lowe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Parker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Alderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/bjs.9394</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Xp2c97a">Br J Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="172" to="188" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nicholson A, Lowe MC, Parker J, Lewis SR, Alderson P, Smith AF. Systematic review and meta-analysis of enhanced recovery programmes in surgical patients. Br J Surg 2014;101:172-88.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_7AzhQwR">Effect of mobile phone short text messages on glycemic control in type 2 diabetes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bassam Bin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Al</forename><surname>Fares</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jabbari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">El</forename><surname>Dali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Al</forename><surname>Orifi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5812/ijem.18791</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_X8wAyVd">Int J Endocrinol Metab</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">18791</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bassam Bin A, Al Fares A, Jabbari M, El Dali A, Al Orifi F. Effect of mobile phone short text messages on glycemic control in type 2 diabetes. Int J Endocrinol Metab 2015;13:e18791.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_jdp6Nc4">Opinions and attitudes of participants in a randomized controlled trial examining the efficacy of SMS reminders to enhance antiretroviral adherence: a cross-sectional survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mja</forename><surname>Reid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Dhar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/qai.0b013e3182a9c72b</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_aSRQsbR">J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="86" to="88" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Reid MJA, Dhar SI, Cary M, et al. Opinions and attitudes of participants in a randomized controlled trial examining the efficacy of SMS reminders to enhance antiretroviral adher- ence: a cross-sectional survey. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr 2014;65:e86-8.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_2sbzhyK">Use of telephone and SMS reminders to improve attendance at hospital appointments: a systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hasvold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wootton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1258/jtt.2011.110707</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_jSf6Rmf">J Telemed Telecare</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="358" to="364" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hasvold PE, Wootton R. Use of telephone and SMS reminders to improve attendance at hospital appointments: a systematic review. J Telemed Telecare 2011;17:358-64.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ACsg25W">How effective are short message service reminders at increasing clinic attendance? A meta-analysis and systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Guy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hocking</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Stott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kaldor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1475-6773.2011.01342.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_uaEc3wr">health Serv Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="614" to="632" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Guy R, Hocking J, Wand H, Stott S, Ali H, Kaldor J. How effec- tive are short message service reminders at increasing clinic attendance? A meta-analysis and systematic review. health Serv Res 2012;47:614-32.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_vPZwBcr">Efficacy of SMS text message interventions for smoking cessation: a meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Spohr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Nandy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gandhiraj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vemulapalli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Anne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Walters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jsat.2015.01.011</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_42SM3w6">J Subst Abuse Treat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Spohr SA, Nandy R, Gandhiraj D, Vemulapalli A, Anne S, Walters ST. Efficacy of SMS text message interventions for smok- ing cessation: a meta-analysis. J Subst Abuse Treat 2015;56: 1-10.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_XGHMbRy">Risk management in ambulatory and short-stay gastrointestinal surgery. Guidelines of the French Federation of Visceral and Gastrointestinal surgery (Fédération de chirurgie viscérale et digestive--FCVD), and the Francophone working group for enhanced recovery after surgery (Groupe francophone de réhabilitation améliorée après chirurgie--GRACE)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Slim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Theissen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Raucoules-Aimé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jviscsurg.2015.12.002</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jviscsurg.2015.12.002" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_F2M2Uy2">J Visc Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">153</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Slim K, Theissen A, Raucoules-Aimé M, et al. Risk management in ambulatory and short-stay gastrointestinal surgery. Guide- lines of the French Federation of Visceral and Gastrointestinal surgery (Fédération de chirurgie viscérale et digestive--FCVD), and the Francophone working group for enhanced recovery after surgery (Groupe francophone de réhabilitation améliorée après chirurgie--GRACE). J Visc Surg 2016;153:55-60, http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jviscsurg.2015.12.002.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_yZC2fsQ">Utility of routine postoperative visit after appendectomy and cholecystectomy with evaluation of mobile technology access in an urban safety net population</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Balentine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jviscsurg.2015.12.002</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_vEUqwTq">J Surg Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">190</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="478" to="483" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Chen DW, Davis RW, Balentine CJ, et al. Utility of routine post- operative visit after appendectomy and cholecystectomy with evaluation of mobile technology access in an urban safety net population. J Surg Res 2014;190:478-83.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_rzY4jqd">Post-tonsillectomy pain in 24 children -utilising short message service (SMS) to assess postoperative outcomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Chin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Greenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Johnstone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mcguinness</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1749-4486.2012.02521.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_rhwyXU5">Clin Otolaryngol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="412" to="414" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Chen Y, Chin M, Greenberg S, Johnstone C, McGuinness J. Post-tonsillectomy pain in 24 children -utilising short mes- sage service (SMS) to assess postoperative outcomes. Clin Otolaryngol 2012;37:412-4.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_s37RftU">Mobile phone SMS messages can enhance healthy behaviour: a meta-analysis of randomised controlled trials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Orr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>King</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/17437199.2015.1022847</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_kXsT97p">Health Psychol Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="397" to="416" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Orr JA, King RJ. Mobile phone SMS messages can enhance healthy behaviour: a meta-analysis of randomised controlled trials. Health Psychol Rev 2015;9:397-416.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_vhaefR4">Understanding failure to rescue and improving safety culture</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ghaferi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Dimick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/sla.0000000000001135</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_KndD35X">Ann Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">261</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="839" to="840" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ghaferi AA, Dimick JB. Understanding failure to rescue and improving safety culture. Ann Surg 2015;261:839-40.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
