<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_WeNXRYS">Behavior Change The Transtheoretical Model of Health Behavior Change</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">National Heart, Lung, and Blood b*stitute</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_w5jtvNB">
					<orgName type="full">unknown</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_ynzfRbz #_mTC2ZNQ">
					<orgName type="full">Natio~ml Cancer Institute</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Prochaska</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wayne</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Velicer</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">Wayne</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Velic~</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">are at the Cancer Prevention Research Cent~ University of Rhode Island , Kingston , Rhode Island.</note>
								<orgName type="department">Cancer Prevention Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Cent~ University of Rhode Island</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Kingston</settlement>
									<region>Rhode Island</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Cancer Prevention Research Center , 2 Chafee Road , University of Rhode Island , Kingston , RI 02881-0808 ;</note>
								<orgName type="department">Cancer Prevention Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Rhode Island</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2 Chafee Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>02881-0808</postCode>
									<settlement>Kingston</settlement>
									<region>RI</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_HURYvwC">Behavior Change The Transtheoretical Model of Health Behavior Change</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">23F33C809434E209A89A6BB6622289E5</idno>
					<note type="submission">was submitted April 1, 1997; revisions roere requested April 7, 1997; the manuscript was accepted for publication May 5, 199Z</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T11:32+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term xml:id="_4NzBVra">Transtheoretical Model</term>
					<term xml:id="_wBks2DH">Stages of Change</term>
					<term xml:id="_T7Usqm4">Proactive Recruitment</term>
					<term xml:id="_DubaePc">Computerized Interventions</term>
					<term xml:id="_efWaDCj">Decisional Balance</term>
					<term xml:id="_JsgcjWq">Processes of Change</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_nf8cjVS"><p xml:id="_MJqTnYV"><s xml:id="_Ejctvdc">The transtheoretical model posits that health behavior change involves progress through six stages of change: precontemplation, contemplation, preparation, action, maintenance, and termination.</s><s xml:id="_dS9V5kh">Ten processes of change have been identified for producing progress along with decisional balance, self-efficacy, and temptations.</s><s xml:id="_bZCXMcp">Basic research has generated a rule of thumb for at-risk populations: 40 % in precontemplation, 40 % in contemplation, and 20% in preparation.</s><s xml:id="_hnKVSj9">Across 12 health behaviors, consistent patterns have been found between the pros and cons of changing and the stages of change.</s><s xml:id="_SxcWwGG">Applied research has demonstrated dramatic improvements in recruitment, retention, and progress using stagematched interventions and proactive recruitment procedures.</s><s xml:id="_AvXG7sS">The most promising outcomes to date have been found with computer-based individualized and interactive interventions.</s><s xml:id="_URquahp">The most promising enhancement to the computer-based programs are personalized counselors.</s><s xml:id="_bgsYb4v">One of the most striking results to date for stage-matched programs is the similarity between participants reactively recruited who reached us for help and those proactively recruited who we reached out to help.</s><s xml:id="_xVbDr6b">If results with stage-matched interventions continue to be replicated, health promotion programs will be able to produce unprecedented impacts on entire at-risk populations.</s><s xml:id="_xHqZz5h">(</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="604.0" lry="787.0"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="600.0" lry="784.0"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="602.0" lry="784.0"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="600.0" lry="785.0"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="602.0" lry="786.0"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="600.0" lry="784.0"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="602.0" lry="785.0"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="600.0" lry="784.0"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="602.0" lry="785.0"/>
		<surface n="10" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="602.0" lry="782.0"/>
		<surface n="11" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="602.0" lry="783.0"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_UHnn7RC"><p xml:id="_v7mdsVy"><s xml:id="_4UfNw87">The transtheoretical model uses a temporal dimension, the stages of change, to integr~.te</s><s xml:id="_dcrRp8H">processes and principles of change from different theories of intervention, hence the name transtheoretical.</s></p><p xml:id="_n9Wnzft"><s xml:id="_u2K9eZH">This model emerged from a comparative analysis of leading theories of psychotherapy and behavior change.</s><s xml:id="_37MzsR4">The goal was a systematic integration of a field that had fragmented i:ato more than 300 theories of psychotherapy. 1 The comparative analysis i,zlentified 10 distinct processes of change, such as consciousness raising from the Freudian tradition, contingency management from the Skinnerian tradition, and helping relationships from the Rogerian tradition.</s></p><p xml:id="_PfpBGxf"><s xml:id="_vZ5rAuq">In an empiric~.l</s><s xml:id="_DQEdf8B">analysis of selfchangers compared to smokers in professional treatments, we assessed how frequently each group used each of the 10 processes.</s><s xml:id="_8nUncp4">2 Our research participants kept saying that they used different processes at different times in their straggles with smoking.</s><s xml:id="_GFPdbaH">These naive subjects were teaching us about a phenomenon that was not included in any of the multitude of therapy theories.</s><s xml:id="_vXBxhNY">They were revealing to us that behavior change unfolds through a series of stages.</s><s xml:id="_nRa4F4T"><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> From the initial studies of smoking, the stage model rapidly expanded in scope to ir.clude investigations and applications with a broad range of health and mental health behaviors.</s><s xml:id="_YmQt3ge">These include alcohol and substance abuse, anxiety and panic disorders, delinquency, eating disorders and obesity, high-fat diets, AIDS prevention, mammography screening, medication compliance, unplanned pregnancy prevention, pregnancy and smoking, ration testing, seden-tary lifestyles, sun exposure, and physicians practicing preventive medicine.</s><s xml:id="_66uJgdT">Over time, these studies have applied, expanded, validated, and challenged the core constructs of the transtheoretical model.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_X3tw2BM">CORE CONSTRUCTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_8fMYMUr">Stages of Change</head><p xml:id="_GMeMSsm"><s xml:id="_zRKfRGw">The stage construct is important in part because it represents a temporal dimension.</s><s xml:id="_tTSSJew">Change implies phenomena occurring over time, but surprisingly, none of the leading theories of therapy contained a core construct representing time.</s><s xml:id="_9Qkth8a">Behavior change was often construed as an event, such as quitting smoking, drinking, or overeating.</s><s xml:id="_8gBRanT">The transtheoretical model construes change as a process involving progress through a series of six stages.</s></p><p xml:id="_UDDPS3P"><s xml:id="_kbuCmxG">Precontemplation is the stage in which people are not intending to take action in the foreseeable future, usually measured as the next 6 months.</s><s xml:id="_yjpVE4t">People may be in this stage because they are uninformed or underinformed about the consequences of their behavior.</s><s xml:id="_gVHPS3A">Or they may have tried to change a number of times and become demoralized about their abilities to change.</s><s xml:id="_avCkW7z">Both groups tend to avoid reading, talking, or thinking about their high risk behaviors.</s><s xml:id="_jspvH5Z">They are often characterized in other theories as resistant or unmotivated clients or as not ready for therapy or health promotion programs.</s><s xml:id="_vAeZvfW">The fact is, traditional health promotion programs were not ready for such individuals and were not motivated to match their needs.</s></p><p xml:id="_wmSsSyP"><s xml:id="_eUuAgJS">Contemplation is the stage in which people are intending to change in the next 6 months.</s><s xml:id="_E3ghjdh">They are more aware of the pros of changing but are also acutely aware of the cons.</s><s xml:id="_6Hg5Sxx">This balance between the costs and benefits of changing can produce profound ambivalence that can keep people stuck in this stage for long periods of time.</s><s xml:id="_cAswg4D">We often characterize this phenomenon as chronic contemplation or behavioral procrastination.</s><s xml:id="_PK3XTvu">These folks are also not ready for traditional action-oriented programs.</s></p><p xml:id="_euTb5q5"><s xml:id="_nYrZZxa">Preparation is the stage in which people are intending to take action in the immediate future, usually measured as the next month.</s><s xml:id="_6WaZs79">They have typically taken some significant action in the past year.</s><s xml:id="_tBhBayA">These individuals have a plan of action, such as joining a health education class, consulting a counselor, talking to their physician, buying a self-help book, or relying on a self-change approach.</s></p><p xml:id="_c5gUgxg"><s xml:id="_VwqMfur">These are the people we should recruit for such action-oriented programs as smoking cessation, weight loss, or exercise.</s><s xml:id="_HKVMqdg">Action is the stage in which people have made specific overt modifications in their life styles within the past 6 months.</s><s xml:id="_fTmb5ZK">Since action is observable, behavior change often has been equated with action.</s><s xml:id="_67FFVxh">But in the transtheoretical model, action is only one of six stages.</s><s xml:id="_zFdkJpc">Not all modifications of behavior count as action in this model.</s><s xml:id="_GVX4krG">People must attain a criterion that scientists and professionals agree is sufficient to reduce risks for disease.</s><s xml:id="_B6FVyRR">In smoking, for example, the field used to count reduction in the number of cigarettes as action, or switching to low tar and nicotine cigarettes.</s><s xml:id="_GfF9ZyT">Now, the consensus is clear--only total abstinence counts.</s><s xml:id="_Ds5He5A">In the diet area, there is a consensus that less than 30% of calories should be consumed from fat.</s><s xml:id="_u5NGtQw">But there are those who believe that this guideline needs to be lowered to 25% or even 20%.</s></p><p xml:id="_FdsGtyj"><s xml:id="_KyhVtGB">Maintenance is the stage in which people are working to prevent relapse but they do not apply change processes as frequently as do people in action.</s><s xml:id="_PAenVdw">They are less tempted to relapse and increasingly more confident that they can continue their changes.</s><s xml:id="_VQTNNFt">Based on temptation and self-efficacy data, we estimated that maintenance lasts from 6 months to about 5 years.</s><s xml:id="_wszs2ef">While this estimate may seem somewhat pessimistic, longitudinal data in the 1990 Surgeon General's report gave some support to this temporal estimate.</s><s xml:id="_ZWFKMx4">4 After 12 months of continuous abstinence, the percentage of individuals who returned to regular smoking was 43%.</s><s xml:id="_9S4b63n">It was not until 5 years of continuous abstinence that the risk for relapse dropped to 7%.</s></p><p xml:id="_VnfUTDy"><s xml:id="_DYC7xBD">In one of our early articles, we gave the misleading impression that we viewed relapse as a separate stage.</s><s xml:id="_dYhwJaS">Relapse is one form of regression, which is a return to an earlier stage.</s><s xml:id="_J8N4DCR">Relapse is the return from action or maintenance to an earlier stage.</s><s xml:id="_Qy79W4G">The bad news is that relapse tends to be the rule when action is taken for most health behavior problems.</s><s xml:id="_rbmfMzv">The good news is that for smoking and exercise only about 15% of people regress all the way to the precontemplation stage.</s><s xml:id="_aGkjmef">The vast majority return to contemplating or preparing for another serious attempt at action.</s><s xml:id="_96rP62B">Termination is the stage in which individuals have zero temptation and 100% self-efficacy.</s></p><p xml:id="_WFfm9Z3"><s xml:id="_CZ4tjVH">No matter whether they are depressed, anxious, bored, lonely, angry, or stressed, they are sure they will not return to their old unhealthy habit as a way of coping.</s><s xml:id="_6nhHtT3">It is as if they never acquired the habit in the first place.</s><s xml:id="_Zy8jQUZ">In a study of former smokers and alcoholics, we found that less than 20% of each group had reached the criteria of zero temptation and total self-efficacy.</s><s xml:id="_p3PT25H">-~ The criteria may be too strict, or it may be that this stage is an ideal goal for the majority of people.</s><s xml:id="_57Bdn2v">In other areas, like exercise, consistent condom use, and weight control, the realistic goal may be a lifetime of maintenance.</s><s xml:id="_hUA5WCd">Since termination may not be a practical reality for a majority of people, it has not been given as much emphasis in our research.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_KB7RGwe">Processes of Change</head><p xml:id="_R9qwzpt"><s xml:id="_54WPTxw">Processes of change are the covert and overt activities that people use to progress through the stages.</s><s xml:id="_Am6KSRU">Processes of change provide important guides for intervention programs, since the processes are like the independent variables that people need to apply to move from stage to stage.</s><s xml:id="_59P6HRY">Ten processes have received the most empirical support in our research to date.</s><s xml:id="_tbmaKVy"><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">6</ref> Consciousness Raising involves increased awareness about the causes, consequences, and cures for a particular problem behavior.</s><s xml:id="_AJQrXaS">Interventions that can increase awareness include feedback, education, confrontation, interpretation, bibliotherapy, and media campaigns.</s></p><p xml:id="_qT9vpCZ"><s xml:id="_GTVHrY8">Dramatic Relief initially produces increased emotional experiences foi-lowed by reduced affect if appropriate action can be taken.</s><s xml:id="_qDY6mae">Psychodrama, role playing, grieving, personal testimonies, and media campaigns are examples of techniques that can move people emotionally.</s></p><p xml:id="_Ku7THVc"><s xml:id="_25rBXav">Self-reevaluation combines both cognitive and affective assessments of one's self-image with and without a particular unhealthy habit, such as one's image as a couch potato and an active person.</s><s xml:id="_2FUnFD5">Value clarification, healthy role models, and imagery are techniques that can move people evaluatively.</s></p><p xml:id="_7sFznwr"><s xml:id="_YMCSkpw">Environmental Reevaluation combines both affective and cognitive assessments of how the presence or absence of a personal habit affects one's social environment such as the effect of smoking on others.</s><s xml:id="_hQfyyhZ">It can also include the awareness that one can serve as a positive or negative role model for others.</s><s xml:id="_7ESdDnF">Empathy training, documentaries, and family interventions can lead to such reassessments.</s></p><p xml:id="_pPGfbEE"><s xml:id="_AWZMqRf">A brief television spot from California's antitobacco campaign was designed to help smokers in precontemplation to progress.</s><s xml:id="_bkvSxwy">In this spot, a middle-aged man clearly in grief says, "I always worried that my smoking would cause lung cancer.</s><s xml:id="_m6UruPS">I was always afraid that my smoking would lead to an early death.</s><s xml:id="_5H73Udd">But I never imagined that it would happen to my wife."</s><s xml:id="_GYnKXEp">Then on the screen is flashed the message, "50,000 deaths per year due to passive smoking"--California Department of Health.</s></p><p xml:id="_YkQSA7b"><s xml:id="_S58UPKN">There are no action directives in .</s><s xml:id="_Y6bHQA9">this intervention but there is: (1) consciousness raising--50,000 deaths per year; (2) dramatic relief---around grief, guilt, and fear that can be reduced if appropriate action is taken;</s></p><p xml:id="_6ZBGRZa"><s xml:id="_B3c97bd">(3) self-reevaluation--how do I think and feel about myself as a smoker; and (4) environmental reevaluation-how do I feel and think about the effects of my smoking on my environment.</s></p><p xml:id="_aspf8m2"><s xml:id="_G36JvXb">Self-liberation is both the belief that one can change and the commitment and recommitment to act on that belief.</s><s xml:id="_UtBb8fD">New Year's resolutions, public testimonies, and multiple rather than single choices can enhance self-liberation or what the public calls willpower.</s><s xml:id="_nRQTA5h">Motivation research indicates that people with two choices have greater commitment than people with one choice; those with three choices have even greater commitment; having four choices does not further enhance willpower.</s><s xml:id="_W9KbP9J">4 So with smokers, for example, three excellent action choices they can be given are cold turkey, nicotine fading, and nicotine replacement.</s><s xml:id="_GKdMKBu">Social Liberation requires an increase in social opportunities or alternatives especially for people who are relatively deprived or oppressed.</s><s xml:id="_gfwY4ef">Advocacy, empowerment procedures, and appropriate policies can produce increased opportunities for minority health promotion, gay health promotion, and health promotion for impoverished people.</s><s xml:id="_ZawrnsY">These same procedures can also be used to help all people change such as smoke-free zones, salad bars in school lunches, and easy access to condoms and other contraceptives.</s></p><p xml:id="_fJubYf2"><s xml:id="_sXamqYm">Counterconditioning requires the learning of healthier behaviors that can substitute for problem behaviors.</s><s xml:id="_6ZEruyr">Relaxation can counter stress; assertion can counter peer pressure; nicotine replacement can substitute for cigarettes; and fat-free foods can be safer substitutes.</s></p><p xml:id="_ZsjpAnf"><s xml:id="_jzSX2p3">Stimulus Control removes cues for unhealthy habits and adds prompts for healthier alternatives.</s></p><p xml:id="_APX5jnU"><s xml:id="_zHVHQ5R">Avoidance, environmental reengineering, and self-help groups can provide stimuli that support change and reduce risks for relapse.</s><s xml:id="_Fbz8pnw">Planning parking lots with a 2-minute walk to the office and putting art displays in stairwells are examples of reengineering that can encourage more exercise.</s></p><p xml:id="_SvypY9A"><s xml:id="_8SjBT6y">Contingency Management provides consequences for taking steps in a particular direction.</s><s xml:id="_tDwVZAJ">While contingency management can include the use of punishments, we found that self-changers rely on rewards much more than punishments.</s><s xml:id="_USWVVJN">So reinforcements are emphasized, since a philosophy of the stage model is to work in harmony with how people change naturally.</s></p><p xml:id="_MbDeTJR"><s xml:id="_J6wkrje">Contingency contracts, overt and covert reinforcements, positive self-statements, and group recognition are procedures for increasing reinforcement and the probability that healthier responses will be repeated.</s></p><p xml:id="_zCQ22Td"><s xml:id="_a6QYD6b">Helping Relation,chips combine caring, trust, openness, and acceptance as well as support :!or the healthy behavior change.</s><s xml:id="_T2p3jcK">Rapport building, a therapeutic alliance, counselor calls, and buddy systems can be sources of social support.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_msnpRsq">Decisional Balance,</head><p xml:id="_fCENHJg"><s xml:id="_Rwth7ht">Decisional balance reflects the individual's relative weighing of the pros and cons of changing.</s><s xml:id="_4mg4Vvw">Originally, we relied on Janis and Mann's model of decision making that included four categories of pros (instrumental gains for self and others and approval for self and others).7</s><s xml:id="_GeZtVCT">The four categoric s of cons were instrumental costs tc, self and others and disapproval from self and others.</s><s xml:id="_5mUFpyH">In a long series of studies attempting to produce this structure of eight factors, we always found a much simpler structure--just the pros and cons of changing.</s><s xml:id="_Q5dbmhs">8</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_zkF2WB9">Self-efficacy</head><p xml:id="_6ZSDXvG"><s xml:id="_tdjEn6T">Self-efficacy is the situation-specific confidence people have that they can cope with high risk situations without relapsing to their unhealthy or high risk habit.</s><s xml:id="_tRaSGE3">This construct was integrated from Bandura's self-efficacy theory.9,</s><s xml:id="_8zZGdGB">l0</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_YBTYjC8">Temptation</head><p xml:id="_AjjkcY6"><s xml:id="_aUncBQX">Temptation reflects the intensity of urges to engage, in a specific habit when in the midst of difficult situations.</s><s xml:id="_CxZzfZM">In our research, we typically find three factors reflecting the most common types of ::empting situations: negative affect or .emotional</s><s xml:id="_VjvYuP4">distress, positive social situations, and craving.</s><s xml:id="_u4Z9Yft">~</s></p><p xml:id="_36Vqf6b"><s xml:id="_etV9Fqf">The transtheoretical model has concentrated on five stages of change, 10 proces.ses of change, the pros and cons of c hanging, self-efficacy, and temptati3n.</s><s xml:id="_xYt3jEV">In addition, the model includes a measure of the target behavior.</s><s xml:id="_6reeA9Q">The transtheoretical model is also base :1 on critical assumptions about tlae nature of behavior change and in:erventions that can best facilitate ~uch change.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_R9zvG2D">Critical Assumptions</head><p xml:id="_MZJFa2G"><s xml:id="_waRzyFJ">The following are a set of assumptions that drive transtheoretical theory, research, and practice.</s><s xml:id="_9EnU59w">populations will remain stuck in the early stages.</s><s xml:id="_Cz9aMwM">There is no inherent motivation to progress through the stages of intentional change as there seems to be in stages of physical and psychological development.</s><s xml:id="_DRXmgFy"><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(5)</ref> The majority of at-risk populations are not prepared for action and will not be served by traditional action-oriented prevention programs.</s><s xml:id="_EVgswUx">Health promotion can have much greater impacts if it shifts from an action paradigm to a stage paradigm.</s><s xml:id="_SEsFQ5q">(6) Specific processes and principles of change need to be applied at specific stages if progress through the stages is to occur.</s><s xml:id="_zqjpwBk">In the stage paradigm, intervention programs are matched to each individual's stage of change.</s><s xml:id="_c2psHZt">(7) Chronic behavior patterns are usually under some combination of biological, social, and self-control.</s><s xml:id="_cqBXGS4">Stage-matched interventions have been primarily designed to enhance self-controls.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_K9RXDqs">BASIC RESEARCH SUPPORT</head><p xml:id="_beXCd8Y"><s xml:id="_XZVgXdY">Each of the core constructs has been subjected to a wide variety of studies across a broad range of behaviors and populations.</s></p><p xml:id="_JCTsaMn"><s xml:id="_YnwEXKT">Only a sampling of these studies can be reviewed here.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_n7WX6z3">Stage Distribution</head><p xml:id="_YW6PYm2"><s xml:id="_HgjNJpZ">If we are to match the needs of entire populations, we need to know</s></p><p xml:id="_xGarP68"><s xml:id="_g4PzhbK">Table 1 Distribution of Smokers by Stage Across Four Different Samples* Precon-Sample templation Contemplation Preparation Sample Size Random digit dial 42.1% 40.3% 17.6% 4144 Four U.S. worksites 41.1% 38.7% 20.1% 4785 California 37.3% 46.7% 16.0% 9534 RI high schools 43.8% 38.0% 18.3% 208 * These studies assess current smokers; therefore, no respondents are in action or maintenance.</s></p><p xml:id="_9QtSUbz"><s xml:id="_yeS2BTV">the stage distributions of specific high risk behaviors.</s><s xml:id="_gBavdf5">Table <ref type="table">1</ref> presents results from a series of studies on smoking that have clearly demonstrated that less than 20% of smokers are in the preparation stage in most populations, l'~ Approximately 40% of smokers are in the contemplation stage, and another 40% are in precontemplation.</s><s xml:id="_cmP59YT">These results show that action-oriented cessation programs will not match the needs of the vast majority of smokers.</s></p><p xml:id="_REGZZFN"><s xml:id="_J95JeZH">With a sample of 20,000 members of an HMO, the stage distribution was assessed for 15 health behaviors.</s><s xml:id="_ytUCwgv">1-~ While there are variations in the distributions, for these high risk behaviors, the results support a general rule of thumb: 40% in precontemplation, 40% in contemplation, and 20% in preparation.</s></p><p xml:id="_xhB2cTd"><s xml:id="_Qmg3Szk">Our research has focused on the stage distribution of people currently at risk because these are the groups typically targeted for health promotion programs.</s><s xml:id="_sEK7JxE">There is research in the literature on the percentages of populations who were formerly at risk but not currently at risk.</s><s xml:id="_xqFA4Jy">For example, of ever smokers, about 45% are former smokers.</s><s xml:id="_uj8zrZh">The Surgeon General's Report of 1990 reports the percent of ever smokers who quit in the last year (57%), 1 to 5 years (10%), and more than 5 years (30%).4</s><s xml:id="_dTZwaum">While such data have epidemiological significance, they are not nearly as helpful in program planning as is the stage distribution of populations currently at risk.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_3hmW3Rb">Pros and Cons Structure Across 12 Behaviors</head><p xml:id="_stXpg4V"><s xml:id="_dCMppP5">As indicated earlier, the pros and cons of decisional balance have a much simpler structure than Janis and Mann's theory suggests.</s><s xml:id="_24WqaWN">Across studies of 12 different behaviors (smoking cessation, quitting cocaine, weight control, dietary fat reduction, safer sex, condom use, exercise acquisition, sunscreen use, radon testing, delinquency reduction, mammography screening, and physicians practicing preventive medicine), the two-factor structure was remarkably stable.</s><s xml:id="_35wj4xA">14</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_JeGGXpq">Integration of Pros and Cons and Stages of Change Across 12 Health Behaviors</head><p xml:id="_6TgDfpp"><s xml:id="_4NcZ6pf">Stage is not a theory; it is a variable.</s><s xml:id="_WNra39k">A theory requires systematic relationships between a set of variables, ideally culminating in mathematical relationships.</s></p><p xml:id="_TzjUWMS"><s xml:id="_WRceYYj">Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> shows that in all 12 studies, the pros of changing are higher than the cons for people in precontemplation.</s><s xml:id="_ZMCUmhF">14 In all 12 studies, the pros increase between precontemplation and contemplation.</s><s xml:id="_X6wfR4f">There arc no systematic differences on the cons between prccontcmplation and contemplation.</s></p><p xml:id="_6kAu9DZ"><s xml:id="_bBR6qhw">But from contemplation to action for all 12 behaviors, the cons of changing arc lower in action than in contemplation.</s><s xml:id="_FbuuX4M">In 11 of the 12 studies, the pros of changing are higher than the cons for people in action.</s></p><p xml:id="_Q3xuQvz"><s xml:id="_NXZyyZg">These basic findings suggest principles for progressing through the stages.</s><s xml:id="_WAfdwdk">To progress from precontemplation to contemplation, the pros of changing must increase.</s><s xml:id="_7Rz59h3">To progress from contemplation to action, the cons of changing must decrease.</s><s xml:id="_PDytWEE">So with people in precontcmplation, we would target the pros for intervention and save the cons for after they progress to contemplation.</s><s xml:id="_RURtAUa">Before progressing to action, we would want to see the pros and cons crossing over, with the pro., higher than the cons as a sign of being well prepared for action.</s><s xml:id="_xQbE654">Practical implications of these principles are that the pros of changing must increase twice as much as the cons decrease.</s><s xml:id="_rkGWfMv">Perhaps twice as much emphasis should be placed on raising the benelits as on reducing the costs or barr!.ers.</s><s xml:id="_BNFm8Fv">For example, if couch potatoes in precontemplation can list only five pros of exercise, then being too lzusy will be a big barrier to change.</s><s xml:id="_j8DSWH7">]~.ut if program participants come to appreciate that there can be more than 50 benefits for 60 minutes of exercise a week, being too busy becomes a relatively smaller barrier.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_8QE6VRg">Processes of Change Across Behaviors</head><p xml:id="_ppsTrVY"><s xml:id="_xzbHTFu">One of the a.,sumptions of the transtheoretical model is that there is a common set o~ change processes people can applv across a broad range of behaviors.</s><s xml:id="_kZGYWsF">While we have focused most on 10 separate processes, we have also examined how these 10 factor together.</s><s xml:id="_t6fAKnR">This is called the higher order structure of the processes.</s><s xml:id="_952daqd">With the higher order, we consistently find two factors: (1) experiential processes that include more internal experiences like consciousness raising, dramatic relief, and self-reevaluation; and (2) behavioral processes that include more overt activities like helping relationships, contingency management, and stimulus control.</s><s xml:id="_EDMD3sJ">The experiential and behavioral processes have replicated across problem behaviors better than have the 10 specific processes.</s><s xml:id="_2mdZ3qb"><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">16</ref> Typically, we have found support for our standard set of 10 processes across such behaviors as smoking, diet, cocaine use, exercise, condom use, and sun exposure.</s><s xml:id="_seWCfRj">But the structure of the processes across studies has not been as consistent as the structure of the stages and the pros and cons of changing.</s><s xml:id="_nxMEeR4">In some studies, we find fewer processes and occasionally, we find evidence for one or two more.</s><s xml:id="_gYABzya">It is also very possible that with some behaviors fewer change processes may be used.</s><s xml:id="_umxbEyT">With an infrequent behavior like yearly mammograms, for example, fewer processes may be required to progress to long-term maintenance) 7</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_qakdfQj">Integration of Relationships Between Stages and Processes of Change</head><p xml:id="_hzs2puK"><s xml:id="_Sdt8JWC">One of our earliest empirical integrations was the discovery of systematic relationships between the stage people were in and the processes they were applying.</s><s xml:id="_HMwsqCS">This discovery allowed us to integrate processes from theories that were typically seen as incompatible and in conflict.</s><s xml:id="_ddyBbqG">For example, Freudian theory that relied almost entirely on consciousness raising for producing change was viewed as incompatible with Skinnerian theory that relied entirely on contingency management for modifying behavior.</s><s xml:id="_9N2jRYK">But self-changers did not know that these processes were theoretically incompatible, and they taught us that processes from very different theories needed to be emphasized at different stages of change.</s><s xml:id="_a9Bpygg">Table <ref type="table">2</ref> presents our current empirical integration.</s><s xml:id="_ACWMUmJ">Is This integration suggests that in early stages, people apply cog-</s></p><p xml:id="_nBgCHZ2"><s xml:id="_CRZe3Ng">Table 2 Stages of Change in Which Change Processes Are Most Emphasized Stages of Change Precontemplation Contemplation Preparation Action Maintenance Processes Consciousness raising Dramatic relief Environmental reevaluation Self-reevaluation Self-liberation Contingency management Helping relationship Counterconditioning Stimulus control nitive, affective, and evaluative processes to progress through the stages.</s></p><p xml:id="_Xee5ESg"><s xml:id="_exz6V4U">In later stages, people rely more on commitments, conditioning, contingencies, environmental controls, and social support for progressing toward termination.</s></p><p xml:id="_jGtDEGa"><s xml:id="_CZFb7AW">Table <ref type="table">2</ref> has important practical implications.</s></p><p xml:id="_aZu2gad"><s xml:id="_pFM8JwY">To help people progress from precontemplation to cohtemplation, we need to apply such processes as consciousness raising and dramatic relief.</s><s xml:id="_edCzexw">Applying processes like contingency management, counterconditioning, and stimulus control to people in precontemplation would represent a theoretical, empirical, and practical mistake.</s><s xml:id="_sEjHyv7">But for people in action, such strategies would represent an optimal matching.</s></p><p xml:id="_W9YJGQ8"><s xml:id="_6Fq6Ve3">As with the structure of the processes, the integration of the processes and stages has not been as consistent as the integration of the stages and pros and cons of changing.</s><s xml:id="_pqxPukF">While part of the problem may be due to the greater complexity of integrating 10 processes across five stages, the processes of change need more basic research.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_eUdm2zu">APPLICATIONS OF THE TRANSTHEORETICAL MODEL: SMOKING CESSATION INTERVENTIONS AS PROTOTYPES FOR STAGE-MATCHED PROGRAMS</head><p xml:id="_hY2zZWn"><s xml:id="_GUuR2jR">Smoking is costly to individual smokers and to society.</s><s xml:id="_supy7Dw">In the United States, approximately 47 million Americans continue to smoke.</s><s xml:id="_jenbeWN">Over 400,000 preventable deaths per year are attributable to smoking. 4 Globally, the problem promises to be catastrophic.</s><s xml:id="_nRFQKjU">Of the people alive in the world today, 500 million are expected to die from this single behavior, losing approximately 5 billion years of life to tobacco use.</s><s xml:id="_EjeNKan">v~ If we could make even modest gains in our science and practice of smoking cessation, we could prevent millions of premature deaths and help preserve billions of years of life.</s></p><p xml:id="_7QaAPj9"><s xml:id="_pwxTYHB">Currently, smoking cessation clinics have little impact.</s><s xml:id="_d2JTa2k">When offered for free by HMOs in the United States, such clinics recruit only 1% of subscribers who smoke.</s><s xml:id="_fqWPADd">Such behavior health services simply cannot make much difference if they treat such a small percentage of the problem.</s><s xml:id="_WJtrQKv"><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">20</ref> Startled by such statistics, behavioral scientists took health promotion programs into communities.</s><s xml:id="_cbn6wxe">The results are now being reported, and in the largest trials ever attempted, the outcomes are discouraging.</s><s xml:id="_m2eAeHr">In the Minnesota Heart Health Program, for example, $40 million was spent with 5 years of intervention in four communities totalling 400,000 people.</s><s xml:id="_E7kFcPS">There were no significant differences between treatment and control communities on smoking, diet, cholesterol, weight, blood pressure, and overall risks for cardiovascular dis-CaSe.</s><s xml:id="_wnyy6zt"><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">21</ref> What went wrong?</s><s xml:id="_AUnZcnh">The investigators speculate that maybe they dilut-ed their programs by targeting multiple behaviors.</s><s xml:id="_d7K3WvF">But the COMMIT trial had no effects with its primary target of heavy smokers and only a small effect with light smokers, z'~A closer look at participation rates may explain some of the disappointing results.</s><s xml:id="_Dgk7Atq">In the Minnesota study, nearly 90% of smokers in both the treatment and control communities had processed media information about smoking in the past year.</s><s xml:id="_mcr2K3K">But only about 10% had been advised to quit by their physicians, z:~ And only about 3% had participated in the most powerful behavioral programs, such as individualized and interactive clinics, classes, and contests.</s><s xml:id="_yBNG7Dr">In one of the Minnesota Heart Health studies, smokers were randomly assigned to one of three recruitment methods for home-based cessation programs.</s><s xml:id="_qWGJfCG">'~4 These announcements generated 1 to 5% participation rates, with a personalized letter doing the best.</s><s xml:id="_GEU7hXd">We cannot have much impact on the health of our communities if we only interact with a small percentage of populations at high risk for disease and early death.</s></p><p xml:id="_UCjWEhF"><s xml:id="_jdbjRJa">One alternative is to shift from an action paradigm to a stage paradigm, in order to increase our reach and interact with a much higher percentage of populations at risk.</s><s xml:id="_9nnUrNK">Let us examine how the stage paradigm has been applied to five of the most important phases of health promotion programs.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_xYHGApM">Recruitment</head><p xml:id="_G5vfvFe"><s xml:id="_XmjH4Fz">Recall that action-oriented cessation programs falter in this first phase of intervention and produce low participation rates.</s><s xml:id="_2uQGXvd">Table <ref type="table">1</ref> reported results that can help explain such low rates.</s><s xml:id="_ZFBCKyu">Across four different samples, 20% or less of smokers were in the preparation stage, v' When we advertise or announce action-oriented programs, we are explicitly or implicitly targeting less than 20% of a population.</s><s xml:id="_ymXhKev">The other 80% plus are left on their own.</s><s xml:id="_jjYa6mk">In two home-based recruitments with approximately 5000 and 4600 smokers in each study, we reached out either by telephone alone or by personal letters followed by telephone calls, if needed, and recruited smokers to stage-matched interventions.</s><s xml:id="_pwP3pNY">For each of five stages, these interventions included self-help manuals; individualized computer feedback reports based on assessments of the pros and cons, processes, self-efficacy, and temptations; and, for some participants, counselor protocols based on the computer reports.</s><s xml:id="_WNMnkFV">Using these proactive recruitment methods and stage-matched interventions, we were able to generate participation rates of 82 to 85%, respectively (Prochaska, et al., unpublished manuscript; Velicer, et al., unpublished manuscript).</s></p><p xml:id="_DzhXdkm"><s xml:id="_Q5FXpD2">Such quantum increases in participation rates provide the potential to generate unprecedented impacts with entire populations of smokers.</s></p><p xml:id="_92SPNTy"><s xml:id="_8cakWKe">Population impact equals participation rate times the rate of efficacy or action.</s><s xml:id="_HQVu4Yn">"~5 If a program produced 30% efficacy (such as long-term abstinence), historically it was judged to be better than a program that produced 25% abstinence.</s></p><p xml:id="_q4R7dAp"><s xml:id="_fN5Nahp">But a program that generates 30% efficacy but only 5% participation has an impact of only 1.5% (30% × 5%).</s><s xml:id="_KCGXfV4">A program that produces only 25% efficacy but 60% participation has an impact of 15%.</s><s xml:id="_tgWqFvm">With health promotion programs, this would be 1000% greater impact on a high risk population.</s></p><p xml:id="_uYWXsav"><s xml:id="_ByBcseA">The stage paradigm would shift our outcomes from efficacy alone to impact.</s><s xml:id="_VrkQhNy">To achieve such high impact, we need to shift from reactive recruitment, where we advertise or announce our programs and react when people reach us, to proactive recruitments, where we reach out to interact with all potential participants.</s></p><p xml:id="_7JVg63X"><s xml:id="_8aAv6Xf">But proactive recruitment alone won't work.</s><s xml:id="_yhhKeeM">In the most intensive recruitment protocol to date, Lichtenstein and Hollis had physicians spend time with each smoker just to get them to sign up for an action-oriented cessation clinicY 6 If that didn't work, a nurse spent 10 minutes persuading each smoker to sign up, followed by 12 minutes with a videotape and health educator and even a proactive counselor call if necessary.</s><s xml:id="_VW3HTrX">The base rate was 1% participation.</s><s xml:id="_tssY5wK">This proactive protocol resulted in 45 43 Premature Terml ~ation --o.. Appropriate Tern ~lnation -~-Continuers Pre-Contemplati0n Action Conten tplation Maintenance 35% of smokers ir~ precontemplation signing up.</s><s xml:id="_8H4ryTJ">But ortly 3% showed up and 2% finished.</s></p><p xml:id="_2QTmaHn"><s xml:id="_ux9KskX">With a combination of smokers in con :emplation and preparation, 65% signed up, 15% showed up, and 111% finished.</s></p><p xml:id="_SBcjcBF"><s xml:id="_zW7pjwe">To optimize our impacts, we need to use proactive p::otocols to recruit participants to programs that match the stage they are in.</s><s xml:id="_stnX9Wu">Once we generate high recruitm~:nt rates, we then have to be concerned about high retention rates, lest we lose many of the initial participants in our health promotion programs.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_dnAU8gg">Retention</head><p xml:id="_ymHHTAT"><s xml:id="_Sd5P3Nq">One of the ske~etons in the closet of psychotherapy and behavior change interventions is their relatively poor retention cares.</s><s xml:id="_2mMw6H5">Across 125 studies, the average retention rate was only about 50%.</s><s xml:id="_4FZnQUr">27 Furthermore, this meta-analysis found few consistent predictors of which participants would drop out p::ematurely and which would conttnue in therapy.</s><s xml:id="_guU34RN">In studies on smoking, weight control, substance abuse, and a mixture of Diagnostic and S~:ttistical Manual IV (DSM-IV) disordecs, stage-of-change measures proved ~:o be the best predictors of premature termination.</s><s xml:id="_HEX49Ck">Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref> presents the stage profile of three groups of therapy participants in treatment for a variety of mental health problems: the pretreatment stage profile of the entire 40% who dropped out prematurely as judged by their therapist~ was that of patients in precontemplation.</s></p><p xml:id="_CFDzdx3"><s xml:id="_yuUa8Rb">The 20% who terminated quickly but appropriately had a profile of patients in action.</s><s xml:id="_Na82sfm">Using pretreatment stage-related measures, we were able to correctly predict retention status for 93% of the three groups (Medeiros, et al., unpublished manuscript).</s><s xml:id="_TdgtnFT">We simply cannot treat people with a precontempla.tion</s><s xml:id="_duSbE6k">profile as if they were ready for action interventions and expect them to stay in treatment.</s><s xml:id="_d43wCPB">Relapse prevention strategies would be indicated with smokers who are taking action.</s><s xml:id="_teFSx6Z">But those in precontemplation are more likely to need dropout prevention strategies.</s></p><p xml:id="_Fd8gZ4D"><s xml:id="_qHrU8RY">The best strategy we have found to promote retention is matching our interventions to stage of change.</s><s xml:id="_cHDSap7">In four smoking cessation studies using such matching strategies, we found we were able to retain smokers in the precontemplation stage at the same high levels as those who started in the preparation stage (Prochaska, et al., unpublished manuscript; Velicer, et al., unpublished manuscript).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_V9M4VCJ">Progress</head><p xml:id="_seyjesM"><s xml:id="_WZQVHCB">The amount of progress participants make following health promotion programs is directly related to the stage they were in at the start of the interventions.</s><s xml:id="_QhXMEKw">This stage effect is illustrated in Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref>, where smokers initially in precontemplation show the smallest amount of abstinence over 18 months and those in preparation progress the most.</s><s xml:id="_vNK4c74">2s Across 66 different predictions of progress, we found that smokers starting in contemplation were about two-thirds more successful than those in precontemplation at 6-, 12-, and 18-month follow-ups.</s><s xml:id="_YQWuuzF">Similarly, those in preparation were about two-thirds more successful than those in contemplation at the same follow-ups.</s><s xml:id="_UME7ruG">',9</s></p><p xml:id="_V2xseaW"><s xml:id="_me3CdF8">These results can be used clinically.</s><s xml:id="_4jFK9j9">A reasonable goal for each therapeutic intervention with smokers is to help them progress one stage.</s><s xml:id="_aSpGVrE">If over the course of brief therapy they progress two stages, they will be about two-and-two-thirds times more successful at longer term follow-ups.</s><s xml:id="_e4b7Z6g"><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">29</ref> This strategy has been taught to more than 4000 primary care physicians, nurses, health educators, and physicians' assistants in Britain's Na- 30 o Pretest 1 6 12 18</s></p><p xml:id="_8W6KB4E"><s xml:id="_mU5CF7P">ASSESSMENT PERIODS tional Health System.</s><s xml:id="_g87mg8v">With stagematched counseling, the strategic goal is to help each patient progress one stage following one brief intervention.</s><s xml:id="_6DTmRnH">One of the first reports is a marked improvement in the morale of such health promoters intervening with all patients who smoke, abuse substances, and have unhealthy diets (E Mason, unpublished data, 1996).</s><s xml:id="_6Pzfyae">These professionals now have strategies that match the needs of all of their patients, not just the minority prepared to take action.</s><s xml:id="_5Eexpqp">Furthermore, these professionals can assess progress across stages in the majority of their patients, where previously they experienced mostly failure when taking action was their only measure of movement.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_rbYm8Xh">Process</head><p xml:id="_ExpHqQt"><s xml:id="_HpC7F8B">To help populations progress through the stages, we need to understand the processes and principles of change.</s><s xml:id="_SNbP6RE">One of the fundamental principles for progress is that different processes of change need to be applied at different stages of change.</s><s xml:id="_JhWdVpU">Traditional conditioning processes like counterconditioning, stimulus control, and contingency control can be highly successful for participants taking action but can produce resis-tance with individuals in precontemplation.</s><s xml:id="_nkpXfX9">With these individuals, more experiential processes like consciousness raising and dramatic relief can move people cognitively and affectively, and help them shift to contemplation.</s><s xml:id="_4C85E6K">-~A fter 15 years of research, we have identified 14 variables on which to intervene in order to accelerate progress across the first five stages of change.</s><s xml:id="_VPS4qtE">-~° At any particular stage, we only need to intervene with a maximum of six variables.</s><s xml:id="_yu7xJck">To help guide individuals at each stage of change, we have developed computer-based expert systems that can deliver individualized and interactive interventions to entire populations.</s><s xml:id="_JMgVMjj">"~ These computer programs can be used alone or in conjunction with counselors.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_maWuEYb">Outcomes</head><p xml:id="_m3MXN8E"><s xml:id="_9SBBATj">In our first large-scale clinical trial, we compared four treatments: (1) one of the best home-based actionoriented cessation programs (standardized);</s></p><p xml:id="_YuVjhBM"><s xml:id="_KwtvWw2">(2) stage-matched manuals (individualized); (3) expert tem computer reports plus manuals (interactive); and (4) counselors computers and manuals (personalized).</s><s xml:id="_RjVckmn">We randomly assigned by stage 739 smokers to one of the four treat°m ents.</s><s xml:id="_e5uxXVk">28</s></p><p xml:id="_xX5urex"><s xml:id="_B3EEXZJ">In the computer condition, participants completed by mail or telephone 40 questions that were entered in our central computers and generated feedback reports.</s><s xml:id="_uBWyYcf">The reports informed participants about their stage of change, their pros and cons of changing, and their use of change processes appropriate to their stages.</s><s xml:id="_KpguBmp">At baseline, participants were given positive feedback on what they were doing correctly and guidance on which principles and processes they needed to apply more in order to progress.</s><s xml:id="_B7vfSQF">In two progress reports delivered over the following 6 months, participants also received positive feedback on any improvement they made on any of the variables relevant to progressing.</s><s xml:id="_fs7m9MH">So, demoralized and defensive smokers could begin progressing without having to quit and without having to work too hard.</s><s xml:id="_sx8zfQ9">Smokers in the con- 2O Pretest 6 12 18</s></p><p xml:id="_YXUGyfC"><s xml:id="_CTj3G6n">ASSESSMENT PERIODS templation stage could begin taking small steps, like delaying their first cigarette in the morning for an extra 30 minutes.</s><s xml:id="_TE2suMV">They could choose small steps that would increase their self-efficacy and help them become better prepared for quitting.</s></p><p xml:id="_8a8BFDp"><s xml:id="_QEfY7MJ">In the personalized condition, smokers received four proactive counselor calls over the 6-month intervention period.</s><s xml:id="_68JaWTW">Three of the calls were based on the computer reports.</s><s xml:id="_7Aj3Gjf">On the other call, counselors reported much more difficulty in interacting with participants without any progress data.</s><s xml:id="_yzd4vKz">Without scientific assessments, it was much harder for both clients and counselors to tell whether any significant progress had occurred since their last interaction.</s></p><p xml:id="_RxhmHbg"><s xml:id="_aJJyK5P">Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref> presents point prevalence abstinence rates for each of the four treatment groups over 18 months with treatment ending at 6 months.</s><s xml:id="_wyze9s3"><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">28</ref> The two self-help manual conditions paralleled each other for 12 months.</s><s xml:id="_frt2X4x">At 18 months, the stage-matched manuals moved ahead.</s><s xml:id="_7zb3Au2">This is an example of a delayed action effect, which we often observe with stage-matched programs.</s><s xml:id="_bws5UHC">It takes time for participants in early stages to progress all the way to action.</s><s xml:id="_2wRFVq9">Therefore, some treatment effects as measured by action will be observed only after considerable delay.</s><s xml:id="_5D6F9ga">But it is encouraging to find treatments producing therapeutic effects months and even years after treatment ended.</s></p><p xml:id="_juRRFvP"><s xml:id="_8nBcs6j">The computer alone and comput-er plus counselor conditions paralleled each other for 12 months.</s><s xml:id="_4P2grs5">Then, the effects of the counselor condition flattened out while the computer condition effects continued to increase.</s><s xml:id="_mt5bvtb">We can only speculate as to the delayed differences between these two conditions.</s><s xml:id="_hSbseqG">Participants in the personalized condition may have become somewhat dependent on the social support and social control of the counselor calling, The last call was after the 6-month assessment, and benefits were observed at 12 months.</s><s xml:id="_PXqZW9P">Termination of the counselors could result in no further progress because of the loss of social support and control.</s><s xml:id="_u3vTeQP">The classic pattern in smoking cessation clinics is rapid relapse beginning as soon as the treatment is terminated.</s><s xml:id="_qV47QmA">Some of this rapid relapse could well be due to the sudden loss of social support or social control provided by the counselors and other participants in the clinic.</s><s xml:id="_5zV5g7Z">The next test was to demonstrate the efficacy of the expert system when applied to an entire population recruited proactively.</s><s xml:id="_whxaQyG">With over 80% of 5170 smokers participating and fewer than 20% in the preparation stage, we demonstrated significant benefits of the expert system at each 6-month follow-up (Prochaska, et al., unpublished manuscript).</s><s xml:id="_et6guye">Furthermore, the advantages over proactive assessment alone increased at each followup for the full 2 years assessed.</s><s xml:id="_KzAsXQu">The point prevalence abstinence rates for the expert system at 6, 12, 18, and 24 months were 9.78, 18.0, 21.7, and 25.6%, respectively, compared to 7.4, 14.5, 16.6, and 19.7% for the assessment alone.</s><s xml:id="_TV3Tcsw">The implications here are that expert system interventions in a population can continue to demonstrate benefits long after the intervention has ended.</s></p><p xml:id="_6TxfeDk"><s xml:id="_gcvAf9M">We then showed excellent replication of the expert system's efficacy in an HMO population of 4653 smokers with 85% recruited (Prochaska, et al., unpublished manuscript; Velicer, et al., unpublished manuscript).</s><s xml:id="_AYMDvKR">At 18-month follow-up in the first study, the abstinence rate for the expert system was 21.7% vs. 16.6% for assessment alone.</s><s xml:id="_azKwmeD">In the HMO study, the abstinence rate fo:: the expert system was 23.2% vs. 17.5% for assessment alone.</s><s xml:id="_AJWFNw6">The difference between the expert system and assessment alone for the two studie~ was 5.9 and 5.7 percentage points, respectively.</s><s xml:id="_AVC5CE8">These replicated differences were highly significant as well.</s><s xml:id="_c7SkARQ">~]aile working on a population basis, we were able to produce the level of success normally found only in intense clinic-based programs with low participation rates of much more selected samples of smokers.</s><s xml:id="_B6r8h4S">The implication is that once expert systems ar,.</s><s xml:id="_PpMgszA">~ developed and show effectivenes;~ with one population, they can be transferred at much lower cost and produce replicable changes in new Fopulations.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_DX5Wq24">Enhancing Interactive Interventions</head><p xml:id="_qUeEt6u"><s xml:id="_kyJWWzS">In recent bem:hmarking research, we have been trying to create enhancements to o~r expert system to produce even greater outcomes.</s><s xml:id="_kZQPhBn">In the first enhancement in our HMO populatior~, we added a personal hand-held ~omputer designed to bring the behavior under stimulus control (Prochaska, et al., unpublished manuscript).</s><s xml:id="_uB95Gap">This commercially successful innovation was an action-oriented intervention that did not enhance om expert system program on a poputation basis.</s><s xml:id="_W4vcvFm">In fact, our expert system alone was twice as effective as the system plus the enhancement.</s><s xml:id="_nWaZh2y">There are two major implications here: (1) more is not necessarily better, and (2) providing interventions that are mismatched to stage can make 3utcomes markedly worse.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_W8DxGWg">Counselor Enh~ ncements</head><p xml:id="_X9Ty5f2"><s xml:id="_u8N6JEX">In our HMO population, counselors plus expert :;ystem computers were outperforraing expert systems alone at 12 months (Prochaska, et al., unpublished manuscript).</s><s xml:id="_tMk3h9w">But at 18 months, the counselor enhancement had declined while the computers alone had increased.</s><s xml:id="_eBZSZrG">Both interventions wer,_ ~ producing identical outcomes of 23 2% abstinence, which are excellent for an entire population.</s><s xml:id="_DSm9rKd">Why did the effect of the counselor condition drop after the intervention?</s><s xml:id="_r5gWhqY">Our leading hypothesis is that people can become dependent on counselors for the social support and social monitoring that they provide.</s><s xml:id="_cD2F5x6">Once these social influences are withdrawn, people may do worse.</s><s xml:id="_5Zc8kNS">The expert system computers, by contrast, may maximize self-reliance.</s><s xml:id="_AQqfcfe">In a current clinical trial, we are fading out counselors over time as a method for dealing with dependency on the counselor.</s><s xml:id="_sM8wVdm">If fading is effective, it will have implications for how counseling should be terminated: gradually over time rather than suddenly.</s></p><p xml:id="_AZ7Nk8S"><s xml:id="_8QGx92K">We believe that the most powerful change programs will combine the personalized benefits of counselors and consultants with the individualized, interactive, and dam-based bene fits of expert system computers.</s><s xml:id="_J8vZcmA">But to date we have not been able to demonstrate that more costly counselors, who had been our most powerful change agents, can actually add value over computers alone.</s><s xml:id="_QDz5yqm">These findings have clear implications for cost-effectiveness of expert systems for entire populations needing health promotion programs.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_XBFDnAp">Interactive vs. Noninteractive Interventions</head><p xml:id="_XRmucgK"><s xml:id="_cdEqutB">Another important aim of the HMO project was to assess whether interactive interventions (computergenerated expert systems) are more effective than noninteractive communications (self-help manuals) when controlling for number of intervention contacts <ref type="bibr">(Velicer, et al., unpublished manuscript)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_JtzUzeR">At 6, 12, and 18 months for groups of smokers receiving a series of one, two, three, or six interactive vs. noninteractive contacts, the interactive interventions (expert system) outperformed the noninteractive manuals in all four comparisons.</s><s xml:id="_ba2hYS3">In three of the comparisons (1, 2, and 3), the difference 18 months was at least five percentage points, a difference between treatment conditions assumed to be clinically significant.</s><s xml:id="_sP2evDf">These results clearly support the hypothesis that interactive interventions will outperform the same number of noninteractive interventions.</s></p><p xml:id="_rVUS7Br"><s xml:id="_VxjUXap">These results support our hypothesis that the most powerful health promotion programs for entire popu-lations will be interactive.</s><s xml:id="_x6xvk2q">In the reactive clinical literature, it is clear that interactive interventions such as behavioral counseling produce greater long-term abstinence rates (20 to 30%) than do noninteractive interventions such as self-help manuals (10 to 20)? "-'~4 It should be kept in mind that these traditional action-oriented programs were implicitly or explicitly recruiting for populations in the preparation stage.</s><s xml:id="_GkwKSbB">Our results indicate that even with proactively recruited smokers with less than 20% in the preparation stage, the longterm abstinence rates are in the 20 to 30% range for the interactive interventions and in the 10 to 20% range for the noninteractive interventions.</s><s xml:id="_jWRk5w5">The implications are clear.</s><s xml:id="_8D4MAVc">Providing interactive interventions via computers are likely to produce greater outcomes than relying on noninteractive communications, such as newsletters, media, or self-help manuals.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_XK4BQ8n">Proactive vs. Reactive Results</head><p xml:id="_xf8FGB7"><s xml:id="_p9zM5WG">We believe that the future of health promotion programs lies with stage-matched, proactive, and interactive interventions.</s><s xml:id="_5qVGWcB">Much greater impacts can be generated by proactive programs because of much higher participation rates, even if efficacy rates are lower.</s><s xml:id="_YXz2sDG">But we also believe that proactive programs can produce comparable outcomes to traditional reactive programs.</s><s xml:id="_bTZW5gH">It is counterintuitive to believe that comparable outcomes can be produced with people who we reach out to help as with people who call us for help.</s><s xml:id="_CAPKPxA">But that is what informal comparisons strongly suggest.</s><s xml:id="_Hc6pKYV">We compared 18-month follow-ups for all subjects who received our three expert system reports in our previous reactive study 2s and in our first proactive study (Prochaska, et al., unpublished manuscript).</s><s xml:id="_fHFZV9y">The abstinence curves are remarkably similar.</s></p><p xml:id="_s5jV5wc"><s xml:id="_BNCvE8A">The results with our counseling plus computer conditions were even more impressive.</s><s xml:id="_QuW36PQ">Proactively recruited smokers working with counselors and computers had higher abstinence rates at each follow-up than did the smokers who had called for help.</s><s xml:id="_UNB8RC6">One of the differences is that our proactive counseling protocol had been revised and hopefully improved based on previous data and experience.</s><s xml:id="_WFmUyTD">But, the point is, if we reach out and offer people improved health behavior programs that are appropriate for their stage, we probably can produce efficacy or abstinence rates at least equal to those we produce with people who reach out to us for help.</s><s xml:id="_WWJZjzJ">Unfortunately, there is no experimental design that could permit us to randomly assign people to proactive vs. reactive recruitment programs.</s><s xml:id="_pk9Qd8N">We are left with informal but provocative comparisons.</s></p><p xml:id="_YWkyQhc"><s xml:id="_nY5atR3">If these results continue to be replicated, health promotion programs will be able to produce unprecedented impacts on entire populations.</s><s xml:id="_MmajyPw">We believe that such unprecedented impacts require scientific and professional shifts:</s></p><p xml:id="_YZ2xumK"><s xml:id="_HFsp3aE">(1) from an action paradigm to stage paradigm; (2) from reactive to proactive recruitment; (3) from expecting participants match the needs of our programs to having our programs match their needs; and (4) from clinic-based to populationbased behavioral health programs that still apply the field's most powerful individualized and interactive intervention strategies.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>( 1 )</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_3W6EAtg"><s xml:id="_H8HSNay">No single theory can account for all of the complexities of behavior change.</s><s xml:id="_SvB9aUd">Therefore, a more comprehensive model will most likely emerge from an integration across major theories.</s><s xml:id="_zQxZp6E">(2) Behavior change is a process that unfolds over time through a sequence of stages.</s><s xml:id="_HYgTJrN">(3) Stages are both stable and open to change, just as chronic behavioral risk factors are both stable and open to change.</s><s xml:id="_AnC9mpS">(4) Without planned interventions,</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1 The</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_P9F53EP"><s xml:id="_RWZZbSx">Figure 1 The Pros and Cons of Changing Across the Stages of Change for 12 Problem Behaviors</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_D6qyVRy"><s xml:id="_84EDF6G">Followup AppointmentsStrong and Weak Principles of Progress Across these saine 12 studies, mathematical relationships were found between th,.</s><s xml:id="_n4ADPjh">~ pros and cons of changing and progress across the stages.1,T he Stron[: Principle is.' PC-~ A -i[ SD T PROSProgress from precontemplation to action involves approximately one standard deviation (SD) increase the pros of changing.</s><s xml:id="_kgNhwQe">On intelligence tests, a one-SD increase would be 15 points, which is a substantial increase.The Weak Principle is: PC-~ A = .5</s><s xml:id="_zvNDzKY">SD $ CONS Progress from precontemplation to action involves approximately a .5-SD</s><s xml:id="_PuZBCTk">decrease in the cons of changing.</s><s xml:id="_pQt3dgn">Because the first principle involves twice as gr._~at a change as the second, we titled the first strong and the second weak.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 2 Pre</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_9tPDyGJ"><s xml:id="_ckeeWTu">Figure 2 Pre-therapy Stage Profiles for Premature Terminators, Appropriate Terminators, ~nd Continuers 55 53 ~ 51 ~ 49</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>20 Figure 3 Percentage</head><label>203</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_aQVsZaU"><s xml:id="_sde5R9F">Figure 3 Percentage Abstinent over 18 Months for Smokers in Precontemplation (PC), Contemplation (C), and PreparatiOn (C/A) Stages Before Treatment (n 570) POINT-PREVALENT ABSTINENCE (%) BY STAGE OF CHANGE</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 4 Point</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_SsUsYGx"><s xml:id="_VURFYZw">Figure 4 Point Prevalence Abstinence (%) for Four Treatment Groups at Pretest and at 6, 12, and 18 Months</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p xml:id="_zCDh98d"><s xml:id="_A6ARuA5">September/October 1997, Vol. 12, No. 1</s></p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head xml:id="_WFyCxcT">Acknowledgments</head><p xml:id="_pDfFsP4"><s xml:id="_AHQvSkt">This research zoas partially supported by Grants <rs type="grantNumber">CA 50087</rs> and <rs type="grantNumber">CA 27821</rs> fiom the <rs type="funder">Natio~ml Cancer Institute</rs> and Grant <rs type="grantNumber">HC 48190</rs> fiom the <rs type="funder">National Heart, Lung, and Blood b*stitute</rs>.</s></p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_w5jtvNB">
					<idno type="grant-number">CA 50087</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_ynzfRbz">
					<idno type="grant-number">CA 27821</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_mTC2ZNQ">
					<idno type="grant-number">HC 48190</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Prochaskajo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_w3zPWXV">Systems of Psychotherapy: A Transtheoretical Analysis</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Pacific Grove, California</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Brooks-Cole</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2ud ed</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">ProchaskaJO. Systems of Psychotherapy: A Transtheoretical Analysis. 2ud ed. Pacific Grove, California: Brooks-Cole, 1984.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_DFkshze">Self change and therapy change of smoking behavior. A comparison of processes of change in cessation and maintenance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Diclemente</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Prochaskajo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0306-4603(82)90038-7</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_9hMYC8x">Addict Behav</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="142" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">DiClemente CC, ProchaskaJO. Self change and therapy change of smoking behavior. A comparison of processes of change in cessa- tion and maintenance. Addict Behav 1982;7: 133-42.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_mFSzQUk">Stages and processes of self-change of smoking: toward an integrative model of change</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Diclemente</forename><surname>Prochaskajo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Cc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037//0022-006x.51.3.390</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_3cpT66T">J Consult Clin Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="390" to="395" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">ProchaskaJO, DiClemente CC. Stages and processes of self-change of smoking: toward an integrative model of change. J Consult Clin Psychol 1983;51:390-5.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_EWh8wcv">The Health Benefits of Smoking Cessation: A Report of the Surgeon General</title>
		<idno>CDC 90-8416</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_q7NbdTN">DHHS Publication</title>
		<imprint/>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>US Department of Health aud Human Services</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">US Department of Health aud Human Ser- vices. The Health Benefits of Smoking Cessa- tion: A Report of the Surgeon General. DHHS Publication No. CDC 90-8416.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Washington</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1163/9789004287648.useo_b03081</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<publisher>US Governmeut Priuting Office</publisher>
			<pubPlace>DC</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Wash- ington, DC: US Governmeut Priuting Office, 1990.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ybEkUsf">Processes of change in AA: maintenance factors in long-term sobriety</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Snow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Prochaska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rossi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.15288/jsa.1994.55.362</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_fnk5CBR">J Stud Alcohol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="362" to="371" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Snow MG, Prochaska JO, Rossi JS. Processes of change in AA: maintenance factors in long-term sobriety. J Stud Alcohol 1994;55: 362-71.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_JGtYrCy">Measnring the processes of change: applications to the cessation of smoking</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Prochaskajo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Velicer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Diclemente</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037//0022-006x.56.4.520</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_KDU8DAh">J Consult Clin Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="520" to="528" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">ProchaskaJO, Velicer WF, DiClemente CC, et al. Measnring the processes of change: appli- cations to the cessation of smoking. J Consult Clin Psychol 1988;56:520-8.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Janis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Mann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_K7bTseR">Decision Making: A Psychological Analysis of Conflict, Choice and Commitment</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Free Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Janis IL, Mann L. Decision Making: A Psycho- logical Analysis of Conflict, Choice and Com- mitment. New York: Free Press, 1977.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_VmDfDC8">Decisional balance measure for assessing and predicting smoking status</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Velicer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Diclemente</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Prochaskajo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037//0022-3514.48.5.1279</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ThscvWG">J Pers Soc Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1279" to="1289" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Velicer WF, DiClemente CC, ProchaskaJO, et al. Decisional balance measure for assessing and predicting smoking status.J Pers Soc Psy- chol 1985;48:1279-89.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_cDJjuHB">Self-efficacy: toward a unifying theory of behavior change</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bandnra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037//0033-295x.84.2.191</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_9zAdCU5">Psychol Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="215" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bandnra A. Self-efficacy: toward a unifying theory of behavior change. Psychol Rev 1977; 84:191-215.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_WausAwm">Self-efficacy mechanism in human agency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bandnra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037//0003-066x.37.2.122</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_MbZt9vw">Am Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="122" to="147" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bandnra A. Self-efficacy mechanism in hu- man agency. Am Psychol 1982;37:122-47.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_4NakFbY">Relapse situations and self-efficacy: an integrative model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">~</forename><surname>Velicer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">~</forename><forename type="middle">'</forename><surname>Diclemente</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Rossi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0306-4603(90)90070-e</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_tcxRVqa">Addict Behav</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="271" to="283" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Velicer ~,~&apos;, DiClemente CC, Rossi JS, et al. Relapse situations and self-efficacy: an integra- tive model. Addict Behav 1990;15:271-83.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_DfHu6dG">Distribution of smokers by stage in three representative samples</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Velicer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Favajl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Prochaskajo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1006/pmed.1995.1065</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ZxvtKTF">Prev Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="401" to="411" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Velicer WF, FavaJL, ProchaskaJO, et al. Dis- tribution of smokers by stage in three repre- sentative samples. Prev Med 1995;24:401-11.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qv6Ehhz">Stages of change for 15 health risk behaviors in an HMO population</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Rossijs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_nK43KC3">13th meeting of the Society for Behavioral Medicine</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Paper presentation at</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">RossiJS. Stages of change for 15 health risk behaviors in an HMO population. Paper pre- sentation at 13th meeting of the Society for Behavioral Medicine, 1992. New York.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_PHzRUtg">Stages of change and decisional balance for twelve problem behaviors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Prochaskajo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Velicer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Rossijs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037//0278-6133.13.1.39</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_cv8DGje">Health Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="45" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">ProchaskaJO, Velicer WF, RossiJS, et al. Stages of change and decisional balance for twelve problem behaviors. Health Psychol 1994; 13:39~t6.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_wqZwcFu">Strong and weak principles for progressing from precontemplation to action based on twelve problem behaviors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Prochaskajo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037//0278-6133.13.1.47</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_xRqv3My">Health Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="51" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">ProchaskaJO. Strong and weak principles for progressing from precontemplation to action based on twelve problem behaviors. Health Psychol 1994;13:47-51.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_XMdFkjs">Common processes of change across nine problem behaviors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rossi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/e529392009-001</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_cqRKMTm">100th meeting of American Psychological Association</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Washington, DC</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Paper presentation at</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rossi JS. Common processes of change across nine problem behaviors. Paper presentation at 100th meeting of American Psychological Association, 1992. Washington, DC.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_j8egUHz">Considerations for extending the transtheoretical model of behavior change to screening mammography</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Rakowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Dube</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Goldstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/her/11.1.77</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_GduvWWN">Health Educ Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>In press</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rakowski W, Dube CE, Goldstein MG. Con- siderations for extending the transtheoretical model of behavior change to screening mam- mography. Health Educ Res 1997. In press.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_JzdJJQk">In search of how people change: applications to the addictive behaviors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Diclemente</forename><surname>Prochaskajo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Cc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Norcrossjc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037//0003-066x.47.9.1102</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Chh4dbW">Axn Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1102" to="1114" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">ProchaskaJO, DiClemente CC, NorcrossJC. In search of how people change: applications to the addictive behaviors. Axn Psychol 1992; 47:1102-14.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_vBfMEuF">World-wide mortality from current smoking patterns</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Pert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lopes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_CrDRg2e">The Global War: Proceeding of the Seventh World Conference on Tobacco and Health. East Perth, Western Australia: Organizing Committee of Seventh World Conference on Tobacco and Health</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Durstone</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Jamrogik</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="62" to="68" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Pert R, Lopes A. World-wide mortality from current smoking patterns. In: Durstone B, Jamrogik K, editors. The Global War: Pro- ceeding of the Seventh World Conference on Tobacco and Health. East Perth, Western Aus- tralia: Organizing Committee of Seventh World Conference on Tobacco and Health, 1990:62-8.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_8jd3bDn">Effectiveness of self-help quit smoking strategies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Orleans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Schoenback</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sahnon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_Tn2UHMx">Four National Cancer Institute-funded self-help smoking cessation trials: interim resnlts and emerging patterns</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Glynn</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Chair</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>the annual meetiug of the Association for the Advancement of Behavior Therapy</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Orleans CT, Schoenback VJ, Sahnon MA, et al. Effectiveness of self-help quit smoking strategies. In: Glynn T, chair, Four National Cancer Institute-funded self-help smoking ces- sation trials: interim resnlts and emerging pat- terns. Symposium presented at the annual meetiug of the Association for the Advance- ment of Behavior Therapy, 1988. New York.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_4t8kWXu">Community education for cardiovascular disease prevention: risk factor changes in the Minnesota Heart Health Program</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Luepker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Jacobs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2105/ajph.84.9.1383</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_eruaaa2">3ma J Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1383" to="1393" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Luepker RV, Murray DM, Jacobs DR, et al. Community education for cardiovascular dis- ease prevention: risk factor changes in the Minnesota Heart Health Program. 3ma J Pub- lic Health 1994;84:1383-93.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_AqzhS7W">Community Intervention Trial for Smoking Cessation (COM-MIT): I. Cohort results from a four-year community interveution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gronp</forename><surname>Research</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2105/ajph.85.2.183</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_sdRxHqR">Am J Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="183" to="192" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">COMMIT Research Gronp. Community Inter- vention Trial for Smoking Cessation (COM- MIT): I. Cohort results from a four-year com- munity interveution. Am J Public Health 1995;85:183-92.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_GHXGE45">Changes in adult cigarette smoking in the Minnesota Heart Health Program</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lando</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Pechacek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Pirie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2105/ajph.85.2.201</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_d3buDqa">Am J Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="201" to="208" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lando HA, Pechacek TF, Pirie PL, et al. Changes in adult cigarette smoking in the Minnesota Heart Health Program. Am J Pub- lic Health 1995;85:201-8.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_WVDja74">Hellerstedt WE Direct mail recruitment to house-based smoking and weight control [,rograms: a comparison of strengths</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Schmid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Jeffrey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0091-7435(89)90009-1</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_7gJWkYX">Prev M</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="503" to="517" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Schmid TL, Jeffrey RW, Hellerstedt WE Di- rect mail recruitment to house-based smoking and weight control [,rograms: a comparison of strengths. Prev M,.&apos;d 1989;18:503-17.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_GTymEyz">Understanding and intervening with the total population of smokers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Velicer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Diclem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Cc</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_hfhAXS3">Tob Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="95" to="96" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Velicer WG, DiClem,mte CC. Understanding and intervening with the total population of smokers. Tob Control 1993;2:95-6.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_TQaDEgK">Patient referral to smoking cessation p:-ograms: who follows through?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Lichtensteiu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Holl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.33009/fsu_372d6abc-76b8-4775-90ff-83ae195c2faf</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_cdQrM4b">J Family Pract</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="739M" to="743" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lichtensteiu E, Holl.sJ. Patient referral to smoking cessation p:-ograms: who follows through?J Family Pract 1992;34:739M-4.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_zwjbCBX">A meta-analysis of psychotherapy dropnut</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wierzbicki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pekarik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_wY6GZT8">Prof Psychol Res Pract</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="190" to="195" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Wierzbicki M, Pekarik G. A meta-analysis of psychotherapy dropnut. Prof Psychol Res Pract 1993;29:190-5</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_nXQ6wMG">Standardized, imfividualized, interactive and personalized self-help programs for smoking cessation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Diclemente</forename><surname>Prochaskajo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Cc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Velicer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037//0278-6133.12.5.399</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_xYXXgGE">Health Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="399" to="405" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">ProchaskaJO, DiClemente CC, Velicer WF, et al. Standardized, imfividualized, interactive and personalized self-help programs for smoking cessation. Health Psychol 1993;12: 399-405.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_vqTCNdJ">Stagi~g: a revolution in health promotion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Prochaskajo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.26616/nioshheta9308602438</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_yhStjPn">Master .~cience lecture at the Society for Behavioral IV~edicine&apos;s/Mmnal Meeting</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Boston, Massachusetts</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">ProchaskaJO. Stagi~g: a revolution in health promotion. Master .~cience lecture at the Soci- ety for Behavioral IV~edicine&apos;s/Mmnal Meet- ing, 1994. Boston, Massachusetts.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_RR7B8Xq">Changing for Good New York</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Norc</forename><surname>Prochaskajo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ww/9780199540884.013.u227947</idno>
		<editor>ossJC, DiClemente CC</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<publisher>William Morrow &amp; Co., Inc</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">ProchaskaJO, Norc:ossJC, DiClemente CC. Changing for Good New York: William Mor- row &amp; Co., Inc., 1994.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_G5PkxwT">An expert system inter~ ention for smoking cessation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Velicer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Prochaskajo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Bellisjm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Eta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0306-4603(93)90029-9</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_deGvyKX">Addict Behav</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">993</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="269" to="290" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Velicer WF, ProchaskaJO, BellisJM, eta]. An expert system inter~ ention for smoking cessa- tion. Addict Behav .993;18:269-90.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_twJsN9n">Tobacco use reduction amorg high risk youth: recommendations of a National Cancer Institute Expert Advisory Panel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Glynn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Aaaderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Schwarz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0091-7435(91)90027-2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_HqQM3Ur">Prey Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="354" to="362" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Glynn TJ, Aaaderson DM, Schwarz L. Tobacco use reduction amorg high risk youth: recom- mendations of a National Cancer Institute Ex- pert Advisory Panel Prey Med 1992;24:354- 62.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_5BNNQvQ">rod Evaluation of Smokiug Cessation Methods: The United States and Canada</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Schwartzj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Review</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978. 87-2940. 1987</date>
			<publisher>National Cancer Instit.ate</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Bethesda, Maryland</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">SchwartzJ. Review ;rod Evaluation of Smok- iug Cessation Methods: The United States and Canada. 1978-[985. DHHS Publication No. (NIH) 87-2940. Bethesda, Maryland: Na- tional Cancer Instit.ate, 1987.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_2dWF9fQ">Self-help nterventions for smoking cessation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Curry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037//0022-006x.61.5.790</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_tVEuFwG">J Consult Clin Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="790" to="803" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Curry SJ. Self-help nterventions for smoking cessation. J Consult Clin Psychol 1993;61:790- 803.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
