<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_C4ftAET">CATEGORY 1 CME CREDIT Perceived Workplace Health and Safety Climates: Associations With Worker Outcomes and Productivity</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">Abigail</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Katz</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">Nico</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Pronk</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">Deborah</forename><surname>Mclellan</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">Jack</forename><surname>Dennerlein</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD, MSc</roleName><forename type="first">Jeffrey</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Katz</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_8mxygFY">CATEGORY 1 CME CREDIT Perceived Workplace Health and Safety Climates: Associations With Worker Outcomes and Productivity</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">F76560B8BF74A7F08527B00AAE4C0BCC</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T11:52+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="576.0" lry="773.972"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_hfsRYM5"><p xml:id="_HDR3jeD"><s xml:id="_FN9d3yz">1. Discuss the effect of workplace climate on worker health behaviors (i.e., alcohol use, nutrition, physical activity, sleep, and tobacco use) and worker outcomes (i.e., abuse, back pain, depression, job satisfaction, life satisfaction, selfperceived general health), and be able to answer the question, for which behaviors and outcomes were statistically significant associations observed?</s></p><p xml:id="_kkGBVBQ"><s xml:id="_QNeNd2v">2. State the effect of workplace climate on employer outcomes (i.e., worker productivity).</s></p><p xml:id="_NMnDVCe"><s xml:id="_N4E6e6U">3. Describe the application of a conceptual model in exploring complex pathways to worker well-being.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_QPM4f6J">Accreditation Statement</head><p xml:id="_cmGmK6E"><s xml:id="_rsU5jBq">This activity has been planned and implemented in accordance with the accreditation requirements and policies of the Accredita-</s></p><p xml:id="_HnQeXBY"><s xml:id="_t8hsKax">tion Council for Continuing Medical Education (ACCME) through the joint providership of the American College of Preventive Medicine and the American College of Lifestyle Medicine.</s><s xml:id="_78js5a9">The American College of Preventive Medicine is accredited by the ACCME to provide continuing medical education for physicians.</s><s xml:id="_gVQWGe5">Credit Designation ACPM designates this enduring material for a maximum of 1 AMA PRA Category 1 TM Credit per exam.</s><s xml:id="_NyCXBCC">Physicians should claim only the credit commensurate with the extent of their participation in the activity.</s><s xml:id="_nexWZSh">ACPM is not accredited to offer credit to non-physicians.</s><s xml:id="_3mwtY5J">To determine if activities designated for AMA PRA Category 1 TM Credit are acceptable for your licensing or certification needs, please contact your credentialing body directly.</s><s xml:id="_CucKAkq">Disclosures In accordance with the disclosure policy of the American College of Preventive Medicine (ACPM) and the American Journal of Preventive Medicine (AJPM), as well as the standards set forth by the Accreditation Council of Continuing Medical Education (ACCME), authors and any individuals in a position to control the content of a CME activity are required to disclose relevant financial relationships in any amount with commercial interests (within the past 12 months).</s><s xml:id="_CgFh6vV">The authors, Abigail S. Katz, Nico P. Pronk, Deborah McLellan, Jack Dennerlein, and Jeffrey N. Katz, have disclosed that no relevant financial relationships exist.</s><s xml:id="_Cd3ZYHt">Term of approval October 2, 2019-October 2, 2022 Estimated time to complete this activity is 1 hour.</s><s xml:id="_AXQdVWt">Instructions to receive CME credit Once you have read the CME article, please visit <ref type="url" target="https://www.ajpmonline.org/cme">www.ajp  monline.org/cme</ref> to complete the CME exam (with a score of at least 70%) and the CME evaluation survey.</s><s xml:id="_7zbr7Mf">You will be able to download your CME certificate and will also receive an email with a link toyour certificate.</s></p><p xml:id="_DtSdfwn"><s xml:id="_NVqxGhS">Privacy policy ACPM collects personal information from participants in this online activity for purposes of assigning CME credit only.</s><s xml:id="_qVJDmy2">We will not share or sell your contact information, and your answers to quizzes and feedback forms will be kept confidential.</s></p></div>		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
