<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qzRtbNh">Systematic Literature Review of Text Messaging Interventions to Promote Medication Adherence Among People With Serious Mental Illness</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Nuromate</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Alkermes</orgName>
					<idno type="DOI" subtype="crossref">https://doi.org/10.13039/100018529</idno>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Otsuka</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute of the National Institutes of Health</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2022-08-12">August 12, 2022.</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>B.S</roleName><forename type="first">Emily</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.P.H</roleName><forename type="first">Alyssa</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Martha</forename><surname>Sajatovic</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>B.S</roleName><forename type="first">Nisha</forename><surname>Jain</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Jessica</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Montoya</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Jennifer</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Levin</surname></persName>
							<email>jennifer.levin@uhhospitals.org</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Edwards, Sajatovic, Jain, Levin</roleName><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Department of Psychiatry , School of Medicine , Case Western Reserve University , Cleveland );</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Psychiatry</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Case Western Reserve University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Cleveland</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Depart- ment of Psychiatry , University Hospitals Cleveland Medical Center , Cleveland (</note>
								<orgName type="department">Depart- ment of Psychiatry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospitals Cleveland Medical Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Cleveland</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Sajatovic , Levin) ; Department of Psychiatry , University of California , San Diego , San Diego</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Sajatovic</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Levin)</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Department of Psychiatry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>San Diego</addrLine>
									<settlement>San Diego</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Frontline Medical Communications , Health Analytics , Janssen , Lund- beck , Myriad , Neurocrine , Johns Hopkins University Press , Oxford University</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Frontline Medical Communications</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Health Analytics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Lund- beck</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Janssen</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Myriad</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Neurocrine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">Johns Hopkins University Press</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit5">Oxford University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_7jE6XBb">Systematic Literature Review of Text Messaging Interventions to Promote Medication Adherence Among People With Serious Mental Illness</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2022-08-12">August 12, 2022.</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">1D3D9E0B5BF4ECFDDF8452F84EBBE24B</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1176/appi.ps.202100634</idno>
					<note type="submission">was supported by award R01HL149409 from the Psychiatric Services 73:10, October 2022 Received November 4, 2021; revision received December 22, 2021; accepted January 7, 2022;</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T12:00+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_tdafvUG"><p xml:id="_FAXZR2j"><s xml:id="_vh48Vb8">Of 10 selected articles, seven reported a significant improvement in medication adherence after the intervention and at least one significant improvement in a clinical outcome.</s></p><p xml:id="_cWhGqHv"><s xml:id="_tWtaRu5">• Research is needed to assess implementation approaches and how to scale up interventions in a clinical setting.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="584.957" lry="782.986"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="584.957" lry="782.986"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="584.957" lry="782.986"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="584.957" lry="782.986"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="584.957" lry="782.986"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="584.957" lry="782.986"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="584.957" lry="782.986"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="584.957" lry="782.986"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="584.957" lry="782.986"/>
		<surface n="10" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="584.957" lry="782.986"/>
		<surface n="11" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="584.957" lry="782.986"/>
		<surface n="12" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="584.957" lry="782.986"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_Uk6dPZv"><p xml:id="_Vmr4xzw"><s xml:id="_nejh66g">Objective: Mobile health tools are feasible options to encourage behavior change among patients with serious mental illness.</s><s xml:id="_hVmjvGe">Mobile health tools vary widely, both in platforms used and content delivered.</s><s xml:id="_hCKQane">This literature review assessed the use of text messaging interventions to promote medication adherence among patients with serious mental illness.</s></p><p xml:id="_WWNTnFp"><s xml:id="_HExSEcr">Methods: A systematic literature review using PRISMA guidelines examined short message service (SMS) text messaging interventions promoting medication adherence to people with a serious mental illness diagnosis.</s><s xml:id="_krCp2mK">Databases included PubMed, Cochrane, CINAHL, and PsycINFO.</s><s xml:id="_PzSavCP">Data extraction included demographic information, participant diagnoses, intervention components, medication class, adherence measures, research design, and study outcomes.</s><s xml:id="_hKpjPxF">Study quality was also assessed.</s></p><p xml:id="_b5zWWGE"><s xml:id="_ECRTf7u">Results: Of 114 full-text articles screened, 10 articles were selected from nine unique interventions (N5937 people with serious mental illness).</s><s xml:id="_eP9JA83">Study durations ranged from 30 days to 18 months, with frequency of SMS ranging from twice weekly to 12 times daily.</s><s xml:id="_2JpKVfk">Of the nine unique trials, most reported using an automated server to deliver SMS messages (N57), two-way SMS capabilities (N56), customized message content or timing (N57), and additional components (e.g., provider contact, educational content, and monetary rewards) (N57).</s><s xml:id="_975UkVG">Seven of the 10 articles reported statistically significant improvement in medication adherence and in at least one clinical outcome.</s></p><p xml:id="_8eUDvJ5"><s xml:id="_Hs75S3s">Conclusions: Evidence to date indicates that text messaging interventions are feasible and appear to improve medication adherence and clinical outcomes among patients with serious mental illness.</s><s xml:id="_pM9cwkD">Future research should assess implementation approaches and how to scale up efforts in nonresearch settings.</s></p><p xml:id="_2WrPTHk"><s xml:id="_BvHPFmk">Psychiatric Services 2022; 73:1153-1164; doi: 10.1176/appi.ps.202100634</s></p><p xml:id="_QFbAQ4m"><s xml:id="_aNW4KvM">Serious mental illness can have an impact on cognitive, social, and occupational functioning; add stress to family units; and ultimately decrease quality of life <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(4)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_R8Q72qT">The scientific literature maintains that adherence to evidence-based medications can dampen symptomatic disease and, in turn, improve global functioning and quality of life <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_KGyWTA2">However, medication nonadherence is a pervasive problem for individuals with serious mental illness, with rates of partial or total nonadherence between 40% and 50% <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_H4rWhAk">Drivers of nonadherence are complex, including unintentional nonadherence factors (i.e., forgetfulness), which in part stem from illness symptoms and poor baseline functioning (e.g., poor insight into illness, impaired cognition, and apathy), and intentional nonadherence factors (e.g., negative attitudes toward medications, aversion to side effects, and past treatment ineffectiveness) <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_6FRAC8A"><s xml:id="_SnT7Bdj">Furthermore, defining what constitutes nonadherence is also complex.</s><s xml:id="_Yk8RnMy">For example, categorizing patients into binary HIGHLIGHTS • This systematic review demonstrated that use of short message service (SMS) platforms to increase medication adherence among people with serious mental illness is feasible and effective.</s></p><p xml:id="_aTz3C3N"><s xml:id="_he5KZD5">• One-and two-way messaging, customized and standardized content, and frequency of messaging ranging from infrequent messages to several daily messages led to appreciable improvement in medication adherence.</s></p><p xml:id="_f4eARxc"><s xml:id="_5JhzuRP">adherent versus nonadherent groups fails to capture the difference between those who take none of their medications versus those who take them 50% of the time.</s><s xml:id="_XnXmz3x">It also neglects other potentially clinically relevant dimensions, such as the timing of taking medications or what circumstances surround missing doses.</s><s xml:id="_6jUBagb">Indeed, expert consensus on capturing adherence suggests that using multiple methods to capture adherence and quantifying the proportion of missed drug or doses are useful approaches <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_8uZYVVc"><s xml:id="_GheF77c">Technological platforms are increasingly utilized to promote patient wellness and treat disease across many diverse illnesses and patient populations <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_azXCU9D">Given the potential for downstream effects on patient and clinical outcomes, medication adherence has been a target of such platforms.</s><s xml:id="_Ays2YDj">In the era of the COVID-19 pandemic, the normativity and culture around remote health care delivery are rapidly shifting, with long-term implications <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_ZCuxvdu">However, "technological platforms" represent a heterogeneous group of services-from mobile applications, video conferencing, and Web browsers to smart-home technology and wearable devices <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(23)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26)</ref>-with equally diverse intervention content and goals.</s><s xml:id="_A3kBG9y">This variety creates a practical challenge for researchers and clinicians interested in implementing technological platforms effectively.</s></p><p xml:id="_k4Tv2QH"><s xml:id="_nFd7u9g">A large body of research suggests that mobile health, or mHealth, interventions are feasible, acceptable, and efficacious for persons with serious mental illness <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(28)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(29)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(30)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(31)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(32)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(33)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(34)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(35)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(36)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(37)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(38)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_Jngyx7t">In an early systematic literature review on mobile and Web-based text messaging in mental health, a notable rise in efforts to implement mHealth platforms was observed across several diverse patient populations, starting around 2006.</s><s xml:id="_vA3RVaq">These studies predominantly assessed feasibility and acceptability by patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_6TdafN4">Similarly, another systematic literature review reported acceptance and feasibility of online, social media, and mobile technologies in treating psychosis <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(28)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_HGPpYmF">Earlier systematic literature reviews also reported on the expansion of technology to address medication adherence specifically among patients with mental health concerns, such as schizophrenia <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(31)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(32)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(33)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_WcbJtdJ">Furthermore, more recent systematic literature reviews provided greater evidence for improved outcomes, such as increased clinical engagement and medication adherence, through mHealth interventions in populations with serious mental illness <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">35,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">38)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_C5qnspU"><s xml:id="_bktwUxz">On the whole, most of the previous reviews have included a variety of intervention delivery platforms, treatment goals, and clinical diagnoses.</s><s xml:id="_zbEdjrm">This systematic literature review aimed to supplement the current literature on mHealth platforms targeting treatment of individuals with serious mental illness by focusing on a specific subset of intervention delivery methods, treatment goals, and clinical conditionsnamely, mobile text messaging, or short message service (SMS), to promote medication adherence among patients with serious mental illness.</s><s xml:id="_AvqayJg">This focus may be particularly practical considering favorable estimates of cell phone ownership, a relatively low skill set required for usability <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(39)</ref>, and the importance of daily medication adherence among people with serious mental illness.</s><s xml:id="_BJ3s9jf">In this systematic literature review, serious mental illness was defined as one of the following diagnoses: schizophrenia spectrum disorders, bipolar disorders, major depressive disorder, and otherwise unspecified psychosis, because there is clear evidence of the need for pharmacotherapy in the treatment of these conditions <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(40)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(41)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(42)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_Bf7UAe7">We used the systematic approach outlined below to answer four questions: What is the literature on the use of text messaging to promote medication adherence?</s><s xml:id="_UrDwTUW">What properties of a text messaging intervention have been shown to be efficacious in enhancing medication adherence?</s><s xml:id="_3BFdQrV">What are common limitations or pitfalls to using text messaging to promote adherence?</s><s xml:id="_M8WQPgp">What questions or next steps in research are suggested by the current body of work?</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_nK3pyPZ">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_2nuAcGr">Literature Search</head><p xml:id="_B5GQ8My"><s xml:id="_bwmt7xU">The search protocol outlined below followed PRISMA guidelines <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(43)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_Uxf6mzz">PubMed (MEDLINE), Cochrane, CINAHL, and PsycINFO databases were searched in February 2021.</s><s xml:id="_vbUGyWu">Boolean logic was used to combine search terms to find relevant indexing to represent adherence promotion interventions with text messaging.</s><s xml:id="_VTc99uA">The literature search used the following terms: "medication adherence," "serious mental illness," and "text-messaging," along with other closely related or synonymous words.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_najQE7C">Inclusion and Exclusion Criteria</head><p xml:id="_UuFN4c4"><s xml:id="_3hX7Gkp">Inclusion of articles was based on the following criteria: peer-reviewed literature written in English; original research reports; prospective interventional studies; research involving humans only; research involving any age group; and research involving patients with a serious mental illness diagnosis, which was defined as major depressive disorder, bipolar disorder, schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder, or other psychotic disorder based on self-report, clinical evaluation, standardized diagnostic interview, or medical record diagnosis.</s><s xml:id="_nyZGDgB">Additionally, the study intervention must have assessed or promoted medication adherence by using a standardized medication questionnaire or quantitative measure of medication-and not solely by assessing changes in attitudes about medication or endorsing yes or no regarding taking medications as prescribed at only two time points.</s><s xml:id="_Ev4w2a7">The intervention must also have included a text messaging component that offered the following: medication reminders, health education, encouragement or health promotion, or prompts to which a patient could respond; the intervention consisted of more than appointment reminders or data collection.</s><s xml:id="_N5WYN2h">The SMS component could be automated or delivered by a clinician, nurse, researcher, etc., and participants could have additional comorbid diagnoses.</s><s xml:id="_WHtGtwT">Similarly, medication adherence did not need to be specific to medications prescribed for serious mental illness (i.e., adherence to hypertension medications by patients with major depressive disorder was permissible).</s></p><p xml:id="_8ptzesv"><s xml:id="_ykHZ3QW">Exclusion criteria from the study included the following: studies in which the SMS intervention was a simple notification regarding an appointment or for the sole purpose of data collection; interventions in which patients used mobile applications to receive messages or interact but in which no SMS was used; studies that assessed medication adherence based only on patients' opinions or attitudes toward medication, without any measurement of how often the patient was taking any given medication; opinion pieces or editorials; other literature reviews; literature that described only research methods, with no interventional component; case studies (fewer than five were found); studies that reported only on access or availability of technology; reports that described only methods (no outcome data); book chapters; and posters or conference abstracts.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Bnn4xsS">Data Extraction</head><p xml:id="_ybegdgA"><s xml:id="_DAEHUDc">Data extracted included the components of the intervention, psychiatric disorder, care setting, number of participants, primary outcomes, secondary outcomes, comorbid conditions, adherence measurements, duration of the intervention, medication class, one-way versus two-way SMS, frequency of SMS, automated versus care provider-generated messages, SMS content, research design, medication adherence change, and the demographic characteristics age, gender, raceethnicity, and socioeconomic status (SES) or employment.</s><s xml:id="_szNd7Vf">Both qualitative and quantitative data were collected regarding text messaging and medication adherence.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_P6wZ75K">Study Quality Assessment</head><p xml:id="_yRpVm76"><s xml:id="_gzcShDw">Quality assessment of the studies was completed by using the adapted Methodological Quality Rating Scale (MQRS) <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(44)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_8mAQM8F">The MQRS is a widely used tool to evaluate the quality of studies on the basis of several components: study design, replicability, baseline characteristics, quality control, follow-up length, intervention dosage, collaterals and objective verification, attrition, statistical power, independent outcomes assessment, statistical analyses, and number of study sites.</s><s xml:id="_byVETyf">Scores on the MQRS can range from 0 to 17, with higher scores indicating greater methodological quality.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_F7aNvBa">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_hDDhmQR">Study Characteristics</head><p xml:id="_tbxuMSx"><s xml:id="_4kX4FFC">Of 114 publications identified, 11 met initial inclusion criteria.</s><s xml:id="_Z7CZsjj">One publication was excluded because it was an additional analysis of the same study sample and no new adherence data were reported.</s><s xml:id="_z4Yyr5s">One publication represented an extension of a previously reported intervention that was included because it provided additional medication adherence data.</s><s xml:id="_gQzNb4B">Thus, 10 publications, including nine unique interventions, underwent data extraction (a CONSORT diagram is provided in an online supplement to this article) <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(46)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(47)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(48)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(49)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(50)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(51)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(52)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(53)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(54)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(55)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_uvWZCQC">Characteristics of the 10 publications are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_4XZuGJQ">Seven of the 10 publications were randomized controlled trials (RCTs) <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54)</ref>, including one stepped-wedge RCT <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(54)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_hVuJQfb">One publication was a prospective cohort study <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(52)</ref>, and one publication piloted an intervention without a comparison group <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(49)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_zdgPrP6">Finally, one publication employed nonrandomized allocation of participants into intervention or comparison groups <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(46)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_MwhWZJ3"><s xml:id="_j4KC27u">A total of 937 people with serious mental illness were included in the 10 studies.</s><s xml:id="_8rGYyWP">Of the nine unique participant samples, the diagnostic breakdown included 610 with schizophrenia, 47 with schizoaffective disorder, 220 with bipolar disorder, and 60 with major depressive disorder.</s><s xml:id="_ayTYwJD">All participants were outpatients.</s><s xml:id="_4DmsT5p">Care settings included community-based mental health programs, psychiatric clinics, residential programs, and academic medical or research centers.</s><s xml:id="_UxuS4ua">Most of the nine samples were collected in the United States <ref type="bibr">(47-49, 52, 53)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_2s4q3bW">The other studies were conducted in rural China <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54)</ref>, urban Iran <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(46)</ref>, Spain <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(50)</ref>, and India <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(51)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_BuSXYwa"><s xml:id="_zPJ2p9V">The mean6SD age of participants was 44.666.2, and 44.1% of the participants were women.</s><s xml:id="_g3KrCtU">SES was reported for three of the study populations: in two, most participants were classified as having low SES <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51)</ref>, and in the other study, most were classified as having moderate SES <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(46)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_su4FGWh">The five samples from populations based in the United States included the following racial or ethnic data: in two studies, most participants were Black (85% <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref> and 73.7% <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52]</ref>); in one study, 50% of participants were Black <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(48)</ref>; and in two studies, most participants were White (74% <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref> and 54% <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52]</ref>).</s></p><p xml:id="_m6ghZJA"><s xml:id="_BEDXJr6">Study durations ranged from 30 days to 18 months (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>), with some studies capturing data after a period without the intervention, allowing for analysis of extinction or maintenance of study outcomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_5yfSV2J">One intervention obtained baseline data for a month prior to implementing the intervention, providing more robust baseline data than self-report alone <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(52)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_8r9y78y">Interventions</head><p xml:id="_nS7XhCT"><s xml:id="_HNmhCTv">SMS intervention delivery, structure, and frequency.</s><s xml:id="_Krq63fz">Although all nine interventions used SMS, the format, timing, and frequency of these messages varied (Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> and <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_vt6jv9Z">Seven of the nine interventions reported use of an automated server to deliver messages <ref type="bibr">(45-47, 49, 50, 52, 53)</ref> and allowed for or prompted a response from participants (i.e., six studies used two-way SMS capabilities <ref type="bibr">[45, 47-49, 52, 53]</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_bKrDmcg">One of the interventions delivered messages via the principal investigator <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(48)</ref>, and one did not report delivery method <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(51)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_XBw9DcJ">In three of the interventions, no responses were provided by participants (i.e., one-way SMS capabilities) <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(46,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_cFnX2wn">In five interventions, participants were able to customize the content of the messages <ref type="bibr">(47-49, 52, 53)</ref>, and in six interventions, they were able to customize the timing for receipt of the messages <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(49)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(50)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(51)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(52)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(53)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_cA36e5J">Customization included simple choices, such as selecting reminder or reinforcement stems from a predetermined list <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(53)</ref>, patient-created symptom surveillance <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(47)</ref>, or reminder content <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(52,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_kheFs3p"><s xml:id="_HpZ6GUR">One of the more complex and diverse elements of the study interventions was the frequency of text messages.</s><s xml:id="_Z4VFDBq">Frequency of SMS messages ranged from as low as twice weekly (51) to 12 times daily <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(49)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_kNdQMqt">Some customization was designed to meet specific patient needs.</s><s xml:id="_hNAXPNQ">Two of the studiesboth variations of the individualized texting for adherence building (iTAB) technology-determined the number of reminders on the basis of individual medication schedules <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(52,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_HpaXAfP">Additionally, these interventions created a system using outreach messages or telephone calls to reengage participants who had not responded to several messages.</s><s xml:id="_ZwFyJ4s">One of the interventions had algorithmic systems that modified the frequency and message content on the basis of participant responses <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(47)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_VUvcxDw"><s xml:id="_x7KpUe8">SMS themes and content.</s><s xml:id="_pTgn5Tz">Beyond the mechanics of intervention delivery, the thematic elements of the messages delivered varied, both within a given intervention and across studies.</s><s xml:id="_8CDnGcq">Generally, the themes included the following: medication reminders, coping strategies or educational content, symptom surveillance, and encouragement or reinforcement (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_nmCP3Cq">All of the interventions included some form of medication reminder, with two interventions using medication reminders as their only SMS content <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(50,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_Ug5jg9S">Medication reminders varied from simple, closed-ended remarks ("Please remember to take your medication'' <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref>) to more complex, personalized messages ("John, your meds r important.</s><s xml:id="_8TBjSs4">It is time to take ur meds.</s><s xml:id="_BrUFmmk">Take ur big blue pill now.</s><s xml:id="_ZmgMqDY">Pls reply (A) took (D) didn't (G) snooze" <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref>).</s></p><p xml:id="_8BTE9nA"><s xml:id="_ByBvKju">Coping strategies, such as incorporation of cognitivebehavioral therapy techniques in messages, or education was provided in five of the nine interventions (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>) <ref type="bibr">(45-47, 49, 52)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_Vq7pcaF">Educational content focused on medication side effects <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(46)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(47)</ref>; symptom management and relapse prevention ("If I don't take my meds, I may become manic/ hypomanic or very irritable" <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52]</ref>; "Adhering to your medication on time and on the prescribed dose is the key to control your symptoms.</s><s xml:id="_6kMERvq">We are here to help you."</s><s xml:id="_N3uwHnh"><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>); and self-care and social resources <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_7ahsrny"><s xml:id="_UPKC2VK">Symptom surveillance or relapse monitoring was provided in five of the nine interventions <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(47)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(48)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(49)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">52)</ref> (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_uxCNc3D">The content was disease or patient centered.</s><s xml:id="_SF7Mjfn">For example, Granholm et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(49)</ref> included inquiries about hallucinations and socialization, both components of schizophrenia spectrum disorders, and Cullen et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(47)</ref> created patient-selected signs of relapse.</s><s xml:id="_PK9aNRD">Conversely, in two  <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_NAxyxd3">Many were reactionary to participants' responses.</s><s xml:id="_hc73AfF">For example, the testing for relapse prevention intervention provided a supportive follow-up statement when a participant denied the presence of a relapse symptom <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(47)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_wxTn4rd">In iTAB-CV (iTAB-cardiovascular), the second month of intervention followed up medication reminders with messages such as "You're doing wonderfully with taking your meds," with the option to customize the reinforcement <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(52)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_DeTSsFq">Additional intervention components. Table 3 provides a summary of additional components of the interventions.</head><p xml:id="_EMUKJda"><s xml:id="_STazFqg">Only two of the interventions were solely SMS based, without another element to the intervention <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(50,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_xzd4WVY">One study included a comparison group in which participants received both SMS and telephone calls to enhance medication adherence <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(48)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_MdktcYu">Two interventions involved embedded additional support people in the design <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_7vsye5Z">The LEAN trial (for lay health supporters, e-platform, award, and integration) required a health supporter who could receive and send text messages for each participant and allowed for village doctors or psychiatrists to be contacted if signs of relapse were endorsed <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_cjdpBQp">Similarly, the intervention by Cullen et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(47)</ref> included a customized threshold of symptom endorsement that would trigger contact of a provider, who would then follow up with participants within 24 hours.</s></p><p xml:id="_5D4EuZJ"><s xml:id="_j5CsmGd">Three of the interventions provided participants with educational content in addition to the SMS intervention <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(46,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">52,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_ttVvBQy">Themes from these sessions included benefits of adhering to medications, coping with serious mental illness diagnosis, strategies for adherence, and medication side effects.</s><s xml:id="_SCzAkuG">Finally, two of the studies provided participants with small monetary rewards or gifts in response to engagement with the intervention <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">49)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_cjN87vz">Medications and Measuring Adherence</head><p xml:id="_NJAFcBG"><s xml:id="_8Uw6XbD">The medication classes targeted for enhancing adherence included oral psychotropic medications (first-and secondgeneration antipsychotics, mood stabilizers, antiparkinsonism medications, hypnotics, anxiolytics, antidepressants, and anticonvulsants), long-acting injectables, oral medications for general medical illnesses (antihypertensives and antiretrovirals), or otherwise unspecified oral medications (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">4</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_TsYABK3">Studies differed in terms of how medication requirements affected participant inclusion or intervention target.</s><s xml:id="_YC3AgNK">For example, Montes et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(50)</ref> specified that participants must be prescribed only one oral antipsychotic to be included.</s><s xml:id="_xRMWxhd">Conversely, both iTAB studies explicitly targeted a minimum of two medications, including an appropriate psychotropic medication and an appropriate medication to address the comorbid general medical condition of the study population (i.e., hypertension or HIV) <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(52,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_TzbqJJd"><s xml:id="_nXZDDJu">In terms of measuring medication adherence, most of the studies used self-report, either exclusively or in combination with objective measures <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(46)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(47)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(49)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(50)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(51)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(52)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(53)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(54)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_3HEwRwb">Two used the Brief Adherence Rating Scale <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47)</ref>, one used the Morisky Green Adherence Questionnaire <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(50)</ref>, one used the Morisky Medication Adherence Scale-8 <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(51)</ref>, one used the Tablets Routine Questionnaire <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(52)</ref>, and the remaining three used study-specific measures <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(46,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">49,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_YF8gC4E">In addition to selfreport, four of the studies also used objective measures, such as random pill counts <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48)</ref>, medication refill records <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45)</ref>, number of pill bottle openings <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(52,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53)</ref>, or proportion of injections received <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_BhqjzBY">The study by Beebe et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(48)</ref> was the only study to use exclusively objective data, using proportion of pills or injections received based on pill counts or injection schedule, respectively Outcomes Medication adherence.</s><s xml:id="_gaMDSQ2">In seven of the 10 articles, significant improvement in medication adherence was observed from baseline to postintervention or in intervention groups compared with control groups <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(49)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(50)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(51)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(52)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54)</ref> (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">4</ref>).</s></p><p xml:id="_BXzTTxa"><s xml:id="_2nQY3kV">Particularly robust results were observed in the LEAN trial.</s><s xml:id="_DzBe492">In this trial, a significantly greater proportion of pills taken by the intervention group, compared with the control group, was maintained in subgroup analysis of participants who were nonadherent at baseline, representing efficacy of the intervention for particularly vulnerable participants <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_f4yYDrA">Furthermore, after a 3-month hiatus from the intervention, reintroduction for an extended 3 months  reaffirmed significant improvement in adherence, albeit to a smaller magnitude <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(54)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_redmwSn">Two publications, which reassessed adherence 3 months after the intervention, found maintenance of adherence gains after intervention completion <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(50,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_PUJkVx2"><s xml:id="_agCRjY2">Of the three publications that did not find significant improvement in medication adherence <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(46,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53)</ref>, lack of study power was cited as a potential contributor <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(46,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_pmRfWD8">Additionally, in an attempt to create a rigorous control group, researchers in one study sent a daily text message, albeit not the full intervention, to the control group, which was suggested by the authors as driving the high adherence (compared with pilot data in similar populations) in both the intervention and the control conditions <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(53)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_3WuRkKz">Similarly, in the study by <ref type="bibr">Granholm et al. (49)</ref>, only the subset of individuals living independently showed significant improvement in medication adherence, which was likely a function of high baseline medication adherence secondary to staff support given to individuals in assisted living.</s></p><p xml:id="_kZc8u4f"><s xml:id="_kZpCEq9">Attitudes toward medication.</s><s xml:id="_E8fdKWC">Five of the 10 articles assessed participant attitudes toward medication <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54)</ref> (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">4</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_F4pEFkB">Four used a version of the Drug Attitudes Inventory (DAI), including both LEAN trial studies (same study sample but reported on different time intervals) <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_daBBehQ">Granholm et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(49)</ref> used selfreport data collected directly via the intervention.</s><s xml:id="_xy53sxX">The two LEAN trial reports <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54)</ref> did not find a significant change in attitudes via DAI, but the other two studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(50,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51)</ref> reported significantly improved attitudes, one of which saw maintenance of effects 3 months after intervention completion <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(50)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_u7k6aCZ">Finally, a significant decrease in negative attitudes was observed via self-report data by Granholm et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(49)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_f3kuAKD"><s xml:id="_UBgcsmK">Clinical outcomes.</s><s xml:id="_dMkkFGz">All 10 papers measured at least one clinical outcome, such as serious mental illness symptoms, mood, quality of life, hospitalizations, and rate of suicide (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">4</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_4wKAyRk">Of these, seven reported at least one statistically significant improvement in clinical outcomes or reduction in symptomatology <ref type="bibr">(45, 47-50, 52, 54)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_TZTpw8b"><s xml:id="_Wxgsrbg">Study quality assessment.</s><s xml:id="_caUXjHn">The MQRS results are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_eMY2AGU">Scores for the included studies ranged from 8 to 13, with a mean score of 11.</s><s xml:id="_xjdkFSk">Strengths in study quality included the predominance of RCTs (N57) <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54)</ref> and inclusion of preintervention baseline and postintervention follow-up analysis (N54) <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(50)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(51)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(52)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_sBNHU2b">Lack of randomization or lack of inclusion of a control group limited three of the studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(46,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">49,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">52)</ref>, and underpowered analyses or ceiling effects were cited in studies that lacked significant findings in regard to medication adherence <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(46,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_4b2nDq3">Finally, although most of the studies collected data over the course of several months, medication adherence among persons with serious mental illness is a typically lifelong commitment.</s><s xml:id="_HDaQCGz">Thus, study duration limited the validity of the results on the long-term time scale.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_PEkQpTC">DISCUSSION</head><p xml:id="_SDCyQ2v"><s xml:id="_NzDF8cd">The delivery of clinical interventions using mobile technology is increasingly commonplace, including for persons with serious mental illness <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(39)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_PzzbyVQ">Furthermore, the demands of the current COVID-19 pandemic have accelerated the delivery of health care services via mobile technology <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">(56)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_W9QD8J7">However, the heterogeneity in the platforms of mobile technology (SMS, telephone calls, Web browsers, smartphone applications, video meetings, etc.), the content delivered (appointments, reminders, and education), and the goals of the interventions (medication adherence, health care delivery, and disease surveillance) create a challenge to those interested in utilizing remote delivery services in terms of how to be most effective.</s><s xml:id="_gv5EK3Q">Among persons with serious mental illness, this challenge is exacerbated by the interaction of the patients' underlying illness with treatment engagement <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">57)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_sZZmjuj"><s xml:id="_Zf45Vt4">Improvement in attitudes toward medications was observed across several studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(50,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_N5mFCQk">This finding has potential implications as to how the interventions are driving increased medication adherence.</s><s xml:id="_7g7Kfgs">Although in its simplest form, text messaging can serve as a reminder to take medications, targeting unintentional nonadherence alone (i.e., forgetfulness) addresses only one of the drivers of patient behavior.</s><s xml:id="_ZEbzpbz">Attitudes and beliefs around medication, side-effect profiles, and insight into illness have been proposed as prominent components of medication nonadherence in populations with serious mental illness <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">58)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_APjetap">Of note, two of the studies that reported improved attitudes toward medication, Montes et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(50)</ref> and Menon et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(51)</ref>, represented the most minimalist interventions of those included.</s><s xml:id="_qnhEPwm">Both used a one-way SMS messaging model, with medication-reminder-only content, provided no additional interventional components, and messaged only once daily or twice weekly, respectively.</s><s xml:id="_qXdXd8K">Furthermore, both included a 3-month follow-up and showed maintenance of the improved adherence.</s><s xml:id="_NeAtxK7">Given that the other interventions included multiple content themes and supplemental interventional components, these two studies offer evidence that even simple SMS messaging has the potential to drive robust changes in patient behavior.</s></p><p xml:id="_N98Yx7h"><s xml:id="_3rUdMQU">In contrast, two of the interventions provided evidence that inclusion of providers and support persons for patients with mental illness is a feasible and efficacious extension of texting platforms <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_YCB9pMY">Xu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45)</ref> integrated local physicians, psychiatrists, and personal support members into their intervention in the LEAN trial.</s><s xml:id="_bRcfAcP">The integration of support was particularly compelling, given the rural setting of the study, where technology such as SMS can have an even greater impact on enhancing connectivity.</s><s xml:id="_WbYGZMA">Beyond improved medication adherence, risk of relapse and rates of rehospitalization were significantly reduced in this integrated</s></p><p xml:id="_p525JCY"><s xml:id="_xU3xhBJ">Psychiatric Services 73:10, October 2022 ps.psychiatryonline.org</s><s xml:id="_HhjzBRg">1161 model.</s><s xml:id="_qPMkx2P">Provision of support aligns with general treatment ideologies for serious mental illness and schizophrenia in particular (the diagnosis of patients in the LEAN trial), in which intradisciplinary approaches to treatment have been encouraged (59), including integration of family members (60).</s><s xml:id="_njhr9mX">Cullen et al. (47) incorporated direct contact with patient providers when a predetermined, patient-specific threshold of symptom endorsement was met via SMS responses.</s><s xml:id="_Q5ssHJF">The opportunity for providers to intervene at early signs of relapse is an exciting prospect in disease management.</s><s xml:id="_NRk8DwR">It conceptually aligns with best-care strategies for treating schizophrenia, in which higher rates of relapse have been demonstrated among persons with medication nonadherence in both placebo-controlled trials and reviews of hospitalization records (61).</s></p><p xml:id="_9zbnNRM"><s xml:id="_jWmMDp8">Another promising expansion of more recent interventions includes targeting comorbid conditions beyond serious mental illness through SMS platforms.</s><s xml:id="_PRpBHvm">In the iTAB and iTAB-CV studies, antiretroviral and antihypertensive medication adherence, respectively, was also integrated into the model <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">52)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_wsyFFYA">Antiretrovirals were taken closer to their intended time window by participants in the iTAB intervention group.</s><s xml:id="_tzqYdYU">In iTAB-CV, significant reduction in systolic blood pressure was observed from baseline to postintervention.</s><s xml:id="_JxmKk6N">High rates of cardiovascular disease have been reported among those with bipolar disorder <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">(62)</ref>, and there is a disproportionate prevalence of HIV among those with psychiatric conditions <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">(63)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_cv9UyFz">Nonadherence to medications for chronic general medical conditions have their own consequences in terms of well-being, which can affect patients' ability to manage their mental health.</s><s xml:id="_WVMqXXz">Furthermore, having to take multiple medications creates increased demands on patients in terms of organization and routine; thus, platforms that address multiple conditions or medications offer a low-cost, high-yield collaborative care model, particularly for high-need patients.</s></p><p xml:id="_9FcbtmA"><s xml:id="_Kcy9Nu2">Our review illustrated that many practical questions remain in terms of how to most effectively deliver an SMS intervention to individuals with serious mental illness.</s><s xml:id="_W69Dy6z">Despite a rather narrow set of inclusion criteria, the interventions varied widely, and few clear themes emerged in terms of what was most effective.</s><s xml:id="_7C3vsh6">One-and two-way messaging, customized and standardized content, and frequency of messaging ranging from infrequent messages to several daily messages led to appreciable improvement in medication adherence.</s><s xml:id="_h9nsQ4E">Additionally, measurement of medication adherence, although captured in each study, was largely via self-report or by methods that allowed for introduction of additional confounding variables.</s><s xml:id="_KdTbYNv">Furthermore, study limitations, such as poorly powered studies, lack of a control group, ceiling effects, and relatively short study durations (particularly in light of the chronic nature of medication therapy required for most of the included conditions) hindered interpretation of what is likely to make a clear impact on clinical outcomes.</s></p><p xml:id="_HYMck2y"><s xml:id="_yRxpeHJ">Future studies are needed to address remaining limitations, both in terms of study methodology and real-world application.</s><s xml:id="_CUCUXEt">Creating multiple study conditions, each of which captures a single dimension of an intervention, would allow for more clarity about which specific components are effective.</s><s xml:id="_Vveqh6n">For example, having two groups, one that receives one-way messaging and one that receives two-way messaging, or having groups that receive varying numbers of messages a day would aid in finding the "sweet spot" between sufficient reminders and fatiguability.</s><s xml:id="_X5UheZF">In terms of real-world application, studies that follow participants for years (with or without continual interventional support) would illuminate the durability of study effects, the time scale for habit formation, and the potential need to reinstate interventions after certain intervals without them.</s><s xml:id="_5vMmSqV">Finally, increasing the objectivity of the measure of "improved adherence" by using automated pill counts or patient-recorded video clips of taking medications may strengthen the quality of the data but must be balanced with proper controls to reduce the risk of introducing potential confounders.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_v4CHt2r">CONCLUSIONS</head><p xml:id="_DuYsrvW"><s xml:id="_PesGNk6">This review has provided evidence that increasing medication adherence via SMS platforms among people with serious mental illness is likely feasible and achievable.</s><s xml:id="_vnmrkBe">Most interventions resulted in significant improvement in medication adherence with SMS and associated improvement on clinical measures, including reduced rehospitalization, improved quality of life, and decreased symptom burden <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">52,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_Fw4rdrD">A strength is that these findings were for several diverse patient populations across the included studies, with differing geographical locations, races, ethnicities, and SES.</s><s xml:id="_cpqa8qw">However, caution should be used in presuming the robustness of these findings, because many of the measures of improved medication adherence were subjective.</s></p><p xml:id="_UM6kq2w"><s xml:id="_Cj6nk7Y">Future studies are needed with better controls for confounds to allow for identification of what is driving study outcomes, longer study durations to confirm durability of effects, more objective measurement of medication adherence, and methodology that evaluates the minimal time needed to establish a habit of medication adherence and how to maintain it once it has been established.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLE 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_rbzxP27"><s xml:id="_AfKvBjX">Demographic, setting, and duration characteristics and quality scores of 10 articles included in the systematic review a</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Article</cell><cell>Mean age</cell><cell>Women N %</cell><cell>Socioeconomic status</cell><cell>Race-ethnicity</cell><cell>Location</cell><cell>Recruitment care setting</cell><cell>Study duration</cell><cell>MQRS score b</cell></row><row><cell>Xu et al.,</cell><cell cols="3">46.0 154 55.4 Low</cell><cell>nr</cell><cell>China (rural)</cell><cell>Enrolled in community</cell><cell>5.5 months</cell><cell>13</cell></row><row><cell>2019 (45)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>treatment program</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mohammadi</cell><cell>33.1</cell><cell cols="2">37 61.7 Moderate</cell><cell>nr</cell><cell>Iran (urban)</cell><cell>Outpatient psychiatric</cell><cell>6 weeks</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>et al.,</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>clinic(s)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>2016 (46)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Cullen et al.,</cell><cell>49.1</cell><cell cols="2">17 42.5 nr</cell><cell>Black, 85%;</cell><cell cols="2">United States Enrolled in community</cell><cell>6 months</cell><cell>11</cell></row><row><cell>2020 (47)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>White, 7.5%;</cell><cell></cell><cell>treatment program</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>other, 7.5%</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Beebe et al.,</cell><cell>48.7</cell><cell cols="2">19 63.3 nr</cell><cell>Black, 50%;</cell><cell>United States</cell><cell>Enrolled in community</cell><cell>3 months</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>2014 (48)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>White, 50%</cell><cell>(Southeast)</cell><cell>treatment program</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Granholm et al.,</cell><cell>48.7</cell><cell>13 31</cell><cell>nr</cell><cell>Black, 7%;</cell><cell>United States</cell><cell>Outpatient residential</cell><cell>12 weeks</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>2012 (49)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>White, 74;</cell><cell>(San Diego)</cell><cell>and treatment</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Hispanic, 10%</cell><cell></cell><cell>settings</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Montes et al.,</cell><cell>39.6</cell><cell cols="2">85 33.5 nr</cell><cell>nr</cell><cell>Spain</cell><cell>Outpatient psychiatric</cell><cell>6 months;</cell><cell>13</cell></row><row><cell>2012 (50)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>clinic(s)</cell><cell>3 months of</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>intervention</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Menon et al.,</cell><cell>37.9</cell><cell cols="2">63 47.7 Low</cell><cell>nr</cell><cell>India</cell><cell>Academic medical</cell><cell>6 months;</cell><cell>12</cell></row><row><cell>2018 (51)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>center, outpatient</cell><cell>3 months of</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>psychiatric clinic(s)</cell><cell>intervention</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Levin et al.,</cell><cell>51.5</cell><cell>20 53</cell><cell>nr</cell><cell>Black, 73.7%;</cell><cell>United States</cell><cell>Academic medical</cell><cell>3 months;</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>2019 (52)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>White, 23.7%;</cell><cell>(urban)</cell><cell>center</cell><cell>2 months of</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>other, 2.6%</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>intervention</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Moore et al.,</cell><cell>47.2</cell><cell>6 12</cell><cell>nr</cell><cell>White, 54%</cell><cell>United States</cell><cell>Research program at a</cell><cell>30 days</cell><cell>11</cell></row><row><cell>2015 (53)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(San Diego)</cell><cell>university</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Cai et al.,</cell><cell cols="3">46.0 154 55.4 Low</cell><cell>nr</cell><cell>China (rural)</cell><cell>Enrolled in community</cell><cell>18 months;</cell><cell>13</cell></row><row><cell>2020 (54) c</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>treatment program</cell><cell>6 or 12</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>months of</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>intervention</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Average or total 44.6 414 44.5</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>TABLE 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s xml:id="_usrSbJy">(52,53)y of short message service (SMS) texting messaging interventions in 10 articles included in the systematic review a the interventions that centered on individuals with bipolar disorder, surveillance focused on monitoring participants' daily mood(52,53).Finally, encouragement or reinforcement messages were provided in five of the nine interventions(46-48, 52, 53)(Table</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Content</cell><cell>Themes Details</cell><cell>Medication reminder, education Medication reminder and education</cell><cell>or coping strategy, symptom or coping strategy, daily; symptom</cell><cell>and relapse surveillance and relapse surveillance, monthly</cell><cell>Medication reminder, education Medication reminder or education</cell><cell>or coping strategy, or coping strategy, daily;</cell><cell>encouragement-encouragement-reinforcement,</cell><cell>reinforcement daily</cell><cell>Medication reminder, education Medication reminder, education</cell><cell>or coping strategy, symptom or coping strategy, symptom</cell><cell>and relapse surveillance, and relapse surveillance, or</cell><cell>encouragement-encouragement-reinforcement,</cell><cell>reinforcement once daily minimum</cell><cell>Medication reminder, symptom Medication reminder, symptom</cell><cell>and relapse surveillance, and relapse surveillance, or</cell><cell>encouragement-encouragement-reinforcement,</cell><cell>reinforcement once daily</cell><cell>Medication reminder, symptom Medication reminder, symptom</cell><cell>and relapse surveillance, and relapse surveillance, and</cell><cell>education or coping strategy education or coping strategy,</cell><cell>each 4 times daily (total of</cell><cell>12 messages per day)</cell><cell>Medication reminder Medication reminder, once daily</cell><cell>Medication reminder Medication reminder, once daily</cell><cell>Medication reminder, education During month 1: education or</cell><cell>or coping strategy, symptom coping strategy, symptom and</cell><cell>and relapse surveillance, relapse surveillance, each once</cell><cell>encouragement-daily; during month 2: medication</cell><cell>reinforcement reminder, once daily for each</cell><cell>medication; symptom and relapse</cell><cell>surveillance and encouragement-</cell><cell>reinforcement, each once daily</cell><cell>Medication reminder, Medication reminder, once daily</cell><cell>encouragement-for each medication;</cell><cell>reinforcement encouragement-reinforcement,</cell><cell>once daily minimum</cell><cell>Medication reminder, education Medication reminder, once daily;</cell><cell>or coping strategy, symptom education or coping strategy,</cell><cell>and relapse surveillance once every other day; symptom</cell><cell>and relapse surveillance, monthly</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Follow-up</cell><cell>Text Provider</cell><cell>No Yes</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>No No</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Yes Yes</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Yes No</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Yes No</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>No No</cell><cell>No No</cell><cell>Yes No</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Yes No</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>No Yes</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Frequency</cell><cell>minimum</cell><cell>Once daily</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Twice daily</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Twice daily</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Once daily</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>12 times daily</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Once daily</cell><cell>2 per week</cell><cell>3 or more daily b</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>3 or more daily b</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Once daily</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Message customizing</cell><cell>Content Timing</cell><cell>No No</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>No nr</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Yes Yes</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Yes nr</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Yes Yes</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>No Yes</cell><cell>No Yes</cell><cell>Yes Yes</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Yes Yes</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>No No</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>One-way</cell><cell>vs. two-Automated</cell><cell>way SMS vs. manual</cell><cell>2 Automated</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1 Automated</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2 Automated</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2 Manual</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2 Automated</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1 Automated</cell><cell>1 nr</cell><cell>2 Automated</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2 Automated</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2 Automated</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Article</cell><cell>Xu et al., 2019 (45)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Mohammadi et al.,</cell><cell>2016 (46)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Cullen et al., 2020 (47)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Beebe et al., 2014 (48)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Granholm et al.,</cell><cell>2012 (49)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Montes et al., 2012 (50)</cell><cell>Menon et al., 2018 (51)</cell><cell>Levin et al., 2019 (52)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Moore et al., 2015 (53)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Cai et al., 2020 (54) c</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note xml:id="_pM8GAuF"><p><s xml:id="_EAeHUeu">a nr, not reported.</s><s xml:id="_UaerRSE">b Baseline minimum dependent on number of medications.</s><s xml:id="_q2mEftG">c An extension of the study by Xu et al., 2019 (45).</s><s xml:id="_CQm7RXU">Psychiatric Services 73:10, October 2022 ps.psychiatryonline.org</s><s xml:id="_4gAD35w">1157 of</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>TABLE 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_wuTqSpe"><s xml:id="_kk6uwyC">Intervention components in the studies included in the systematic review</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Intervention or</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Article</cell><cell>trial name a</cell><cell>SMS only</cell><cell>Additional interventions</cell></row><row><cell>Xu et al., 2019 (45),</cell><cell>LEAN trial</cell><cell>No</cell><cell>Monetary rewards or gifts, provider or</cell></row><row><cell>Cai et al. (54)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>support person involvement</cell></row><row><cell>Mohammadi et al., 2016 (46)</cell><cell></cell><cell>No</cell><cell>Educational materials or sessions</cell></row><row><cell>Cullen et al., 2020 (47)</cell><cell>T4RP</cell><cell>No</cell><cell>Provider or support person involvement</cell></row><row><cell>Beebe et al., 2014 (48)</cell><cell>TIPS</cell><cell>No</cell><cell>Telephone calls</cell></row><row><cell>Granholm et al., 2012 (49)</cell><cell>MATS</cell><cell>No</cell><cell>Monetary rewards or gifts</cell></row><row><cell>Montes et al., 2012 (50)</cell><cell></cell><cell>Yes</cell><cell>None</cell></row><row><cell>Menon et al., 2018 (51)</cell><cell></cell><cell>Yes</cell><cell>None</cell></row><row><cell>Levin et al., 2019 (52)</cell><cell>iTAB-CV</cell><cell>No</cell><cell>Educational materials or sessions</cell></row><row><cell>Moore et al., 2015 (53)</cell><cell>iTAB</cell><cell>No</cell><cell>Educational materials or sessions</cell></row></table><note xml:id="_agr6tDN"><p><s xml:id="_QtBT7x4">a iTab, individualized texting for adherence building; iTab-CV, individualized texting for adherence buildingcardiovascular; LEAN trial, lay health supporters, E-platform, Award, and iNtegration; MATS, Mobile Assessment and Treatment for Schizophrenia; T4RP, Texting for Relapse Prevention; TIPS, Telephone Intervention Problem Solving for Schizophrenia (adapted to include short message service [SMS] texting messaging).</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>TABLE 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_cKqEN8Z"><s xml:id="_vNRNEeF">Measures and outcomes in the studies included in the systematic review</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Medication adherence</cell></row></table><note xml:id="_vbpUZXv"><p><s xml:id="_huUv9Wr">continued Psychiatric Services 73:10, October 2022 ps.psychiatryonline.org</s><s xml:id="_K2qShDP">1159</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>TABLE 4 ,</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_xwxfu2k"><s xml:id="_KhB9JHw">continued American National Adult Reading Test; BARS, Brief Adherence Rating Scale; BDI-II-Persian, Beck Depression Inventory-II-Persian; BPRS, Brief Psychiatric Rating Scale; BUES, Boston University Empowerment Scale; CGI, Clinical Global Impression; CGI-SCH, SI, and DC, Clinical Global Impression-schizophrenia, -severity of illness, and -degree of change; DAI-10, Drug Attitude Inventory-10; EQ-5D VAS, Euroqol 5D, visual analog scale; ILSS, Independent Living Skills Survey; eCap, a pharmacy bottle cap that tracks each opening with date and time; MADRS, Montgomery-Åsberg Depression Rating Scale; MAQ, Morisky Green Adherence Questionnaire; MMAS, Morisky Medication Adherence Scale; PANSS, Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale; RAS-R, Recovery Assessment Scale-Revised; SRHI, Self-Report Habit Index; SUMD, Scale to Assess Unawareness of Mental Disorder; TRQ, Tablets Routine Questionnaire; WHODAS, World Health Organization Disability Assessment Schedule 2.0; WHOQOL, WHO Quality of Life Instrument; YMRS, Young Mania Rating Scale.</s><s xml:id="_YPK868w">An extension of the study by Xu et al., 2019 (45).</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Medication adherence</cell></row></table><note xml:id="_djT2uBB"><p><s xml:id="_ZYedNP9">a ANART, b For at least one analysis related to medication adherence.</s><s xml:id="_6gBsxJZ">c</s></p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1154" xml:id="foot_0"><p xml:id="_Vk8h4sm"><s xml:id="_hxTWgWe">ps.psychiatryonline.org</s><s xml:id="_Cx5vgmQ">Psychiatric Services 73:10, October 2022 SYSTEMATIC LITERATURE REVIEW OF TEXT MESSAGING</s></p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p xml:id="_Nhe748d"><s xml:id="_B9ZT8nE">Psychiatric Services 73:10, October 2022 ps.psychiatryonline.org</s><s xml:id="_q2YMvuf">1155</s></p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_2"><p xml:id="_nRX4grt"><s xml:id="_TGkMBaH">a nr, not reported.</s><s xml:id="_NV8zCkb">b Methodological Quality Rating Scale.</s><s xml:id="_yuWHZSD">Possible scores range from 0 to 16, with higher scores indicating greater methodological quality.</s><s xml:id="_XnPzfga">c An extension of the study by Xu et al., 2019 (45); only duration and rating scale score differ.</s><s xml:id="_n6jX7A2">1156 ps.psychiatryonline.org</s><s xml:id="_ZhpFfjf">Psychiatric Services 73:10, October 2022 SYSTEMATIC LITERATURE REVIEW OF TEXT MESSAGING</s></p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div xml:id="_zdsBqbC"><p xml:id="_gDsSWek"><s xml:id="_e9rRjmF"><rs type="funder">National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute of the National Institutes of Health</rs>.</s><s xml:id="_UVrFUwJ">The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the National Institutes of Health.</s></p><p xml:id="_9E7kEj6"><s xml:id="_8xH5Mhr"><rs type="person">Dr. Sajatovic</rs> reports receipt of research grants from <rs type="funder">Alkermes</rs>, <rs type="funder">Nuromate</rs>, and <rs type="funder">Otsuka</rs>; service as a consultant to <rs type="institution">Alkermes</rs>, <rs type="institution">Bracket</rs>,</s></p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_4WhSpEx">Cognitive impairment in schizophrenia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rse</forename><surname>Keefe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Harvey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-3-642-25758-2_2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_ZmKgfhV">Handbook of Experimental Pharmacology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Geyer</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Gross</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">213</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Novel Antischizophrenia Treatments</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Keefe RSE, Harvey PD: Cognitive impairment in schizophrenia; in Novel Antischizophrenia Treatments (Handbook of Experimental Pharmacology, 213). Edited by Geyer MA, Gross G. New York, Springer, 2012</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_sD5xuRD">Social and occupational functioning impairment in patients in partial versus complete remission of a major depressive disorder episode: six-month prospective epidemiological study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Romera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Perez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Menchón</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_hrhaeae">Eur Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="58" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Romera I, Perez V, Menchón JM, et al: Social and occupational functioning impairment in patients in partial versus complete remission of a major depressive disorder episode: six-month prospective epidemiological study. Eur Psychiatry 2010; 25:58-65</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Nx4eWcq">The relationship between neurocognitive functioning and occupational functioning in bipolar disorder: a literature review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Duarte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Becerra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Cruise</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_qsGYSuS">Eur J Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="659" to="678" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Duarte W, Becerra R, Cruise K: The relationship between neu- rocognitive functioning and occupational functioning in bipolar disorder: a literature review. Eur J Psychol 2016; 12:659-678</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_fjMsRwM">Quality of life of people with mental health problems: a synthesis of qualitative research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Connell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Brazier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>'cathain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/1477-7525-10-138</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_XSNspmK">Health Qual Life Outcomes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">138</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Connell J, Brazier J, O&apos;Cathain A, et al: Quality of life of people with mental health problems: a synthesis of qualitative research. Health Qual Life Outcomes 2012; 10:138</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_XdjDa2k">Beliefs, suffering, and healing: a clinical practice model for families experiencing mental illness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Marshall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Moules</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_mQWYCM8">Perspect Psychiatr Care</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="197" to="208" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Marshall A, Bell JM, Moules NJ: Beliefs, suffering, and healing: a clinical practice model for families experiencing mental illness. Perspect Psychiatr Care 2010; 46:197-208</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_c9GKk3A">Antipsychotic drugs versus placebo for relapse prevention in schizophrenia: a systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Leucht</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tardy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Komossa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0140-6736(12)60239-6</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_En7dZ2e">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">379</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2063" to="2071" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Leucht S, Tardy M, Komossa K, et al: Antipsychotic drugs versus placebo for relapse prevention in schizophrenia: a systematic re- view and meta-analysis. Lancet 2012; 379:2063-2071</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_7KZRXRN">Initial severity of schizophrenia and efficacy of antipsychotics: participant-level meta-analysis of 6 placebo-controlled studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Furukawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Levine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tanaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2014.2127</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Dz5vAky">JAMA Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="21" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Furukawa TA, Levine SZ, Tanaka S, et al: Initial severity of schizophrenia and efficacy of antipsychotics: participant-level meta-analysis of 6 placebo-controlled studies. JAMA Psychiatry 2015; 72:14-21</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_TuENZek">Atypical antipsychotics in bipolar disorder: systematic review of randomised trials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Derry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/1471-244x-7-40</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_s8RShrj">BMC Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">40</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Derry S, Moore RA: Atypical antipsychotics in bipolar disorder: systematic review of randomised trials. BMC Psychiatry 2007; 7: 40</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_QH3JZGr">Quality of life assessment in antidepressant treatment of patients with depression and/or anxiety disorder</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dzevlan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Redzepagic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hadzisalihovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5455/msm.2019.31.14-18</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_qjzstqQ">Mater Sociomed</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Dzevlan A, Redzepagic R, Hadzisalihovic M, et al: Quality of life assessment in antidepressant treatment of patients with depres- sion and/or anxiety disorder. Mater Sociomed 2019; 31:14-18</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_bugqEz4">Effects of antipsychotic medications on quality of life and psychosocial functioning in patients with early-stage schizophrenia: 1-year follow-up naturalistic study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Zgy2EaJ">Compr Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1006" to="1012" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Guo X, Zhang Z, Zhai J, et al: Effects of antipsychotic medications on quality of life and psychosocial functioning in patients with early-stage schizophrenia: 1-year follow-up naturalistic study. Compr Psychiatry 2012; 53:1006-1012</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_xuAGEng">Why do psychiatric patients stop antipsychotic medication? A systematic review of reasons for nonadherence to medication in patients with serious mental illness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Velligan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sajatovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hatch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2147/ppa.s124658</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_49jWXAg">Patient Prefer Adherence</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="449" to="468" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Velligan DI, Sajatovic M, Hatch A, et al: Why do psychiatric pa- tients stop antipsychotic medication? A systematic review of reasons for nonadherence to medication in patients with serious mental illness. Patient Prefer Adherence 2017; 11:449-468</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_F5kpnAv">The expert consensus guideline series: adherence problems in patients with serious and persistent mental illness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bellack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bowden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Bowie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4088/jcp.7090su1cj</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_cVtft6R">J Clin Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="48" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bellack AS, Bowden CL, Bowie CR, et al: The expert consensus guideline series: adherence problems in patients with serious and persistent mental illness. J Clin Psychiatry 2009; 70:1-48</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_gVC9YaV">Treatment adherence with antipsychotic medications in bipolar disorder</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sajatovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Valenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Blow</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_9b4p4Ga">Bipolar Disord</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="232" to="241" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sajatovic M, Valenstein M, Blow FC, et al: Treatment adherence with antipsychotic medications in bipolar disorder. Bipolar Disord 2006; 8:232-241</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_WgDWk5P">Prevalence of and risk factors for medication nonadherence in patients with schizophrenia: a comprehensive review of recent literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Lacro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Dunn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Dolder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_PrxwEv4">J Clin Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="892" to="909" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lacro JP, Dunn LB, Dolder CR, et al: Prevalence of and risk factors for medication nonadherence in patients with schizo- phrenia: a comprehensive review of recent literature. J Clin Psychiatry 2002; 63:892-909</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_sPaHXCW">Determinants of suboptimal medication adherence in patients with a major depressive episode</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Baeza-Velasco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Olié</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Béziat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_SzntkzX">Depress Anxiety</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="244" to="251" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Baeza-Velasco C, Olié E, Béziat S, et al: Determinants of subop- timal medication adherence in patients with a major depressive episode. Depress Anxiety 2019; 36:244-251</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_SxWwZxt">The Expert Consensus Guideline Series: adherence problems in patients with serious and persistent mental illness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Velligan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Weiden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sajatovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_YZcNyJS">J Clin Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="46" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Velligan DI, Weiden PJ, Sajatovic M, et al: The Expert Consensus Guideline Series: adherence problems in patients with serious and persistent mental illness. J Clin Psychiatry 2009; 70:1-46</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_gFnJD7r">Effectiveness of telemedicine: a systematic review of reviews</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Ekeland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bowes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Flottorp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2010.08.006</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_JsjTfru">Int J Med Inform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="736" to="771" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ekeland AG, Bowes A, Flottorp S: Effectiveness of telemedi- cine: a systematic review of reviews. Int J Med Inform 2010; 79:736-771</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_msnyAS3">Effectiveness of mHealth interventions in improving medication adherence among people with hypertension: a systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Xiong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Berkhouse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schooler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11906-018-0886-7</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_xVfT62s">Curr Hypertens Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">86</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Xiong S, Berkhouse H, Schooler M, et al: Effectiveness of mHealth interventions in improving medication adherence among people with hypertension: a systematic review. Curr Hypertens Rep 2018; 20:86</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_h48vZ9p">Attitudes, beliefs, and willingness toward the use of mHealth tools for medication adherence in the Florida mHealth Adherence Project for People Living With HIV (FL-mAPP): pilot questionnaire study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Morano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Clauson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/12900</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_dKPArR6">JMIR Mhealth Uhealth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e12900</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Morano JP, Clauson K, Zhou Z, et al: Attitudes, beliefs, and willingness toward the use of mHealth tools for medication ad- herence in the Florida mHealth Adherence Project for People Living With HIV (FL-mAPP): pilot questionnaire study. JMIR Mhealth Uhealth 2019; 7:e12900</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_yvfuJaF">Utilizing mobile technologies to improve physical activity and medication adherence in patients with heart failure and diabetes mellitus: rationale and design of the TARGET-HF-DM Trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sharma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mentz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Granger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_KnjuGpY">Am Heart J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">211</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sharma A, Mentz RJ, Granger BB, et al: Utilizing mobile tech- nologies to improve physical activity and medication adherence in patients with heart failure and diabetes mellitus: rationale and design of the TARGET-HF-DM Trial. Am Heart J 2019; 211:22-33</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Vm3YHF8">Use and content of primary care office-based vs telemedicine care visits during the COVID-19 pandemic in the US</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Alexander</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tajanlangit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Heyward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.21476</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_DQUzjRE">JAMA Netw Open</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e2021476</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Alexander GC, Tajanlangit M, Heyward J, et al: Use and content of primary care office-based vs telemedicine care visits during the COVID-19 pandemic in the US. JAMA Netw Open 2020; 3: e2021476</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_dnnk9jY">Telemedicine: patient-provider clinical engagement during the COVID-19 pandemic and beyond</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Contreras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Metzger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Beane</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_md4sDks">J Gastrointest Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1692" to="1697" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Contreras CM, Metzger GA, Beane JD, et al: Telemedicine: patient-provider clinical engagement during the COVID-19 pan- demic and beyond. J Gastrointest Surg 2020; 24:1692-1697</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_jKPXuPw">Wearable health technology and electronic health record integration: scoping review and future directions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Dinh-Le</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chokshi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_hChQckn">JMIR Mhealth Uhealth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12861</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Dinh-Le C, Chuang R, Chokshi S, et al: Wearable health tech- nology and electronic health record integration: scoping review and future directions. JMIR Mhealth Uhealth 2019; 7:e12861</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_UUdeKrQ">A research on the classification and applicability of the mobile health applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Pires</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Marques</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Garcia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_NRcbC4Y">J Pers Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">11</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Pires IM, Marques G, Garcia NM, et al: A research on the clas- sification and applicability of the mobile health applications. J Pers Med 2020; 10:11</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_nr8PPFa">Telemedicine technology: a review of services, equipment, and other aspects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Stanley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_NUBwjB5">Curr Allergy Asthma Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">60</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Baker J, Stanley A: Telemedicine technology: a review of services, equipment, and other aspects. Curr Allergy Asthma Rep 2018; 18:60</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_nGA9xdK">Health &quot;smart&quot; home: information technology for patients at home</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Rialle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Duchene</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Noury</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1089/15305620260507530</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_KX4Y6nQ">Telemed J e-Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="395" to="409" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rialle V, Duchene F, Noury N, et al: Health &quot;smart&quot; home: in- formation technology for patients at home. Telemed J e-Health 2002; 8:395-409</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_pakagud">Fundamentals for future mobile-Health (mHealth): a systematic review of mobile phone and web-based text messaging in mental health</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Berrouiguet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Baca-García</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Brandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_5ZDxCTn">J Med Internet Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">135</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Berrouiguet S, Baca-García E, Brandt S, et al: Fundamentals for future mobile-Health (mHealth): a systematic review of mobile phone and web-based text messaging in mental health. J Med Internet Res 2016; 18:e135</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Db4F2Y7">Online, social media and mobile technologies for psychosis treatment: a systematic review on novel user-led interventions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Alvarez-Jimenez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Alcazar-Corcoles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">González-</forename><surname>Blanch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_qc496bk">Schizophrenia Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">156</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="96" to="106" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Alvarez-Jimenez M, Alcazar-Corcoles MA, González-Blanch C, et al: Online, social media and mobile technologies for psychosis treatment: a systematic review on novel user-led interventions. Schizophrenia Res 2014; 156:96-106</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_CZuJhtE">Acceptability of interventions delivered online and through mobile phones for people who experience severe mental health problems: a systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Berry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Lobban</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Emsley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/jmir.5250</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_RJGABj5">J Med Internet Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e121</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Berry N, Lobban F, Emsley R, et al: Acceptability of interventions delivered online and through mobile phones for people who ex- perience severe mental health problems: a systematic review. J Med Internet Res 2016; 18:e121</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_dKBrCeV">The use of text messaging to improve clinical engagement for individuals with psychosis: systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>D'arcey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Collaton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kozloff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/16993</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_HKyfd9v">JMIR Ment Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e16993</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">D&apos;Arcey J, Collaton J, Kozloff N, et al: The use of text messaging to improve clinical engagement for individuals with psychosis: systematic review. JMIR Ment Health 2020; 7:e16993</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_GEugbvT">Strategies to improve medication adherence in patients with schizophrenia: the role of support services</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>El-Mallakh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Findlay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2147/ndt.s56107</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_CJDC7JY">Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1077" to="1090" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">El-Mallakh P, Findlay J: Strategies to improve medication ad- herence in patients with schizophrenia: the role of support ser- vices. Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat 2015; 11:1077-1090</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_tnUUquj">The effectiveness of mobile phone text messaging in improving medication adherence for patients with chronic diseases: a systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ershad</forename><surname>Sarabi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sadoughi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jamshidi</forename><surname>Orak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_wUvPJg3">Iran Red Crescent Med J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">18</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ershad Sarabi R, Sadoughi F, Jamshidi Orak R, et al: The effec- tiveness of mobile phone text messaging in improving medication adherence for patients with chronic diseases: a systematic review. Iran Red Crescent Med J 2016; 18:18</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_KTdmWcq">Information and communication technology based prompting for treatment compliance for people with serious mental illness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kauppi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Välimäki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hätönen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_d8EBGxq">Cochrane Database Syst Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">9960</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kauppi K, Välimäki M, Hätönen HM, et al: Information and communication technology based prompting for treatment com- pliance for people with serious mental illness. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 2014:2014:CD009960</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_4yA5vPE">The use of mobile apps and SMS messaging as physical and mental health interventions: systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Rathbone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Prescott</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_2pdaRr4">J Med Internet Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e295</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rathbone AL, Prescott J: The use of mobile apps and SMS mes- saging as physical and mental health interventions: systematic review. J Med Internet Res 2017; 19:e295</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qjdVSUs">Technological interventions for medication adherence in adult mental health and substance use disorders: a systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Steinkamp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Goldblatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Borodovsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_xAx23Fu">JMIR Ment Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12493</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Steinkamp JM, Goldblatt N, Borodovsky JT, et al: Technological interventions for medication adherence in adult mental health and substance use disorders: a systematic review. JMIR Ment Health 2019; 6:e12493</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_aVgXEhA">Text messaging interventions for individuals with mental health disorders including substance use: a systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Simpson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hughes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.psychres.2016.06.050</idno>
		<ptr target="psychiatryonline.org1163" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_bthgYC8">Psychiatric Services</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">243</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016-10">2016. October 2022 ps</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Psychiatry Res</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Watson T, Simpson S, Hughes C: Text messaging interventions for individuals with mental health disorders including substance use: a systematic review. Psychiatry Res 2016; 243:255-262 Psychiatric Services 73:10, October 2022 ps.psychiatryonline.org 1163</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_GNaQxMe">Integrative review of mobile phone contacts and medication adherence in severe mental illness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bright</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Wp3VMFd">J Am Psychiatr Nurses Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="209" to="222" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bright CE: Integrative review of mobile phone contacts and medication adherence in severe mental illness. J Am Psychiatr Nurses Assoc 2018; 24:209-222</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_wQzcxqd">Telemedicine interventions for medication adherence in mental illness: a systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Basit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mathews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Kunik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.genhosppsych.2019.11.004</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_jBjX6r9">Gen Hosp Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="28" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Basit SA, Mathews N, Kunik ME: Telemedicine interventions for medication adherence in mental illness: a systematic review. Gen Hosp Psychiatry 2020; 62:28-36</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qpcF9BF">Mobile phone and smartphone use by people with serious mental illness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Niv</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1176/appi.ps.201900203</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_y422Ygd">Psychiatry Serv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="280" to="283" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Young AS, Cohen AN, Niv N, et al: Mobile phone and smartphone use by people with serious mental illness. Psychiatry Serv 2020; 71:280-283</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Qyhg5eY">Practice guideline for the treatment of patients with major depressive disorder</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_kyuTNwC">Am J Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">167</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">suppl 10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="152" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Practice guideline for the treatment of patients with major de- pressive disorder. Am J Psychiatry 2010; 167(suppl 10):1-152</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_jJcEaTH">Schizophrenia: overview and treatment options</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Patel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cherian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Gohil</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_rXAWabB">P T</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="638" to="645" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Patel KR, Cherian J, Gohil K, et al: Schizophrenia: overview and treatment options. P T 2014; 39:638-645</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_r2RECjm">Treatment of bipolar disorder</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Geddes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Miklowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_WNYyRNf">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">381</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1672" to="1682" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Geddes JR, Miklowitz DJ: Treatment of bipolar disorder. Lancet 2013; 381:1672-1682</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_De77w39">Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses: the PRISMA statement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Moher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Liberati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tetzlaff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_rD6cXVr">BMJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">339</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2535</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Moher D, Liberati A, Tetzlaff J, et al: Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses: the PRISMA statement. BMJ 2009; 339:b2535</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_RWfZ7aV">Integrated psychosocial and opioidantagonist treatment for alcohol dependence: a systematic review of controlled evaluations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vaughn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Howard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_GapQh2X">Soc Work Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="53" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Vaughn M, Howard M: Integrated psychosocial and opioid- antagonist treatment for alcohol dependence: a systematic review of controlled evaluations. Soc Work Res 2004; 28:41-53</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qJNtneH">Lay health supporters aided by mobile text messaging to improve adherence, symptoms, and functioning among people with schizophrenia in a resource-poor community in rural China (LEAN): a randomized controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pmed.1002785</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_mKbxE8K">PLoS Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1002785</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Xu D, Xiao S, He H, et al: Lay health supporters aided by mobile text messaging to improve adherence, symptoms, and functioning among people with schizophrenia in a resource-poor community in rural China (LEAN): a randomized controlled trial. PLoS Med 2019; 16:e1002785</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qnBPBMz">The effect of supportive text message on the adherence to medication in depression: an experimental study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mohammadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zolfaghari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nikfarjam</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_uxShdZG">Nurs Pract Today</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="98" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mohammadi A, Zolfaghari M, Nikfarjam M, et al: The effect of supportive text message on the adherence to medication in depression: an experimental study. Nurs Pract Today 2016; 3: 91-98</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_7Ddhagh">Clinical outcomes from the Texting for Relapse Prevention (T4RP) in schizophrenia and schizoaffective disorder study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cullen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Rodriguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Eaton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ARa29kn">Psychiatry Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">292</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">113346</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Cullen BA, Rodriguez K, Eaton WW, et al: Clinical outcomes from the Texting for Relapse Prevention (T4RP) in schizophrenia and schizoaffective disorder study. Psychiatry Res 2020; 292:113346</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_prxkWhv">A comparison of telephone and texting interventions for persons with schizophrenia spectrum disorders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Beebe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Phillips</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_rAE4EVg">Issues Ment Health Nurs</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="323" to="329" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Beebe L, Smith KD, Phillips C: A comparison of telephone and texting interventions for persons with schizophrenia spectrum disorders. Issues Ment Health Nurs 2014; 35:323-329</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_EK9KZ2J">Mobile Assessment and Treatment for Schizophrenia (MATS): a pilot trial of an interactive text-messaging intervention for medication adherence, socialization, and auditory hallucinations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Granholm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ben-Zeev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Link</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/schbul/sbr155</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_q3TmCtW">Schizophrenia Bull</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="414" to="425" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Granholm E, Ben-Zeev D, Link PC, et al: Mobile Assessment and Treatment for Schizophrenia (MATS): a pilot trial of an interac- tive text-messaging intervention for medication adherence, so- cialization, and auditory hallucinations. Schizophrenia Bull 2012; 38:414-425</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_V7xqmxS">A short message service (SMS)-based strategy for enhancing adherence to antipsychotic medication in schizophrenia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Montes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Medina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gomez-Beneyto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.psychres.2012.07.034</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_33hhfTD">Psychiatry Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">200</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="89" to="95" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Montes JM, Medina E, Gomez-Beneyto M, et al: A short message service (SMS)-based strategy for enhancing adherence to anti- psychotic medication in schizophrenia. Psychiatry Res 2012; 200: 89-95</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_xThzjdu">Therapeutic effects of mobile-based text message reminders for medication adherence in bipolar I disorder: are they maintained after intervention cessation?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Menon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Selvakumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kattimani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2018.07.013</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_xUvWdrJ">J Psychiatr Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="163" to="168" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Menon V, Selvakumar N, Kattimani S, et al: Therapeutic effects of mobile-based text message reminders for medication adherence in bipolar I disorder: are they maintained after intervention cessa- tion? J Psychiatr Res 2018; 104:163-168</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_WZY9CJB">Outcomes of psychoeducation and a text messaging adherence intervention among individuals with hypertension and bipolar disorder</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Levin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sajatovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rahman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1176/appi.ps.201800482</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_SC8TQtt">Psychiatry Serv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="608" to="612" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Levin JB, Sajatovic M, Rahman M, et al: Outcomes of psycho- education and a text messaging adherence intervention among individuals with hypertension and bipolar disorder. Psychiatry Serv 2019; 70:608-612</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_9gbECjn">Individualized texting for adherence building (iTAB): improving antiretroviral dose timing among HIV-infected persons with co-occurring bipolar disorder</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Poquette</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Casaletto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_caauUAV">AIDS Behav</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="459" to="471" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Moore DJ, Poquette A, Casaletto A, et al: Individualized texting for adherence building (iTAB): improving antiretroviral dose timing among HIV-infected persons with co-occurring bipolar disorder. AIDS Behav 2015; 19:459-471</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_24jXpDv">Mobile texting and lay health supporters to improve schizophrenia care in a resource-poor community in rural China (LEAN trial): randomized controlled trial extended implementation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Cai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Gong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_yjH3V5K">J Med Internet Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">22631</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Cai Y, Gong W, He H, et al: Mobile texting and lay health supporters to improve schizophrenia care in a resource-poor community in rural China (LEAN trial): randomized controlled trial extended implementation. J Med Internet Res 2020; 22: e22631</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_TqUfK5C">Differential medication attitudes to antihypertensive and mood stabilizing agents in response to an automated text-messaging adherence enhancement intervention</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Klein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Aebi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sajatovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_z2KUT7A">J Behav Cogn Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Klein PJ, Aebi ME, Sajatovic M, et al: Differential medication attitudes to antihypertensive and mood stabilizing agents in re- sponse to an automated text-messaging adherence enhancement intervention. J Behav Cogn Ther 2020; 30:57-64</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_yTEmAES">COVID-19 and applications of smartphone technology in the current pandemic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Iyengar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Upadhyaya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Vaishya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.dsx.2020.05.033</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_JWmA4Q2">Diabetes Metab Syndr Clin Res Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="733" to="737" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Iyengar K, Upadhyaya GK, Vaishya R, et al: COVID-19 and ap- plications of smartphone technology in the current pandemic. Diabetes Metab Syndr Clin Res Rev 2020; 14:733-737</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_vpBseTp">Treatment engagement of individuals experiencing mental illness: review and update</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Dixon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Holoshitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Nossel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Zx5fBCU">World Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Dixon LB, Holoshitz Y, Nossel I: Treatment engagement of indi- viduals experiencing mental illness: review and update. World Psychiatry 2016; 15:13-20</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_VKnQcdY">Comparing medication attitudes and reasons for medication nonadherence among three disparate groups of individuals with serious mental illness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Levin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Seifi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cassidy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/nmd.0000000000000201</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_HGsRVAC">J Nerv Ment Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">202</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="769" to="773" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Levin JB, Seifi N, Cassidy KA, et al: Comparing medication atti- tudes and reasons for medication nonadherence among three disparate groups of individuals with serious mental illness. J Nerv Ment Dis 2014; 202:769-773</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_xsJ6WMp">Requirements for multidisciplinary teamwork in psychiatric rehabilitation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Liberman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hilty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Drake</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_QJVC5mt">Psychiatry Serv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1331" to="1342" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Liberman RP, Hilty DM, Drake RE, et al: Requirements for mul- tidisciplinary teamwork in psychiatric rehabilitation. Psychiatry Serv 2001; 52:1331-1342</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_tPzrBcu">Family interventions for schizophrenia and the psychoses: a review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mcfarlane</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_MFJsMP9">Fam Proc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="460" to="482" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">McFarlane WR: Family interventions for schizophrenia and the psychoses: a review. Fam Proc 2016; 55:460-482</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_YhQZ6Uj">Factors influencing relapse in the long-term course of schizophrenia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ayuso-Gutiérrez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Río</forename><surname>Del</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Vega</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0920-9964(97)00131-x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ugSes2P">Schizophr Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="206" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ayuso-Gutiérrez JL, del Río Vega JM: Factors influencing relapse in the long-term course of schizophrenia. Schizophr Res 1997; 28: 199-206</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_p36u4d3">Cardiovascular morbidity and mortality in bipolar disorder</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Weiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Warren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Fiedorowicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_SMbWbEK">Ann Clin Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="40" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Weiner M, Warren L, Fiedorowicz JG: Cardiovascular morbidity and mortality in bipolar disorder. Ann Clin Psychiatry 2011; 23: 40-47</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_YwXh4QW">Prevalence of HIV infection in a general psychiatric outpatient population</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Beyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Gersing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1176/appi.psy.48.1.31</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_P5H2TUk">Psychosomatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="37" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Beyer JL, Taylor L, Gersing KR, et al: Prevalence of HIV infection in a general psychiatric outpatient population. Psychosomatics 2007; 48:31-37</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
