<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_DyT5E2m"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2024-10-10">October 10, 2024</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Eran</forename><surname>Roseman</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Department of Health and Human Physiology , University of Iowa 0001</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Health and Human Physiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Iowa</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>0001</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Prof</roleName><forename type="middle">Megan</forename><surname>Lewey</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Health Behavior Health Promotion</note>
								<orgName type="department">Health Behavior Health Promotion</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2024-10-10">October 10, 2024</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">464E53FBF19472BADF7A68B489198842</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T12:03+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Tvhbk5w">Application Paper 1</head><p xml:id="_BxRvubB"><s xml:id="_WAp58kn">Over 1 billion people worldwide suffer from hypertension.</s><s xml:id="_rRbmwnd">It is the third leading cause of death globally, with over 7.5 people dying from it each year.</s><s xml:id="_Z5hHteq">Managing and preventing hypertension requires adopting a healthy lifestyle <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Jalali et al., 2022)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_R7T8k5W">The Transtheoretical Model (TTM) is commonly used to understand how individuals progress toward adopting and maintaining healthy behaviors, including physical activity (PA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Spencer et al., 2006)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_XW6fDuE">Interactive digital interventions (IDIs) can take advantage of the TTM and provide lifestyle behavioral intervention cost-effectively on a large scale <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(McLean et al., 2016)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_F2WdQUG"><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Spencer et al. (2006)</ref> provide an overview of the TTM and its constructs as they apply to PA:</s></p><p xml:id="_YWxpThX"><s xml:id="_wHmzQCj">1. Stages of change (SoC) are five stages individuals typically move through when changing behavior, with the more advanced stages correlating to higher PA levels.</s><s xml:id="_7t2HKaN">4. Self-efficacy (SE) is an individual's confidence in performing specific behaviors in specific situations.</s><s xml:id="_gHp3qvZ">Individuals with higher SE are likelier to maintain or increase their PA level. 5. Temptation refers to the barriers that can prevent an individual from being physically active <ref type="bibr">(Sharma, 2022, p.94)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_7TY8r9V"><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Nolan et al. (2012)</ref> aim to evaluate the effectiveness of internet-based lifestyle counseling as an intervention for patients with hypertension as a viable alternative or complement to traditional in-person management.</s><s xml:id="_mpHepcQ">The research employed a randomized controlled trial (RCT) design.</s><s xml:id="_HRkTvpr">Participants with diagnosed hypertension were recruited and randomly assigned to either the intervention group or a control group that received standard care.</s><s xml:id="_aCQzeH7">The participants were requested to choose between diet, exercise, and smoke-free lifestyle modifications.</s><s xml:id="_Tfm9a5q">They received a series of emails over four months tailored to their self-reported SoC.</s><s xml:id="_cBrn2WT">The intervention also included educational material and self-help tips for lifestyle change.</s></p><p xml:id="_gEdyg2j"><s xml:id="_8VZRVcw">The study found that the intervention group significantly reduced systolic and diastolic blood pressure compared to the control group at the 6-month follow-up.</s><s xml:id="_8zaNKMQ">Additionally, participants in the intervention group reported higher adherence to dietary and PA guidelines.</s><s xml:id="_qXZAfKx">The online format was associated with high patient satisfaction and engagement.</s><s xml:id="_x2cstFk">This research highlights the potential of IDIs in chronic disease management and supports further exploration of internet-based approaches for hypertension care.</s><s xml:id="_NfeM874">The TTM offers a structured approach to interventions by outlining different SoCs.</s><s xml:id="_mjUZmQN">However, one of its main limitations is the assumption that individuals progress through these stages linearly and within specific timeframes.</s><s xml:id="_B4Ghwdw">In reality, people may skip stages, move back and forth between them, or progress at their own pace.</s><s xml:id="_XNDb9AS">This oversimplified approach may lead to rigid intervention designs.</s><s xml:id="_6ju8RJm">Jelali et al. ( <ref type="formula">2022</ref>) had all participants start at the same SoC.</s><s xml:id="_2APUGCW"><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Nolan et al. (2012)</ref> checked each participant's SoC and provided tailored intervention.</s><s xml:id="_zWbdbk2">However, in both cases, the intervention progressed at a predetermined order and pace once the intervention started.</s></p><p xml:id="_tz9QX54"><s xml:id="_Qd3zW4c">The dynamic nature of IDIs can help to overcome the rigid nature and the predetermined pace of TTM based intervention.</s><s xml:id="_e6EQJWF">At the beginning of each session, the IDI can assess the participant's SoC, SE, PC, DB, and PA levels using a shortened version of the questionnaires used by <ref type="bibr">Jelali et al. (2022)</ref> or similar.</s><s xml:id="_UsmX3PK">Based on the answer, the IDI can decide if the participant is ready to progress to the next step, repeat the previous one, move back, or skip some of the PC or PA educational content steps.</s></p><p xml:id="_ePepZKh"><s xml:id="_WwYfhv7">Each SoC intervention step will have one full version and two short versions.</s><s xml:id="_JvVhkFA">The first time a participant does a step, they will do the extended version.</s><s xml:id="_WN2BnRt">They will be able to repeat each step up to three times.</s><s xml:id="_wrdj5DW">If a participant needs to repeat a step for the fourth time, then IDI will assume the participant has a more significant challenge and refer them to receive additional help.</s><s xml:id="_zepfkTb">The IDI will also have PA education that will gradually reach at least 150 minutes of moderate-intensity PA per week.</s></p><p xml:id="_QSM7GN6"><s xml:id="_5WCujqS">An overview of the TTM constructs and educational content (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.):</s><s xml:id="_zUujgU5">The TTM provides a practical theoretical framework for developing PA IDI to manage and prevent hypertension <ref type="bibr">(Jellali et al., 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Nolan et al., 2012)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_zyPjVD7">However, the effectiveness of these implementations are limited by the rigid structure of the TTM.</s><s xml:id="_EZfYm8D">Researchers should utilize the interactive and dynamic nature of IDIs to its fullest extent and provide interventions tailored to the individual's specific needs.</s><s xml:id="_Pb3MJ7H">As the prevalence of chronic disease increases, strains the healthcare and communities, and deepens socioeconomic disparities, it is crucial to explore innovative approaches <ref type="bibr">(Benavidez et al.,</ref></s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>2.</head><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_SMkUwCm"><s xml:id="_K4uuF6k">Processes of change (PC) are five behavioral and five cognitive strategies an individual can employ to improve PA behavior.</s><s xml:id="_RwvkxmX">3. Decision balance (DB) is an individual's belief about the advantages and disadvantages of PA behavior change.</s><s xml:id="_cFs4f9e">Individuals seeing more benefits to increasing PA are likelier to progress in their SoC.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_vzGTSZU"><s xml:id="_UVPmFPp"><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Jalali et al. (2022)</ref> evaluated the effectiveness of using tailored IDI grounded in the TTM to promote PA behaviors to manage people with hypertension and prevent the disease.</s><s xml:id="_b762jv9">The study used a quasi-experimental design, with participants divided into intervention and control groups.</s><s xml:id="_SUUGcvB">The participants were evaluated before the intervention and six months after using a valid and reliable researcher-made questionnaire about their SoC, SE, PC, DB, and PA levels.</s><s xml:id="_85MJnkR">All the participants were in the precontemplation and contemplation SoCs before the intervention.</s><s xml:id="_xdfTErs">The intervention consisted of six training sessions, each containing 15 minutes of PC-based training and a PA training program with gradual progression.</s><s xml:id="_4udXjG4">The PA training was designed so the participant could gradually reach at least 150 minutes of moderate-intensity PA per week.</s><s xml:id="_7C2f9pb">Participants who used this IDI regularly for over 100 minutes showed significant changes in the TTM constructs and the PA minutes.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="9,73.50,150.71,470.25,353.25" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_WVrgNkw"><s xml:id="_3Zsq94r">The structures of TTM and educational content in each session</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>TTM constructs</cell><cell>Educational content</cell></row><row><cell>SoC: Precontemplation</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Consciousness-raising</cell><cell>Defining PA, PA guidelines, the significance and benefits of PA</cell></row><row><cell>Decision balance</cell><cell>Testimonials of individuals who made a significant lifestyle change</cell></row><row><cell>Environmental re-evaluation</cell><cell>The effect of the change in PA behavior on the living environment of</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>the individual and others</cell></row><row><cell>Dramatic relief</cell><cell>Helping the learners to show the feelings and emotions related to the</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>risk of inactivity</cell></row><row><cell>SoC: Contemplation</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Self-reevaluation</cell><cell>helping the learners to imagine themselves when they are inactive or,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>conversely, when they are active</cell></row><row><cell>Self-efficacy</cell><cell>How to gradually increase PA, solutions to common barriers</cell></row><row><cell>SoC: Preparation</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Self-liberation</cell><cell>designing long-term and short-term goals and commitment to</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>reaching the goals</cell></row><row><cell>Counter conditioning</cell><cell>learning new healthy behaviors instead of previous unhealthy ones</cell></row><row><cell>Social liberation</cell><cell>How can social opportunities be created to be more physically active?</cell></row><row><cell>SoC: Action</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Stimulus control</cell><cell>removing stimulants leading to unhealthy habits and quick addition</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>of a healthy option</cell></row><row><cell>Reinforcement management</cell><cell>How do you reward yourself for being physically active and increase</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>motivation?</cell></row><row><cell>Helping relationships</cell><cell>Finding social support for adopting healthier PA behavior</cell></row><row><cell>Soc: Maintenance</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Temptation</cell><cell>Testimonial of individuals about the obstacles to PA and the</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>problem-solving process</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_MSY4Uq9">2024</head><p xml:id="_6bPpqFe"><s xml:id="_63CDapz">). IDIs offer a new approach to delivering cost-effective large-scale lifestyle and behavioral interventions needed to combat public health's current challenges.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_dkWyZmf">Appendix A Conceptual Model Diagram</head><p xml:id="_42unyvv"><s xml:id="_grNKh8F">The educational content of each intervention is detailed in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_zEZNS2K">Chronic disease prevalence in the US: Sociodemographic and geographic variations by ZIP code tabulation area</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Benavidez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Zahnd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Eberth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5888/pcd21.230267</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.5888/pcd21.230267" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_tjGb3Yu">Preventing Chronic Disease</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Benavidez, G. A., Zahnd, W. E., Hung, P., &amp; Eberth, J. M. (2024). Chronic disease prevalence in the US: Sociodemographic and geographic variations by ZIP code tabulation area. Preventing Chronic Disease, 21. https://doi.org/10.5888/pcd21.230267</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Er52UeK">The effectiveness of tailored interactive multimedia software based on the Trans-theoretical model for the promotion of physical activity behaviours</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jalali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Roozbahani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Shamsi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.21315/mjms2022.29.4.13</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.21315/mjms2022.29.4.13" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_b85S2Hs">Malaysian Journal of Medical Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="140" to="151" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Jalali, S., Roozbahani, N., &amp; Shamsi, M. (2022). The effectiveness of tailored interactive multimedia software based on the Trans-theoretical model for the promotion of physical activity behaviours. Malaysian Journal of Medical Sciences, 29(4), 140-151. https://doi.org/10.21315/mjms2022.29.4.13</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_TVtjkk2">Transtheoretical model for physical activity in older adults: Systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Jiménez-Zazo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Romero-Blanco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Castro-Lemus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dorado-Suárez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Aznar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3390/ijerph17249262</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph17249262" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_gXmdvFJ">International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">24</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020. 9262</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Jiménez-Zazo, F., Romero-Blanco, C., Castro-Lemus, N., Dorado-Suárez, A., &amp; Aznar, S. (2020). Transtheoretical model for physical activity in older adults: Systematic review. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 17(24), 9262. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph17249262</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_u966ErM">Digital interventions to promote self-management in adults with hypertension systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mclean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Band</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Saunderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hanlon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Little</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mcmanus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Yardley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Mair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/hjh.0000000000000859</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1097/hjh.0000000000000859" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_PTuNgGg">Journal of Hypertension</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="600" to="612" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">McLean, G., Band, R., Saunderson, K., Hanlon, P., Murray, E., Little, P., McManus, R. J., Yardley, L., &amp; Mair, F. S. (2016). Digital interventions to promote self-management in adults with hypertension systematic review and meta-analysis. Journal of Hypertension, 34(4), 600-612. https://doi.org/10.1097/hjh.0000000000000859</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_rcJReKc">Therapeutic benefit of internet-based lifestyle counselling for hypertension</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Nolan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Shoemaker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Hachinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lynn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mikulis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wennberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lum-Kwong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zbib</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cjca.2012.02.012</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cjca.2012.02.012" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_JmzCtQX">Canadian Journal of Cardiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="390" to="396" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nolan, R. P., Liu, S., Shoemaker, J. K., Hachinski, V., Lynn, H., Mikulis, D. J., Wennberg, R. A., Lum-Kwong, M. M., &amp; Zbib, A. (2012). Therapeutic benefit of internet-based lifestyle counselling for hypertension. Canadian Journal of Cardiology, 28(3), 390-396. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cjca.2012.02.012</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sharma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_fkR7thW">Theoretical Foundations of Health Education and Health Promotion</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Jones &amp; Bartlett Learning</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sharma, M. (2022). Theoretical Foundations of Health Education and Health Promotion. Jones &amp; Bartlett Learning.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_F7QRCT7">Applying the transtheoretical model to exercise: A systematic and Comprehensive Review of the literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Spencer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Adams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Malone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Roy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Yost</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1524839905278900</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1524839905278900" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_9jXqwhv">Health Promotion Practice</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="428" to="443" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Spencer, L., Adams, T. B., Malone, S., Roy, L., &amp; Yost, E. (2006). Applying the transtheoretical model to exercise: A systematic and Comprehensive Review of the literature. Health Promotion Practice, 7(4), 428-443. https://doi.org/10.1177/1524839905278900</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_HDxqJsE">Vaccine hesitancy in the era of COVID-19</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Troiano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.puhe.2021.02.025</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.puhe.2021.02.025" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_7yQzpew">Public health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">194</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="245" to="251" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Troiano, G., &amp; Nardi, A. (2021). Vaccine hesitancy in the era of COVID-19. Public health, 194, 245-251. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.puhe.2021.02.025</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_jKCtEd3">Social networks and social support</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Heaney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Israel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_sAkERwK">Health Behavior and Health Education: Theory, research, and Practice</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="189" to="210" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Heaney, C. A., &amp; Israel, B. A. (2008). Social networks and social support. In Health Behavior and Health Education: Theory, research, and Practice (pp. 189-210).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_wukFqQP">Theoretical foundations of health education and health promotion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sharma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<publisher>IBSN</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="978" to="1284208627" />
			<pubPlace>Burlington, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>4th Ed</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sharma, M. (2022). Theoretical foundations of health education and health promotion (4th Ed.), Burlington, MA: Jones &amp; Bartlett Learning. IBSN: 978-1284208627</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
