<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_8dCVYwA">A simple method for converting an odds ratio to e ect size for use in meta-analysis</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Susan</forename><surname>Chinn</surname></persName>
							<email>sue.chinn@kcl.ac.uk</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Department of Public Health Sciences ; King&apos;s College ; London ; 5th oor; Capital House ; 42 Weston Street ; London SE1 3QD ; U.K.</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Public Health Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">King&apos;s College</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>5th oor; Capital House 42 Weston Street</addrLine>
									<postCode>SE1 3QD</postCode>
									<settlement>London London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">U.K</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Department of Public Health Sciences ; King&apos;s College ; London ; 5th oor; Capital House ; 42 Weston Street ; London SE1 3QD ; U.K.</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Public Health Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">King&apos;s College</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>5th oor; Capital House 42 Weston Street</addrLine>
									<postCode>SE1 3QD</postCode>
									<settlement>London London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">U.K</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_MxK5XZg">A simple method for converting an odds ratio to e ect size for use in meta-analysis</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">C0B0895EDB96CED9DA81103BE05F91D7</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1002/1097-0258(20001130)19:22&lt;3127::aid-sim784&gt;3.0.co;2-m</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received February 1999 Accepted June 2000</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T12:38+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_kCjn64e"><p xml:id="_cjCAKqC"><s xml:id="_KgZV2Fb">A systematic review may encompass both odds ratios and mean di erences in continuous outcomes.</s><s xml:id="_hUwXRgB">A separate meta-analysis of each type of outcome results in loss of information and may be misleading.</s><s xml:id="_ZCRcccK">It is shown that a ln(odds ratio) can be converted to e ect size by dividing by 1.81.</s><s xml:id="_ZZxqy3R">The validity of e ect size, the estimate of interest divided by the residual standard deviation, depends on comparable variation across studies.</s><s xml:id="_j6FV6wT">If researchers routinely report residual standard deviation, any subsequent review can combine both odds ratios and e ect sizes in a single meta-analysis when this is justiÿed.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="738.0"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="738.0"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="738.0"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="738.0"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="738.0"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1." xml:id="_gAFptHz">INTRODUCTION</head><p xml:id="_B6Y2pQq"><s xml:id="_5UjjMHG">Meta-analysis is now used extensively in reviews of randomized controlled trials and observational studies, but the problems include how to compare non-identical outcomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_WkQX68W">A review of guidelines for systematic reviews of randomized trials recommended 'identiÿcation of a common set of deÿnitions of outcome'.</s></p><p xml:id="_mE2KHuq"><s xml:id="_E4apXqV">One form of lack of common deÿnition is the use of a continuous outcome by some authors, and a dichotomous outcome by others.</s><s xml:id="_9yaYDrP">This can lead to reviewers performing two separate meta-analyses <ref type="bibr">[2; 3]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_UtFw4tu">This problem has already been tackled in a systematic review of the prophylactic use of oxytocics on postpartum blood loss in the third stage of labour <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_xJnSksx">The authors considered that postpartum haemorrhage, deÿned as the loss of 500 ml or more, was the outcome of interest, but some trials summarized blood loss by mean and standard deviation.</s><s xml:id="_zGtAuUt">A method of estimating the log-odds ratio for the latter trials was presented, under the assumption of a Normal distribution.</s></p><p xml:id="_qFGXws8"><s xml:id="_y65haWN">However in many situations there is no natural dichotomy, and reviewers will wish to retain the greater power generally provided by continuous outcome measures.</s><s xml:id="_CbSjFHr">Continuous outcome measures on di erent scales can be combined using 'e ect size', the estimate of interest, which may be a di erence in means or a regression coe cient, divided by the residual standard deviation <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_BEtMZaG">The simple approximate method for converting an odds ratio to e ect size presented here enables reviewers to maximize the information available.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2." xml:id="_XkUAuGp">THE EQUIVALENCE OF ODDS RATIOS AND EFFECT SIZE</head><p xml:id="_rA6n3a7"><s xml:id="_xqX9X5F">Logistic regression with results reported as odds ratios, or a close equivalent, is unavoidable for truly dichotomous outcome variables.</s><s xml:id="_PK4XzfV">However some continuous outcomes, such as blood pressure <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, are frequently dichotomized.</s><s xml:id="_utgrun4">The odds of a subject being hypertensive depend on the mean and variation of the underlying distribution of blood pressure.</s><s xml:id="_DQybxFc">The odds ratio for one risk factor group compared to another is invariant to choice of cut-o point if the logit of the proportion with hypertension plotted against blood pressure is parallel for the two risk factor groups.</s><s xml:id="_HW7T4Fy">It is a su cient, but not necessary, condition for the underlying distribution of blood pressure in the two groups to be logistic with equal variances.</s></p><p xml:id="_myq82wM"><s xml:id="_VZ3Yceq">Most analyses of continuous outcomes proceed on the assumption that the distribution is Normal, often after transformation of the data.</s><s xml:id="_nTP37zS">However it is known that the logistic and Normal distributions di er little, except in the tails of the distributions <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_GVnCpA7">This is illustrated in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, where the logit of a proportion is plotted against the Normal equivalent deviate (NED).</s><s xml:id="_gCcrqCy">The standard logistic distribution <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> has variance 2 =3; so a di erence in ln(odds) can be converted to an approximate di erence in NED by dividing by = √ 3, which is 1.81 to 2 decimal places.</s><s xml:id="_x9eW46X">As a di erence in NED is the e ect size <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, a meta-analysis of ln(odds) is equivalent, albeit with loss of power, to one of e ect size except for the scaling factor of 1.81.</s></p><p xml:id="_9SUQtRS"><s xml:id="_SuwQ2My">In order to convert a di erence in NED to a di erence on the underlying scale, a standard deviation is required.</s><s xml:id="_8ng67gq">Hence conversion of an odds ratio to an absolute di erence is possible if the standard deviation is known.</s><s xml:id="_ywESsGW">It follows from this that studies reporting odds ratios are truly comparable in absolute terms if and only if the underlying standard deviation is the same for each study.</s><s xml:id="_R8bVPUr">Table I.</s><s xml:id="_8axgEq2">Published odds ratios for improvement in asthma symptoms following house dust mite control measures, published standardized mean di erence in symptom scores [2] and re-analysis.</s><s xml:id="_PVDrmN9">Study Total n Odds 95 per cent Utilized 95 per cent Utilized ratio conÿdence interval e ect size * conÿdence interval * SE 1 30 1.32 0.31 to 5.68 0.153 0.410 2 53 1.27 0.43 to 3.76 0.132 0.306 3 42 5.33 1.07 to 26.5 0.924 0.452 4 56 0.58 0.18 to 1.89 -0:301 0.331 5 49 0.83 0.17 to 4.05 -0:103 0.447 6 2 3 -0:237 -1:059 to 0.585 0.395 7 4 6 -0:552 -1:141 to 0.038 0.292 8 52 0.387 -0:162 to 0.936 0.273 9 18 0.288 -0:632 to 1.219 0.436 10 28 -0:032 -0:773 to 0.709 0.360 11 24 1.433 0.518 to 2.348 0.691 12 35 -0:541 -1:217 to 0.135 0.331 Pooled: published 1.20 0.66 to 2.18 -0:064 † -0:408 to 0:536 † Pooled: re-analysis 1.23 0.62 to 2.40 -0:070 † -0:402 to 0:542 † Pooled: all studies 0.087 -0:222 to 0.395 * Sign reversed from that published for studies 6 to 12. † Studies 6 to 12 only.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3." xml:id="_qmBvVWV">AN EXAMPLE</head><p xml:id="_w9nUJXt"><s xml:id="_Negvsqf">The example is a review of house dust mite control measures in the management of asthma <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_gnvTeXQ">Twelve studies were included, of which ÿve reported the odds ratio for an improvement in symptoms in the treated group relative to the control group, and seven reported a standardized mean di erence in symptoms, that is, e ect size.</s><s xml:id="_gkFwTna">The estimate and associated 95 per cent conÿdence interval, and number of subjects, were reported for each individual study.</s><s xml:id="_8yxJeVk">In order to convert the odds ratios to e ect size each odds ratio and associated conÿdence interval was ln-transformed, and the standard error calculated as the width of the conÿdence interval divided by 2 × 1:96.</s><s xml:id="_aqeB8Yc">Each ln(odds ratio) and associated standard error were then converted to e ect size and its standard error by dividing by 1.81.</s><s xml:id="_qP5wtfz">The standard error of each reported e ect size was calculated from the width of the conÿdence interval divided by 2 × t df ;0:05 .</s><s xml:id="_deHGGCT">The two separate meta-analyses in the paper were repeated, as di erent software was used, and then one estimate of e ect size was combined in a single random e ects meta-analysis.</s><s xml:id="_3kzq3cp">Stata 5.0 was used <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, which provides the moment estimator of DerSimonian and Laird <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, with a random e ects analysis as the authors reported using this if heterogeneity was detected <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_623kDX3"><s xml:id="_kbpJmSx">The results are shown in Table <ref type="table">I</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_WVSDX9R">As a positive e ect size represented more symptoms in the treated group, the e ect sizes for studies 6 to 12 have been reversed in sign for the single analysis so that they were comparable with the e ect size derived from the odds ratio for improvement in the treated compared to the control group.</s><s xml:id="_y6m3Rrr">Neither of the published separate meta-analyses gave much support to an e ect of house dust mite control measures, but conÿdence intervals were wide.</s><s xml:id="_4jbJQFm">The re-analysis of all 12 studies together provides a narrower conÿdence interval than the seven study e ect size analysis, and conÿrms the conclusion.</s></p><p xml:id="_Svze2dJ"><s xml:id="_gnZKts3">Copyright ? 2000 John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd.</s><s xml:id="_Ph6SUKu">Statist.</s><s xml:id="_DxvV2tw">Med.</s><s xml:id="_KTz7zUm">2000; 19:3127-3131</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4." xml:id="_bDevMaf">DISCUSSION</head><p xml:id="_wMTs32e"><s xml:id="_kda6b6Y">This paper does not advocate the use of e ect size.</s><s xml:id="_CGrFAH4">If all outcomes are continuous on the same scale then that is how they should be analysed.</s><s xml:id="_gcPN7Af">Greenland has warned against the use of standardized regression coe cients in meta-analysis <ref type="bibr">[10; 11]</ref>, and although it appears that it is standardizing the explanatory variable that is at the root of most of the problems he reports, caution should also be exercised over e ect size.</s><s xml:id="_9pmcpHu">However, in some cases reviewers have no alternative.</s><s xml:id="_ueV9nMU">It has been shown here that a meta-analysis of odds ratios is equivalent to a meta-analysis of e ect size when there is an underlying continuous distribution, albeit with some loss of power.</s><s xml:id="_MVwBqPp">This also lends some justiÿcation to the combination of odds ratios from studies with di erent outcome variables, or from studies using di erent cut-o points of a continuous distribution.</s></p><p xml:id="_DSRkpE3"><s xml:id="_S7wp7RM">If combining e ect size is justiÿed, then meta-analysis of odds ratios is also warranted.</s><s xml:id="_DCuq7Dt">From the viewpoint of Greenland's criticism of e ect size this can be reversed; if a meta-analysis of e ect size is rejected then so should one of odds ratios even if the exposure variables are all on the same scale.</s></p><p xml:id="_m4Nh4A6"><s xml:id="_NuX8xu3">While neither e ect size nor odds ratio is ideal when the outcome is truly continuous, use of two separate meta-analyses of dichotomous and continuous outcomes can lead to a number of problems.</s><s xml:id="_wzUDMPU">First, neither will have as much power as the combined analysis, and an erroneous conclusion may be reached, a problem also identiÿed by Whitehead et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_fgfzeDw">Secondly, results of the two analyses could con ict.</s><s xml:id="_jxfth5v">Thirdly, information from one study may be used in both analyses, so the seemingly conÿrmatory results may be little more than a repetition in disguise.</s><s xml:id="_vXS79Ea">Combining the two forces the reviewer to choose one of the estimates from each study, that of direct e ect size to be preferred on grounds of power over e ect size derived from an odds ratio.</s><s xml:id="_yncG6z5">The estimates from dichotomous and binary outcomes, but not the standard errors, will be of comparable size.</s><s xml:id="_6qXwZWN">This was noted by Whitehead et al. for studies that report both when Normal distributions with common variance are assumed <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> and found when the method here presented was applied to the estimates in the study of Hazell et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_uC6XGXB">Fourthly, the studies reporting odds ratios and a continuous outcome may di er in size, and examination of funnel plots <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> may erroneously conclude that there is publication bias, or such bias may be undetected because of the reduced number of studies in each analysis.</s><s xml:id="_MB3KJJx">Fifthly, heterogeneity may be undetected, or possibly erroneously reported.</s><s xml:id="_sAvCcqH">Possible causes of heterogeneity should be investigated <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> and the more studies that are included the more feasible this becomes.</s></p><p xml:id="_qehhDnf"><s xml:id="_KERTxZD">In the example it was possible to combine estimates only because e ect sizes were reported directly.</s><s xml:id="_z98duCv">Unless e ect size, or a residual standard deviation allowing e ect size to be calculated, is published for each eligible study, reviewers will be unable to carry out a single metaanalysis, and the above problems will continue.</s><s xml:id="_xTTKWE5">The method of Whitehead et al. also requires an estimate of standard deviation from each study <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_49ghBXZ"><s xml:id="_4Ahp9by">Both methods assume an underlying Normal distribution, although Whitehead et al. also provide for estimation of ln(odds ratio) if the distribution is assumed log-Normal.</s><s xml:id="_5fU86E2">E ect size assumes a common variance, and Whitehead et al. recommend using this assumption when plausible.</s><s xml:id="_ybhHKtJ">The method given here for dichotomous and continuous outcomes is complementary to and simpler than that of Whitehead et al., and should be more powerful in that all the information is retained.</s><s xml:id="_4MdU57h">The factor of 1.81 for converting ln(odds ratio) to e ect size is an approximation, but a good one over the likely range of use.</s></p><p xml:id="_vKk7ycH"><s xml:id="_VD2BEp4">No researcher should assume that results from a single study will be accepted without attempts at replication.</s><s xml:id="_XYHRuMn">To meet Greenland's objections <ref type="bibr">[10; 11]</ref>, provided the continuous outcome variables are on the same scale, a subanalysis of these alone should also be presented on the scale of measurement.</s><s xml:id="_v7rhwBp">If the residual standard deviations are very di erent then this is an indication of heterogeneity that needs to be investigated as much as that in the estimates themselves.</s><s xml:id="_Ez7bYWC">The recommendation to report residual standard deviation needs to be incorporated in guidelines for publication by medical journals with an explanation of why this is required.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_pmxWUVe"><s xml:id="_8kq7ryb">Figure 1.</s><s xml:id="_nxXGsyu">The relation between the logit of a proportion and the Normal equivalent deviate (curved line), and the ÿt of a Normal distribution with variance equal to that of the logistic distribution (straight line, gradient 1.81).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,191.09,471.61,188.34,110.86" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p xml:id="_2BmnGm7"><s xml:id="_BXeFXte">10970258, 2000, 22, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/1097-0258(20001130)19:22&lt;3127::AID-SIM784&gt;3.0.CO;2-M by University Of Iowa Libraries -Serials Acquisitions, Wiley Online Library on [17/07/2025].</s><s xml:id="_yaE6qtA">See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions)</s><s xml:id="_58mSrrC">on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License</s></p></note>
		</body>
		<back>


			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_M5mCfE5">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p xml:id="_WTzar2H"><s xml:id="_gb7cwf9">The author thanks an anonymous referee for helpful comments.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_YbPwhxb">A survey of current problems in meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Hasselblad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mosteller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Littenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Chalmers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Hunink</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Morton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Diehr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Powe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/00005650-199533020-00007</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_nyJZYdt">Medical Care</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="202" to="220" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hasselblad V, Mosteller F, Littenberg B, Chalmers TC, Hunink MG, Turner JA, Morton SC, Diehr P, Wong JB, Powe NR. A survey of current problems in meta-analysis. Medical Care 1995; 33(2):202-220.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_m33BpNh">House dust mite control measures in the management of asthma: metaanalysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Ghtsche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hammarquist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Burr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmj.317.7166.1105</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_qpZntHK">British Medical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">317</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7166</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1105" to="1110" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">GHtsche PC, Hammarquist C, Burr M. House dust mite control measures in the management of asthma: meta- analysis. British Medical Journal 1998; 317(7166):1105-1110.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_trpQ42E">E cacy of tricyclic drugs in treating child and adolescent depression: a meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hazell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O'</forename><surname>Connell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Heathcote</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Robertson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmj.310.6984.897</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_hW2PjCB">British Medical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">310</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="897" to="901" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995. 6984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hazell P, O&apos;Connell DO, Heathcote D, Robertson J, Henry D. E cacy of tricyclic drugs in treating child and adolescent depression: a meta-analysis. British Medical Journal 1995; 310(6984):897-901.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_dsCp8EF">Combining summaries of binary outcomes with those of continuous outcomes in a meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Whitehead</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bailey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Elbourne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1081/bip-100100997</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_XTguJff">Journal of Biopharmaceutical Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Whitehead A, Bailey A, Elbourne D. Combining summaries of binary outcomes with those of continuous outcomes in a meta-analysis. Journal of Biopharmaceutical Statistics 1999; 9(1):1-16.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_5vjJTE7">Reduced heart rate variability and newonset hypertension: insights into pathogenesis of hypertension: the Framingham Heart Study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Singh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Larson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Tsuji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Evans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O'</forename><surname>Donnell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Levy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1161/01.hyp.32.2.293</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_nhUfhmA">Hypertension</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="293" to="297" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Singh JP, Larson MG, Tsuji H, Evans, JC, O&apos;Donnell, CJ, Levy D. Reduced heart rate variability and new- onset hypertension: insights into pathogenesis of hypertension: the Framingham Heart Study. Hypertension 1998; 32(2): 293-297.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_JNcNgEV">Statistical Method in Biological Assay</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Finney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
			<publisher>Charles Gri n</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="362" to="368" />
			<pubPlace>London and High Wycombe</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>3rd edn</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Finney DJ. Statistical Method in Biological Assay; 3rd edn. Charles Gri n: London and High Wycombe, 1978; 362-368.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_g89nmm2">The Advanced Theory of Statistics Volume I</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Kendal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Stuart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
			<publisher>Charles Gri n</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">126</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>London and High Wycombe</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>4th edn</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kendal MG, Stuart A. The Advanced Theory of Statistics Volume I. 4th edn. Charles Gri n: London and High Wycombe, 1977; 126.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1536867x20976323</idno>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_tmQw7Uv">Stata Statistical Software Release</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Texas</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Stata Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Stata Corporation</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Stata Corporation. Stata Statistical Software Release 5. Stata Press, Texas, 1997.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_yECS8M9">Meta-analysis in clinical trials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Dersimonian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Laird</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0197-2456(86)90046-2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_TMDvSDj">Controlled Clinical Trials</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="188" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">DerSimonian R, Laird N. Meta-analysis in clinical trials. Controlled Clinical Trials 1986; 7(3):177-188.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_NX9cUsy">The fallacy of employing standardized regression coe cients and correlations as measures of e ect</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Greenland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Schlesselman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Criqui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/oxfordjournals.aje.a114229</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_GKytnsn">American Journal of Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">123</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="208" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Greenland S, Schlesselman JJ, Criqui, MH. The fallacy of employing standardized regression coe cients and correlations as measures of e ect. American Journal of Epidemiology 1986; 123(2):203-208.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ffxCbHK">Quantitative methods in the review of epidemiologic literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Greenland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/oxfordjournals.epirev.a036298</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_4WfeNX4">Epidemiologic Reviews</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Greenland S. Quantitative methods in the review of epidemiologic literature. Epidemiologic Reviews 1987; 9:1-30.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_8QgeSxS">Systematic reviews of randomised trials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sutton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Abrams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sheldon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3310/hta2190</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_dUYx7xr">Health Services Research Methods</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Black</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Brazier</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Reeves</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>BMJ Books</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="175" to="186" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sutton AJ, Jones DR, Abrams K, Sheldon TA, Song F. Systematic reviews of randomised trials. In Health Services Research Methods, Black N, Brazier J, Fitzpatrick R, Reeves B (eds). BMJ Books: London, 1998; 175-186.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_nrZK9Nk">Controversies in meta-analysis: the case of the trials of serum cholesterol reduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/096228029300200205</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_dtsKhB5">Statistical Methods in Medical Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="192" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Thompson, S. Controversies in meta-analysis: the case of the trials of serum cholesterol reduction. Statistical Methods in Medical Research 1993; 2(2):173-192.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Copyright</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_mvbMHvY">Ltd. Statist. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3127" to="3131" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000. 2000</date>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Copyright ? 2000 John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. Statist. Med. 2000; 19:3127-3131</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
