<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_yU5DNdt"></title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Japan Pharmaceutical Manufacturers Association</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Takemi Memorial Trust for Research of Seizon and Life Sciences</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Pharmaceutical Research and Manufacturers of America</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Japan Medical Association</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">JMA</orgName>
					<idno type="DOI" subtype="crossref">https://doi.org/10.13039/100018507</idno>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">FF5B3B7A47FEE3EF3C8A471A6764BAED</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1080/23288604.2024.2400722</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T12:39+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="634.32" lry="833.04"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="609.449" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="609.449" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="609.449" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="609.449" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="609.449" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="609.449" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="609.449" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="609.449" lry="793.701"/>
		<surface n="10" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="609.449" lry="793.701"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_skqjBmk">Introduction to the Special Issue on Digital Health: Opportunities and Challenges for Global Health</head><p xml:id="_gp5cukW"><s xml:id="_TzPKtgZ">This Special Issue on Digital Health celebrates the 40th Anniversary of the Takemi Program in International Health at Harvard University.</s><s xml:id="_VK6quUm">During the past four decades, 323 mid-career global health professionals from 61 countries have participated in the program as Takemi Fellows.</s><s xml:id="_SN5ZQaJ">These fellows are a select group of midcareer health professionals and scholars from around the world who conduct advanced research and develop leadership skills at the Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health.</s><s xml:id="_BKYBKtM">Takemi Fellows examine problems of mobilizing, allocating, and managing scarce resources to improve health, and design strategies for disease control and prevention and health promotion, with a focus on low-and middle-income countries.</s></p><p xml:id="_yzkSxc4"><s xml:id="_CvJxHvm">Earlier versions of the articles in this Special Issue were first presented at the program's 40th Anniversary Takemi Symposium held in Boston in October 2023, organized around the theme of "Digital Health: Opportunities and Challenges for Global Health."</s><s xml:id="_YPtwGEK">A follow-up 40th Anniversary Symposium was held in Tokyo in November, with a focus on digital technologies for community health, organized by the Japan Medical Association and the Takemi Program. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> "Digital health" encompasses a broad range of current and potential interventions in health systems that make use of digital technology and innovations, including smartphones and apps, data systems, and artificial intelligence.</s><s xml:id="_3xKb2QN">During the past 40 years, the digital revolution has unfolded around the world-in recent years it feels as though it has exploded.</s><s xml:id="_83qJyGU">In the early years of the Takemi Program in the mid-1980s, many of the midcareer researchers who arrived at Harvard had never typed on a keyboard connected to a mainframe computer, and most had rarely used a personal computer, then just beginning to appear in universities.</s><s xml:id="_rY4ksJM">Circumstances have changed dramatically since then.</s></p><p xml:id="_rxNgW69"><s xml:id="_nYGgRnb">Digital technologies are already fundamentally changing how health systems perform.</s><s xml:id="_G6UrqMj">Over time, digital technologies will likely influence nearly every process and every person in the health system.</s><s xml:id="_ygHvwd4">However, many digital technologies are being rolled out in health systems before their impacts are fully understood by providers, patients, or governments.</s></p><p xml:id="_ryu3g5Z"><s xml:id="_C8awxvs">The articles in this Special Issue explore the opportunities and challenges presented by the influx of digital technologies into health systems around the world, and in both public and private sectors.</s><s xml:id="_FQb3M35">Most of the papers are written by former Takemi Fellows and their colleagues, along with several by global experts who are friends of the program.</s><s xml:id="_MmZDK48">With these articles, the Takemi Program seeks to contribute to the global discussion about digital health and its impacts, and to encourage more public health research and policy attention to these topics.</s><s xml:id="_7pRZZFp">This introductory paper provides background and context for these papers, and summarizes the contributions of each paper to the field of digital health.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_JgR9tCh">The Global Context of Digital Health</head><p xml:id="_QNf47yD"><s xml:id="_csFBuCk">In 2019, the World Health Organization (WHO) presented a set of preliminary recommendations about how digital interventions can strengthen health systems. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> WHO's global strategy presents useful guidance for national policy makers.</s><s xml:id="_tKRnxjn">WHO identified nine digital health interventions with particular promise: birth notification, death notification, commodity stock notification and management, patient-to-provider telemedicine, provider-to-provider telemedicine, targeted patient communication, tracking patients' health status and services, provider decision support, and delivery of training and education to providers.</s><s xml:id="_4KwKegZ">This list was prepared with the expectation that it would be regularly expanded and revised.</s><s xml:id="_8EK4fn5">Two years later, in 2021, WHO issued a global strategy on digital health for 2020-2025, including this important normative statement: <ref type="bibr">38</ref> Digital health should be an integral part of health priorities and benefit people in a way that is ethical, safe, secure, reliable, equitable and sustainable.</s><s xml:id="_pgqmMW2">It should be developed with principles of transparency, accessibility, scalability, replicability, interoperability, privacy, security and confidentiality.</s></p><p xml:id="_9tb6zrZ"><s xml:id="_QFTFmP7">To examine how digital health is actually being implemented in health systems, the Takemi Symposium solicited research papers from past Takemi Fellows and other prominent researchers.</s><s xml:id="_9gbFSQe">The papers were organized around topics proposed in the 2019 commentary, "Digital Technology and the Future of Health Systems" by Marc Mitchell and Lena Kan. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> Their commentary was published shortly before Dr. Mitchell's untimely death in 2019.</s><s xml:id="_fzT39SJ">Dr. Mitchell served as Faculty Advisor to the Takemi Program from 2005 to 2010.</s><s xml:id="_WxgUeXA">The organization he founded in 2004, D-tree International, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> is a global pioneer in the use of hand-held digital technology for diagnostic support to improve maternal and child health in lowincome countries.</s></p><p xml:id="_aR3FfhQ"><s xml:id="_Dp8pwcf">Mitchell and Kan made five predictions about how digital technology will change healthcare delivery: <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> (1) Access to Internet-Based Information Will Be Universal (2) Health Workers Will Be Digitally Supported (3) Most Health Care Will Be Provided at Home (4) Transportation and Logistics Management Could Be Revolutionized (5) Data Will Be Central to Health Systems</s></p><p xml:id="_wQzwhea"><s xml:id="_MhjRu2V">We use these five topics to frame the contributions of the articles in the Special Issue.</s></p><p xml:id="_qFZVqxk"><s xml:id="_TAB2tXj">Before exploring these five predictions, it is important to note one area that Mitchell and Kan mentioned only briefly: the role of artificial intelligence (AI).</s><s xml:id="_5J3bq49">In the five years since their commentary was published, AI has arrived on the global scene.</s><s xml:id="_Za2Q6Us">Given the growing importance of AI in health systems, we asked África Periáñez and colleagues at Causal Foundry Inc. to explore how AI could transform the health sector and improve the performance of health systems.</s><s xml:id="_VwupsKX">Causal Foundry Inc. seeks to build AI products that "ensure each person lives their healthiest possible life."</s><s xml:id="_vcgG3uD">The company is "committed to making AI technologies available to everyone" (<ref type="url" target="http://www.causalfoundry.ai">www.cau  salfoundry.ai</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_VFPn6ec">This is the first paper in the Special Issue. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref></s><s xml:id="_3TXhkrm">eriáñez and colleagues begin by explaining that AI is based on "techniques that enable systems to learn patterns from large sets of data without being explicitly programmed for specific tasks."</s><s xml:id="_rEHC6P5">AI offers the potential to combine and analyze multiple sources of data to support decision-making related to health system operations and create personalized interventions to change individual behavior.</s><s xml:id="_NxMkWRa">Integrating multiple data sources, they write, can "support patients, medical facilities, pharmacists, Community Health Workers (CHWs), midwives, and distributors of drugs and medical consumables by enhancing their operational efficacy."</s><s xml:id="_kTU2FR9">Machine learning can thus transform data into "adaptive interventions" that can improve health outcomes worldwide.</s></p><p xml:id="_55MgUJs"><s xml:id="_dAQc2dM">Consider two examples that illustrate how AI could be used to improve healthcare delivery.</s><s xml:id="_6tBYWRr">First, if a pregnant woman enters data on her health and medical visits, an AI system can compare her personal data with the data of other women with similar characteristics to provide the woman with information that is presumed to be necessary, at a time that is presumed to be appropriate, and prompt her to take specific actions.</s><s xml:id="_4AntswW">Her responses can then be used as data for subsequent provision of services -to her and to others.</s><s xml:id="_XRHgMsw">Another example is a system that allows healthcare professionals to easily collect and analyze information on their patients (for example, patients with the most visits in a time period).</s><s xml:id="_2Ny8gXg">Periáñez and colleagues argue that AI-based technologies will revolutionize, for both patients and providers, how healthcare is delivered around the world.</s><s xml:id="_KpngWrV">Now let's return to the five predictions of Mitchell and Kan to examine the Special Issue's articles exploring these predictions in specific situations and contexts.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_ctXRyxA">Universal Access to Internet-Based Information</head><p xml:id="_dQJYguc"><s xml:id="_ckq5Smp">The first prediction is that internet-based information related to health will become available to "everyone or very close to everyone" in the world.</s><s xml:id="_ZrmxS8N">Mitchell and Kan describe an explosion of access to information driven by commercial interests and with far-reaching consequences for health systems.</s><s xml:id="_2EdcDHK">Health workers, they write, will no longer be the primary source of health information for lay people; this expansion of sources will change professional roles.</s><s xml:id="_EMVHYGv">The proliferation of information sources, they warn, may also lead to problems with the quality of information, which is difficult for governments and professional associations to control.</s></p><p xml:id="_7MTd9TJ"><s xml:id="_tBabdC5">One country that is actively pursuing a national policy of expanding access to digital health information is India, which has taken important steps toward universal access to internet-based information.</s><s xml:id="_5dzcBnX">India is among the first nations to adopt a national digital health policy and strategy, with implementation nationwide beginning in 2021.</s><s xml:id="_CEaDydf">In their paper, Udaya S. Mishra and colleagues assess India's Ayushman Bharat Digital Mission, which seeks to strengthen the country's digital health ecosystem. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s xml:id="_b7b354X">Mishra and colleagues found significant progress in the registration of beneficiaries (400 million people, as of June 3, 2023) and in the linkage of health records (273 million).</s><s xml:id="_FhWe79Q">Since implementation is still in process, they cannot assess its effects on health system performance; instead, they examine its operational progress and propose possible mid-course corrections.</s><s xml:id="_YKmnQxb">Their assessment does reveal variations by state in two important performance indicators: health professional registration and health facility registration.</s></p><p xml:id="_fw5jqJg"><s xml:id="_Aq24PrM">Mishra and colleagues also identify significant advances in adopting digital mechanisms in the health sector, especially the spread of the national biometric ID system known as Aadhar ID and the use of the Unified Payment Interface for digital payment.</s><s xml:id="_cgkHXu4">These are mammoth tasks for a country of over a billion people.</s><s xml:id="_CSaFPkU">Implementation is also complicated by the federal structure of India: different states, with their different health sub-systems, have achieved different levels of progress.</s><s xml:id="_UjAjupe">While the authors are concerned about "ecosystem inertia" and the challenges of protecting the confidentiality of patient data, they conclude that thus far the implementation of India's national policy is "progressing toward its basic objectives."</s><s xml:id="_fSxvAcY">The world will be watching the Indian national experience to see how digitalization affects health system performance over the next decade.</s></p><p xml:id="_xbyySs7"><s xml:id="_kTwYRp4">Internet telemedicine is one of the key ways that internet-based information is disseminated.</s><s xml:id="_vvpN6wN">China is achieving major advances in this area, as presented in the article by Terence C. Cheng and Winnie Yip. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref> Their paper highlights how China created an internet healthcare ecosystem led by private-sector innovation, even before the emergence of the COVID-19 pandemic in 2020.</s><s xml:id="_bFrjvwu">China's government policies had opened up opportunities for internet telemedicine, and the private sector rapidly exploited those opportunities to create a fast-growing internet health market.</s><s xml:id="_dzmcQQ6">Cheng and Yip examine the origins and expansion of this market, with the emergence of public and private "internet hospitals" and a startling array of public-private interactions (particularly public hospital doctors who, in their free time, provide private internet services and set their own prices).</s><s xml:id="_aBqwg5c">They write, "This new digital ecosystem encompasses the exchange and sale of a wide range of health care and related services, including medical advice, prescriptions, health information and health insurance [and has] radically transformed how consumers access and receive health services and information."</s><s xml:id="_B7CR5jE">They show how the publicprivate mix in the internet telemedicine market in China has served by "reducing geographic barriers and improving access to care," but could also "further exacerbate inequalities in access" and affordability.</s></p><p xml:id="_6yegF3z"><s xml:id="_SvccWdB">They conclude that there is a need to "understand the role telemedicine plays in the future" in China, especially how to integrate delivery systems with telemedicine, assure that telemedicine is used appropriately, address equity concerns raised by private sector prices and the impacts of incentives on physician behavior, and evaluate and improve the quality of telemedicine.</s></p><p xml:id="_Mpjc4MT"><s xml:id="_eySjTch">Social media provides another major channel for access to health information, as illustrated by the explosion of health information (and misinformation) during the COVID-19 pandemic.</s><s xml:id="_yVH9VCY">Shuko Takahashi and colleagues in their article examine how social media use in Japan affected vaccine hesitancy and risk behaviors during the pandemic. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref></s><s xml:id="_sYuHUFh">Using data collected from online rapid surveys in Iwate Prefecture, Japan, during 2021, they analyze where people obtained health information and how that information affected their vaccine intentions and risk behaviors.</s><s xml:id="_wYXcz7v">The dataset included over 8,000 respondents to online questionnaires distributed via the social media platform known as LINE (which is used by about 70% of the Japanese population).</s></p><p xml:id="_cX3RbMt"><s xml:id="_e4BsDPu">Takahashi and colleagues focused on one question about vaccine intention and used the "microCOVID" method to calculate behavioral risk for COVID-19 based on daily activities.</s><s xml:id="_4A7P4AK">They found that "[social network services] users in this Japanese sample were neither more likely to be vaccine hesitant nor more likely to engage in risk behaviors for acquiring COVID-19.</s><s xml:id="_xKfWnKc">Users of the internet or news apps were more likely to be vaccine hesitant, but at the same time they were less likely to engage in high-risk behaviors."</s><s xml:id="_xcHqKWp">These results are similar to what has been found in other Asian countries, but differ from patterns found in Western contexts.</s></p><p xml:id="_uwB4pyX"><s xml:id="_wEFH3nT">The authors suggest that these differences may be related to the lower level of political polarization in Japan (compared to the United States).</s><s xml:id="_BF9kw39">They suggest that the Japanese government's risk information campaign about the pandemic (to avoid the "three C's:" closed spaces, crowded spaces, and close-contact settings) may have been more effective than what was done, for example, in the United States.</s><s xml:id="_ZMZnher">In conclusion, they recommend that policymakers preparing for future pandemics need to understand the effects of different kinds of information media in each society and for particular demographic subgroups.</s><s xml:id="_am3URKH">The study highlights that expanded access to internet information does not always yield the desired or expected behavior changes, and that the particular patterns of influence may differ by political and cultural contexts.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_5Up9GxS">Digitally Supported Health Workers</head><p xml:id="_GbGxE3A"><s xml:id="_VGHhxvM">Mitchell and Kan's commentary next predicts that eventually every health worker "will have a digital tool" to help with making diagnoses, guiding treatment decisions, and communicating with patients and the health system.</s><s xml:id="_tWhn4cU">These tools will include a range of digital and artificial intelligence interventions, from checklists to diagnostic algorithms, and from treatment guidance to video explanations of processes.</s><s xml:id="_HXNAXsr">Introducing digital tools into health care delivery will affect patientprovider relationships, the providers' work environment and responsibilities, the quality of care provided and health outcomes, as well as processes of training, supervision, and administration.</s></p><p xml:id="_kx2T5Wa"><s xml:id="_5FxbeFm">In this Special Issue, Miwako Hosoda examines how the digitalization of peer support for patients is driving changes in the roles of patients and providers, and how they relate to each other. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref></s><s xml:id="_fPjjNGa">She conducted a mixedmethods study in Japan with three groups of patients affected by a range of diseases and disabilities, exploring how digital communication is affecting peer support groups and social roles.</s><s xml:id="_rNUCw4A">She found that digitalization "has the potential of removing the stigma of being a sick person" and can allow patients to adopt new social roles that also allow healthcare professionals to relate to patients in new ways.</s><s xml:id="_aRs5ySf">Increasingly, patient support groups are developing online communication mechanisms, sometimes using avatars, that allow them to meet and share their concerns without traveling.</s><s xml:id="_3W8UumZ">Hosoda concludes, "The traditional asymmetrical relationship between healthcare professionals and patients is shifting to one in which [they] are on a more equal footing and have the potential to collaborate."</s></p><p xml:id="_Gk8eGVB"><s xml:id="_WPRQdVV">Digital communication is also transforming the training of healthcare professionals, for example, by facilitating international collaboration and instruction.</s><s xml:id="_fPRAyzV">In their article, Caroline Benski and Aya Goto examine how two different international collaborative efforts in health training adjusted to replace long-distance travel and faceto-face training with digital communication during the COVID-19 pandemic. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref></s><s xml:id="_ZyfPAh2">One collaboration involved partners in Japan and Indonesia (for participatory school health education) and the other had participants in Switzerland and Madagascar (for respectful obstetric and newborn emergencies).</s><s xml:id="_NU7qX7v">In their paper, Benski and Goto present the two cases and discuss their implications.</s></p><p xml:id="_TGg8FUG"><s xml:id="_NzvFmfy">Although there were "vast differences in the cultural and socioeconomic features in the countries involved," Benski and Goto found that participants in digital learning in these two settings "shared similar positive and negative experiences during the trainings."</s><s xml:id="_qDDANgZ">They concluded that even simple technology can improve "communication for planning and redesigning the training to allow remote participation [that] resulted in better outcomes: innovative trainings that are based on international protocols and best practices, are tailored to local needs and capacities, and are delivered by a combined team of local and non-local trainers."</s><s xml:id="_kVkdCYX">The authors also emphasize the continued importance of "human factors" when using digital technologies to create successful online training, especially noting the combination of trusting relationships, shared goals, and a sense of "ownership of learned skills."</s><s xml:id="_q627x2m">Their work highlights the roles of social values and human exchanges in harnessing the potential contributions of digital technologies.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_BwmrdDP">Provision of Healthcare at Home</head><p xml:id="_kxzPRX2"><s xml:id="_kh6samh">Mitchell and Kan boldly predicted that the location where health care is provided is going to radically change, writing: "The new model will bring care to the patient rather than the patient to care."</s><s xml:id="_nUU2bfz">They state that telemedicine and new diagnostic technologies will reduce the need for patients to visit a facility.</s><s xml:id="_BPQKbVc">Instead, people will increasingly be able to seek guidance and care from healthcare providers while at home.</s><s xml:id="_k8dxPt6">In order for this to happen, home-based telemedicine requires accurate and effective identification technology (biometrics) and electronic medical record systems.</s></p><p xml:id="_tnqcwwr"><s xml:id="_wVk56SC">The Special Issue paper by Hwa-Young Lee, Minji Ju, and colleagues examines what happened when a digital health care model was introduced to a low-access rural area of South Korea to bring "care to the patient rather than patient to care," to use the phrase of Mitchell and Kan. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref> The government called the project the "Smart Online-to-Offline Digital Health Care Model," stressing the combination of digital and personal care mechanisms to create a "continuum of care" for the management and prevention of chronic diseases.</s><s xml:id="_Mzct4fC">The authors conducted focus group interviews with stakeholders at several levels of care to explore their preparedness for, as well as the challenges and opportunities in implementing, the program.</s><s xml:id="_kDP2SCU">They spoke with elderly and nonelderly community residents, health care providers, and area officials at the Health and Medical Centerand found both positive and negative perceptions, as well as a lack of preparedness at each level in the health system.</s></p><p xml:id="_EYdMrzN"><s xml:id="_Tgh6ppR">Lee, Ju, and colleagues illustrate the challenges of implementing a digital health program in a rural community.</s><s xml:id="_vmshQDS">Among community residents, the authors found low levels of both health and digital literacy, especially among the elderly, along with limited social support.</s><s xml:id="_bsAEepc">Many elderly residents lacked smartphones or could not effectively use digital technologies.</s><s xml:id="_6QqdXYT">In addition, although health providers recognized the importance of continuous care between doctor's visits, they showed a "low acceptance' of the digital health program and skepticism about using patient's self-measured health data to make clinical decisions.</s><s xml:id="_kdNDjgk">Providers were also concerned about the additional workload and the lack of adequate payment for the new services.</s><s xml:id="_nsPqykm">At the health center level, the researchers found inadequacies in human resources, a lack of capacity in the staff, and unclear job descriptions for new tasks, noting that the initial enthusiasm about engaging in the program declined over time.</s><s xml:id="_2eAW984">The authors emphasize the importance of understanding how various social actors at different levels must engage collaboratively in applying digital technologies, in order to achieve the desired health gains.</s></p><p xml:id="_s4q2WCE"><s xml:id="_6qjtGAT">Another arena where digital technologies could have an important impact is in reporting and preventing gender-based violence (GBV) against women.</s><s xml:id="_46EEj69">As Friday Okonofua and colleagues note in their paper, Nigeria's National Demographic Survey of 2018 found that one-third of women (15-49 years) reported experience with GBV. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> The authors state, "GBV remains a persistent and unresolved challenge in sexual and reproductive health and rights programming in the country."</s><s xml:id="_GkGuuaR">Their study examines the results of a mobile phone health intervention, called "text4life," designed to assist women in self-reporting gender-based violence in Nigeria.</s><s xml:id="_wpHtup2">The technology allows women to text a code to a central service that notifies nearby healthcare providers and civil society organization (CSO) officials.</s><s xml:id="_mnNueYh">On receiving a notification, trained providers could then assist the caller with social and health services, beginning with a visit to the home by a CSO representative.</s></p><p xml:id="_6zsRVFN"><s xml:id="_QhpgFgM">Okonofua and colleagues conducted both quantitative and qualitative analyses of data from the central server and of interviews with some callers, providers, and CSO staff to examine patterns of reporting and services in underserved communities in 10 Nigerian states.</s><s xml:id="_PPB5Pzp">The authors analyzed data from 3,403 messages collected over 27 months and conducted qualitative interviews with 21 women who had texted the code, 15 CSO representatives, and 16 health facility managers.</s><s xml:id="_FPjU7tE">Of the messages received, 1,933 were reports of GBV and other health matters; of these, about 35% were GBV cases.</s><s xml:id="_e6EzMGa">Most users said the phone-based message system was useful to report GBV in a "confidential and safe manner."</s><s xml:id="_cb9Cgs7">Women said it allowed them to report GBV, "when they had previously not been able to report repeated cases of abuse, including rape."</s><s xml:id="_rnYAayd">Providers noted, however, that even when women were treated for "injuries, pain, and psychological disorders" associated with GBV, "they were often unwilling to report the abusers to the police or proceed with legal actions."</s><s xml:id="_Qf77Qh7">The authors recommend that Nigeria should focus more on primary prevention (preventing GBV from occurring) rather than secondary prevention (taking action to punish perpetrators).</s><s xml:id="_eVgd9FW">The paper concludes that a mobile phone-driven social response system can be effective in increasing reporting and responses for GBV in low-resource settings, but additional interventions are still needed to reduce the occurrence of GBV.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_v4mDAyM">Revolutionary Transportation and Logistics Management</head><p xml:id="_WNbXWxr"><s xml:id="_jF9Rd3j">As Mitchell and Kan point out, the digital revolution has already disrupted the transportation sector in major ways, for example, by expanding access to bicycles, scooters, and cars (with and without drivers)-just think about how Uber and other ridesharing apps have transformed the taxi industry around the world.</s><s xml:id="_Qyws8cH">Similar changes could happen in the health care sector by improving public and private sector emergency transport options and by developing new technologies (such as drones) for delivering medical supplies to remote areas.</s><s xml:id="_ePgKwZa">Radical changes could also occur in healthcare administration and payment systems.</s><s xml:id="_Uzp2PWr">This section includes two articles: the first on transport to health facilities (including inter-facility transport), and the second on transport and logistics for delivering health products to health facilities and patients.</s></p><p xml:id="_EQVW7VW"><s xml:id="_cMWUkUJ">One example of introducing digital technologies to improve the transportation component of the health system is the Maharashtra Emergency Medical Services (MEMS) "108" ambulance service in India.</s><s xml:id="_NjfpkSz">Emergency medical services, also known as pre-hospital care, are critically important in providing lifesaving attention and comfort to people in distress.</s><s xml:id="_G5yg6Vk">In their Special Issue paper, Ahana Sarkar and colleagues note that "India has yet to create a single, comprehensive [emergency medical transport] system that can be accessed throughout the country." 14</s><s xml:id="_ZZcDejV">Different states, for example, use different numbers to call for emergency services.</s></p><p xml:id="_dW9qbZA"><s xml:id="_d57mevw">Maharashtra is the third largest state in India, with a population of over 112 million in 2011.</s><s xml:id="_FG5SWNt">This paper describes Maharashtra's pioneer introduction of a publicly-funded, completely digital facility.</s><s xml:id="_q5xzJZf">MEMS' 108 is a toll-free number (similar to 911 in the USA) free to all users in the state, regardless of location, that offers both hospital-to-hospital transport service as well as responding to emergency calls.</s><s xml:id="_cKKw9rJ">MEMS 108 operates through "a web-based dashboard with a continuous feed of real-time data, maps, and a live tracking system" of all ambulances, including those in maintenance.</s><s xml:id="_jxrs7Gx">The MEMS 108 facility captures digital records for each individual patient, with the episode time of emergency services and details on the patient's health condition.</s></p><p xml:id="_z4qUAA3"><s xml:id="_tXJ9XQA">The authors used spatial analysis to examine 38,823 calls to the 108 service in November 2022, exploring the causes behind the calls and the remaining challenges faced by the service.</s><s xml:id="_myJXxZg">As part of their analysis, they identified districts in the state where the response time exceeded the international "golden hour" standard, which reduces the mortality of patients receiving emergency care by assuring a rapid response.</s><s xml:id="_XU5QjXR">The authors propose a number of factors that affect the delay of providing "definitive care" within one hour, including lack of infrastructure and trained personnel, lack of ambulances at the base, challenges in reaching patients in remote villages, poor road infrastructure, and early closure of tertiary or specialized facilities in rural areas.</s><s xml:id="_3u6HuHF">The paper concludes with suggestions to improve the effectiveness and efficiency of Maharashtra's pioneer MEMS 108 service, providing important lessons to other states in India and elsewhere considering adopting similar systems.</s><s xml:id="_EV4rGRM">Prashant Yadav's paper provides a broad perspective on how digital technologies can transform product supply chains for health systems to improve access, quality, and efficiency. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref></s><s xml:id="_n7DQEQT">Yadav points out that most governments lack adequate expertise in digital health to select appropriate interventions to manage health products.</s><s xml:id="_yVBEM2G">In order to assure that investments in digital technologies actually improve health system performance, Yadav recommends that governments begin "by asking where lack of information is the primary constraint impeding supply chain performance."</s><s xml:id="_RvxQvVf">His paper is designed to help governments decide: "where to implement digital technologies in the health product supply chain; how to sequence and prioritize different use cases; and, how to avoid the pitfalls of digital solutions without clear logic models for yielding long-term performance improvements."</s></p><p xml:id="_UMdweyd"><s xml:id="_gAF78Dm">In his paper, Yadav introduces the Supply Chain Operations Reference (SCOR) model, which includes six main processes: Plan, Source, Make, Deliver, Return, and Enable.</s><s xml:id="_tzGzK7t">He focuses on the application of digital technology in four of these processes (Plan, Source, Deliver, and Enable) and relates these processes to the "4 A's" Access Framework proposed by Frost and Reich, <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref> with attention to how the four processes can improve Availability and Affordability, can influence global Adoption, and can help reconfigure the Architecture around access to health technologies.</s><s xml:id="_KCDJdFS">For each process, he uses specific examples to explore how access can be improved through digitalization.</s></p><p xml:id="_XB9QPcW"><s xml:id="_WwKWrG9">Yadav's comprehensive paper on how to manage digital interventions in the health sector is a tour de force that will be useful to supply chain managers and experts around the world.</s><s xml:id="_9nqQsca">He concludes by noting that while digital technologies provide an opportunity to revolutionize health supply chains, "the actual realized effects . . .</s><s xml:id="_KrSdjBJ">have generally been modest to date."</s><s xml:id="_du3J5x9">To achieve the full potential gains, he writes, technology "must be integrated with the underlying processes and the incentives of the internal actors involved."</s><s xml:id="_f79mzm9">Yadav also provides some guidance for governments that seek to navigate the "highly complicated" decisions related to digital health initiatives, in order to help governments "formulate clear plans for implementation, rather than getting stuck in the intricacies of the process."</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_xJ7PvrF">Using Data to Improve Health System Performance</head><p xml:id="_P8DArph"><s xml:id="_sABSNfc">The last prediction by Mitchell and Kan is that major changes will occur in the structure and use of digital health data to improve health system performance, particularly in low-and middle-income countries.</s><s xml:id="_Kydb3Hj">These changes will occur through the introduction of frontline data collection tools linked to national networks.</s><s xml:id="_UcVV2de">New digitally-supported connections can facilitate diagnostics, appropriate treatment, and system planning.</s><s xml:id="_ACTvtVs">They could also be used to improve the quality of care delivered and support earlier identification of infectious disease outbreaks.</s><s xml:id="_G2kkMpp">However, the plethora of new digital data also raises potential concerns about the use of the information for commercial, political, or other purposes that could undermine public health objectives.</s></p><p xml:id="_6ENaXXg"><s xml:id="_Ec4Pc8J">Jui-fen Rachel Lu and Li-Lin Liang examine how digital technologies have been used in Taiwan's National Health Insurance, including in response to the COVID-19 pandemic. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref></s><s xml:id="_H4xUPYH">They particularly address two digital opportunities: 1) the role of big data management and analytics, and 2) the use of innovative telemedicine service models.</s><s xml:id="_fNVwDcK">They describe how Taiwan was an early innovator in the use of telemedicine to reach patients in remote areas.</s><s xml:id="_y67ZnRT">Taiwan started its telemedicine program between medicinal institutions in 1995, the same year that they achieved universal coverage, and continued with additional digital innovations in subsequent years, providing patients with a smart IC card and creating a centralized record system for medication and clinical services.</s></p><p xml:id="_Xf42rHh"><s xml:id="_rwqVvtZ">Lu and Liang report on how Taiwan used these digital technologies to effectively control the COVID-19 pandemic.</s><s xml:id="_fSPq6v2">For example, during the pandemic, "the NHI MediCloud System was linked with the national immigration system and recorded individuals' occupations, travel and contact history, and medical records, allowing health professionals to identify high-risk patients."</s><s xml:id="_SPyvZtn">This contact tracing system was combined with "early and timely border control," to give Taiwan "the world record for the longest period without a local infection (253 days) and to avoid imposing lockdowns throughout 2020."</s><s xml:id="_xWx6F7F">Taiwan also created a tracking system that was imposed on quarantined people to create a "geofencing" system that contained confirmed cases and reduced infections in other people.</s><s xml:id="_Vxm5bxw">Despite general public support for these and other measures, Lu and Liang identify two specific challenges that arose in Taiwan: digital trust (concerns about whether digitalization would protect stakeholders' interests and values) and the digital divide (how socially disadvantaged groups can lack access to internet services and devices).</s><s xml:id="_3aS8HnE">They offer a number of policy suggestions for Taiwan (and other nations) to address these two "daunting challenges" that affect the "trend of the future" that is digital health.</s></p><p xml:id="_vAeKMGq"><s xml:id="_w7AhsEs">The final paper in the Special Issue, by Akihiro Seita and colleagues, examines how UNRWA (the United Nations Relief and Works Agency for Palestine Refugees in the Near East) used digital health during the COVID-19 pandemic to address the crisis and provide continuity of services for Palestine refugees, and how those experiences helped to transform the United Nations health system for this population in the postpandemic period. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref></s><s xml:id="_awh6tCn">UNRWA delivers primary care services for about 5.9 million Palestine refugees at 140 health centers.</s><s xml:id="_hPPCVsA">UNRWA developed an in-house electronic medical records system called e-Health in 2009, instituted systemic data protection mechanisms based on the UN Personal Data Protection and Privacy Principles, and introduced a Family Health Team model of primary care delivery in a reform effort in 2012.</s><s xml:id="_5BYQpwc">In 2017, UNRWA developed a smartphone version of its maternal and child health booklet (e-MCH), and in 2020 introduced a similar application for non-communicable diseases (NCDs) (called e-NCDs)-both linked to e-Health.</s></p><p xml:id="_KNVtG6m"><s xml:id="_ev2bmaJ">UNRWA's digitalization efforts prepared the foundation for the agency's actions to address the pandemic.</s><s xml:id="_SE74q5y">For example, data from e-Health allowed medical staff to determine that a high proportion of NCD patients (around 70% in early 2020) continued to attend their medical appointments during the pandemic, reflecting a good level of continuity of care.</s><s xml:id="_X9t4MWH">The system further allowed for following the results of COVID-19 tests in UNRWA health centers, and then assuring appropriate interventions.</s><s xml:id="_3JtJ8Ee">UNRWA implemented its telemedicine consultations during the pandemic to help with continuity of care, especially for NCDs.</s><s xml:id="_526krMs">The agency also promoted the use of two e-Health apps (e-MCH and e-NCDs) on mobile phones that encourage self-management by patients; these apps each reached over 20,000 active users in 2023.</s><s xml:id="_PGEYuXZ">These various digital interventions allowed UNRWA to "strengthen health systems, promote patient-centered care, and improve health outcomes in the face of challenges such as pandemics."</s><s xml:id="_8eVjtHx">While the agency's work in Gaza has shifted its focus due to the ongoing war, in other locations UNRWA is maintaining and expanding its use of digital technologies in the post-pandemic period as a way of "continuously protecting the health and well-being of [the people] it serves."</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_AqXHPv6">Concluding Comments</head><p xml:id="_avEFK43"><s xml:id="_ButYhKT">The five themes about digital health presented above are relevant to health systems around the world and in various situations.</s><s xml:id="_dPppNjF">As noted in a number of the Special Issue papers, digital technologies have great potential to improve our responses to crises, such as the COVID-19 pandemic.</s><s xml:id="_Z7AeA4F">They can also transform the operations of health systems in normal times.</s><s xml:id="_ej9mqPR">We believe that, with continued attention to both human factors and data security, digital technologies can be used to foster human security at global, national, and local levels.</s><s xml:id="_sx6xjpX">The availability of routine digital health data can also support disaster and crisis preparedness and response, playing critically important roles in identifying and designing responses to crises and assessing the effects of interventions to mitigate the effects.</s><s xml:id="_ENY3DMV">Deployed thoughtfully, AI and machine learning tools can also assist in both designing responses and assessing effectiveness-and we are likely to witness increasing use of AI in strengthening health systems during crises as well as normal operations.</s></p><p xml:id="_ZcmA69e"><s xml:id="_9AUeC6M">The twelve papers in this Special Issue cover a wide range of topics related to digital health, providing in-depth case studies of digital interventions, quantitative and qualitative assessments of what those interventions have produced in specific settings, and the introduction of concepts and frameworks for thinking and strategizing about the evolution and use of digital health tools.</s><s xml:id="_zGcKgUE">We hope that these papers contribute to better understanding of the ongoing tsunami of digital health technologies and the resulting changes in health systems.</s><s xml:id="_y3ZPWJS">Healthcare providers will need to learn how to integrate digital technologies into their work.</s><s xml:id="_q9SMTXw">With careful attention to both technical and social aspects, digital changes can contribute to more effective and equitable health care around the world.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_KF8qAB8">Disclosure Statement</head><p xml:id="_3Bw4xvM"><s xml:id="_Yscz7zd">The author reported there is no funding associated with the work featured in this article.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>ARTICLE HISTORY Received 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_ZRYJZ5Z"><s xml:id="_pAfYApD">August 2024; Revised 1 September 2024; Accepted 31 August 2024 KEYWORDS Digital health; health system reform; takemi program in international health</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head xml:id="_pEwGkk7">Acknowledgments</head><p xml:id="_JC9tpmD"><s xml:id="_UdWwkuG">Earlier versions of the papers in this Special Issue were presented at the 40th Anniversary Takemi Symposium on "Digital Health: Opportunities and Challenges for Global Health," held on 20-21 October 2023, in Boston, Massachusetts, at <rs type="institution">Harvard University</rs>.</s><s xml:id="_F284Ha6">The Symposium was organized by the <rs type="institution">Takemi Program in International Health</rs>, at the <rs type="institution">Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health</rs>, with support from the <rs type="funder">Japan Medical Association</rs>, and sponsorship from the <rs type="funder">Japan Pharmaceutical Manufacturers Association</rs>, the <rs type="funder">Takemi Memorial Trust for Research of Seizon and Life Sciences</rs>, and the <rs type="funder">Pharmaceutical Research and Manufacturers of America</rs>.</s><s xml:id="_Zerh5kZ">The author appreciates comments on earlier drafts of this Introduction from <rs type="person">Anya L. Guyer</rs>, <rs type="person">Aya Goto</rs>, <rs type="person">Jesse Bump</rs>, <rs type="person">Corrina Moucheraud</rs>, and the main authors of the 12 papers in this Special Issue.</s></p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_YWQaPZ3">Chan school of public health takemi program in international health 40th anniversary symposium</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Harvard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0968-8080(00)90268-4</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.med.or.jp/english/activities/pdf/20231111_report.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023-11-11">2023 Nov 11</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Japan Medical Association</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Report of meeting In Japanese and English</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Japan Medical Association. Harvard T.H. Chan school of public health takemi program in interna- tional health 40th anniversary symposium. Report of meeting. 2023 Nov 11. [In Japanese and English]. https://www.med.or.jp/english/activities/pdf/ 20231111_report.pdf .</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_dmwPyMF">WHO guideline: recommendations on digital interventions for health system strengthening</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2471/b09429</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789241550505" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<publisher>WHO</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Geneva</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Executive summary</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">World Health Organization. WHO guideline: recom- mendations on digital interventions for health system strengthening. Executive summary. Geneva: WHO; 2019. (WHO/RHR/19.8). https://www.who.int/publica tions/i/item/9789241550505 .</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_2Td6Mu3">Global strategy on digital health 2020-2025</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ww/9780199540884.013.u256626</idno>
		<ptr target="https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/344249" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<publisher>World Health Organization</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Geneva</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">World Health Organization. Global strategy on digi- tal health 2020-2025. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2021. https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/ 10665/344249 .</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qPYHjfn">Digital technology and the future of health systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/23288604.2019.1583040</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_DKQxTdm">Health Syst Reform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="120" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mitchell M, Kan L. Digital technology and the future of health systems. Health Syst Reform. 2019;5(2):113-20. doi: 10.1080/23288604.2019.1583040 .</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_RFG9tdc">Better Decisions Saves Lives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D-Tree</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1515/9781400873333-014</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.d-tree.org/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024-06-12">2024 June 12</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">D-tree, Better Decisions Saves Lives. [2024 June 12]. https://www.d-tree.org/ .</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_jQaMSYx">The digital transformation in health: how AI can improve the performance of health systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Periánéz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fernandez De Río</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Nazarov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Jané</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hassan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rastogi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/23288604.2024.23876138</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_sMZx5AD">Health Syst Reform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">23876138</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Periánéz A, Fernandez de Río A, Nazarov I, Jané E, Hassan M, Rastogi A, Tang D. The digital transfor- mation in health: how AI can improve the perfor- mance of health systems. Health Syst Reform. 2024;10(2):23876138. doi: 10.1080/23288604.2024. 23876138 .</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Jsn67hg">The national digital health mission of India: a concurrent assessment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Mishra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yadav</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/23288604.2024.2392290</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Wxm6JKv">Health Syst Reform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2392290</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mishra U, Yadav S. The national digital health mission of India: a concurrent assessment. Health Syst Reform. 2024;10(2):2392290. doi: 10.1080/23288604.2024. 2392290 .</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_R2TFhzF">Policies, progress, and prospects for internet telemedicine in China</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yip</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/23288604.2024.2389570</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_J8d3TfD">Health Syst Reform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2389570</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Cheng TC, Yip W. Policies, progress, and prospects for internet telemedicine in China. Health Syst Reform. 2024;10(2):2389570. doi: 10.1080/23288604.2024. 2389570 .</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_q3SUvFQ">Vaccine hesitancy and COVID-19 risk behaviors associated with social media use in Japan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Takahashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Takahashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nohara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kawachi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/23288604.2024.2377070</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_xzRmqDv">Health Syst Reform</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Takahashi S, Takahashi N, Nohara M, Kawachi I. Vaccine hesitancy and COVID-19 risk behaviors associated with social media use in Japan. Health Syst Reform. 2024; doi: 10.1080/23288604.2024. 2377070 .</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_NrC9bjk">Transforming the patient-provider relationship through digitalized peer support in Japan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hosoda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/23288604.2024.2392306</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_VJNPMWY">Health Syst Reform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2392306</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hosoda M. Transforming the patient-provider relation- ship through digitalized peer support in Japan. Health Syst Reform. 2024;10(2):2392306. doi: 10.1080/ 23288604.2024.2392306 .</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_XJcdBc7">Technological innovation in international training and advancing health services: two cases during the COVID-19 pandemic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Benski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Goto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/23288604.2024.2387646</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_cHj6gdG">Health Syst Reform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2387646</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Benski C, Goto A. Technological innovation in inter- national training and advancing health services: two cases during the COVID-19 pandemic. Health Syst Reform. 2024;10(2):2387646. doi: 10.1080/23288604. 2024.2387646 .</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_V26jbNd">Preparedness, challenges, and opportunities for digital health intervention for chronic disease management: a qualitative study in rural areas of South Korea</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ju</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Oh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2196/52402</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_EtNyANk">JMIR Public Health Surveill</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2375101</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lee HY, Ju M, Kang M, Lee H, Choi J, Oh J. Preparedness, challenges, and opportunities for digital health intervention for chronic disease management: a qualitative study in rural areas of South Korea. JMIR Public Health Surveill. 2024;10(2):2375101. doi: 10. 2196/52402 .</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_fhuhhk6">Applying mobile technology to address gender-based violence in rural Nigeria: experiences and perceptions of users and stakeholders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Okonofua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Babatunde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Goldson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Abubakar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Mueller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Alayande</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ojogun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ntoimo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Sanyaolu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Omokaro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Onoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Muhammed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Adeniran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Anakhuekha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Ogochukwu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yaya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/23288604.2024.2389569</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_9vU5cet">Health Syst Reform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2389569</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Okonofua F, Babatunde A, Goldson E, Abubakar Z, Mueller U, Alayande A, Ojogun T, Ntoimo L, Sanyaolu O, Omokaro J, Onoh V, Williams B, Muhammed I, Adeniran J, Anakhuekha E, Ogochukwu U, Yaya S. Applying mobile technology to address gender-based violence in rural Nigeria: experiences and perceptions of users and stakeholders. Health Syst Reform. 2024;10 (2):2389569. doi: 10.1080/23288604.2024.2389569 .</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_HAT9fDa">Analyzing the Maharashtra ambulance service &quot;108&quot;: the prospects and challenges</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sarkar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jana</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Saunik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/23288604.2024.2380251</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_uxDfjGz">Health Syst Reform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2380251</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sarkar A, Jana A, Saunik S. Analyzing the Maharashtra ambulance service &quot;108&quot;: the prospects and challenges. Health Syst Reform. 2024;10(2):2380251. doi: 10.1080/ 23288604.2024.2380251 .</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_jgcazQe">Digital transformation in the health product supply chain: a framework for analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Yadav</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/23288604.2024.2386041</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_VaX7J3s">Health Syst Reform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2386041</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Yadav P. Digital transformation in the health product supply chain: a framework for analysis. Health Syst Reform. 2024;10(2):2386041. doi: 10.1080/23288604. 2024.2386041 .</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Frost</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Reich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_BRX6mqq">Access: how do good health technologies get to poor people in poor countries?</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge (MA)</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Harvard Center for Population and Development Studies</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Frost LJ, Reich MR. Access: how do good health tech- nologies get to poor people in poor countries? Cambridge (MA): Harvard Center for Population and Development Studies; 2008.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qhEAxsV">The role of digital health under Taiwan&apos;s national health insurance system: progress and challenges</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/23288604.2024.2375433</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_4VXVDyh">Health Syst Reform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2375433</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lu JR, Liang LL. The role of digital health under Taiwan&apos;s national health insurance system: progress and challenges. Health Syst Reform. 2024;10 (2):2375433. doi: 10.1080/23288604.2024.2375433 .</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_9gczmw8">Leveraging digital health data to transform the united nations systems for Palestine refugees for the post pandemic time</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Seita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Balout</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Albeik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Salameh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zeidan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Atallah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Horino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/23288604.2024.2378505</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_vWSxywt">Health Syst Reform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2378505</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Seita A, Balout G, Albeik S, Salameh Z, Zeidan W, Shah S, Atallah S, Horino M. Leveraging digital health data to transform the united nations systems for Palestine refugees for the post pandemic time. Health Syst Reform. 2024;10(2):2378505. doi: 10. 1080/23288604.2024.2378505.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">Reich</forename><surname>Michael</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Takemi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.21801/ppcrj.2023.91.6</idno>
		<ptr target="http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3338-0612" />
		<title level="m" xml:id="_euhjzKy">Program in International Health</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Boston, MA, USA michael_reich</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint/>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Michael R. Reich Takemi Program in International Health, Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health, Boston, MA, USA michael_reich@harvard.edu http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3338-0612</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
