<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_JscJbX3">Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic reviews and Meta-Analyses extension for Scoping Reviews (PRISMA-ScR) Checklist</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_yzxfvpZ">Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic reviews and Meta-Analyses extension for Scoping Reviews (PRISMA-ScR) Checklist</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">76B97C5B6524B414BDEECCA4709F6055</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.7326/m18-0850</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T12:42+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_4WqENYf"><p xml:id="_CYTeKGG"><s xml:id="_2wJnD4x">includes (as applicable): background, objectives, eligibility criteria, sources of evidence, charting methods, results, and conclusions that relate to the review questions and objectives.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_5putNMg">INTRODUCTION</head><p xml:id="_dakVhwF"><s xml:id="_EbRDA7A">Rationale 3</s></p><p xml:id="_CgqEHCc"><s xml:id="_AjBM7Ug">Describe the rationale for the review in the context of what is already known.</s><s xml:id="_QD7jg7E">Explain why the review questions/objectives lend themselves to a scoping review approach.</s></p><p xml:id="_Pf3EHfH"><s xml:id="_G4yyHwp">Objectives 4</s></p><p xml:id="_cN9BsJR"><s xml:id="_dSanhuk">Provide an explicit statement of the questions and objectives being addressed with reference to their key elements (e.g., population or participants, concepts, and context) or other relevant key elements used to conceptualize the review questions and/or objectives.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_uQsrZGb">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_GDDjWcX">Protocol and registration 5</head><p xml:id="_EHrBX2s"><s xml:id="_hPQUzr7">Indicate whether a review protocol exists; state if and where it can be accessed (e.g., a Web address); and if available, provide registration information, including the registration number.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_w8WAyF3">Eligibility criteria 6</head><p xml:id="_nr5uQ4e"><s xml:id="_zTwJFkT">Specify characteristics of the sources of evidence used as eligibility criteria (e.g., years considered, language, and publication status), and provide a rationale.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_639DDE9">Information sources* 7</head><p xml:id="_JYkKRcQ"><s xml:id="_93tCRq7">Describe all information sources in the search (e.g., databases with dates of coverage and contact with authors to identify additional sources), as well as the date the most recent search was executed.</s></p><p xml:id="_RdVQjfF"><s xml:id="_YzwbhYy">Search 8</s></p><p xml:id="_5kfg5C7"><s xml:id="_XbMkRuC">Present the full electronic search strategy for at least 1 database, including any limits used, such that it could be repeated.</s><s xml:id="_DBqJERb">Selection of sources of evidence † 9</s></p><p xml:id="_gxbgPdJ"><s xml:id="_e6mRVnM">State the process for selecting sources of evidence (i.e., screening and eligibility) included in the scoping review.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Hb5t46T">Data charting process ‡ 10</head><p xml:id="_YtAdbs8"><s xml:id="_6GAr6kA">Describe the methods of charting data from the included sources of evidence (e.g., calibrated forms or forms that have been tested by the team before their use, and whether data charting was done independently or in duplicate) and any processes for obtaining and confirming data from investigators.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_9A5ntDr">Data items 11</head><p xml:id="_Qv5K88w"><s xml:id="_yepRq4X">List and define all variables for which data were sought and any assumptions and simplifications made.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_kPwbb2w">Critical appraisal of individual sources of evidence § 12</head><p xml:id="_hb8Uksu"><s xml:id="_39zH2uR">If done, provide a rationale for conducting a critical appraisal of included sources of evidence; describe the methods used and how this information was used in any data synthesis (if appropriate).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_TDGCr6c">Synthesis of results 13</head><p xml:id="_7FWsEQe"><s xml:id="_5r2Uw6p">Describe the methods of handling and summarizing the data that were charted.</s></p><p xml:id="_3USnYaC"><s xml:id="_TUvtRMS">1 1 2-3 3 3 3-4 3-4 &amp; Appx 2 Appx 2 3-4 4 4 Not done SECTION ITEM PRISMA-ScR CHECKLIST ITEM REPORTED ON PAGE # RESULTS</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_CZThD4C">Selection of sources of evidence 14</head><p xml:id="_mGBw4Vq"><s xml:id="_9XJ8TXR">Give numbers of sources of evidence screened, assessed for eligibility, and included in the review, with reasons for exclusions at each stage, ideally using a flow diagram.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_F5neXyc">Characteristics of sources of evidence 15</head><p xml:id="_WvScnPG"><s xml:id="_Pbqq9xW">For each source of evidence, present characteristics for which data were charted and provide the citations.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_XSvprdq">Critical appraisal within sources of evidence 16</head><p xml:id="_wkC5E4Q"><s xml:id="_nduxsH5">If done, present data on critical appraisal of included sources of evidence (see item 12).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_g6xzjau">Results of individual sources of evidence 17</head><p xml:id="_cBFxtjj"><s xml:id="_SuJ6gQW">For each included source of evidence, present the relevant data that were charted that relate to the review questions and objectives.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_kjtPCk7">Synthesis of results 18</head><p xml:id="_KYrkYdy"><s xml:id="_CSEB7Mr">Summarize and/or present the charting results as they relate to the review questions and objectives.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_agRWUrj">DISCUSSION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_RaspxUC">Summary of evidence 19</head><p xml:id="_vtguCSW"><s xml:id="_UYgCgZ6">Summarize the main results (including an overview of concepts, themes, and types of evidence available), link to the review questions and objectives, and consider the relevance to key groups.</s><s xml:id="_3dE2zvv">Limitations 20 Discuss the limitations of the scoping review process.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_PbjBvU2">Conclusions 21</head><p xml:id="_4BjGVbA"><s xml:id="_PDRHNCt">Provide a general interpretation of the results with respect to the review questions and objectives, as well as potential implications and/or next steps.</s><s xml:id="_AqgBg6P">FUNDING</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_pj5thFn">Funding 22</head><p xml:id="_ZQmCqr2"><s xml:id="_jgCPDdV">Describe sources of funding for the included sources of evidence, as well as sources of funding for the scoping review.</s><s xml:id="_4KJNQqN">Describe the role of the funders of the scoping review.</s></p><p xml:id="_6GzrmhN"><s xml:id="_uYU6Xb8">JBI = Joanna Briggs Institute; PRISMA-ScR = Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic reviews and Meta-Analyses extension for Scoping Reviews.</s><s xml:id="_gamCrpS">* Where sources of evidence (see second footnote) are compiled from, such as bibliographic databases, social media platforms, and Web sites.</s><s xml:id="_mBHmQnM">† A more inclusive/heterogeneous term used to account for the different types of evidence or data sources (e.g., quantitative and/or qualitative research, expert opinion, and policy documents) that may be eligible in a scoping review as opposed to only studies.</s><s xml:id="_ZzEbjfR">This is not to be confused with information sources (see first footnote).</s><s xml:id="_kYhHrWY">‡ The frameworks by <ref type="bibr">Arksey and O'Malley (6)</ref> and Levac and colleagues (7) and the JBI guidance (4, 5) refer to the process of data extraction in a scoping review as data charting.</s><s xml:id="_PxESgK9">§ The process of systematically examining research evidence to assess its validity, results, and relevance before using it to inform a decision.</s><s xml:id="_gbsvQ4Q">This term is used for items 12 and 19 instead of "risk of bias" (which is more applicable to systematic reviews of interventions) to include and acknowledge the various sources of evidence that may be used in a scoping review (e.g., quantitative and/or qualitative research, expert opinion, and policy document).</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>From:</head><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_a5g3bGT"><s xml:id="_8X2UAQK">Tricco AC, Lillie E, Zarin W, O'Brien KK, Colquhoun H, Levac D, et al.</s><s xml:id="_fp3FfVV">PRISMA Extension for Scoping Reviews (PRISMAScR): Checklist and Explanation.</s><s xml:id="_ADDtVJh">Ann Intern Med.</s><s xml:id="_XXCVTQs">2018;169:467-473.</s><s xml:id="_H9MTJqb">doi: 10.7326/M18-0850.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
