<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_grmTcgV"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
					<p type="raw">Copyright © 2021 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2021-04">April 2021</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sarah</forename><forename type="middle">Collins</forename><surname>Rossetti</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Judy</forename><forename type="middle">Murphy</forename><surname>Honored With</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MSN, RN-BC</roleName><forename type="first">Susan</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hull</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">NEA-BC , FAMIA Alliance for Nursing Informatics Principal , Consumer Health Informatics , MITRE Corporation , Chicago , IL.</note>
								<orgName type="department">FAMIA Alliance for Nursing Informatics Principal</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">NEA-BC</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Consumer Health Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">MITRE Corporation</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Chicago</settlement>
									<region>IL</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">CIN: Computers , Informatics , Nursing</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">CIN: Computers</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Nursing</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2021-04">April 2021</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">951E326989BABE97EF3694591609D571</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T12:44+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="557.972" lry="773.972"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="557.972" lry="773.972"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_4qNwnYT">T</head><p xml:id="_yafKgrB"><s xml:id="_TmCbQrK">he Alliance for Nursing Informatics (ANI) celebrates the recognition of two of our esteemed colleagues as recipients of 2020 AMIA Signature Awards for significant contributions to the field of informatics: Sarah Collins Rossetti, PhD, RN, FACMI, FAMIA, as the recipient of the Don Eugene Detmer Award for Health Policy Contributions in Informatics; and Judy Murphy, RN, FACMI, LFHIMSS, FAAN, as the recipient of the Virginia K. Saba Informatics Award.</s></p><p xml:id="_ZyvgNTf"><s xml:id="_Ut3XuBE">The Don Eugene Detmer Award for Health Policy Contributions in Informatics recognizes an individual who has made a significant singular contribution or series of contributions over the course of a career exemplifying the expertise, passion, and spirit that Dr Detmer has for health policy.</s><s xml:id="_UXgDnGn">Dr Detmer received the first award in 2008.</s><s xml:id="_FvP5Mks">Recipients, nominated annually by AMIA peers, are honored for their contribution(s) to health policy in biomedical and health informatics and demonstrated commitment to AMIA through membership.</s><s xml:id="_bh7vJ2e">The award requires contributions to be aligned with the philosophy that all citizens and populations deserve a state-of-the-art health system that provides safe, effective, patient-centered, timely, efficient, and equitable healthcare services.</s><s xml:id="_TvNC8m5">Awardees are recognized for their visionary leadership in the health policy realm; action-oriented advocacy work producing a regional, national, or global result; and advancement to the domain health policy through leadership generating a sustainable contribution to the health system.</s></p><p xml:id="_uJVwYS3"><s xml:id="_Kndc8dv">Previous nurse recipients are Judy Murphy in 2014 and Susan C. Hull in 2017.</s><s xml:id="_dnm6At4">We are honored to congratulate Sarah Collins Rossetti, PhD, RN, FACMI, FAMIA, as the 2020 recipient of this signature award.</s><s xml:id="_XSh8vkX">Sarah Collins Rossetti is an assistant professor of biomedical informatics and nursing at Columbia University.</s><s xml:id="_D8hVx4M">Her research is focused on identifying and intervening on patient risk for harm by applying computational tools to mine and extract value from electronic health record data and maximizing user-centered design for patientcentered technologies.</s><s xml:id="_P33TqBE">Previously, she was a senior informaticist at Brigham and Women's Hospital and Harvard Medical School.</s><s xml:id="_hU2zDkh">Sarah is an experienced critical care nurse, received her PhD from Columbia University School of Nursing, and completed a Postdoctoral Research Fellowship at Columbia University's Department of Biomedical Informatics.</s></p><p xml:id="_rPEMC9u"><s xml:id="_4EmwZ7B">Dr Rossetti was a 2019 recipient of the Presidential Early Career Award for Scientists and Engineers (PECASE).</s><s xml:id="_w4zV8vp">The PECASE is the highest honor bestowed by the US Government to outstanding scientists and engineers who are beginning their independent research careers and who show exceptional promise for leadership in science and technology.</s><s xml:id="_8yPP3cq">Sarah served on the AMIA Board of Directors, served also served as an ANI Emerging Leader in its second cohort <ref type="bibr">(2012)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2013)</ref> and first Policy Coordinator for ANI in 2015.</s></p><p xml:id="_MXbu5mB"><s xml:id="_Kks5YHj">The Virginia K. Saba Informatics Award recognizes an individual's distinguished career and significant impact on the care of patients and the discipline of nursing.</s><s xml:id="_3krZb5s">The award honors a professional with exemplary principles and practices and a substantial record of contribution to the field of nursing informatics and demonstrated commitment to AMIA through membership.</s><s xml:id="_cmNGqdq">Criteria for this international award include characteristics and achievements of visionary leadership, global impact, and enduring contribution to nursing professional practice, education, administration, research, and/or health policy and demonstrated commitment to AMIA through membership.</s><s xml:id="_EhmbHdq">Virginia K. Saba, EdD, RN, was the first recipient of this award in 2005.</s><s xml:id="_Qh5EMNH">We are honored to congratulate Judy Murphy, RN, FACMI, LFHIMSS, FAAN, as the 2020 recipient of this signature award.</s></p><p xml:id="_VcReHaN"><s xml:id="_QDYFVWV">Judy Murphy is a nurse executive and health information technology (IT) leader with a long history in health and nursing informatics.</s><s xml:id="_G43zxa4">Judy was chief nursing officer at IBM Global Healthcare, where she built relationships and expanded business across the healthcare industry.</s><s xml:id="_mmjRCEE">She was strategic advisor to clients and helped align IBM's health IT solutions for providers to improve health and healthcare and lower costs.</s><s xml:id="_NcZvXfD">She has published more than 100 articles and book chapters and has done hundreds of presentations nationally and internationally.</s><s xml:id="_aerzM6U">She served on the AMIA and HIMSS Board of Directors and is a fellow in the American Academy of Nursing and the American College of Medical Informatics and is an HIMSS Lifetime Fellow.</s></p><p xml:id="_qFQZ7M9"><s xml:id="_nFyxP7N">She has received numerous awards, including the HIMSS 2018 Most Influential Women in Health IT, the AMIA 2014 Don Eugene Detmer Award for Health Policy Contributions in Informatics, the HIMSS 2014 Federal Health IT Leadership Award, and the HIMSS 2006 Nursing Informatics Leadership Award.</s></p><p xml:id="_kDaFCmq"><s xml:id="_d926ktn">From all of us in the ANI community and beyond, we extend our heartiest congratulations and applause for the international recognition for Sarah and Judy and gratitude for the contributions each has made to advancing the field of nursing and nursing informatics.</s></p></div>			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p xml:id="_P2t9bjr"><s xml:id="_6ty8kYA">Volume 39 | Number 4 CIN: Computers, Informatics, Nursing</s></p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p xml:id="_dkb4pcs"><s xml:id="_p2sWsbC">Copyright © 2021 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</s><s xml:id="_DTCSMu6">All rights reserved.</s></p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
