<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_pTqTehX">Remote Monitoring and Behavioral Economics in Managing Heart Failure in Patients Discharged From the Hospital A Randomized Clinical Trial</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
					<p type="raw">This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License. © 2022 Asch DA et al. JAMA Internal Medicine.</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2022-05-09">May 9, 2022</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Asch</surname></persName>
							<email>asch@wharton.upenn.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Andrea</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Troxel</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD, MPH</roleName><forename type="first">Lee</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Goldberg</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Monique</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Tanna</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD, MBA, MSHP</roleName><forename type="first">Shivan</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mehta</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MA</roleName><forename type="first">Laurie</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Norton</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MS, MBA</roleName><forename type="first">Jingsan</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>BA</roleName><forename type="first">Lauren</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Iannotte</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">Tamar</forename><surname>Klaiman</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MS</roleName><forename type="first">Yuqing</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">Louise</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Russell</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Kevin</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Volpp</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Asch</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tanna</forename><surname>Goldberg</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Volpp</forename><surname>Mehta</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Leonard</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Mehta</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Russell</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Troxel</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Goldberg</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Zhu, Iannotte, Klaiman</roleName><surname>Norton</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lin</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Volpp</forename><surname>Asch</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Iannotte</roleName><forename type="first">Norton</forename><surname>Goldberg</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Department of Medicine , Perelman School of Medicine , University of Pennsylvania , Philadelphia</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Perelman School of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pennsylvania</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Institute of Health Economics , University of Pennsylvania , Philadelphia</note>
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Health Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pennsylvania</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Department of Medical Ethics and Health Policy , Perelman School of Medicine , University of Pennsylvania , Philadelphia</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Medical Ethics and Health Policy</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Perelman School of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pennsylvania</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Division of Biostatistics , NYU Grossman School of Medicine , New York , New York</note>
								<orgName type="department">Division of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">NYU Grossman School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>New York</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Center for Health Care Innovation , 3600 Civic Center Blvd , Philadelphia , PA 19104</note>
								<orgName type="department">Center for Health Care Innovation</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>3600 Civic Center Blvd</addrLine>
									<postCode>19104</postCode>
									<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_zmWMTaP">Remote Monitoring and Behavioral Economics in Managing Heart Failure in Patients Discharged From the Hospital A Randomized Clinical Trial</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2022-05-09">May 9, 2022</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">0A6B92E63DC126809FD4CD7B72DAF1F5</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1001/jamainternmed.2022.1383</idno>
					<note type="submission">Accepted for Publication: March 12, 2022.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T13:17+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_GnaFcjk"><p xml:id="_z8GBnqy"><s xml:id="_5gtZEcs">IMPORTANCE Close remote monitoring of patients following discharge for heart failure (HF) may reduce readmissions or death.</s></p><p xml:id="_2fZ5HmH"><s xml:id="_d4X6JPD">OBJECTIVE To determine whether remote monitoring of diuretic adherence and weight changes with financial incentives reduces hospital readmissions or death following discharge with HF.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_BmepUxZ">DESIGN, SETTING, AND PARTICIPANTS</head><p xml:id="_4kWpcXr"><s xml:id="_sfwJJpR">The Electronic Monitoring of Patients Offers Ways to Enhance Recovery (EMPOWER) study, a 3-hospital pragmatic trial, randomized 552 adults recently discharged with HF to usual care (n = 280) or a compound intervention (n = 272) designed to inform clinicians of diuretic adherence and changes in patient weight.</s><s xml:id="_faVkqjC">Patients were recruited from May 25, 2016, to April 8, 2019, and followed up for 12 months.</s><s xml:id="_veQax2w">Investigators were blinded to assignment but patients were not.</s><s xml:id="_NG9xdHs">Analysis was by intent to treat.</s></p><p xml:id="_5VVQVhM"><s xml:id="_fNKKGrZ">INTERVENTIONS Participants randomized to the intervention arm received digital scales, electronic pill bottles for diuretic medication, and regret lottery incentives conditional on the previous day's adherence to both medication and weight measurement, with $1.40 expected daily value.</s><s xml:id="_P6ea5wV">Participants' physicians were alerted if participants' weights increased 1.4 kg in 24 hours or 2.3 kg in 72 hours or if diuretic medications were missed for 5 days.</s><s xml:id="_RvGVHVs">Alerts and weights were integrated into the electronic health record.</s><s xml:id="_R8qJpdW">Participants randomized to the control arm received usual care and no further study contact.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_v377tcp">MAIN OUTCOMES AND MEASURES Time to death or readmission for any cause within 12 months.</head><p xml:id="_yuK4WH2"><s xml:id="_ES9rmfs">RESULTS Of the 552 participants, 290 were men (52.5%); 291 patients (52.7%) were Black, 231 were White (41.8%), and 16 were Hispanic (2.9%); mean (SD) age was 64.5 (11.8) years.</s><s xml:id="_jZuVXkZ">The mean (SD) ejection fraction was 43% (18.1%).</s><s xml:id="_gnwrtuB">Each month, approximately 75% of participants were 80% adherent to both medication and weight measurement.</s><s xml:id="_FXjyEXb">There were 423 readmissions and 26 deaths in the control group and 377 readmissions and 23 deaths in the intervention group.</s><s xml:id="_5ChtaCN">There was no significant difference between the 2 groups for the combined outcome of all-cause inpatient readmission or death (unadjusted hazard ratio, 0.91; 95% CI, 0.74-1.13;</s><s xml:id="_BKFtYrH">P = .40)</s><s xml:id="_r6C2CCk">and no significant differences in all-cause inpatient readmission or observation stay or death, all-cause cardiovascular readmission or death, time to first event, and total all-cause deaths.</s><s xml:id="_s2tM3D8">Participants in the intervention group were slightly more likely to spend fewer days in the hospital.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_2KsHgxG">CONCLUSIONS AND RELEVANCE</head><p xml:id="_VvhX9XK"><s xml:id="_XVmCbGc">In this randomized clinical trial, there was no reduction in the combined outcome of readmission or mortality in a year-long intensive remote monitoring program with incentives for patients previously hospitalized for HF.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_QpvAARm">H</head><p xml:id="_cFRkE9A"><s xml:id="_SBBkAsc">eart failure (HF) management depends on a complex array of medications, lifestyle changes, follow-up care, and patient participation: a few missed doses of a diuretic medication or a small increase in dietary sodium can result in readmission. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref></s><s xml:id="_ccXmHuw">Clinicians need timely awareness of often subtle changes in weight or adherence to intervene before clinical deterioration, and yet those indicators are typically out of view. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref></s><s xml:id="_ayS5vRu">The result is a combination of awareness of the many potential opportunities for intervention along the pathway to HF readmission, and yet no efficient approaches to implement them. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr">[6]</ref></s><s xml:id="_BfJcqdA"><ref type="bibr">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr">[10]</ref> A hope has been to engage patients in self-monitoring and efficiently engage clinicians in the care of those patients outside of office visits.</s><s xml:id="_TAX9ZqU">New insights from the field of behavioral economics offer promise for sustaining this kind of patient engagement, for example, by offering rewards that not only provide immediate incentives for adherence but that are designed to harness known behavioral tendencies. <ref type="bibr">11</ref></s><s xml:id="_tdrSGGu">Daily lotteries have improved medication adherence and weight loss, and those that incorporate anticipated regret (people are notified whether they won or would have won) and variable rewards (frequent small payoffs and infrequent large payoffs) have been demonstrated to be engaging in a variety of contexts. <ref type="bibr">12</ref></s><s xml:id="_vA6qJcd">In addition, new technology allows important information from remote monitoring to be automatically integrated into the electronic health record (EHR), simplifying clinical workflows and presenting data in the context of care.</s></p><p xml:id="_z3jDwYm"><s xml:id="_XTyX2Dv">Herein we report the main results of the Electronic Monitoring of Patients Offers Ways to Enhance Recovery (EMPOWER) trial, a pragmatic randomized clinical trial to evaluate whether an automated approach to patient engagement that incorporates behavioral economic principles can reduce readmissions in patients with HF discharged from the hospital.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_tZsArf6">Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_gsSGBEU">Overview</head><p xml:id="_8SJfxZ7"><s xml:id="_FWWWvAh">The EMPOWER trial was a 2-arm pragmatic randomized clinical trial comparing usual care in the management of patients discharged from the hospital after an admission for HF with a compound intervention comprising (1) daily automated assessments of weight and adherence to oral diuretic medications, (2) financial incentives and a support partner to encourage those assessments, and (3) reporting of substantial weight changes or nonadherence to diuretics to the managing clinician in the EHR.</s><s xml:id="_HM4tRax">Participants provided verbal informed consent and received financial compensation.</s><s xml:id="_rJdYzWv">Patients were enrolled after discharge from a hospitalization for HF and were followed up for 1 year.</s><s xml:id="_4eKgjvt">The protocol and statistical analysis plan are reported in Supplement 1 and elsewhere. <ref type="bibr">13</ref></s><s xml:id="_7yzr4vK">The study was approved by the institutional review board of the University of Pennsylvania.</s><s xml:id="_RGpG2y6">This study followed the Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials (CONSORT) reporting guideline.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_UUh39K4">Participants, Recruitment, and Randomization</head><p xml:id="_R3SpupG"><s xml:id="_dtt7Pk3">Participants were recruited between May 25, 2016, and April 8, 2019.</s><s xml:id="_6KvTWux">Eligible participants were aged 18 to 80 years, discharged from 1 of 3 Penn Medicine hospitals in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, with either a primary diagnosis of HF (preserved or reduced ejection fraction), a secondary diagnosis of HF with intravenous diuretics administered during their inpatient stay, or HF appearing on their problem list with intravenous diuretics administered during their hospital stay.</s><s xml:id="_6CjgTdg">Participants were eligible to enroll up to 30 days postdischarge if prescribed a daily diuretic and expected to have HF followed up by a Penn Medicine clinician (cardiology or primary care).</s><s xml:id="_PENznr6">Participants were excluded if they had kidney failure, required inotrope therapy, were listed for or receiving a heart transplant or ventricular assist device, were receiving palliative or hospice care, had a history of uncontrolled cognitive or psychiatric conditions that could affect study participation, or were participating in another telemonitoring program.</s></p><p xml:id="_7hWsrFW"><s xml:id="_tm8sdh9">We enrolled patients with both preserved and reduced ejection fractions.</s><s xml:id="_RQC99V4">Clinical practice guidelines recommend that all patients with HF be enrolled in a disease management program. <ref type="bibr">14</ref></s><s xml:id="_gek2fCC">For both diseases, similar lifestyle changes and monitoring are recommended.</s></p><p xml:id="_Ew8xrYA"><s xml:id="_WnKfghF">Potentially eligible participants received up to 5 telephone calls from study staff.</s><s xml:id="_E4gMbtM">Participants providing verbal informed consent were then randomized to intervention or control in a 1:1 ratio stratified by hospital site.</s><s xml:id="_7VtW3hF">Investigators and data analysts were blinded to arm assignment; patients, study staff, and treating clinicians were not blinded.</s><s xml:id="_BvuPW2a">All enrolled participants received $25 for participation.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_DBwQQyc">Study Arms</head><p xml:id="_V2kZpsj"><s xml:id="_tbGgS6X">Participants randomized to the usual care arm received no further engagement with study personnel.</s><s xml:id="_ANETp73">Participants randomized to the intervention arm received (1) a digital scale; (2) an electronic pill bottle (LLC Technologies) to use for diuretic medication; (3) daily regret lottery incentives with an 18% chance of a $5 payout and a 1% chance of a $50 payout (expected daily value, $1.40) conditional on adherence to both medication and weight measurement from the previous day.</s><s xml:id="_hdYTzyB">Regret lotteries are seen as more motivating than regular lotteries because participants are informed of the prize they would have won had they been adherent the day before and anticipate and seek to avoid the regret of missing a prize. <ref type="bibr">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">16</ref></s><s xml:id="_2vbmSwa">Participants were also invited to identify a support partner who,</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_gYvkUfN">Key Points</head><p xml:id="_EjyNBaP"><s xml:id="_fauV6h3">Question Among patients discharged after a hospitalization for heart failure, does remote monitoring and rewarding their weight and diuretic adherence reduce subsequent chances of death or rehospitalization?</s></p><p xml:id="_C2VWxgf"><s xml:id="_Ww8Rqwg">Findings In this randomized clinical trial of 552 adults followed up for 12 months, hospital readmissions or death were not significantly different whether patients received remote monitoring and financial incentives or usual care.</s></p><p xml:id="_UxfDyXX"><s xml:id="_TGkUgMV">Meaning In this randomized clinical trial, a comprehensive remote monitoring system with incentives did not improve patient outcomes in patients with heart failure discharged from the hospital.</s></p><p xml:id="_fQ37YFA"><s xml:id="_BdHSFYS">with agreement, would receive alerts about nonadherence to remote monitoring.</s><s xml:id="_e7WKfYW">Support partners might directly encourage participant adherence or enhance it by creating known witnesses to it. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">18</ref></s><s xml:id="_bQ5gZPc">n the intervention arm, participants' weights were automatically assessed against prespecified weight change thresholds of either 1.4 kg in 24 hours or 2.3 kg in 72 hours.</s><s xml:id="_zzBxJRE">Patients crossing either threshold were contacted by study staff to verify weights and answer a symptom questionnaire.</s><s xml:id="_uvk5Y3D">Verified information was then posted as an abnormal result into the EHR and routed to the patient's managing clinician.</s><s xml:id="_ZqPmvxS">Weekly, all verified weights were automatically imported into an EHR flowsheet in the participant's record.</s></p><p xml:id="_hqskEPw"><s xml:id="_rqUMz8A">Participants not weighing themselves or opening their pill bottle for 2 days received an automated message encouraging adherence; support partners also received the message.</s><s xml:id="_AWN7eCF">After 3 days of nonadherence, study staff called the participant; after 4 days, study staff called the support partner.</s><s xml:id="_3Pa3AES">After 5 days of nonadherence, study staff alerted the participant's clinicians through the EHR.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_3keFHcM">Study Outcomes</head><p xml:id="_tJWdR4s"><s xml:id="_WG2zx2k">The primary outcome was time to death or readmission for any cause.</s><s xml:id="_JngGPrJ">Outcomes were observed using EHR data from Penn Medicine, along with all-payer state data on inpatient admissions from Pennsylvania, New Jersey, and Delaware.</s><s xml:id="_GHjPJhf">Secondary outcomes included cardiovascular-related admissions or death; all-cause readmission, death, or observation stay; adherence to study devices; and alerts and responses to them.</s><s xml:id="_P9cmBYH">We performed sensitivity analyses by studying time to first patient event instead of analyzing repeated events per patient and additional outcomes including total number of days in the hospital.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_DwajBEF">Statistical Analysis</head><p xml:id="_xcpf3PR"><s xml:id="_SxMtP6h">The trial was designed to provide approximately 80% power, using a 2-sided significance level of .05, to detect a hazard ratio (HR) of 0.73 for the primary outcome (time to death or readmission for any cause).</s><s xml:id="_AeKctnk">Preliminary data indicated an expected primary event rate at 1 year of approximately 47% in the control group; thus, the trial had approximately 80% power to detect a reduction in the primary event rate of 10 percentage points, to 37% in the intervention group.</s><s xml:id="_efNSVsS">The primary hypothesis was tested with an unadjusted Andersen-Gill formulation of the standard Cox proportional hazards regression model to properly incorporate repeated events (ie, hospitalizations) within the same individual and account for their correlation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">20</ref></s><s xml:id="_dRZTgbz">In sensitivity analysis, we applied standard Cox proportional hazards regression models to estimate HRs for time to first event.</s><s xml:id="_AjdXxUn">We also reported models adjusted for selfreported race and ethnicity, age, body mass index, ejection fraction greater than or equal to 40%, and income, using backward elimination augmented with a standard change-inestimate criterion, successively removing the least significant variable (other than the trial arm) until all remaining variables are significant or they cause a change in the estimate of arm by more than 10%. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">21</ref></s><s xml:id="_9CjmyU6">o estimate total hospital days, we applied generalized linear models with a Poisson link function.</s><s xml:id="_sK245uM">We also assessed the likelihood of future events (readmission or death in the next 1, 2, or 4 weeks) as a function of earlier alerts using multivariate Cox proportional hazards regression models fitted on data from patients in the intervention group.</s><s xml:id="_qNC2r3E">To assess subgroup effects, we interacted arm and a dichotomized indicator for baseline risk factors of interest (eg, ejection fraction at least 35%).</s><s xml:id="_CVnBdpE">Analyses were performed with SAS, version 9.4 (SAS Institute Inc).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_6r9sqSZ">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_J83TmzJ">Study Population</head><p xml:id="_S7Cybfz"><s xml:id="_b2Qhxgb">A total of 566 patients were initially deemed eligible and randomly assigned (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>; eTable 1 in Supplement 2).</s><s xml:id="_5mHtVhR">Nine patients assigned to the intervention group and 5 patients assigned to the control group were removed from the study within 24 hours because new information revealed them to be ineligible clinically (eg, kidney function below threshold for inclusion) or administratively (eg, enrolled in a competing trial), or because they withdrew their consent immediately following randomization.</s><s xml:id="_MNs9hVD">Thus, 552 patients were allocated to the intervention (n = 272) or usual care (n = 280) cohorts.</s><s xml:id="_RfUUfRs">One patient assigned to the intervention group discontinued participation later in the study and contributed information up to that point.</s><s xml:id="_97DWey7">Patients' mean (SD) age was 64.5 (11.8) years; 262 were women (47.5%) and 290 were men (52.5%); 291 patients (52.7%) were Black, 231 were White (41.8%), and 30 patients reported other races or declined to provide information; 16 were Hispanic (2.9%).</s><s xml:id="_R3GjMUs">The mean (SD) ejection fraction was 43.0% 8759 Assessed for eligibility 8193 Excluded 7324 Did not meet inclusion criteria 482 Declined to participate 387 Other reasons 0 Lost to follow-up 1 Discontinued participation 272 Analyzed 0 Excluded from analysis 280 Analyzed 0 Excluded from analysis 0 Lost to follow-up 281 Randomized to intervention 272 Received allocated intervention 9 Did not receive allocated intervention 3 Found to be clinically ineligible 6 Found to be administratively ineligible 285 Randomized to control 280 Received allocated intervention 5 Did not receive allocated intervention 2 Found to be administratively ineligible 3 Discontinued participation immediately upon randomization 566 Randomized Remote Monitoring and Behavioral Economics in Managing Heart Failure in Patients Original Investigation Research jamainternalmedicine.com (Reprinted) JAMA Internal Medicine June 2022 Volume 182, Number 6</s></p><p xml:id="_zmvf7RE"><s xml:id="_4mrkJRA">(18.1%).</s><s xml:id="_ZewjmaT">There were no substantial differences in patient characteristics across the 2 arms (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_ZgN8B7T">Physicians with patients in the study had a mean (SD) of 3.1 (4.4) and a median of 2 patients in the study.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_2cjbC5B">Primary End Points</head><p xml:id="_dhS6K4W"><s xml:id="_g2qA5sV">There were 423 (230 related to cardiovascular causes) readmissions and 26 deaths in the control group and 377 (206 related to cardiovascular causes) readmissions and 23 deaths in the intervention groups; 178 patients in the control group (64%) and 171 patients in the intervention group (63%) had at least 1 event.</s><s xml:id="_Y4cTrZA">There was no significant difference between the 2 groups for the combined outcome of all-cause inpatient readmission or death (unadjusted HR, 0.91; 95% CI, 0.74-1.13;</s><s xml:id="_wQKnZdc">P = .40).</s><s xml:id="_uNysxDq">The results were essentially the same when observation admissions were included in the outcome, when only admissions for cardiovascular causes were included, and when analyses were adjusted for patient characteristics (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_QEeewcd">Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref> reveals no separation between the 2 groups in the cumulative incidence of the 2 components (mortality and readmission) of the primary outcome.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Nx8Tf44">Secondary End Points</head><p xml:id="_ufUPcQn"><s xml:id="_KyhFwpv">There were no statistically significant differences between the 2 groups in time-to-first-event only (all-cause inpatient readmission or death, all-cause inpatient observation stay or death, and cardiovascular-related inpatient readmission or death), and total all-cause deaths.</s><s xml:id="_buDAx3g">Patients in the intervention group were slightly more likely to spend fewer days in the hospital (HR, 0.94; 95% CI, 0.9-0.99)</s><s xml:id="_qjmKPFC">(Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_z5G2VxG">There were no significant differences in effects when comparing patients with preserved vs reduced ejection fractions (HR for interaction, 0.72; 95% CI, 0.46-1.11;</s><s xml:id="_fM7thvt">P = .13);</s><s xml:id="_f3ZQJZ9">results leaned toward greater effect for patients with preserved ejection fraction.</s><s xml:id="_CUWg4SK">Nor were there subgroup differences based on initial body mass index or on recruitment in the first half of the study vs the second.</s><s xml:id="_CDP2Rq8">Mean weight change since the start of the study assessed with weights collected similarly in intervention and control groups through routine care was 0 for both the intervention and control groups (eFigure 1 in Supplement 2).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_MemSuUb">Intervention Process Measures</head><p xml:id="_3aEd49Z"><s xml:id="_NzCGXtf">Adherence to medication or to weight measurement could be assessed only in the intervention group and ranged from approximately 80% at the start of the observation period to 60% toward the end (eFigure 2 in Supplement 2).</s><s xml:id="_6nrMpQH">Each month, approximately 75% of the participants were 80% adherent to both medication and weight measurement (eTable 2 in Supplement 2).</s><s xml:id="_rTtqeyt">Two hundred sixty intervention participants (95.6%) identified a support partner; 165 partners received alerts about nonadherence to medication or weight measurement (median, 8 alerts; IQR, 3-27).</s></p><p xml:id="_j3mxFch"><s xml:id="_pCR454D">Of the 261 patients in the intervention group who set up study devices, 237 generated 3736 EHR alerts to clinicians about weight change (median, 10; IQR, 3-21) and 85 alerts about nonadherence (median, 1; IQR, 1-2).</s><s xml:id="_W98aQcD">Essentially all alerts were opened, and 34.4% of weight change alerts were followed up by a physician response documented in the EHR; 259 alerts indicated chest pain or shortness of breath; 651 were associated with symptoms such as worsening of swelling, decreased appetite, nausea, or difficulty with medications; and 198 indicated other symptoms.</s><s xml:id="_DMnK6xd">The remainder of the participants either had no symptoms or were not reachable.</s><s xml:id="_GyUpCXn">Patients indicating chest pain or shortness of breath had a 1-week cardiovascular event rate of 6.95% compared with 0.50% among those generating alerts with no symptoms reported (eTable 3 in Supplement 2).</s></p><p xml:id="_PsZyRUW"><s xml:id="_Shpzk49">Compared with patients generating no alert, the riskadjusted HRs of all-cause readmission or death for those generating an alert were 2.95 (95% CI, 2.33-3.73;</s><s xml:id="_AYhx6YZ">P &lt; .001)</s><s xml:id="_RatfHBy">within 1 week, 3.66 (95% CI, 2.99-4.48;</s><s xml:id="_2QKs3fj">P &lt; .001)</s><s xml:id="_QQSRQC9">within 2 weeks, and</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Anx8fnB">Discussion</head><p xml:id="_u5Qnm7f"><s xml:id="_kyx2KJa">We aimed to reduce readmissions or death among patients discharged from the hospital after an admission for HF.</s><s xml:id="_EwVAbxV">We used a comprehensive intervention combining daily remote monitoring of weight and diuretic adherence, state-of-the-art behavioral economic techniques to encourage that monitoring, and low-friction ways to communicate potential patient problems to clinicians in the EHR.</s><s xml:id="_Qxf5k3D">The patients in the intervention group did no better than those receiving usual care.</s><s xml:id="_UmseEGK">Each of the components of the intervention was executed mostly as planned.</s><s xml:id="_hPeg9pP">Patients set up the remote monitoring devices.</s><s xml:id="_5sKw9Na">They largely maintained engagement, although that engagement decreased over 12 months.</s><s xml:id="_BZFjdKc">Alerts were read by monitoring clinicians, and a third of the alerts were responded to.</s><s xml:id="_4KWGhWY">No step along this pathway was executed perfectly, but this trial was pragmatic-testing a highly complex intervention in the context of usual care. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">22</ref></s><s xml:id="_3Q4DjnF">he results suggest that the combination of elements in this intervention when executed at this level of success was insufficient to alter these patients' trajectories.</s><s xml:id="_uT8JVSD">Perhaps trial enrollment and device set up occurred too late following the index discharge.</s><s xml:id="_a7tF5Pc">Many HF readmissions occur in the early days following discharge; although the timing of trial enrollment was the same in both arms, if earlier admissions would be differentially prevented by the intervention, an overall effect could have been missed.</s><s xml:id="_EmM2ckk">Maybe adherence to diuretics or weight reporting needed to be even higher.</s><s xml:id="_EenA72y">Patient adherence was associated with outcome (eTable 2 in Supplement 2), but these associations can be attributed to a healthy user effect in which adherence is not the cause of better outcomes but is instead a marker for health-promoting behaviors more directly on the causal pathway toward them. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">23</ref></s><s xml:id="_zgNzdUy">Nevertheless, the adherence seen in this study is lower than that previously associated with better HF outcomes. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">24</ref></s><s xml:id="_u4J6af7">Maybe the weight change thresholds were too insensitive.</s><s xml:id="_UvQnFFj">Perhaps clinicians responded to too few of the alerts, too late, or incorrectly.</s><s xml:id="_7kJkgBY">Or maybe the intervention was targeted at too broad a patient population-taking in, as it did, a generally unselected heterogeneous set of patients hospitalized with HF, whether with preserved or reduced ejection fraction.</s><s xml:id="_rgyCXtm">More generally, given that this study and another 12 revealed that many readmissions following discharge for HF are not related to HF (eTable 4 in Supplement 2), it is possible that interventions specifically targeted toward HF are too narrow.</s></p><p xml:id="_UA3Vwr7"><s xml:id="_ykGt22Y">We can speak to some of these issues.</s><s xml:id="_K5HHmDv">The alerts themselves were associated with increases in the events constituting our primary outcome.</s><s xml:id="_qbNbAVm">Although the generation of alerts is a postrandomization variable and such estimates can be subject to omitted variable bias, this finding is consistent with an earlier study suggesting that increasing weight is a risk factor for imminent HF hospitalization. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref></s><s xml:id="_9ad7Gdb">In addition, we found that adding alerts to the risk-adjusted model increased the model's discriminating power in predicting short-term events, so use of alerts as a component of a risk prediction algorithm may be warranted.</s><s xml:id="_E5WeSeP">These findings suggest that too few alerts may have prompted clinical responses.</s></p><p xml:id="_QUrKPvW"><s xml:id="_WNNnXuU">Most individual trials of structured telephone support have similarly not shown a benefit in outcomes; however, a Cochrane meta-analysis reported a significant reduction in HFrelated hospitalizations and all-cause mortality. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">25</ref></s><s xml:id="_q69USWy">Most HF centers, including ours, incorporate such structured telephone follow up after hospitalization, and it is possible that our intervention did not show a significant benefit given this and other interventions that are already in place, resulting in a low</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_SdNfXc3">Limitations and Strengths</head><p xml:id="_5FRcgu7"><s xml:id="_QQnJesV">This study has limitations.</s><s xml:id="_zTpH9qm">First, it was conducted in a single academic health system, although across 3 hospitals and among a diverse set of patients.</s><s xml:id="_a3eWYnv">Second, the participants were recruited and observed over a 4-year period when great effort was being introduced into usual care to reduce readmissions and improve guideline-directed medical care for HF.</s><s xml:id="_Akqyj7S">However, we found no differences in effect size for patients recruited earlier in the study compared with later.</s><s xml:id="_EExtj7U">This study also has strengths.</s><s xml:id="_F57VtbS">It was a pragmatic randomized clinical trial against usual care.</s><s xml:id="_xg7D8zE">It captured a relevant patient population at a time that could have plausibly made a difference.</s><s xml:id="_f8JsFdY">It used the study period's best available technology and clinical and behavioral insights and the execution of the logistic elements succeeded.</s><s xml:id="_GaSNzQG">The reporting of alerts and daily weights was streamlined, leveraging the EHR and simplifying workflows for clinicians.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_S7aaG4D">Conclusions</head><p xml:id="_FP6fWwE"><s xml:id="_fmgdezg">In this randomized clinical trial, we found no reduction in the combined outcome of readmission or mortality in this yearlong intensive remote monitoring program with incentives for patients previously hospitalized for HF.</s><s xml:id="_QFSK8wG">Success toward this goal may require earlier or deeper patient engagement or expanding engagement to encompass the many non-HF reasons that prompt readmissions of patients with HF.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_hzq53XW"><s xml:id="_DjgJKJu">Figure 1.</s><s xml:id="_FjCtCE5">Flow of Participants in the Electronic Monitoring of Patients Offers Ways to Enhance Recovery (EMPOWER) Randomized Clinical Trial</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_U9VX58g"><s xml:id="_MU938Vw">Participant Characteristics</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>No. (%)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Control</cell></row><row><cell>Characteristic</cell><cell>Intervention (n = 272)</cell><cell>(n = 280)</cell></row><row><cell>Days between index discharge</cell><cell>11.99 (7.37)</cell><cell>12.35 (7.57)</cell></row><row><cell>and enrollment, mean (SD)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Age, mean (SD), y</cell><cell>64.86 (12.39)</cell><cell>64.23 (11.21)</cell></row><row><cell>Sex</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell>139 (51.1)</cell><cell>123 (43.9)</cell></row><row><cell>Male</cell><cell>133 (48.9)</cell><cell>157 (56.1)</cell></row><row><cell>Race</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Black</cell><cell>151 (55.5)</cell><cell>140 (50.0)</cell></row><row><cell>White</cell><cell>112 (41.2)</cell><cell>119 (42.5)</cell></row><row><cell>Other or declined to report</cell><cell>9 (3.3)</cell><cell>21 (7.7)</cell></row><row><cell>Hispanic ethnicity</cell><cell>7 (2.8)</cell><cell>9 (3.2)</cell></row><row><cell>Self-reported annual income, $</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>0-20 000</cell><cell>61 (22.4)</cell><cell>81 (28.9)</cell></row><row><cell>&gt;20 000-40 000</cell><cell>38 (14.0)</cell><cell>41 (14.6)</cell></row><row><cell>&gt;40 000-60 000</cell><cell>27 (9.9)</cell><cell>23 (8.2)</cell></row><row><cell>&gt;60 000-80 000</cell><cell>17 (6.3)</cell><cell>23 (8.2)</cell></row><row><cell>≥80 000</cell><cell>26 (9.6)</cell><cell>29 (10.4)</cell></row><row><cell>Missing</cell><cell>103 (37.9)</cell><cell>83 (29.6)</cell></row><row><cell>Insurance</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Commercial</cell><cell>61 (22.4)</cell><cell>70 (25.0)</cell></row><row><cell>Medicaid</cell><cell>46 (16.9)</cell><cell>53 (18.9)</cell></row><row><cell>Medicare</cell><cell>164 (60.3)</cell><cell>157 (56.1)</cell></row><row><cell>Self-pay</cell><cell>1 (0.4)</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Body mass index</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>&lt;25</cell><cell>49 (18.0)</cell><cell>56 (20.0)</cell></row><row><cell>25-34.9</cell><cell>128 (47.1)</cell><cell>114 (40.7)</cell></row><row><cell>≥35</cell><cell>95 (34.9)</cell><cell>110 (39.3)</cell></row><row><cell>Ejection fraction</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean (SD)</cell><cell>42.43 (17.96)</cell><cell>43.95 (18.16)</cell></row><row><cell>≥40%</cell><cell>153 (56.3)</cell><cell>166 (59.3)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">No. of comorbidities, mean (SD) 4 (1.9)</cell><cell>4 (2.1)</cell></row><row><cell>Most prevalent comorbidities a</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Hypertension</cell><cell>123 (49.8)</cell><cell>122 (48.8)</cell></row><row><cell>Diabetes</cell><cell>112 (45.3)</cell><cell>133 (53.2)</cell></row><row><cell>Valvular disease</cell><cell>95 (38.5)</cell><cell>102 (40.8)</cell></row><row><cell>Chronic kidney disease</cell><cell>96 (38.9)</cell><cell>89 (35.6)</cell></row><row><cell>Obesity</cell><cell>87 (35.2)</cell><cell>97 (38.8)</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">a Because of missing data for comorbidities, intervention estimates are based</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">on n = 247 and control estimates are based on n = 250.</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_XXYvF6n"><s xml:id="_Hzz3ybu">Estimated HRs Comparing Intervention With Control Group for Primary and Secondary Outcomes</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>All-cause</cell></row><row><cell>HR type</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_fm3P74z"><s xml:id="_wwXscwT">Estimated HRs Comparing Intervention With Control Group for Additional Outcomes Cleland JG, Louis AA, Rigby AS, et al; TEN-HMS Investigators.</s><s xml:id="_AcuJNsz">Noninvasive home telemonitoring for patients with heart failure at high risk of recurrent admission and death: the Trans-European Network-Home-Care Management System (TEN-HMS) study.</s><s xml:id="_thQJwVY">J Am Coll Cardiol.</s><s xml:id="_QNTfhwf">2005;45(10): 1654-1664.</s><s xml:id="_ZHnsH6d">doi:10.1016/j.jacc.2005.01.050 10.</s><s xml:id="_CsDPzW3">Ong MK, Romano PS, Edgington S, et al; Better Effectiveness After Transition-Heart Failure (BEAT-HF) Research Group.</s><s xml:id="_jhAhKRt">Effectiveness of remote patient monitoring after discharge of hospitalized patients with heart failure: the Better Effectiveness After Transition-Heart Failure (BEAT-HF) randomized clinical trial.</s><s xml:id="_hmMap5S">JAMA Intern Med.</s><s xml:id="_r97qdGf">2016;176(3):310-318. doi:10.1001/jamainternmed. 2015.7712</s><s xml:id="_637tsTh">11.</s><s xml:id="_5JxjXTk">Loewenstein G, Asch DA, Friedman JY, Melichar LA, Volpp KG.</s><s xml:id="_KNJA3Dn">Can behavioural economics make us healthier?</s><s xml:id="_TEufqrr">BMJ.</s><s xml:id="_W7nzVR9">2012;344:e3482.</s><s xml:id="_Pv3Wfvb">doi:10.1136/bmj.</s><s xml:id="_eNsK2sa">e3482 12. Volpp KG, John LK, Troxel AB, Norton L, Fassbender J, Loewenstein G. Financial incentive-based approaches for weight loss: a randomized trial.</s><s xml:id="_C8Q4gHb">JAMA.</s><s xml:id="_f6jbnbz">2008;300(22):2631-2637. doi:10.1001/jama.2008.804</s><s xml:id="_aVRkh73">13.</s><s xml:id="_9sjVX4p">Mehta SJ, Volpp KG, Asch DA, et al.</s><s xml:id="_RgfyY5m">Rationale and design of EMPOWER, a pragmatic randomized trial of automated hovering in patients with congestive heart failure.</s><s xml:id="_3EC3HeV">Circ Cardiovasc Qual Outcomes.</s><s xml:id="_tXUaZAF">2019;12(4):e005126.</s><s xml:id="_K5mBETm">doi:10.1161/</s><s xml:id="_hsBeCMw">CIRCOUTCOMES.118.005126</s><s xml:id="_mfp4xP2">14. Yancy CW, Januzzi JL Jr, Allen LA, et al. 2017 ACC Expert consensus decision pathway for optimization of heart failure treatment: answers to 10 pivotal issues about heart failure with reduced ejection fraction: a report of the American College of Cardiology Task Force on Expert Consensus Decision Pathways.</s><s xml:id="_ztnYaRX">J Am Coll Cardiol.</s><s xml:id="_5tkDkgW">2018;71(2): 201-230.</s><s xml:id="_DEmUsGK">doi:10.1016/j.jacc.2017.11.025 15.</s><s xml:id="_zqVAtzp">Chaiyachati KH, Roy J, Asch DA, et al.</s><s xml:id="_K9vHD2t">Improving longitudinal survey participation among internal medicine residents: incorporating behavioral economic techniques and avoiding Friday or Saturday invitations.</s><s xml:id="_w7Wtxnh">J Gen Intern Med.</s><s xml:id="_S7hFMrp">2019;34(6): 823-824.</s><s xml:id="_XbwQFTk">doi:10.1007/s11606-019-04836-8</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">First inpatient (all-cause)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">First cardiovascular</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Readmission, observation</cell><cell>inpatient</cell><cell></cell><cell>Total No. days</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Readmission, death</cell><cell>stay, death</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">readmission and death</cell><cell>in hospital</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Death (all-cause) a</cell></row><row><cell>HR type</cell><cell>HR (95% CI)</cell><cell>P value</cell><cell>HR (95% CI)</cell><cell>P value</cell><cell>HR (95% CI)</cell><cell>P value</cell><cell>Days (95% CI)</cell><cell>P value</cell><cell>HR (95% CI)</cell><cell>P value</cell></row><row><cell>Unadjusted</cell><cell>0.95</cell><cell>.62</cell><cell>1.02</cell><cell>.73</cell><cell>0.98</cell><cell>.89</cell><cell>0.94</cell><cell>.02</cell><cell>1.14</cell><cell>.62</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.77-1.17)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.9-1.16)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.77-1.25)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.9-0.99)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.68-1.9)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Adjusted</cell><cell>0.94</cell><cell>.57</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell>.93</cell><cell>0.97</cell><cell>.81</cell><cell>0.95</cell><cell>.09</cell><cell>1.11</cell><cell>.69</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.75-1.17)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.88-1.15)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.76-1.24)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.9-1)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.66-1.88)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Abbreviation: HR, hazard ratio.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="5">a In all time to first-event studies, death was counted as a censoring event.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p xml:id="_Nzk5zcB"><s xml:id="_zRSnyyJ">JAMA Internal Medicine June 2022 Volume 182, Number 6 (Reprinted) jamainternalmedicine.com Downloaded from jamanetwork.com</s><s xml:id="_9eWRfM3">by guest on 07/28/2025</s></p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p xml:id="_aYDA3xq"><s xml:id="_XPgG5tN">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com</s><s xml:id="_wDTbh4W">by guest on 07/28/2025</s></p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_tjQBazY"><p xml:id="_rvyk65D"><s xml:id="_tPnQkG3">Role of the Funder/Sponsor: The funding organization had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_yDdxW3J">Data Sharing</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_F8q9ySt">Adherence to candesartan and placebo and outcomes in chronic heart failure in the CHARM programme: double-blind, randomised, controlled clinical trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Granger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Swedberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ekman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0140-6736(05)67760-4</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_uR7EQGT">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">366</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2005" to="2011" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005. 9502</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Granger BB, Swedberg K, Ekman I, et al; CHARM investigators. Adherence to candesartan and placebo and outcomes in chronic heart failure in the CHARM programme: double-blind, randomised, controlled clinical trial. Lancet. 2005;366(9502): 2005-2011. doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(05)67760-4</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_vN5SNcc">Impact of medication nonadherence on hospitalizations and mortality in heart failure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fitzgerald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Powers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cardfail.2011.04.011</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_3Yms94h">J Card Fail</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="664" to="669" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Fitzgerald AA, Powers JD, Ho PM, et al. Impact of medication nonadherence on hospitalizations and mortality in heart failure. J Card Fail. 2011;17(8): 664-669. doi:10.1016/j.cardfail.2011.04.011</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_AdzSMPa">Objectively measured, but not self-reported, medication adherence independently predicts event-free survival in patients with heart failure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Moser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lennie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cardfail.2007.11.005</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_d7t2fwD">J Card Fail</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="210" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Wu JR, Moser DK, Chung ML, Lennie TA. Objectively measured, but not self-reported, medication adherence independently predicts event-free survival in patients with heart failure. J Card Fail. 2008;14(3):203-210. doi:10.1016/ j.cardfail.2007.11.005</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_5wgYePT">Patterns of weight change preceding hospitalization for heart failure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Chaudhry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Concato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Krumholz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1161/circulationaha.107.690768</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_J4SaHwD">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1549" to="1554" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Chaudhry SI, Wang Y, Concato J, Gill TM, Krumholz HM. Patterns of weight change preceding hospitalization for heart failure. Circulation. 2007; 116(14):1549-1554. doi:10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.107. 690768</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_NWmDqAj">Self-management counseling in patients with heart failure: the Heart Failure Adherence and Retention randomized behavioral trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Powell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Calvin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Richardson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1001/jama.2010.1362?utm_campaign=articlePDF%26utm_medium=articlePDFlink%26utm_source=articlePDF%26utm_content=jamainternmed.2022.1383</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_7ZBYYKK">JAMA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">304</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1331" to="1338" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Powell LH, Calvin JE Jr, Richardson D, et al; HART Investigators. Self-management counseling in patients with heart failure: the Heart Failure Adherence and Retention randomized behavioral trial. JAMA. 2010;304(12):1331-1338. doi:10.1001/ jama.2010.1362</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_6UFzJGd">Modeling lottery incentives for daily adherence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Humphrey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Small</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/sim.8149</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_6qf3vg7">Stat Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2847" to="2867" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Humphrey CH, Small DS, Jensen ST, et al. Modeling lottery incentives for daily adherence. Stat Med. 2019;38(15):2847-2867. doi:10.1002/sim. 8149</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Y9eQyTk">Patient and partner feedback reports to improve statin medication adherence: a randomized control trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Reddy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Huseman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Canamucio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11606-016-3858-0</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_t2PVx5d">J Gen Intern Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="256" to="261" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Reddy A, Huseman TL, Canamucio A, et al. Patient and partner feedback reports to improve statin medication adherence: a randomized control trial. J Gen Intern Med. 2017;32(3):256-261. doi:10.1007/s11606-016-3858-0</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_pK3pd8u">Partners and alerts in medication adherence: a randomized clinical trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kessler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Troxel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Asch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11606-018-4389-7</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_aCT2uPW">J Gen Intern Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1536" to="1542" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kessler JB, Troxel AB, Asch DA, et al. Partners and alerts in medication adherence: a randomized clinical trial. J Gen Intern Med. 2018;33(9):1536-1542. doi:10.1007/s11606-018-4389-7</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_J9ctDNH">Cox&apos;s regression model for counting processes: a large sample study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Andersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Gill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1214/aos/1176345976</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_4HKUpDa">Ann Stat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1100" to="1120" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Andersen PK, Gill RD. Cox&apos;s regression model for counting processes: a large sample study. Ann Stat. 1982;10:1100-1120. doi:10.1214/aos/1176345976</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_kyfFmgr">Modeling Survival Data: Extending the Cox Model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Therneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Grambsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-1-4757-3294-8</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Therneau TM, Grambsch PM. Modeling Survival Data: Extending the Cox Model. Springer-Verlag; 2000. doi:10.1007/978-1-4757-3294-8</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_3a3jAS2">Statistical foundations for model-based adjustments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Greenland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Pearce</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1146/annurev-publhealth-031914-122559</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_VbPJTa6">Annu Rev Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="89" to="108" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Greenland S, Pearce N. Statistical foundations for model-based adjustments. Annu Rev Public Health. 2015;36:89-108. doi:10.1146/annurev- publhealth-031914-122559</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_WQfayn3">Diagnoses and timing of 30-day readmissions after hospitalization for heart failure, acute myocardial infarction, or pneumonia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Dharmarajan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hsieh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1001/jama.2012.216476?utm_campaign=articlePDF%26utm_medium=articlePDFlink%26utm_source=articlePDF%26utm_content=jamainternmed.2022.1383</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ZRV7wDu">JAMA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">309</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="355" to="363" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Dharmarajan K, Hsieh AF, Lin Z, et al. Diagnoses and timing of 30-day readmissions after hospitalization for heart failure, acute myocardial infarction, or pneumonia. JAMA. 2013;309(4):355- 363. doi:10.1001/jama.2012.216476</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_s2Aqrmf">A meta-analysis of the association between adherence to drug therapy and mortality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Simpson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Eurich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Majumdar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmj.38875.675486.55</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_BEKfB2z">BMJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">333</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7557</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Simpson SH, Eurich DT, Majumdar SR, et al. A meta-analysis of the association between adherence to drug therapy and mortality. BMJ. 2006;333(7557):15. doi:10.1136/bmj.38875. 675486.55</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_UBuTr3B">Defining an evidence-based cutpoint for medication adherence in heart failure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Moser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">De</forename><surname>Jong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ahj.2008.10.001</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_tMN72Gz">Am Heart J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">157</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="285" to="291" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Wu JR, Moser DK, De Jong MJ, et al. Defining an evidence-based cutpoint for medication adherence in heart failure. Am Heart J. 2009;157(2): 285-291. doi:10.1016/j.ahj.2008.10.001</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_2Yg7ET9">Structured telephone support or non-invasive telemonitoring for patients with heart failure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Inglis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Dierckx</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Prieto-Merino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Cleland</forename><forename type="middle">Jg</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/14651858.cd007228.pub3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_EYkSsYW">Cochrane Database Syst Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">7228</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Inglis SC, Clark RA, Dierckx R, Prieto-Merino D, Cleland JG. Structured telephone support or non-invasive telemonitoring for patients with heart failure. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2015;(10): CD007228. doi:10.1002/14651858.CD007228.pub3</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_6AZPRpF">Telemedical Interventional Monitoring in Heart Failure Investigators. Impact of remote telemedical management on mortality and hospitalizations in ambulatory patients with chronic heart failure: the Telemedical Interventional Monitoring in Heart Failure Study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Koehler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Winkler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schieber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1161/circulationaha.111.018473</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_qgWDEvP">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">123</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1873" to="1880" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Koehler F, Winkler S, Schieber M, et al; Telemedical Interventional Monitoring in Heart Failure Investigators. Impact of remote telemedical management on mortality and hospitalizations in ambulatory patients with chronic heart failure: the Telemedical Interventional Monitoring in Heart Failure Study. Circulation. 2011;123(17):1873-1880. doi:10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.111.018473</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_VX8ScYA">Efficacy of telemedical interventional management in patients with heart failure (TIM-HF2): a randomised, controlled, parallel-group, unmasked trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Koehler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Koehler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Deckwart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0140-6736(18)31880-4</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_AFKHF9G">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">392</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10152</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1047" to="1057" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Koehler F, Koehler K, Deckwart O, et al. Efficacy of telemedical interventional management in patients with heart failure (TIM-HF2): a randomised, controlled, parallel-group, unmasked trial. Lancet. 2018;392(10152):1047-1057. doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(18)31880-4</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
