<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_XMttfPg">Looking on the Bright Side: Accessing Benign Meanings Reduces Worry</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Medical Research Council</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">MRC</orgName>
					<idno type="DOI" subtype="crossref">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100000265</idno>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>PO77</roleName><forename type="first">Colette</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hirsch</surname></persName>
							<email>colette.hirsch@iop.kcl.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Institute of Psychiatry , King&apos;s College London , and University of Western Australia</note>
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Psychiatry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">King&apos;s College London</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Western</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Department of Psychology , University of Western Australia , Perth , Australia;</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Western Australia</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Perth</settlement>
									<country>Australia;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Department of Psychology , University of California , Davis.</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Davis</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sarra</forename><surname>Hayes</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Institute of Psychiatry , King&apos;s College London University of California , Davis</note>
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Psychiatry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">King&apos;s College London</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Davis</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Department of Psychology , Institute of Psychiatry , King&apos;s College London ; Andrew Mathews ,</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute of Psychiatry</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Andrew</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">King&apos;s College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Mathews</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><surname>Mathews</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Department of Psychology , Institute of Psychiatry , King&apos;s College London , United Kingdom , and</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute of Psychiatry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">King&apos;s College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>AND MATHEWS</roleName><forename type="first">Hayes</forename><surname>Hirsch</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Institute of Psychiatry , De Crespigny Park , London SE5 8AF , United Kingdom.</note>
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Psychiatry</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>De Crespigny Park</addrLine>
									<postCode>SE5 8AF</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_f3mr7pY">Looking on the Bright Side: Accessing Benign Meanings Reduces Worry</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">BD328355E665388CA313FE7057F9BB44</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1037/a0013473</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received July 30, 2007 Revision received April 14, 2008 Accepted June 18, 2008 Ⅲ 54</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T13:35+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term xml:id="_U2vGc3Q">worry</term>
					<term xml:id="_pHYz2W6">anxiety</term>
					<term xml:id="_wzNZpHJ">cognitive bias modification</term>
					<term xml:id="_wjvu8ca">interpretation</term>
					<term xml:id="_bRBd9Hw">working memory</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_UU3PEuR"><p xml:id="_3u8usBX"><s xml:id="_czTPwCd">This research investigated whether increasing access to benign outcomes of ambiguous events decreases excessive worry.</s><s xml:id="_zePuExT">Participants reporting high levels of worry were assigned either to practice in accessing benign meanings of threat-related homographs and emotionally ambiguous scenarios or to a control condition in which threatening or benign meanings were accessed with equal frequency.</s><s xml:id="_ZhGVbW9">Results were assessed by use of a breathing focus task that involved categorizing the valence of thought intrusions before and after an instructed worry period and a test of working memory capacity available to participants while worrying.</s><s xml:id="_dBRXcK8">In comparison with the control group, the benign group reported fewer negative thought intrusions (as rated by both participants and an assessor) and less anxiety during the breathing focus task and showed greater residual working memory capacity while worrying.</s><s xml:id="_8QHupqY">These findings suggest that enhancing access to benign outcomes is an effective method of reducing both the persistence of worry and its detrimental consequences.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="594.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="594.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="594.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="594.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="594.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="594.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="594.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="594.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="594.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="10" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="594.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="11" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="594.0" lry="792.0"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_5WndAZJ"><p xml:id="_4vb2uvM"><s xml:id="_Jr9a2gs">Worry is a primary cognitive characteristic of anxiety and has been described as "a chain of thoughts and images, negatively affect-laden and relatively uncontrollable" <ref type="bibr">(Borkovec, Robinson, Pruzinsky, &amp; Depree, 1983, p. 10)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_RMkhSgP">Worry typically concerns future events whose outcomes are uncertain but that contain the possibility of one or more negative outcomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Sibrava &amp; Borkovec, 2006)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_VdHw4zW">Although reported proneness to worry varies continuously across the population, those diagnosed with generalized anxiety disorder (GAD) report particularly high levels of worry about many different topics, unlike the more specific content characteristic of the worries of those with other anxiety disorders.</s><s xml:id="_gquykAr">Indeed, the defining feature of GAD, based on the criteria set forth in the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (4th ed.; DSM-IV; American Psychiatric <ref type="bibr">Association, 1994)</ref>, is chronic, excessive, and uncontrollable worry about multiple topics.</s><s xml:id="_9g4CgJD">Individuals with GAD and high levels of worry are distinguished from those who do not experience high levels of worry by their reported inability to control worry once it is initiated <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Borkovec et al., 1983)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_GzEteWY">For example, following instructions to worry about a current personally relevant topic, all participants reported more negative thought intrusions during a subsequent attention-focusing task.</s><s xml:id="_uSAg8g5">However, those who worried excessively, or those who met criteria for GAD, experienced a greater frequency of negative thought intrusions than did nonworriers <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Borkovec et al., 1983)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_XmkSGn2"><s xml:id="_4XVhCc9">The question remains of why individuals prone to worry find it so difficult to disengage from worry.</s><s xml:id="_BbAGwPc">Although anticipation of probable danger is adaptive, it is unclear why excessive worry persists when it causes frequent mental distress with few apparent benefits.</s><s xml:id="_pdZQhsD">Some research has suggested that individuals who worry excessively believe that they must continue to worry until uncertainty has been resolved <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Dugas, Gagnon, Ladouceur, &amp; Freeston, 1998)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_46Rdm32">Other researchers (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Davey, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Ruscio &amp; Borkovec, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Wells, 1995)</ref> have found that excessive worriers often endorse certain advantages for worry (e.g., that worry helps them to solve problems), despite also endorsing negative beliefs (e.g., that worry may be harmful to health).</s><s xml:id="_Up7xGqy">In a similar vein, both positive and negative beliefs about worry have been found to be elevated in individuals with GAD <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Borkovec &amp; Roemer, 1995)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_wQ9Typp">Such counterproductive beliefs regarding uncontrollability and possible benefits of worry are likely to undermine the motivation for individuals to stop worrying and thus may play a role in maintaining worry in GAD <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Wells, 1995)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_6FkTXZH"><s xml:id="_ZT54CSA">A further possibility is that such reported beliefs are secondary to more basic cognitive processes, such as cognitive biases in attention and interpretation.</s><s xml:id="_rBep6bg">Relative to nonanxious individuals, those with GAD or high levels of trait anxiety display a bias to attend to threat information (cf.</s><s xml:id="_qDR2NQG"><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Mathews &amp; MacLeod, 1994)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_QAWzk6U">Evidence for this conclusion derives mainly from experiments on attention to external threat cues (e.g., MacLeod, <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Mathews, &amp; Tata, 1986)</ref>, but there is no reason to suppose that such a bias would not equally apply to internal cognitive representations of threat, such as worrisome thoughts.</s></p><p xml:id="_g8EXSkP"><s xml:id="_qRGMyRn">In a similar light, although nonanxious individuals tend to make benign inferences about emotionally ambiguous information <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Hirsch &amp; Mathews, 1997</ref><ref type="bibr">, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Hirsch, Mathews, Clark, Williams, &amp; Morrison, 2003)</ref>, this presumably protective tendency is less evident in high trait anxious individuals, who tend to interpret emotionally ambiguous information in a more threatening manner <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(MacLeod &amp; Cohen, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Richards &amp; French, 1992)</ref>, as do those meeting diagnostic criteria for GAD <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Eysenck, MacLeod, &amp; Mathews, 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Eysenck, Mogg, May, Richards, &amp; Mathews, 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Mathews, Richards, &amp; Eysenck, 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Mogg, Bradley, Miller, &amp; Potts, 1994)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_YqPrpda">Both biased attention and the tendency to interpret ambiguous information in a threatening manner are likely to enhance the perception of threat, perhaps triggering or maintaining negative thoughts and worry <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Mathews, 1990)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_UW7A54V"><s xml:id="_MsXYq6a">A further cognitive characteristic of anxiety is a reduction in available working memory capacity, sometimes thought to be due to worry taking up working memory capacity (cf.</s><s xml:id="_ZZA76tj"><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Eysenck, 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Eysenck &amp; Calvo, 1992)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_FAHUexs">According to the model proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Baddeley and Hitch (1974;</ref><ref type="bibr"></ref> and later revised by <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Baddeley, 1986)</ref>, working memory is a limited-capacity cognitive resource required when one performs, and switches between, different cognitive tasks.</s><s xml:id="_sbehxGu">Recent research <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Hayes, Hirsch, &amp; Mathews, 2008)</ref> has demonstrated that high worriers have less residual working memory capacity (as shown by poorer performance on a random key-press task) when worrying than do low worriers.</s><s xml:id="_ExYZXZS">Given this, the interesting possibility is raised that an additional reason that worriers find it difficult to disengage from worry might be that they have less working memory capacity available to voluntarily switch their thoughts to nonworry topics.</s></p><p xml:id="_FzkZkwF"><s xml:id="_ddXy6VG">If cognitive biases such as interpretation do indeed play a role in maintaining negative thought content, then worry might be reduced by enhancing access to benign outcomes of ambiguous information, thus countering the bias maintaining negative content.</s><s xml:id="_rdwnP98">In fact, repeated practice in accessing different meanings of emotionally ambiguous material has been found to influence anxiety reactions to subsequent stressful situations.</s><s xml:id="_T94KysT">For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Wilson, MacLeod, Mathews, and Rutherford (2006)</ref> found that participants who repeatedly practiced accessing benign meanings of homographs showed less anxiety when they later watched distressing video clips than did those who received practice accessing threatening interpretations.</s><s xml:id="_XgfG3fF">In a similar vein, <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Hirsch, Mathews, and Clark (2007)</ref> found that repeated practice in accessing benign outcomes of ambiguous scenarios resulted in less anticipatory anxiety and more positive predicted performance in a stressful social situation compared to the outcome for those who practiced accessing threatening interpretations.</s></p><p xml:id="_rShBkTk"><s xml:id="_sJD6NKU">Because the research described above was conducted with nonanxious populations, the question remains whether repeated access to benign meanings reduces anxiety in high trait anxious individuals.</s><s xml:id="_DSzj2b3"><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Murphy, Hirsch, Mathews, Smith, and Clark (2007)</ref> reported that high socially anxious individuals who were given repeated practice accessing benign outcomes of ambiguous social scenarios showed less anticipatory anxiety about a socially threatening event than did those who did not have the ambiguity resolved.</s><s xml:id="_6frMWtu"><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Mathews, Ridgeway, Cook, and Yiend (2007)</ref> also demonstrated that repeated practice in accessing benign meanings of ambiguous scenarios reduced trait scores in a high trait anxious group to a greater extent than in a control group who did not practice accessing valenced meanings.</s></p><p xml:id="_Wtg8CBh"><s xml:id="_CQZMuD6">The present study was designed to investigate whether related methods might reduce worry frequency in volunteers (university staff and students) reporting excessive worry.</s><s xml:id="_bhhYwg3">It was expected that practice in accessing benign meanings of emotionally ambiguous information related to worry would reduce the availability or intensity of incompatible negative meanings.</s><s xml:id="_4m98WxS">Hence, this would result in fewer negative thought intrusions when focusing on a nonworry task along with correspondingly lower levels of anxiety in comparison with a control condition.</s><s xml:id="_CwFdkNp">We also hypothesized that if practice in accessing benign meanings of ambiguously threatening information reduced the impact of negative thoughts, this would lead to more residual working memory capacity being available.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_8hjfPGG">Method</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_2JCWH5Z">Design</head><p xml:id="_83rNh4d"><s xml:id="_3kXySHN">The experiment involved three phases: an initial phase designed to enhance access to benign rather than threatening meanings of ambiguous events (ambiguity tasks), a worry assessment phase (breathing focus task), and a working memory assessment phase.</s><s xml:id="_8hWQHVa">High worry volunteers were randomly allocated to a benign or control condition.</s><s xml:id="_XBtFr2F">The benign group consistently accessed benign meanings of threat-related homographs and ambiguously threatening scenarios, whereas the control group accessed threatening or benign meanings of similar material with equal frequency.</s><s xml:id="_GSr5wP5">Following completion of a filler task, participants completed the breathing focus task, which involved focusing on their breathing and categorizing the valence of thought intrusions before and after an instructed worry period.</s><s xml:id="_n5aPbPw">Participants subsequently provided expanded descriptions of these thought intrusions to allow an assessor to categorize their valence.</s><s xml:id="_xkJYmqQ">Finally, participants completed a task to assess the amount of working memory capacity available while they were worrying.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_VETaNny">Participants</head><p xml:id="_aDTCTYj"><s xml:id="_5D4ySJW">Participants were staff and students from King's College London who had responded to an e-mail request for high worriers.</s><s xml:id="_tYRhz3Q">Volunteers initially completed the Penn State Worry Questionnaire (PSWQ; <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Meyer, Miller, Metzger, &amp; Borkovec, 1990)</ref> and were invited to take part in the study if they had a score of 56 or above.</s><s xml:id="_HxexfDY">All participants completed the PSWQ again during the experiment to ensure that they continued to meet this criterion, and 2 volunteers were consequently excluded.</s><s xml:id="_4CnAB4n">Forty volunteers were randomly allocated to the benign or control conditions.</s><s xml:id="_c2DnpYx">Of these, 11 in the benign group met criteria for GAD (as assessed with the Generalized Anxiety Disorder Questionnaire; <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Newman et al., 2002)</ref>, as did 10 in the control group.</s><s xml:id="_pcxnGKx">Groups did not differ in terms of scores on the PSWQ (M ϭ 65.40, SD ϭ 7.60 for the benign group and M ϭ 65.80, SD ϭ 6.79 for the control group), t Ͻ 1, or the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory Trait version (STAI-T; <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Spielberger, Gorsuch, Lushene, Vagg, &amp; Jacobs, 1983</ref>; M ϭ 51.80, SD ϭ 11.65 for the benign group and M ϭ 55.00, SD ϭ 8.28 for the control group), t(38) ϭ 1.00, ns.</s><s xml:id="_9j3PW3g">Both groups consisted of 4 male and 16 female participants.</s><s xml:id="_cvyNM22">Average age was 34.9 years (SD ϭ 13.3) in the benign group and 36.4 years (SDϭ13.8) in the control group, with no significant difference between groups, t Ͻ 1.</s><s xml:id="_QVEYzAE">The average years of education was 14.8 years (SD ϭ 1.9) in the benign group and 14.9 years (SD ϭ 2.1) in the control group, with no significant difference between groups, t Ͻ 1.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_aFJrh6e">Materials Emotional Assessment Instruments</head><p xml:id="_rjH8PtA"><s xml:id="_DngwJcK">Penn State Worry Questionnaire (PSWQ).</s><s xml:id="_92xm5Bc">Trait worry level was measured using the PSWQ <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Meyer et al., 1990)</ref>, a 16-item measure consisting of statements about worry (e.g., "Once I start worrying, I can't stop").</s><s xml:id="_5A6gdtq">The PSWQ has a 5-point answer scale ranging from 1 (not at all typical of me) to 5 (very typical of me).</s><s xml:id="_zt3z35H">Positive items are reverse scored and item scores are summed to form a total score ranging from 16 to 80, with higher scores indicating greater worry levels.</s><s xml:id="_fX3z787">The PSWQ has good psychometric properties in student, community, and clinical samples, with studies reporting high internal consistency, short-term retest reliability, and convergent and criterion-related validity <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Brown, Antony, &amp; Barlow, 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Davey, 1993)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_s9VzHH8">Prior research with college samples <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Molina &amp; Borkovec, 1994)</ref> found a PSWQ score of 56 to fall one standard deviation below the mean of individuals diagnosed with GAD by the Anxiety Disorders Interview Schedule for DSM-IV (ADIS-IV; <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Brown, Di Nardo, &amp; Barlow, 1994)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_p5MYQJQ">Participants in the present study were classified as being high worriers if they scored 56 or above on the PSWQ.</s></p><p xml:id="_qPHnpYr"><s xml:id="_Qu2FYKc">Generalized Anxiety Disorder Questionnaire (GAD-Q-IV).</s><s xml:id="_X7bYt2z">The GAD-Q-IV <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Newman et al., 2002)</ref> is a self-report diagnostic measure of GAD.</s><s xml:id="_J9XeGtQ">This measure has demonstrated good test-retest reliability, convergent and discriminant validity, and a high level of diagnostic agreement with the ADIS-IV.</s><s xml:id="_xgCDdXd">The GAD-Q-IV is scored following the DSM-IV criteria for GAD, and individuals meeting all of the criteria are viewed as meeting diagnosis for GAD.</s></p><p xml:id="_ADjVQ2j"><s xml:id="_DY5swhe">State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI-T).</s><s xml:id="_JJntrgH">Trait anxiety was measured using the STAI-T <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Spielberger et al., 1983)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_wK66uef">It consists of 20 statements describing anxiety symptoms that participants rate for frequency of occurrence.</s><s xml:id="_2j4YpAa">Scores range between 20 and 80, with a higher score indicating greater anxiety.</s><s xml:id="_6U2qvpS">The STAI-T has good internal consistency (.89) and test-retest reliability (.88; <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Barnes, Harp, &amp; Jung, 2002)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_mM4Pk9N"><s xml:id="_A3dgUUx">Mood ratings.</s><s xml:id="_apHMcNE">Three visual analogue mood rating scales, each 100 mm in length, assessed the extent of anxiety, depression, and happiness in participants through the use of a scale labeled not at all at one end and extremely at the other.</s><s xml:id="_GzVRvTz">Participants indicated their current mood by placing a cross (x) on each scale.</s><s xml:id="_MZfjK4X">Mood was measured with a millimeter ruler according to the position of the cross placed on each scale, with scores ranging from 0 (not at all) to 100 (extremely).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_SvD5ekr">Ambiguity Tasks</head><p xml:id="_hHmV8dR"><s xml:id="_VxtbZFP">Homograph task.</s><s xml:id="_Cvhgbsm">A set of 200 word pairs used by <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Grey and Mathews (2000)</ref> were presented in the homograph task.</s><s xml:id="_MT3FvXh">This set comprised 100 cue words: 80 homographs with threat or nonthreat meanings and 20 nonhomograph fillers.</s><s xml:id="_NnZrfuE">Each cue word homograph (e.g., sack) has two word associates linked to the threat meaning of the homograph (e.g., job; dismiss) and two linked to the nonthreat meaning (e.g., potatoes; bag).</s><s xml:id="_zz2mxSV">Each cue word was presented twice, each time with a different associated word in fragment form (a word in which one letter is missing, e.g., d_smiss).</s><s xml:id="_KdftTHr">Homographs were consistently paired with threat-or nonthreat-associated word fragments (depending on assigned condition), whereas nonhomograph fillers were paired with neutral word associates.</s></p><p xml:id="_83GtCZa"><s xml:id="_DVk98rK">In keeping with <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Grey and Mathews (2000;</ref><ref type="bibr"></ref> Experiments 1 &amp; 2), on each trial a fixation cross appeared in the center of the screen for 1,000 ms, and then a blank screen appeared for 500 ms.</s><s xml:id="_2RDxQrv">Next, a single cue word appeared in the location of the fixation cross in yellow (e.g., throttle).</s><s xml:id="_8DHwK9d">Later (after 750 ms), a white word fragment (e.g., br_ke) appeared 5 cm below the location of the cue word (which remained on screen) with an underscored gap indicating the position of the missing letter.</s><s xml:id="_6rmCQV5">Participants were instructed to use the cue to help them find a word that was related in meaning to the cue and that matched the fragment and to press the space bar as soon as they knew what the word was.</s><s xml:id="_xGzqJ4Q">On detecting a response (or after 10 s if no response was detected), the computer produced a message prompting participants to press the key corresponding to the missing letter.</s><s xml:id="_KM4CGbG">When participants typed a letter (or after 6 s if no key was pressed), a feedback message was displayed for 1,000 ms.</s><s xml:id="_DyQwTf9">Once a correct response was detected, the completed word associate appeared on the screen along with the homograph.</s><s xml:id="_MZVRC3u">If an error was detected, the correct word associate appeared in red below the homograph, along with a short tone to signal an error.</s><s xml:id="_Q73bykt">If no response was detected, a "no response detected" message appeared, and the next trial commenced.</s></p><p xml:id="_YbAcU9k"><s xml:id="_JXEqeCq">The benign group was consistently given benign meanings of threat-related homographs, while the control group was presented with the threatening meaning 50% of the time and the benign meaning 50% of the time.</s><s xml:id="_VSa7BEB">All participants received the same word associates for nonhomograph filler cues.</s><s xml:id="_aRheryN">A total of 200 trials were presented, with each cue word appearing twice, in a random order.</s><s xml:id="_gS59WQ9">On the second presentation of each cue word, a different word associate was used, although the valence of these word associates was constant across both presentations.</s></p><p xml:id="_Qph9yv5"><s xml:id="_qy6rgfy">Ambiguous scenarios task.</s><s xml:id="_TZ9Uede">Ninety scenarios covering common worry topics identified in the Worry Domains Questionnaire <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(Tallis, Davey, &amp; Bond, 1994)</ref> were used in the ambiguous scenarios task.</s><s xml:id="_ZVmjyxN">Each scenario described a situation that was emotionally ambiguous until the final word that resolved the ambiguity in either a benign or threatening manner.</s><s xml:id="_XZyTFkP">To cover a variety of worry domains, the scenarios were drawn from a number of different sources.</s><s xml:id="_zsUAhWk">Some were selected from <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Mathews and Mackintosh (2000)</ref>; others were adapted from <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Holmes, Mathews, Dalgleish, and Mackintosh (2006)</ref> or <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Huppert, Pasupuleti, Foa, and Mathews (2007)</ref>; while others were created for this study.</s><s xml:id="_jwJRj5M">An example of a scenario (with final words in parentheses) is as follows: "You are given the task of arranging the annual office party.</s><s xml:id="_pCRHEPt">Despite having very little time, you do your best to prepare food, drink and entertainment.</s><s xml:id="_tYQFRKm">As the night approaches, you think that the event will be a (success/disaster)."</s><s xml:id="_XWHBHrk">All scenarios were digitally recorded.</s></p><p xml:id="_6eYvh89"><s xml:id="_JWPWdga">The 90 scenarios originally designed to induce an interpretive bias were presented to participants over headphones (following the method used by <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Holmes &amp; Mathews, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Holmes et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">and Murphy et al., 2007)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_Qhh8z9w">Each scenario remained ambiguous in terms of its emotional interpretation until the final word that resolved the ambiguity in either a threatening or benign manner was presented.</s><s xml:id="_9xZEK36">Unlike the procedure used by Mathews and Mackintosh (2000; Experiment 1), outcome resolutions were provided rather than generated by participants.</s></p><p xml:id="_dXQ9xHH"><s xml:id="_hYcE9QH">At the conclusion of each scenario, a comprehension question appeared (e.g., "Did everyone enjoy the party you planned?"), and the correct answer to the question confirmed the provided outcome of the scenario.</s><s xml:id="_dVf23ta">A "yes/no" prompt appeared under each question for a maximum of 10 s.</s><s xml:id="_kEGFPnN">At the detection of this yes/no response, a feedback message was displayed for 1,000 ms.</s><s xml:id="_y3578Jj">If correct, the answer remained on screen with the question.</s><s xml:id="_A8GDwVw">If incorrect, a short computer-generated tone was presented and the correct (yes/no) response appeared in red below the question.</s><s xml:id="_HeFskkw">If participants failed to respond, "no response detected" appeared, and the next trial commenced.</s></p><p xml:id="_gfMpuvY"><s xml:id="_k3szbsN">For the benign group, ambiguity was always resolved in a benign manner.</s><s xml:id="_wXME2P2">For the control group, 50% of the time the situation was resolved in a threatening manner, and 50% of the time the situation was resolved in a benign manner.</s><s xml:id="_trJfbPr">Scenarios were presented in five blocks.</s><s xml:id="_6meyDA7">Blocks were in a fixed order, but the order of descriptions within each block was randomized for each participant by the E-Prime software program <ref type="bibr">(Psychology Software Tools, 2002)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_2U2PaMx"><s xml:id="_eNv3bFn">Filler task.</s><s xml:id="_NvwGuMC">The Speed of Comprehension Test (Version A; <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Baddeley, Emslie, &amp; Nimmo-Smith, 1992)</ref> was administered as a filler task to reduce the likelihood of group differences in mood prior to the breathing focus task.</s><s xml:id="_wbFZZvw">This test consists of 100 sentences, half of which are true (e.g., "Dragonflies have wings") and half of which are false (e.g., "Beer lives in trees").</s><s xml:id="_92DDKav">Participants were given a paper version of the task and were asked to indicate with a tick or a cross which sentences were true and which were false.</s><s xml:id="_xGRwhP6">Participants performed this task for 2 min.</s><s xml:id="_EewEgk5">To minimize the likelihood of the task inducing anxiety, instructions were amended to clearly emphasize that speed was not important.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_B8pArnY">Outcome Measures</head><p xml:id="_7e7sgrt"><s xml:id="_XKasxPx">Breathing focus task.</s><s xml:id="_CP34Yvv">This task was adapted from a standard behavioral measure of worry originally developed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Borkovec et al. (1983)</ref> and later refined by <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Ruscio and Borkovec (2004)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_wnuM5Vu">The current version consisted of three phases: a 5-min preworry breathing focus, followed by a 5-min instructed worry period, followed by a 5-min postworry breathing focus.</s><s xml:id="_R3dBrah">During each 5-min breathing focus period, participants were instructed to focus their attention on their breathing, and a computer-generated tone sounded at random intervals of between 20 and 30 s, generating a total of 12 tones during each breathing focus period.</s><s xml:id="_vHAgxwX">At each of these tones, participants indicated whether their attention was focused on their breathing or if at that moment they had experienced a thought intrusion.</s><s xml:id="_Ndyu2Fq">If they had an intrusion, they then rated whether it was positive, neutral, or negative in content and gave a brief description (e.g., "positive-going out tonight").</s><s xml:id="_JxvDwm9">At the end of each breathing focus period, participants completed mood rating scales (see above) and answered three questions related to the breathing focus period: "Estimate the percentage to which you were able to focus on your breathing (0% not at all-100% all of the time)"; "Rate how difficult you found focusing on your breathing (0 not at all difficult-100 extremely difficult)"; and "Estimate the percentage of time you worried during the last 5 minutes (0% none of the time-100% all of the time)."</s></p><p xml:id="_TjHHvxA"><s xml:id="_FdV7sQk">After the first breathing focus period, participants identified a current worry topic which they then discussed briefly with the experimenter to ensure that it was related to a potentially negative future situation.</s><s xml:id="_3aGt3Yq">The experimenter wrote down a brief summary of the worry topic.</s><s xml:id="_cVT2eGE">Participants were then asked to continue to silently worry about this topic for 5 min, at which point the experimenter left the room.</s><s xml:id="_hTj5u9w">At the end of 5 min, the experimenter returned, the second breathing focus period was completed, and ratings were made (as above).</s><s xml:id="_XByKwP7">Following this, participants completed retrospective mood rating scales in relation to the worry period and answered the following three questions: "Estimate the percentage of time that you were able to spend worrying (0% not at all-100% all of the time)"; "Rate how difficult you found it to worry for 5 minutes (0 not difficult at all-100 extremely difficult)"; and "Rate how stressed you were whilst worrying (0 not stressed at all-100 extremely stressed)."</s></p><p xml:id="_JGnR5pW"><s xml:id="_JNM5Nn9">Finally, participants were asked to provide fuller descriptions of the thought intrusions reported during the breathing focus periods.</s><s xml:id="_H2D22zU">For each identified thought intrusion, the experimenter read aloud the participants' summaries and asked them for a fuller description of what was going through their minds at the moment they originally had the thought intrusion.</s><s xml:id="_NXMr8D5">Thought expansions generated by participants were digitally recorded for later rating by an assessor.</s><s xml:id="_NBhFm3r">An undergraduate psychology student, who acted as the assessor, listened to the recordings of the expanded thought descriptions and rated the valence of each intrusion.</s><s xml:id="_Xq389MQ">To assess reliability of the assessor's valence ratings, a psychology graduate also rated 12 participants' thought expansions.</s><s xml:id="_j8rNq8U">Neither assessor was aware of group allocation, nor were they aware of whether the thought intrusion had occurred in the first or second breathing focus period.</s><s xml:id="_D8TyJ5F">Interrater reliability for assessors' valence ratings based on percentage of agreement was 84.3%.</s></p><p xml:id="_W2a6U2b"><s xml:id="_BwJYVyq">Another psychology graduate acted as an assessor to categorize participants' worry topics (on the basis of the summary provided by the experimenter) into the following categories: work/study, social/relationships, physical, and financial.</s><s xml:id="_yHsuR7e">They also rated how negative the worry topics were (i.e., low, medium, or high negativity of the topic).</s><s xml:id="_UpgJWZD">A psychology undergraduate also categorized and rated a quarter of the worry topics in the same way to provide interrater reliability.</s><s xml:id="_4bU878F">Neither assessor was aware of group allocation.</s><s xml:id="_pJffFPB">The interrater reliability of percentage of agreement between assessors on both the worry topic categorization and negativity ratings was 100%.</s></p><p xml:id="_jPau4w8"><s xml:id="_SwswC8J">Working memory task.</s><s xml:id="_NpttuAF">The working memory task followed that used by <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Hayes et al. (2008)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_KyGNAsy">Participants were first asked to indicate and briefly think about a personally relevant and current worry topic, with the specification that this topic should be different from the topic identified earlier in the worry task.</s><s xml:id="_DSgKnej">For the next 2 min, the experimenter asked participants a series of questions designed to prime salient negative attributes of the topic, each taking the general form of "And what would be bad about that?" <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(Vasey &amp; Borkovec, 1992)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_TZjH53C">Participants were then asked to continue to think about the topic and were told that this would be their main task.</s><s xml:id="_SnWVbKk">In addition, every time they heard a tone signal, they were required to press a key that should be chosen at random on a 15-key response box.</s><s xml:id="_CRJFngW">Participants were asked to think of the tone as a signal for them to make a random response, and then to focus back on the worry topic.</s><s xml:id="_u2uv5FM">Participants produced a total of 100 responses by pressing one of the 15 keys, each cued by the signal generated by the computer every 3 s, for a total task duration of 5 min.</s></p><p xml:id="_T4gJegt"><s xml:id="_dw3nxYP">Randomness was calculated using Redundancy (R), a measure of informational redundancy first derived from information theory analyses (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Attneave, 1959;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Baddeley, 1966)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_xWMFEQf">This index reflects (on a scale of 0 to 100) the extent to which each key was pressed equally often.</s><s xml:id="_4k4WbAY">When keys are pressed with too great or small a frequency, R scores will increase.</s><s xml:id="_qd3GyPN">Prior research has indicated that R is one of the most sensitive measures of randomness for use with a random key-pressing task <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Baddeley, Emslie, Kolodny, &amp; Duncan, 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Towse, 1998)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_RZzfwh3"><s xml:id="_29PU8zy">For the purposes of analyses, each of the 15 keys were represented by numerical values, increasing from left to right and top to bottom, such that the top left key was assigned the value of 1 and the bottom right key 15.</s><s xml:id="_S85SwyQ">R randomness measures were then calculated using the software program RGCalc <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Towse &amp; Neil, 1998)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_dGVdjpk">For this measure of randomness, higher values indicate less random performance, implying less residual working memory capacity.</s></p><p xml:id="_xfUKhnE"><s xml:id="_u7NJzr6">To confirm that both groups engaged in this task in the same way, immediately following the task, we asked participants to indicate the extent to which they kept their mind focused on their worry topic.</s><s xml:id="_SeDjh8N">Using a 100-mm scale labeled not at all at one end and totally at the other, they were asked to place a cross (x) on the scale.</s><s xml:id="_77gZ7j2">This was measured with a millimeter ruler according to the position of the cross placed on the scale, with scores ranging from 0 (not at all focused on worry topic) to 100 (totally focused on worry topic).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_neTVxR7">Experimental Apparatus</head><p xml:id="_jJujc9U"><s xml:id="_HSK6wYM">A Sony VAIO laptop computer with E-Prime software was used to administer all experimental tasks.</s><s xml:id="_kek2WDM">In addition, Creative HN-700 stereophonic headphones delivered audio stimuli.</s><s xml:id="_24UuYeG">During the breathing focus task, the computer was programmed to generate a tone at random intervals <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Donaldson, 2004)</ref>, and an Olympus WS-200S digital voice recorder was used to record participants' expanded thought descriptions.</s><s xml:id="_FttJYgg">The response box consisted of 15 one-cm<ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">foot_2</ref> buttons, arranged in three rows of five buttons each.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_gku8yTv">Procedure</head><p xml:id="_2u9XnXc"><s xml:id="_cTkSzks">Participants initially filled in a consent form, the PSWQ, STAI-T, GAD-Q-IV, and mood rating scales.</s><s xml:id="_3vx2PQ5">After instructions were given for the homograph task and five practice trials, the homograph task was administered, followed by mood rating scales.</s><s xml:id="_ubSs5Dq">Participants then completed the ambiguous scenarios task.</s><s xml:id="_sakXzxw">This was followed by mood rating scales, the filler task, and another set of mood rating scales.</s><s xml:id="_CbFCZMV">Participants then received instructions for the breathing focus task, and then practiced focusing on their breathing and providing a capsule summary of their thoughts at three random time intervals within 45 s.</s><s xml:id="_DT2RRzM">When it was clear that all instructions were understood, participants were administered the breathing focus task.</s><s xml:id="_t3edwSN">Following this, they received instructions for the working memory task and a 15-s practice of key pressing before completing this task while worrying.</s><s xml:id="_FV7VzUc">This was immediately followed by mood rating scales and thought ratings.</s></p><p xml:id="_52k8r6D"><s xml:id="_qQkYENq">Following completion of the experimental part of the study, participants were asked three debriefing questions.</s><s xml:id="_VYvycdJ">First they were asked, "Did you notice anything in particular about the items in either the word completion task or the situations task?"</s><s xml:id="_Sp8J5pP">They were then asked, "Do you have any thoughts or ideas as to what the study was about?"</s><s xml:id="_DpTHag4">Following this, participants were informed that the study was designed to examine whether the meaning of word associates they completed and the endings of ambiguous scenarios they heard would influence how much they continued to worry following the 5 min they spent deliberately worrying.</s><s xml:id="_tC6mYwv">Following this they were asked, "So is that what you thought the study was about?"</s><s xml:id="_tgnJsnZ">Finally, participants were debriefed, thanked for their time, and paid £15 ($30).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_juRc6Fe">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_mDZWcjJ">Ambiguity Tasks Accuracy</head><p xml:id="_fwGtQC7"><s xml:id="_CtjrKVc">In the homograph task, accuracy in selecting the correct letter to complete the target word averaged 93.1% for the benign group and 94.0% for the control group.</s><s xml:id="_4ZB2egM">There was no significant difference in accuracy between the two groups, t Ͻ 1, d ϭ 0.27.</s><s xml:id="_3RJUEQc">In the ambiguous scenarios task, accuracy in selecting the correct "yes/no" answer in response to the comprehension question averaged 94.8% for the benign group and 93.0% for the control group.</s><s xml:id="_HTvqmzb">Again, there was no significant difference in accuracy between the two groups, t(38) ϭ 1.33, ns, d ϭ 0.42.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_s9a9UVJ">Self-Reported Mood Before and After Ambiguity Tasks</head><p xml:id="_TUMAhJp"><s xml:id="_jgT3Dka">A mixed model analysis of variance (ANOVA) was carried out separately on each of the three mood rating scales (anxiety, depression, and happiness) that were administered to participants at the start of the experiment and following each ambiguity task (i.e., after participants completed the homograph task and then again after they completed the ambiguous scenarios task).</s><s xml:id="_gQA6jM2">These mixed model ANOVAs considered the between-participants factor group (benign vs. control) and the repeated measures factor time (baseline vs. posthomograph task vs. postambiguous scenarios task). 1 When conducted on anxiety ratings, these analyses revealed a significant main effect of time, F(2, 76) ϭ 10.09, p Ͻ .001,</s><s xml:id="_kcNW2WP">f 2 ϭ 0.51.</s><s xml:id="_uEZNKQW">Bonferroni corrected post hoc t tests 2 revealed that although there was no significant change in anxiety from baseline to posthomograph task (3.90 vs. 3.39), t(39) ϭ 1.30, ns, d ϭ 0.19, there was a significant decrease in anxiety posthomograph task to postambiguous scenarios task (3.39 vs. 2.45), t(39) ϭ 3.47, p Ͻ .005,</s><s xml:id="_Fgh5RF4">d ϭ 0.39.</s><s xml:id="_wtmxrHb">There was no significant main effect of group, F(1, 38) ϭ 1.67, ns, f 2 ϭ 0.21, but there was a significant iinteraction between group and time, F(2, 76) ϭ 4.97, p Ͻ .01,</s><s xml:id="_vM3WbnF">f 2 ϭ 0.36.</s><s xml:id="_j4NWD84">However, post hoc t tests revealed no significant difference between benign and control participants' anxiety ratings at baseline (M ϭ 3.97 vs. M ϭ 3.82), t Ͻ 1; posthomograph (M ϭ 2.44 vs. M ϭ 4.35), t(38) ϭ 2.43, ns, d ϭ 0.77; or postambiguous scenario task (M ϭ 2.06 vs. M ϭ 2.84), t(38) ϭ 1.18, ns, d ϭ 0.38.</s><s xml:id="_ZCsetTQ">When conducted on depressive mood ratings, there was no significant main effect of time, F(2, 76) ϭ 1.03, ns, f 2 ϭ 0.16; no significant main effect of group, F Ͻ 1, f 2 ϭ 0.05; nor any significant interaction between group and time, F (2, 76) ϭ 1.03, ns, f 2 ϭ 0.16.</s><s xml:id="_paUPQKQ">Likewise, when conducted on happiness ratings, there was no significant main effect of time, F(1.72, 65.43) ϭ 2.10, ns, f 2 ϭ 0.23; no significant main effect of group, F Ͻ 1, f 2 ϭ 0.06; nor any significant interaction between group and time, F(1.72, 65.43) ϭ 1.05, ns, f 2 ϭ 0.17.</s><s xml:id="_4XmYDv5">Thus, consistent with Mathews and Mackintosh (2000; Experiment 2) and <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Wilson et al. (2006)</ref>, the induction method in itself caused no or small differential changes in mood.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_jxUfmyg">Breathing Focus Task Negative Intrusions</head><p xml:id="_DSAbs6m"><s xml:id="_qHVwDZm">The central hypothesis was that there would be fewer negative thought intrusions (as categorized by participants or assessor) during breathing focus periods in the benign than the control group (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> for means and standard deviations).</s><s xml:id="_QnV6G6w">To examine this hypothesis, a mixed model ANOVA was conducted on the number of negative thought intrusions during breathing focus periods, with a between-participants factor of group (benign vs. control) and the repeated measures factors time (preworry vs. postworry) and rater (self vs. assessor).</s><s xml:id="_mBGpuGB">This analysis revealed a significant main effect of time, F(1, 38) ϭ 8.69, p Ͻ .01,</s><s xml:id="_dW34Tjp">f 2 ϭ 0.47, with all participants having fewer negative thought intrusions preworry than postworry (1.6 vs. 2.4).</s><s xml:id="_QNDZpEb">A significant main effect was also found for group, F(1, 38) ϭ 15.08, p Ͻ .001,</s><s xml:id="_2xEFAHr">f 2 ϭ 0.63, reflecting the fact that the benign group had fewer negative thought intrusions than the control group (1.2 vs. 2.7).</s><s xml:id="_CMBMWea">There was no interaction between time and group, F Ͻ 1, f 2 ϭ 0.14.</s><s xml:id="_NVkStqk">It is also important to note that there was no significant main effect of rater, F Ͻ 1, f 2 ϭ 0.11, nor any significant interactions concerning rater, all Fs Ͻ 1.</s><s xml:id="_p67R8ex">In sum, the benign group had fewer negative thought intrusions than did the control group both before and after instructed worry, and this effect was not confined to self-ratings, as self-ratings and assessor ratings did not differ.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_8fWkxhQ">Breathing Focus Task Ratings</head><p xml:id="_3bskrUX"><s xml:id="_gZzMK3h">To assess the extent to which the two groups felt that they were able to focus their attention on their breathing during the pre-and postworry breathing focus periods, a mixed model ANOVA was carried out separately on each of the three questions related to the breathing focus periods (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> for means and standard deviations).</s><s xml:id="_GEpXrcn">This mixed model analysis considered one betweenparticipants factor, group, and one repeated measures factor, time (preworry breathing focus period vs. postworry breathing focus period).</s></p><p xml:id="_NyuqzqN"><s xml:id="_snbjQzZ">When conducted on the percentage of time participants were able to focus their attention on their breathing, there was a significant main effect of group, F(1, 38) ϭ 5.81, p Ͻ .05,</s><s xml:id="_MnwhfJG">f 2 ϭ 0.39, with the benign group reporting spending more time focused on their breathing than the control group (65.4% vs. 49.4%).</s><s xml:id="_B3FqwwM">There was no significant main effect of time, F(1, 38) ϭ 2.16, ns, f 2 ϭ 0.24, nor any significant interaction between time and group, F Ͻ 1, f 2 ϭ 0.10.</s><s xml:id="_y3j6vKc">When the analysis was conducted on ratings of how difficult participants found it to focus on their breathing, there was no significant main effect of time, F(1, 38) ϭ 2.24, ns, f 2 ϭ 0.24; no significant main effect of group, F Ͻ 1, f 2 ϭ 0.11; nor any significant interaction between time and group, F Ͻ 1, f 2 ϭ 0.16.</s><s xml:id="_GY32QhX">When conducted on the percentage of time participants spent worrying during the breathing focus periods, there was a significant main effect of time, F(1, 38) ϭ 6.17, p Ͻ .05,</s><s xml:id="_MtyMUwX">f 2 ϭ 0.40, due to participants spending more time worrying during the postworry breathing focus period than during the preworry breathing focus period (32.9% vs. 22.0%).</s><s xml:id="_JU4f7TW">There was also a significant main effect of group, F(1, 38) ϭ 5.69, p Ͻ .05,</s><s xml:id="_7uCaUfP">f 2 ϭ 0.38, due to the benign group spending less time worrying during breathing focus periods than the control group (20.2% vs. 34.8%).</s><s xml:id="_vHnZ6xg">There was no significant interaction between time and group, F Ͻ 1, f 2 ϭ 0.11.</s><s xml:id="_grJKBFd">In summary, although all participants reported worrying more during the postworry than during the preworry breathing focus period, the benign group reported spending more time focused on their breathing and less time worrying during both breathing focus periods.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_dHk3RqN">Worry Period Ratings</head><p xml:id="_JVE3cB3"><s xml:id="_zPZ5SNR">Self-report measures regarding the instructed worry period showed the two groups reported no significant difference in the percentage of time spent worrying when instructed to worry for a 5-min period (81.8% for the benign group vs. 81.0%</s><s xml:id="_qct8kC2">for the control</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_BpK7M6H">Self-Reported Mood During the Breathing Focus Task</head><p xml:id="_a9H8nrU"><s xml:id="_95r5HwR">To establish that groups did not differ in self-reported mood prior to the breathing focus task, independent samples t tests were conducted on each of the three mood rating scales (anxiety, depression, and happiness) that were administered immediately prior to the breathing focus task.</s><s xml:id="_9nA2Xyy">These analyses revealed no significant difference between the two groups in terms of anxiety, t(38) ϭ 1.27, ns, d ϭ 0.40; depressed mood, t Ͻ 1, d ϭ 0.04; or happiness, t(38) ϭ 1.34, ns, d ϭ 0.42.</s><s xml:id="_ejPRHxQ">Thus, we found no evidence of significant mood differences prior to the breathing focus task that could account for any differences in negative thought intrusions between groups.</s></p><p xml:id="_sFm9XUs"><s xml:id="_XPB5X7A">To determine how mood changed for both groups during the breathing focus task, a mixed model ANOVA was carried out separately on each of the three mood rating scales administered to participants pre-and postworry breathing focus periods and at the end of the worry period (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref> for means and standard deviations).</s><s xml:id="_gza66Yy">These mixed model analyses considered the betweenparticipants factor group and the repeated measures factor time (preworry breathing focus period vs. immediately postworry vs. postworry breathing focus period).</s></p><p xml:id="_zJ7Enn5"><s xml:id="_hy2vUkc">When conducted on anxiety ratings, this analysis revealed a significant main effect of time, F(2, 76) ϭ 196.13, p Ͻ .001,</s><s xml:id="_as94uwS">f 2 ϭ 2.27.</s><s xml:id="_S2EWntQ">This reflected a general increase in anxiety from preworry breathing focus to the worry period (2.66 vs. 6.68),</s><s xml:id="_XUYpz9C">t(39) ϭ 9.90, p Ͻ .001,</s><s xml:id="_DMtW52Z">d ϭ 1.71, as well as a significant decrease in anxiety from the worry period to postworry breathing focus (6.68 vs. 3.06), t(39) ϭ 9.01, p Ͻ .001,</s><s xml:id="_DCt9TtH">d ϭ 1.56.</s><s xml:id="_5FED2Us">There was no significant main effect of group, F(1, 38) ϭ 3.54, ns, f 2 ϭ 0.30.</s><s xml:id="_RxDu9R8">However, there was a significant interaction between time and group, F(2, 76) ϭ 3.32, p Ͻ .05,</s><s xml:id="_dtWvAmb">f 2 ϭ 0.29.</s><s xml:id="_RHrzwG5">As predicted, one-tailed independent-samples t tests conducted on anxiety ratings revealed that the benign group reported less anxiety than the control group during both preworry breathing focus (1.70 vs. 3.63), t(38) ϭ 2.64, p Ͻ .01,</s><s xml:id="_KsYFeZv">d ϭ 0.84, and postworry breathing focus (2.39 vs. 3.72), t(38) ϭ 1.79, p Ͻ .05,</s><s xml:id="_AfTctpQ">d ϭ 0.56.</s><s xml:id="_Rq8AsC6">However, there was no difference in anxiety ratings between the two groups during the instructed worry period itself (6.65 vs. 6.71),</s><s xml:id="_ZVwQ8Hm">t Ͻ 1, d ϭ 0.03 (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>).</s></p><p xml:id="_AneVzcV"><s xml:id="_aM53mtB">When conducted on depressed mood ratings, the ANOVA revealed a significant main effect of time, F(1.63, 62.04) ϭ 42.73, p Ͻ .001,</s><s xml:id="_ratQJ5E">f 2 ϭ 1.06, reflecting an increase in depressed mood from preworry breathing focus to postworry (1.88 vs. 4.81), t(39) ϭ 7.7, p Ͻ .001,</s><s xml:id="_AcC7QZn">d ϭ 1.16, as well as a significant decrease in depressed mood from postworry to postworry breathing focus (4.81 vs. 2.62), t(39) ϭ 5.89, p Ͻ .001,</s><s xml:id="_64aRrNw">d ϭ 0.84.</s><s xml:id="_zcpHPnv">There was no significant main effect of group, F Ͻ 1, f 2 ϭ 0.04, nor any significant interaction between time and group, F(1.63, 62.04) ϭ 2.76, ns, f 2 ϭ 0.27.</s><s xml:id="_qu565ng">Thus all participants reported an increase in depressed mood from the end of the preworry breathing focus to the end of the worry period, and then a decrease to the end of postworry breathing focus, regardless of group.</s></p><p xml:id="_zUk9FJk"><s xml:id="_Cq4ktWr">When conducted on happiness ratings, analyses revealed a significant main effect of time, F(1.53, 58.12) ϭ 56.39, p Ͻ .001,</s><s xml:id="_qcGkTrM">f 2 ϭ 1.22, reflecting a decrease in happiness from preworry breathing focus to postworry (5.88 vs. 2.56), t(39) ϭ 7.83, p Ͻ .001,</s><s xml:id="_XfNavWC">d ϭ 1.49, as well as a significant increase in happiness from postworry to postworry breathing focus (2.56 vs. 5.47), t(39) ϭ 7.89, p Ͻ .001,</s><s xml:id="_jAZMHnw">d ϭ 1.36.</s><s xml:id="_sVKWJkU">There was no significant main effect of group, F(1, 38) ϭ 2.01, ns, f 2 ϭ 0.23, but there was a significant interaction between group and time, F(1.53, 58.12) ϭ 3.66, p Ͻ .05,</s><s xml:id="_9sWQtVR">ns, f 2 ϭ 0.31.</s><s xml:id="_7XGdHag">However, post hoc t tests indicated that the groups did not differ in happiness during preworry breathing focus phase (6.73 vs. 5.03), t(38) ϭ 2.22, ns, d ϭ 0.70; postworry, t Ͻ 1, d ϭ 0.07; or postworry breathing focus phase, t(38) ϭ 1.26, ns, d ϭ 0.39.</s></p><p xml:id="_HYnS8ar"><s xml:id="_GPryFaF">In summary, there was a significant effect of practice accessing benign meanings on anxiety ratings, with no significant differences found for depression or happiness.</s><s xml:id="_WCw5tA8">Prior practice in accessing benign meanings was associated with less anxiety during breathing focus, both before and after instructed worry.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_2nfSeRX">Working Memory</head><p xml:id="_kWyGzMC"><s xml:id="_3xn9S9S">Our hypothesis for this task was that when participants were thinking about a current worry topic, redundancy (R) scores would be lower (indexing greater residual working memory capacity) in the benign group.</s><s xml:id="_46NDHCg">As expected, a one-tailed independent samples t test revealed significantly lower R scores in the benign than in the control group (3.21 vs. 5.82), t(38) ϭ 1.89, p Ͻ .05,</s><s xml:id="_xBrPu9X">d ϭ 0.59.</s><s xml:id="_xKQd54u">This</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="50" xml:id="_JTVn7AZ">HIRSCH, HAYES, AND MATHEWS</head><p xml:id="_3VTnZFq"><s xml:id="_r9PajEJ">This document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers.</s><s xml:id="_Wm7ywKV">This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.</s></p><p xml:id="_b33yreH"><s xml:id="_nu8xpb5">result suggests greater residual working memory available while worrying to participants in the benign than in the control group.</s><s xml:id="_SzEUGBa">An independent samples t test on ratings after the working memory task revealed no significant difference in the extent to which the benign and control groups reported focusing on their worry thoughts (5.9 vs. 4.5), t(38) ϭ 1.57, ns, d ϭ 0.49.</s><s xml:id="_RWbsx4K">Furthermore, when ratings of the extent to which participants focused on their worry thoughts was entered as a covariate into a univariate ANOVA of R scores, the group effect remained significant, F(2, 37) ϭ 4.18, p Ͻ .05,</s><s xml:id="_yfa4Khy">f 2 ϭ 0.33.</s><s xml:id="_nfhnZGG">Consequently, group differences in residual working memory capacity when worrying reported above cannot be attributed to differences in the extent to which groups focused on worry during the key press task.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Jy6u3m3">Debriefing Questions</head><p xml:id="_jREQzUn"><s xml:id="_nJTG5w6">In response to the question "Did you notice anything in particular about the items in either the word completion task or the scenarios task?" some participants assigned to the benign condition (30%), but none in the control condition, reported that they had noticed that there were a lot of positive words and positive endings to ambiguous scenarios.</s><s xml:id="_A6maxah">However, no participants in either group reported a link between the ambiguity tasks and the breathing focus task.</s><s xml:id="_fNqBdwV">In response to the question "Do you have any thoughts or ideas as to what the study was about?" no participant was able to provide any more detail than that appearing in the information sheet (i.e., that the study was investigating worry and why worried).</s><s xml:id="_CmffxfJ">Again, no participant reported any relationship between the ambiguity tasks and the breathing focus task.</s><s xml:id="_ynHsD3w">After being informed as to the aim of the study, participants were asked, "So is that what you thought the study was about?"</s><s xml:id="_mJUE8dm">No participant replied in the affirmative.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_AAUfxcC">Discussion</head><p xml:id="_2qVzYF8"><s xml:id="_rzJm4WW">The main aim of this study was to investigate whether practice in accessing benign meanings of ambiguous information would lead to fewer negative thought intrusions and less worry in high worriers.</s><s xml:id="_C4fmjeq">In keeping with the hypothesis, individuals with high levels of trait worry who were allocated to the benign group reported fewer negative thought intrusions during breathing focus than did those in the control group.</s><s xml:id="_xvRDndR">This effect was not confined to self-report, since an assessor (who was not informed about group allocation, or during which breathing focus period the intrusions had occurred) did not differ from participants in terms of categorization.</s><s xml:id="_VDzc275">Participants' ratings of the extent to which they worried during the breathing focus periods were also lower in the benign than in the control condition; conversely, ratings of ability to focus on their breathing were greater in the benign than in the control group.</s><s xml:id="_5fGnjq5">The benign group also reported lower levels of anxiety during both breathing focus periods (i.e., prior to and after instructed worry) in comparison with the control group.</s><s xml:id="_8yHd3J9">In sum, therefore, it seems that prior practice in accessing benign meanings of worry-related information enabled more effective control over negative intrusions when the current task required it and simultaneously reduced concomitant anxiety.</s><s xml:id="_bw9ArjG">It appears that prior access to worry-related benign meanings may have reduced the capacity of worry content to preempt attention, leaving participants better able to maintain their attention on the task at hand (e.g., breathing focus).</s></p><p xml:id="_tWmVHbJ"><s xml:id="_xauF6H4">Consistent with this possibility, group differences were also observed in the amount of residual working memory capacity available when instructed to worry.</s><s xml:id="_kv6rdPK">Key-press responses were more random for participants in the benign than the control group, indicating more residual working memory capacity available to perform other cognitive operations.</s><s xml:id="_uSqYkMd">This finding cannot easily be attributed to the extent to which the groups worried during the working memory task, because there were no such group differences, and the randomness effect remained significant when the extent to which participants worried during the working memory task was covaried out.</s><s xml:id="_TprQce4">As suggested above, however, it could be that the attention-holding quality of these negative thoughts may have been modified by prior practice in accessing benign meanings, potentially freeing up resources for other tasks.</s></p><p xml:id="_ZJqAfXG"><s xml:id="_fnfaHBV">It is difficult to attribute these effects to differences in accuracy of performance during the ambiguity tasks, or to differences in mood prior to the breathing focus task, as groups did not differ in these respects.</s><s xml:id="_9yarVxB">Furthermore, effects are not readily attributable to group differences in the worry topics or perceived ability to engage in worry (when instructed to do so) because no such differences were found in assessor ratings of the type of worry topic or degree of negativity of the worry, and neither were they found on participant ratings of how difficult it was to worry, amount of time worrying, or how stressful it was to engage in worry.</s><s xml:id="_UbTufRM">It remains possible that experimenter demand effects may have influenced self-ratings, although several other findings suggested that demand is unlikely to provide a complete explanation.</s><s xml:id="_QBDHFSj">During the postexperimental interviews, no one was able to describe the purpose of the study, nor any link between the ambiguity tasks and the breathing focus task.</s><s xml:id="_aFQSeF5">Furthermore, after being told the purpose of the study, none of the participants reported having thought that was what the study had been about.</s><s xml:id="_KdYZDzP">Hence, although it is not possible to completely rule out demand effects, they do not appear likely to provide a complete explanation for the current data.</s></p><p xml:id="_tNazsYT"><s xml:id="_yN9Cw8f">If it is granted that such artefactual explanations are unlikely to provide a full account of the findings, then this strengthens the hypothesis that practice in accessing benign meanings was responsible for the effects observed.</s><s xml:id="_p7XejAd">Because worry is characterized by repeated thoughts about future events that could lead to benign as well as negative outcomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Sibrava &amp; Borkovec, 2006)</ref>, prior practice in accessing benign outcomes could have changed the form of processing taking place during the breathing focus periods.</s><s xml:id="_uvydxdB">That is, for participants in the benign condition, later negative intrusions may have cued the generation of alternative and more benign outcomes, thus reducing the capacity of worry to preempt cognitive resources.</s><s xml:id="_y98mSWa">In contrast, those allocated to the control group (who accessed both negative and benign outcomes equally) may have been less likely than those in the benign group to generate alternative and less threatening outcomes of such thoughts, thus maintaining attention on the perceived threat <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Berenbaum, Thompson, &amp; Pomerantz, 2007)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_SYa2HNC"><s xml:id="_u2rYqy8">The current study marks the first objective (assessor) assessment of the valence of thought intrusions reported by participants during the breathing focus task.</s><s xml:id="_4nNQyrK">Previously, this paradigm had only provided participants' subjective categorizations of the valence of their thought intrusions.</s><s xml:id="_PAXsUMg">The current finding that assessor ratings and self-ratings did not differ implies that high worriers are indeed accurate in categorizing the valence of their thought intrusions.</s><s xml:id="_zANrpJd">This suggests that any changes sustained as a result of practice accessing benign meanings led to objectively less negative thought intrusions, rather than to a potential alternative situation in which benign and control participants had objectively similar thoughts (as determined by the assessor); however, the benign group categorized them in a more benign manner.</s></p><p xml:id="_Ct3GSdc"><s xml:id="_A3ayJK8">In keeping with <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Wilson et al. (2006)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Murphy et al. (2007)</ref>, the lack of group differences in anxiety immediately following completion of both of the ambiguity tasks did not preclude significant group differences in anxiety reactivity during the breathing focus task.</s><s xml:id="_EWXGzWt">Specifically, whereas both groups reported increased anxiety when actively worrying, the benign group reported lower levels of anxiety both prior to and following instructed worry than did the control group.</s><s xml:id="_8jmUHbT">This finding suggests that repeated practice accessing benign meanings of emotionally ambiguous information can result in lower levels of anxiety and a greater ability to reduce anxiety following a stressful situation.</s><s xml:id="_FggNN8u">Hence, it seems that these methods may have reduced the vulnerability to anxiety, at least in the short term.</s><s xml:id="_MxxqpSR">Further research will be needed to investigate how long these effects can be sustained.</s><s xml:id="_p7wQvnY">This future research should also include an assessment of negative thought intrusions and randomness prior to practice in accessing benign meanings, as this will enable the extent of change to be assessed, as well as ensure that the groups do not differ prior to practice in accessing benign meanings.</s><s xml:id="_99Np4Pf">Another potentially interesting avenue for the research would be to include an assessment of how the practice in accessing benign meanings would influence other cognitive processes, such as attention.</s></p><p xml:id="_MqdFJG9"><s xml:id="_cHp7ZpA">One potentially problematic feature of the present study was the inclusion of both the homograph and ambiguous scenario tasks.</s><s xml:id="_uxwnbgt">Consequently, we are unable to establish whether group differences observed here are attributable to either one or both of these tasks in combination.</s><s xml:id="_FusSntM">One reason for using both tasks was to provide opportunities for generating benign meanings in more than one context, so as to increase the chances of generalization to the negative intrusions occurring in worry.</s><s xml:id="_cNFtcby">By beginning with singleword meanings (homographs) and progressing to more complex scenarios, we were basing our design on a graded skills learning approach, in which the required response is kept relatively simple at first but then extends to increasingly realistic and complex processes (for similar arguments applied to positive bias modification, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Mathews et al., 2007)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_CUW8MPp">In this case, we supposed that using homographs would provide the simpler initial learning experiences but that the later scenarios would be closer to the more usual form of worry.</s><s xml:id="_yPrm3fw">Clearly, however, a corresponding disadvantage is that we cannot know whether presenting homographs before ambiguous scenarios was indeed helpful in the way we had anticipated.</s><s xml:id="_BdxraS4">Further research is therefore needed to establish which cognitive modification techniques are most effective in decreasing worry and whether there are indeed benefits from using a graded approach, such as the approach that we used here.</s></p><p xml:id="_2fgsbbP"><s xml:id="_PJQNxzB">Another omission from the present study was that of any direct measure of the extent to which the benign group did indeed selectively access more benign outcomes of future worry-related events as a result of practice accessing benign meanings.</s><s xml:id="_fUtRR8A">The materials and methods used here were originally developed to manipulate interpretive biases <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Grey &amp; Mathews, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Mathews &amp; Mackintosh, 2000)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_Dj9bKds">Although the current study did not assess interpretive bias directly, both <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Murphy et al. (2007)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Mathews et al. (2007)</ref> have already shown that use of essentially the same method and materials resulted in high anxious individuals adopting a more benign interpretive bias.</s><s xml:id="_Wyt9S5z">Furthermore, it is difficult to account for the differences seen during the worry task in the present experiment, such as fewer negative thought intrusions, without supposing that the effects of practice in accessing benign meanings did not carry over to the later assessment period.</s><s xml:id="_rFdNsHB">Nonetheless, future research should include more direct measures of the purported mechanism underlying these effects on worry.</s></p><p xml:id="_qWHChqd"><s xml:id="_FVNRjez">A final issue that needs to be considered is that of how far the present results can be generalized to naturally occurring worry and to clinical disorders such as GAD.</s><s xml:id="_4gjSQ9X">The worry task used here was adapted from an established method <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Borkovec et al., 1983;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Ruscio &amp; Borkovec, 2004</ref>), and as with other studies using instructed worry (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Mathews &amp; Milroy, 1994)</ref>, it is assumed that instructed worry is similar to naturally occurring worry.</s><s xml:id="_C3swDv7">However, we cannot be certain that the findings of the present study would generalize to naturally occurring worry when individuals focus on daily (nonworry) tasks.</s><s xml:id="_GXkdFef">It will be important in future research to investigate the extent to which the methods used here reduce real-life problems associated with excessive worry, such as concentration problems, and other anxiety symptoms.</s><s xml:id="_wckPyvy">Nonetheless, we believe the current findings, based on a sample of university staff and students who worry excessively, may have some clinical relevance because they show that practice in accessing benign meanings can have an effect on the cardinal feature of GAD, namely, worry.</s><s xml:id="_pzAkzUw">Furthermore, the observed effects on working memory may help to explain the difficulty in controlling worry experienced by people with GAD.</s></p><p xml:id="_hTUb9TX"><s xml:id="_U5MyJkv">In the present study, over half of the participants in the benign group (and half in the control group) met diagnostic criteria for GAD on the GAD-Q-IV.</s><s xml:id="_e6p9639">Furthermore, individuals who met criteria for GAD on this measure did not significantly differ from those who did not meet these criteria in terms of the number of negative thought intrusions, amount of anxiety, or working memory capacity.</s><s xml:id="_rnGtKYz">This suggests that the presence of a GAD diagnosis does not obviate (or even reduce) the effectiveness of the cognitive bias modification methods used here, although further research is clearly needed to replicate the current findings in a clinical GAD population.</s></p><p xml:id="_T8dCTpz"><s xml:id="_hqJJQh3">Cognitive-behavioral interventions often focus on challenging negative thought and meanings; for example, by having clients generate contrary evidence.</s><s xml:id="_6t3tZbh">More recently, however, interest in methods of enhancing positive cognitive content and processes has been increasing (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Borkovec, Newman, &amp; Castonguay, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Clark et al., 2006)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_SS4MGJu">The findings from this study provide support for this change in clinical focus by suggesting that helping clients to access benign meanings of emotionally ambiguous information may reduce some of problems reported by clients with GAD, such as worry and concentration problems.</s></p><p xml:id="_pgtZuvz"><s xml:id="_nP6KKR2">In summary, the current study demonstrated that repeated practice in accessing benign meanings of emotionally ambiguous information can reduce the number of negative thought intrusions, along with anxious mood, when high worriers attempted to focus on a task unrelated to worry.</s><s xml:id="_YrVchfG">Moreover, these methods were shown to lead to greater residual working memory capacity when engaging in worry.</s><s xml:id="_HHE3QPW">Future research is required to investigate whether these methods can produce similar changes in clients with GAD, perhaps paving the way for potential improvements in clinical interventions.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s xml:id="_M6UWrEU">Mean Number of Negative Thought Intrusions for the Benign and Control Groups Preworry and Postworry periods, as Rated bySelf and Assessor (Standard Deviations in Parentheses)</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Preworry</cell><cell cols="2">Postworry</cell></row><row><cell>Group</cell><cell>Self</cell><cell>Assessor</cell><cell>Self</cell><cell>Assessor</cell></row><row><cell>Benign</cell><cell>0.95 (1.15)</cell><cell>1.00 (1.17)</cell><cell>1.40 (1.14)</cell><cell>1.60 (1.67)</cell></row><row><cell>Control</cell><cell>2.30 (1.63)</cell><cell>2.10 (1.52)</cell><cell>3.40 (2.04)</cell><cell>3.00 (1.78)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s xml:id="_cCYfST5">Self-Report Measures forBenign and Control Groups During Pre-and Postworry Breathing Focus Periods (Standard Deviations in  Parentheses)Ͻ 1, d ϭ 0.05.</s><s xml:id="_ebCQwNV">Moreover, the groups reported no significant difference in how difficult they found it to worry during this 5-min worry period (19.3% for the benign group vs. 27.1% for the control group), t Ͻ 1, d ϭ 0.30, nor any significant difference in how stressed they felt while actively worrying (55.8% for the benign group vs. 62.0% for the control group), t Ͻ 1, d ϭ 0.23.</s><s xml:id="_mWTaGBN">Therefore, group differences in negative thought intrusions cannot readily be accounted for in terms of differences in participants' perceived ability to engage in instructed worry.</s><s xml:id="_HsjhDM9">Furthermore, chisquare tests of assessors' worry topic categorization demonstrated that the groups did not differ in terms of the type of worry topic they selected, 2 (3, N ϭ 40) ϭ 2.69, ns, nor in how negative the topics were (i.e., degree of negativity), 2 (1, N ϭ 40) ϭ 0.23, ns.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Preworry</cell></row><row><cell>Group</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_ADKCtBZ"><s xml:id="_TSWTk2j">Anxiety, Depression, and Happiness Self-Ratings for Benign and Control Groups at Preworry Breathing Focus Period, Postworry,  and Postworry Breathing Focus Period</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Anxiety</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Depression</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Happiness</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Preworry</cell><cell></cell><cell>Postworry</cell><cell>Preworry</cell><cell></cell><cell>Postworry</cell><cell>Preworry</cell><cell></cell><cell>Postworry</cell></row><row><cell>Group</cell><cell cols="2">breathing focus Postworry</cell><cell>breathing focus</cell><cell cols="2">breathing focus Postworry</cell><cell>breathing focus</cell><cell cols="2">breathing focus Postworry</cell><cell>breathing focus</cell></row><row><cell>Benign</cell><cell>1.7 (2.0)</cell><cell>6.7 (2.5)</cell><cell>2.4 (2.3)</cell><cell>1.9 (2.5)</cell><cell>5.3 (3.1)</cell><cell>2.4 (2.6)</cell><cell>6.7 (2.5)</cell><cell>2.5 (2.2)</cell><cell>5.9 (2.6)</cell></row><row><cell>Control</cell><cell>3.6 (2.6)</cell><cell>6.7 (1.9)</cell><cell>3.7 (2.4)</cell><cell>1.9 (1.9)</cell><cell>4.3 (2.5)</cell><cell>2.9 (2.1)</cell><cell>5.0 (2.3)</cell><cell>2.6 (1.6)</cell><cell>5.0 (2.0)</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p xml:id="_TaTQqva"><s xml:id="_Zm3KwUU">This document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers.This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.</s></p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_1"><p xml:id="_ESYQwQ3"><s xml:id="_VjJGjwH">Any violations of sphericity were corrected using Greenhouse-Geisser adjustments.</s></p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_2"><p xml:id="_kJJUQf6"><s xml:id="_En2vhWB">For multiple post hoc t tests, Bonferroni corrections were used.48</s><s xml:id="_xNfryVE">HIRSCH, HAYES, AND MATHEWSThis document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers.This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.</s></p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="51" xml:id="foot_3"><p xml:id="_Qccn6nJ"><s xml:id="_7Tt8dNj">SPECIAL SECTION: ACCESSING BENIGN MEANINGS IN HIGH WORRIERSThis document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers.This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.</s></p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div xml:id="_GsFnT7V"><p xml:id="_d6TPpjG"><s xml:id="_ws5JNpe">This research was supported by a <rs type="funder">Medical Research Council</rs> grant.</s><s xml:id="_Xdmt6yg">We thank <rs type="person">Gemma Perman</rs> for recording the ambiguous scenarios and helping with some of the testing, <rs type="person">John Donaldson</rs> for writing the thought sampling program, and <rs type="person">Victoria Spalding</rs> and <rs type="person">Nicola Swan</rs> for completing the assessor ratings.</s></p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_R3KBrNh">Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Washington, DC</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Author</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>4th ed.</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">American Psychiatric Association. (1994). Diagnostic and statistical man- ual of mental disorders (4th ed.). Washington, DC: Author.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_7Enr3mr">Application of information theory to psychology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Attneave</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1959">1959</date>
			<publisher>Holt</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Attneave, F. (1959). Application of information theory to psychology. New York: Holt.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Da8RmWc">The capacity for generating information by randomization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Baddeley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_wTP4XRt">Quarterly Journal of Experimental Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="129" />
			<date type="published" when="1966">1966</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Baddeley, A. D. (1966). The capacity for generating information by ran- domization. Quarterly Journal of Experimental Psychology, 18, 119 - 129.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_kbCAeYd">Working memory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Baddeley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
			<publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Oxford, England</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Baddeley, A. D. (1986). Working memory. Oxford, England: Clarendon Press.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_8FM3mV5">Random generation and the executive control of working memory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Baddeley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Emslie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kolodny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Duncan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/713755788</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Xsju9HV">The Quarterly Journal of Experimental Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="819" to="852" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Baddeley, A., Emslie, H., Kolodny, J., &amp; Duncan, J. (1998). Random generation and the executive control of working memory. The Quarterly Journal of Experimental Psychology, 51A, 819 -852.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_t5fZGxB">The Speed of Comprehension Test: Version A</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Baddeley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Emslie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Nimmo-Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_DnGfY9g">Speed and Capacity of Language Processing Test</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Suffolk, England</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Thames Valley Test Company</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Baddeley, A., Emslie, H., &amp; Nimmo-Smith, I. (1992). The Speed of Comprehension Test: Version A. In Speed and Capacity of Language Processing Test. Suffolk, England: Thames Valley Test Company.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_BNJczqs">Working memory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Baddeley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hitch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0079-7421(08)60452-1</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_e9aFMJy">Recent advances in learning and motivation</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Bower</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Baddeley, A. D., &amp; Hitch, G. J. (1974). Working memory. In G. H. Bower (Ed.), Recent advances in learning and motivation. New York: Aca- demic Press.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_QYbSBZd">Reliability generalization of scores on the Spielberger State-Trait Anxiety Inventory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">L B</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Harp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Jung</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_FGFvZFg">Educational and Psychological Measurement</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="603" to="618" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Barnes, L. L. B., Harp, D., &amp; Jung, W. S. (2002). Reliability generalization of scores on the Spielberger State-Trait Anxiety Inventory. Educational and Psychological Measurement, 62, 603-618.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_etQYkQ5">The relation between worrying and concerns: The importance of perceived probability and cost</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Berenbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Pomerantz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.brat.2006.03.009</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Xjujc7k">Behaviour Research and Therapy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="301" to="311" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Berenbaum, H., Thompson, R. J., &amp; Pomerantz, E. M. (2007). The relation between worrying and concerns: The importance of perceived probabil- ity and cost. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 45, 301-311.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_4Cpra66">Cognitivebehavioral therapy for generalized anxiety disorder with integrations from interpersonal and experiential therapies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Borkovec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Newman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Castonguay</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_DpghVxg">CNS Spectrums</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="382" to="389" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Borkovec, T. D., Newman, M. G., &amp; Castonguay, L. G. (2003). Cognitive- behavioral therapy for generalized anxiety disorder with integrations from interpersonal and experiential therapies. CNS Spectrums, 8, 382- 389.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_JXnVtkw">Preliminary exploration of worry: Some characteristics and processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Borkovec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Pruzinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Depree</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0005-7967(83)90121-3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_f2zvzbD">Behaviour Research and Therapy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Borkovec, T. D., Robinson, E., Pruzinsky, T., &amp; DePree, J. A. (1983). Preliminary exploration of worry: Some characteristics and processes. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 21, 9 -16.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_gp3bv7B">Perceived functions of worry among generalized anxiety disorder subjects: Distraction from more emotionally distressing topics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Borkovec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Roemer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0005-7916(94)00064-s</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_9RVvSJD">Journal of Behavior Therapy and Experimental Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Borkovec, T. D., &amp; Roemer, L. (1995). Perceived functions of worry among generalized anxiety disorder subjects: Distraction from more emotionally distressing topics? Journal of Behavior Therapy and Ex- perimental Psychiatry, 26, 25-30.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_wssw9Ym">Psychometric properties of the Penn State Worry Questionnaire in a clinical anxiety disorders sample</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Antony</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Barlow</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_FvwKbXC">Behaviour Research and Therapy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="37" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Brown, T. A., Antony, M. M., &amp; Barlow, D. H. (1992). Psychometric properties of the Penn State Worry Questionnaire in a clinical anxiety disorders sample. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 30, 33-37.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Di Nardo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Barlow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_FFBeVPR">Anxiety Disorders Interview Schedule for DSM-IV (ADIS-IV)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Antonio, TX</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>The Psychological Corporation</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Brown, T. A., Di Nardo, P. A., &amp; Barlow, D. H. (1994). Anxiety Disorders Interview Schedule for DSM-IV (ADIS-IV). San Antonio, TX: The Psy- chological Corporation.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_7UWZy2H">Cognitive therapy versus exposure and applied relaxation in social phobia: A randomized controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ehlers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hackman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mcmanus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fennell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Grey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Waddington</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wild</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/0022-006x.74.3.568</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_nDTyBuZ">Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="568" to="578" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Clark, D. M., Ehlers, A., Hackman, A., McManus, F., Fennell, M., Grey, N., Waddington, L., &amp; Wild, J. (2006). Cognitive therapy versus expo- sure and applied relaxation in social phobia: A randomized controlled trial. Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology, 74, 568 -578.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_TzbxdSq">A comparison of three worry questionnaires</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Davey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0005-7967(93)90042-s</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_HX555Yh">Behaviour Research and Therapy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="56" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Davey, G. C. (1993). A comparison of three worry questionnaires. Behav- iour Research and Therapy, 31, 51-56.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_wQtxkxr">A mood-as-input account of perseverative worrying</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">C L</forename><surname>Davey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_rKuN2Sa">Worry and its psychological disorders: Theory, assessment and treatment</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">C L</forename><surname>Davey</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wells</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Hoboken, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="217" to="237" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Davey, G. C. L. (2006). A mood-as-input account of perseverative worry- ing. In G. C. L. Davey &amp; A. Wells (Eds.), Worry and its psychological disorders: Theory, assessment and treatment (pp. 217-237). Hoboken, NJ: Wiley.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_PDdvafg">Beeper program software</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Donaldson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/springerreference_8856</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Donaldson, J. (2004). Beeper program software. London.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_AefkC6E">Generalized anxiety disorder: A preliminary test of a conceptual model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Dugas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Gagnon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ladouceur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Freeston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0005-7967(97)00070-3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_WmKwwf6">Behaviour Research and Therapy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="226" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Dugas, M. J., Gagnon, F., Ladouceur, R., &amp; Freeston, M. H. (1998). Generalized anxiety disorder: A preliminary test of a conceptual model. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 36, 215-226.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Eysenck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_KKTW7mW">Attention and arousal: Cognition and performance</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Eysenck, M. W. (1982). Attention and arousal: Cognition and perfor- mance. Berlin: Springer.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_R4gVt57">Anxiety and performance: The processing efficiency theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Eysenck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Calvo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/02699939208409696</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_NQjCuWS">Cognition and Emotion</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="409" to="434" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Eysenck, M. W., &amp; Calvo, M. G. (1992). Anxiety and performance: The processing efficiency theory. Cognition and Emotion, 6, 409 -434.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_bfYxGbR">Cognitive functioning and anxiety</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Eysenck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Macleod</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mathews</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_88Q7CWN">Psychological Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="189" to="195" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Eysenck, M. W., MacLeod, C., &amp; Mathews, A. (1987). Cognitive func- tioning and anxiety. Psychological Research, 49, 189 -195.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_NcR5ewv">Bias in interpretation of ambiguous sentences related to threat in anxiety</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Eysenck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Mogg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>May</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Richards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mathews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/0021-843x.100.2.144</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_EERf8f9">Journal of Abnormal Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="144" to="150" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Eysenck, M. W., Mogg, K., May, J., Richards, A., &amp; Mathews, A. (1991). Bias in interpretation of ambiguous sentences related to threat in anxiety. Journal of Abnormal Psychology, 100, 144 -150.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_DWJKYQP">Effects of training on interpretation of emotional ambiguity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Grey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mathews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/02724980050156335</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_X2bYfFD">Quarterly Journal of Experimental Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1143" to="1162" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Grey, S., &amp; Mathews, A. (2000). Effects of training on interpretation of emotional ambiguity. Quarterly Journal of Experimental Psychology, 53A, 1143-1162.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_YgqtsNt">Restriction of working memory capacity during worry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hayes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hirsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mathews</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_DS4hxrH">Journal of Abnormal Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="712" to="717" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hayes, S., Hirsch, C. R., &amp; Mathews, A. (2008). Restriction of working memory capacity during worry. Journal of Abnormal Psychology, 117, 712-717.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_hB4QmHR">Interpretative inferences when reading about emotional events</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hirsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mathews</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_uFSAyj5">Behaviour Research and Therapy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1123" to="1132" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hirsch, C. R., &amp; Mathews, A. (1997). Interpretative inferences when reading about emotional events. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 12, 1123-1132.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_YeweqJZ">Impaired positive inferential bias in social phobia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hirsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mathews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037//0021-843x.109.4.705</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Wh84tx9">Journal of Abnormal Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="705" to="712" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hirsch, C. R., &amp; Mathews, A. (2000). Impaired positive inferential bias in social phobia. Journal of Abnormal Psychology, 109, 705-712.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_4dBqAVd">Inducing an interpretation bias changes self-imagery: A preliminary investigation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hirsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mathews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_CsRWKNp">Behaviour Research and Therapy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2173" to="2181" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hirsch, C. R., Mathews, A., &amp; Clark, D. (2007). Inducing an interpretation bias changes self-imagery: A preliminary investigation. Behaviour Re- search and Therapy, 45, 2173-2181.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_CsAaw9N">Negative self-imagery blocks inferences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hirsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mathews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Morrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_GEuQjXc">Behaviour Research and Therapy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1383" to="1396" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hirsch, C. R., Mathews, A., Clark, D. M., Williams, R., &amp; Morrison, J. (2003). Negative self-imagery blocks inferences. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 41, 1383-1396.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_g3cGdma">Mental imagery and emotion: A special relationship?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Holmes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mathews</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Q3TEwFs">Emotion</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="489" to="497" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Holmes, E. A., &amp; Mathews, A. (2005). Mental imagery and emotion: A special relationship? Emotion, 5, 489 -497.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_b4r8aRn">Positive interpretation training: Effects of mental imagery versus verbal training on positive mood</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Holmes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mathews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Dalgleish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mackintosh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.beth.2006.02.002</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_zuXqPzx">Behaviour Therapy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="237" to="247" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Holmes, E. A., Mathews, A., Dalgleish, T., &amp; Mackintosh, B. (2006). Positive interpretation training: Effects of mental imagery versus verbal training on positive mood. Behaviour Therapy, 37, 237-247.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_HAZAH83">Interpretation biases in social anxiety: Response generation, response selection, and self-appraisals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Huppert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Pasupuleti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Foa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mathews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.brat.2007.01.006</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ZHZsjrK">Behaviour Research and Therapy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1505" to="1515" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Huppert, J. D., Pasupuleti, R. V., Foa, E. B., &amp; Mathews, A. (2007). Interpretation biases in social anxiety: Response generation, response selection, and self-appraisals. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 45, 1505-1515.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_bkaFDuU">Anxiety and the interpretation of ambiguity: A text comprehension study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Macleod</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037//0021-843x.102.2.238</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_qhFFx8j">Journal of Abnormal Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="238" to="247" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">MacLeod, C., &amp; Cohen, I. L. (1993). Anxiety and the interpretation of ambiguity: A text comprehension study. Journal of Abnormal Psychol- ogy, 102, 238 -247.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_SsdDWbH">Attentional bias in emotional disorders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Macleod</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mathews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Tata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037//0021-843x.95.1.15</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_3JQ6t5m">Journal of Abnormal Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">MacLeod, C., Mathews, A., &amp; Tata, P. (1986). Attentional bias in emo- tional disorders. Journal of Abnormal Psychology, 95, 15-20.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_gE93Zrp">Why worry? The cognitive function of anxiety</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mathews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0005-7967(90)90132-3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_dxkGDJt">Behaviour Research and Therapy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="455" to="468" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mathews, A. (1990). Why worry? The cognitive function of anxiety. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 28, 455-468.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_XZa5UAz">Induced emotional interpretation bias and anxiety</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mathews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mackintosh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037//0021-843x.109.4.602</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_RduDvYm">Journal of Abnormal Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="602" to="615" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mathews, A., &amp; Mackintosh, B. (2000). Induced emotional interpretation bias and anxiety. Journal of Abnormal Psychology, 109, 602-615.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_xeu64EY">Cognitive approaches to emotion and emotional disorders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mathews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Macleod</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1146/annurev.ps.45.020194.000325</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_yx5fwj4">Annual Review of Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="50" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mathews, A., &amp; MacLeod, C. (1994). Cognitive approaches to emotion and emotional disorders. Annual Review of Psychology, 45, 25-50.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_sZAgVBZ">Effects of priming and suppression of worry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mathews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Milroy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0005-7967(94)90164-3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_jyjgpQS">Behaviour Research and Therapy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="843" to="850" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mathews, A., &amp; Milroy, R. (1994). Effects of priming and suppression of worry. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 32, 843-850.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_bkvjjfd">Interpretation of homophones related to threat in anxiety states</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mathews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Richards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Eysenck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037//0021-843x.98.1.31</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_JPMDQ7N">Journal of Abnormal Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="34" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mathews, A., Richards, A., &amp; Eysenck, M. (1989). Interpretation of ho- mophones related to threat in anxiety states. Journal of Abnormal Psychology, 98, 31-34.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_hbmHnyq">Inducing a benign interpretational bias reduces trait anxiety</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mathews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Ridgeway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yiend</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_nhBCJW2">Journal of Behavior Therapy and Experimental Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="225" to="236" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mathews, A., Ridgeway, V., Cook, E., &amp; Yiend, J. (2007). Inducing a benign interpretational bias reduces trait anxiety. Journal of Behavior Therapy and Experimental Psychiatry, 38, 225-236.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_5BFKyTT">Development and validation of the Penn State Worry Questionnaire</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Metzger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Borkovec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0005-7967(90)90135-6</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_U4s9b6V">Behaviour Research and Therapy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="487" to="495" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Meyer, T. J., Miller, M. L., Metzger, R. L., &amp; Borkovec, T. D. (1990). Development and validation of the Penn State Worry Questionnaire. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 28, 487-495.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_VEKk6H7">Interpretation of homophones related to threat: Anxiety or response bias effects?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Mogg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Bradley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Potts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/bf02357754</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_kxPuGY4">Cognitive Therapy and Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="461" to="477" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mogg, K., Bradley, B. P., Miller, T., Potts, H., et. al. (1994). Interpretation of homophones related to threat: Anxiety or response bias effects? Cognitive Therapy and Research, 18, 461-477.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_nQ9v6by">The Penn State Worry Questionnaire: Psychometric properties and associated characteristics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Molina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Borkovec</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_tNsGufX">Worrying: Perspectives on theory, assessment and treatment</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">C L</forename><surname>Davey</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Tallis</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Oxford, England</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="283" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Molina, S., &amp; Borkovec, T. D. (1994). The Penn State Worry Question- naire: Psychometric properties and associated characteristics. In G. C. L. Davey &amp; F. Tallis (Eds.), Worrying: Perspectives on theory, assessment and treatment (pp. 265-283). Oxford, England: Wiley.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_gtaRK5J">Facilitating a benign interpretation bias in a high socially anxious population</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hirsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mathews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_SDsCctn">Behaviour Research and Therapy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1517" to="1529" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Murphy, R., Hirsch, C., Mathews, A., Smith, K., &amp; Clark, D. M. (2007). Facilitating a benign interpretation bias in a high socially anxious population. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 45, 1517-1529.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_zjhFnNS">Preliminary reliability and validity of the Generalized Anxiety Disorder Questionnaire-IV: A revised self-report diagnostic measure of generalized anxiety disorder</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Newman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Zuellig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Kachin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Constantino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Przeworski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Erickson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cashman-Mcgrath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0005-7894(02)80026-0</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_H2k6nRg">Behavior Therapy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="233" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Newman, M. G., Zuellig, A. R., Kachin, K. E., Constantino, M. J., Przeworski, A., Erickson, T., &amp; Cashman-McGrath, L. (2002). Prelim- inary reliability and validity of the Generalized Anxiety Disorder Ques- tionnaire-IV: A revised self-report diagnostic measure of generalized anxiety disorder. Behavior Therapy, 33, 215-233.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_3shuukk">E-Prime (Version 1.1)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Pittsburgh, PA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Author</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Psychology Software Tools. (2002). E-Prime (Version 1.1). Pittsburgh, PA: Author.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Qq48Ddr">An anxiety-related bias in semantic activation when processing threat/neutral homographs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Richards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>French</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/02724989208250625</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Hgg4vP5">The Quarterly Journal of Experimental Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="503" to="525" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Richards, A., &amp; French, C. C. (1992). An anxiety-related bias in semantic activation when processing threat/neutral homographs. The Quarterly Journal of Experimental Psychology, 45, 503-525.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_cAKzw4W">Experience and appraisal of worry among high worriers with and without generalized anxiety disorder</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ruscio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Borkovec</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_DwSZzBF">Behaviour Research and Therapy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1469" to="1482" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ruscio, A. M., &amp; Borkovec, T. D. (2004). Experience and appraisal of worry among high worriers with and without generalized anxiety disor- der. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 42, 1469 -1482.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_dswX7fm">The cognitive avoidance theory of worry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sibrava</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Borkovec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/9780470713143.ch14</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_eDHkaFS">Worry and its psychological disorders: Theory, assessment and treatment</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">C L</forename><surname>Davey</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wells</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Hoboken, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="239" to="256" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sibrava, N. J., &amp; Borkovec, T. D. (2006). The cognitive avoidance theory of worry. In G. C. L. Davey &amp; A. Wells (Eds.), Worry and its psycho- logical disorders: Theory, assessment and treatment (pp. 239 -256). Hoboken, NJ: Wiley.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Spielberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gorsuch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lushene</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Vagg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Jacobs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.53841/bpstest.2003.stai</idno>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_Cwzt7eZ">Manual for the State Trait Anxiety Inventory</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Palo Alto, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Consulting Psychologists Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Spielberger, C. D., Gorsuch, R. C., Lushene, R. E., Vagg, P. R., &amp; Jacobs, G. A. (1983). Manual for the State Trait Anxiety Inventory. Palo Alto, CA: Consulting Psychologists Press.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_PnPnvGv">The Worry Domains Questionnaire</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Tallis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">C L</forename><surname>Davey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bond</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_9jpF83y">Worrying: Per-spectives on theory, assessment and treatment</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">C L</forename><surname>Davey</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Tallis</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Oxford, England</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="285" to="297" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Tallis, F., Davey, G. C. L., &amp; Bond, A. (1994). The Worry Domains Questionnaire. In G. C. L. Davey &amp; F. Tallis (Eds.), Worrying: Per- spectives on theory, assessment and treatment (pp. 285-297). Oxford, England: Wiley.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Mz8JAMq">On random generation and the central executive of working memory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Towse</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_zWJqspj">British Journal of Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="101" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Towse, J. N. (1998). On random generation and the central executive of working memory. British Journal of Psychology, 89, 77-101.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_WreD2qj">Analyzing human random generation behavior: A review of methods used and a computer program for describing performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Towse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Neil</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_6auJQ34">Behavior Research Methods, Instruments, &amp; Computers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="583" to="591" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Towse, J. N., &amp; Neil, D. (1998). Analyzing human random generation behavior: A review of methods used and a computer program for describing performance. Behavior Research Methods, Instruments, &amp; Computers, 30, 583-591.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_5yx3tcy">A catastrophizing assessment of worrisome thoughts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Vasey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Borkovec</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_WtSUuPY">Cognitive Therapy and Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Vasey, M. W., &amp; Borkovec, T. D. (1992). A catastrophizing assessment of worrisome thoughts. Cognitive Therapy and Research, 16, 1-16.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_5QazmHR">Meta-cognition and worry: A cognitive model of generalized anxiety disorder</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wells</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_2NP85jJ">Behavioural and Cognitive Psychotherapy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="301" to="320" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Wells, A. (1995). Meta-cognition and worry: A cognitive model of gen- eralized anxiety disorder. Behavioural and Cognitive Psychotherapy, 23, 301-320.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_U94sn2j">The causal role of interpretive bias in anxiety reactivity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Macleod</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mathews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rutherford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_7rswmha">Journal of Abnormal Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="103" to="111" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Wilson, E., MacLeod, C., Mathews, A., &amp; Rutherford, E. M. (2006). The causal role of interpretive bias in anxiety reactivity. Journal of Abnormal Psychology, 115, 103-111.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
