<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_mBfw5mD">An experimental design for the development of adaptive treatment strategies</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Center for Prevention Methodology)</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_DgMd6fw #_CVJSJTm">
					<orgName type="full">National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA Independent Scientist</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
					<p type="raw">Copyright ? 2004 John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. Copyright ? 2004 John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. Copyright ? 2004 Copyright ? 2004 Copyright ? 2004 Copyright ? 2004</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2004-12-07">7 December 2004</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
							<email>samurphy@umich.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Department of Statistics ; Institute for Social Research ; University of Michigan ; Ann Arbor ; MI ; U.S.A.</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Statistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute for Social Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Michigan</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Ann Arbor</settlement>
									<region>MI</region>
									<country key="US">U.S.A</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Department of Statistics , Institute for Social Research , University of Michigan , Ann Arbor , MI , U.S.A.</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Statistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute for Social Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Michigan</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Ann Arbor</settlement>
									<region>MI</region>
									<country key="US">U.S.A</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Rax4GaT">An experimental design for the development of adaptive treatment strategies</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2004-12-07">7 December 2004</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">1120697BC5EBCECA5665A88DAC654981</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1002/sim.2022</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received July 2003 Accepted July 2004</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T13:37+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term xml:id="_CYDRT7e">therapeutic strategies</term>
					<term xml:id="_rMp6jDc">treatment algorithms</term>
					<term xml:id="_nR7WfPJ">sequential multiple assignment randomized trial</term>
					<term xml:id="_fbHpFfn">multi-stage decision problems</term>
					<term xml:id="_EhC3QJR">dynamic treatment regimes</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_Mxz9HbX"><p xml:id="_FDvAdJW"><s xml:id="_YDdHQFu">In adaptive treatment strategies, the treatment level and type is repeatedly adjusted according to ongoing individual response.</s><s xml:id="_FwSVK9V">Since past treatment may have delayed e ects, the development of these treatment strategies is challenging.</s><s xml:id="_dcaGQsU">This paper advocates the use of sequential multiple assignment randomized trials in the development of adaptive treatment strategies.</s><s xml:id="_qZHuAJE">Both a simple ad hoc method for ascertaining sample sizes and simple analysis methods are provided.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="10" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="11" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="12" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="13" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="14" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="15" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="16" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="17" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="18" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="19" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="20" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="21" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="22" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="23" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="24" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="25" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="26" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
		<surface n="27" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="567.0" lry="737.0"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1." xml:id="_qpz87bt">INTRODUCTION</head><p xml:id="_tEBHTJn"><s xml:id="_wG5pnNc">Adaptive treatment strategies are emerging as a new paradigm for the treatment and long term management of chronic, relapsing disorders such as alcoholism, smoking cessation, cocaine abuse, depression and hypertension <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[7]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_P6CSXcr">In adaptive treatment strategies the treatment level and type is repeatedly adjusted according to the individual's need.</s><s xml:id="_CaFCA2Z">The rationale is that the response is optimized by varying treatment type and dosage as a function of measures of timedependent information such as response to past treatment.</s><s xml:id="_DUw2Fpf">An adaptive treatment strategy is characterized by a sequence of decision rules, one per treatment decision.</s><s xml:id="_MNYx35r">Adaptive treatment strategies are frequently called dynamic treatment regimes <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[13]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_znNjpQk"><s xml:id="_Qdfc5dS">Currently scientists use a combination of clinical experience, trial and error, behavioural, psychosocial and biological theories, results from observational studies and randomized experimental studies conducted for other purposes, to formulate the decision rules composing adaptive treatment strategies.</s><s xml:id="_WJnFCEf">In this paper we propose the use of experimental trials for the development of the decision rules.</s><s xml:id="_uk3dbhV">Our long term goal is to optimize the adaptive treatment strategies, that is produce a treatment strategy that yields the best mean value of the outcome.</s><s xml:id="_5QbDCKH">We concentrate on a major challenge, that of delayed e ects, to designing randomized trials in this setting.</s><s xml:id="_uE8Vnuz">We propose the use of sequential multiple assignment randomized (SMAR) trials for developing decision rules as these trials do not make a priori assumptions on the existence or form of the delayed e ects.</s><s xml:id="_zZW5wEa">In a SMAR trial, each individual may be randomized multiple times; the multiple randomizations occur sequentially through time.</s></p><p xml:id="_DBfmhcf"><s xml:id="_mhMWUhM">A number of SMAR trials have been or are being conducted.</s><s xml:id="_hAypkrh">These include the CATIE trial for antipsychotic medications in patients with Alzheimer's <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[14]</ref>, the CATIE trial for antipsychotic medications in patients with Schizophrenia, STAR*D for treatment of depression <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">16]</ref> and phase II trials at MD Anderson for treating cancer <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[17]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_Wn7vWWK">In most cases the goals of these trials are to develop adaptive treatment strategies (sequences of treatments for an individual) and are not conÿrmatory.</s><s xml:id="_xWznn3E">That is, the goal does not include conÿrming that one adaptive treatment strategy is better than control or standard treatment.</s><s xml:id="_fQqcKCQ">Conÿrmatory trials comparing an optimized adaptive treatment strategy with the appropriate control or standard treatment would follow such studies.</s></p><p xml:id="_QnQWky9"><s xml:id="_hWzxbzK">To ÿx ideas we use the following simpliÿed example throughout.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_gcs2Gf6">Example</head><p xml:id="_bm8CbQZ"><s xml:id="_BrydEXW">Consider an addiction management study for alcohol dependent subjects.</s><s xml:id="_ZVVrNZw">In this simple example there are only two decisions, choosing the initial treatment and the secondary treatment.</s><s xml:id="_RtEsdUV">Following an intensive outpatient program, alcohol dependent subjects may be prescribed either an opiate antagonist (med with low level of counselling) or intensive cognitive behavioural therapy (cbt).</s><s xml:id="_AbTqPZT">Then in the next two months clinicians record heavy drinking, adherence, self-management skill and other intermediate outcomes.</s><s xml:id="_zGcZjWT">Individuals are classiÿed as responders or non-responders based on their level of heavy drinking.</s><s xml:id="_NErYmFV">Note that the terms responder/non-responder refer to the level of heavy drinking while the individual is on the initial treatment.</s><s xml:id="_yh5e7nq">If an individual is a non-responder to med then we must decide whether to either switch to cbt or assign an enhanced motivational program with a step up(em+cbt +med).</s><s xml:id="_6rNBYwU">If an individual is a non-responder to cbt then we must decide whether to switch to med or provide the step-up in treatment, em + cbt + med.</s><s xml:id="_vRc8g4G">Responders to the initial treatment should be assigned either to telephone monitoring (tm) or telephone counselling and monitoring (tmc).</s><s xml:id="_mpgXM2u">The goal in the decision making is to formulate an adaptive treatment strategy that results in the highest per cent of days abstinent over a one year period.</s><s xml:id="_Kaby5TF">We seek two decision rules that will maximize the mean per cent days abstinent over the deÿned period.</s><s xml:id="_2xgTXE6">The ÿrst decision rule can use pretreatment information such as level of addiction to choose the initial treatment.</s><s xml:id="_nKr2cnG">The second decision rule can utilize intermediate outcomes such as adherence to initial treatment, present level of self-management skill and number of heavy drinking days while on initial treatment to choose the second treatment.</s><s xml:id="_CrxtRj3">ticular primary analysis; associated with this analysis is a simple approach for ascertaining the sample size.</s><s xml:id="_Er9HYut">Lastly we provide an simulation based evaluation of our sample size formula and in the discussion section we discuss methods and areas that need further scientiÿc development.</s></p><p xml:id="_TBNQRk5"><s xml:id="_79TusdZ">Note that the term 'adaptive' as used here refers to a time-varying therapy for managing a chronic, relapsing illness rather than an experimental design.</s><s xml:id="_DTMzrP6">This should not be confused with 'adaptive' experimental designs such as designs in which treatment allocation probabilities for the present patient depend on the responses of past patients References <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">19]</ref> nor should this be confused with two stage adaptive experimental designs in which design parameters of an experimental trial are altered mid-trial <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">21]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2." xml:id="_j84bctJ">ADAPTIVE TREATMENT STRATEGIES</head><p xml:id="_rNYasTV"><s xml:id="_H94wadY">Suppose we will need to make at most k decisions, a 1 ; a 2 ; : : : ; a k per individual.</s><s xml:id="_scz6zjJ">S 1 denotes pretreatment information whereas S j , j6k denotes the intermediate outcome (ongoing information) available after decision a j-1 and prior to decision a j .</s><s xml:id="_54QJ27h">Thus the time order is S 1 ; a 1 ; S 2 ; a 2 ; : : : ; S k ; a k ; S k+1 .</s><s xml:id="_XsuFXdh">We use an overbar to denote past and present information (e.g. S j = {S 1 ; : : : S j }).</s><s xml:id="_Xsn9MZv">The primary outcome is Y = u( S k+1 ; a k ) where u is a known summary function.</s><s xml:id="_HPMnC9g">In the addiction management study, Y is the mean per cent days abstinent so u counts the number of days abstinent and divides by study length in days.</s><s xml:id="_7YxX3fT">An adaptive treatment strategy is a sequence of decision rules, one per decision.</s><s xml:id="_JFraCPF">Thus we denote an adaptive treatment strategy by the decision rules {d 1 ; d 2 ; : : : ; d k } where the decision rule d j takes the information available at time j ( S j = {S 1 ; : : : ; S j } and past treatment a j-1 = {a 1 ; : : : ; a j-1 }) and outputs a treatment type/level, a j .</s><s xml:id="_ehz7kGH">For example in the addiction management study, k = 2 and the possible treatments, values for a 1 , at the ÿrst decision time point are med and cbt.</s><s xml:id="_au6aAUz">The information available for making the second decision includes pretreatment information denoted by S 1 , the ÿrst treatment, and the intermediate outcomes denoted by S 2 .</s><s xml:id="_7VpdcQH">A simple example of a decision rule, d 2 , is: if the individual responds to initial treatment assign telephone monitoring with counselling or if the individual does not respond to initial treatment assign em + med + cbt.</s></p><p xml:id="_ASHKtsY"><s xml:id="_6YrjPC8">As discussed in the introduction, the goal is to develop an adaptive treatment strategy that leads to the highest mean of Y (as compared to other possible adaptive treatment strategies).</s><s xml:id="_mD3C8dy">If we knew the multivariate distribution of S k+1 for each array of treatments a k , then this goal would be easily achieved.</s><s xml:id="_yb5NngA">In this case, the ascertainment of the optimal or best adaptive treatment strategy is an optimization problem treated at great length by many authors <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[23]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[24]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_wX9yMky">Classical algorithms use dynamic programming which is based on a backwards induction argument.</s><s xml:id="_7nhztn5">We denote the optimal adaptive treatment strategy by {d * 1 (s 1 ); d * 2 ( s 2 ; a 1 ); : : : ; d * k ( s k ; a k-1 )}.</s><s xml:id="_uzGD857">Below we review the formulae for the optimal adaptive treatment strategy when k = 2; the formula for general k is similar <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[24]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_GrVwAJB"><s xml:id="_cQutVEm">The optimal decision at time 2 maximizes</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">E a2 [Y | S 2 ] over a 2 . Note that E a2 [Y | S 2 ]</formula><p xml:id="_9fFeYRP"><s xml:id="_Mc5uzTr">is the conditional mean of Y given S 2 when the treatment decisions are set at a 2 .</s><s xml:id="_cxgX4ya">The optimal decision is given by</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_1">d * 2 ( s 2 ; a 1 ) = arg max a2 E a2 [Y | S 2 = s 2 ] (1) S. A. MURPHY Deÿne V 2 ( s 2 ; a 1 ) = max a2 E a2 [Y | S 2 = s 2 ]</formula><p xml:id="_wHxJecQ"><s xml:id="_w3wCaK5">Intuitively V 2 is the highest mean of Y achievable given that we are at time 2, have made the previous decision, a 1 and have recorded information s 2 .</s><s xml:id="_bBThx38">V 2 is called the optimal beneÿt-to-go at time 2. The optimal decision at time 1 is</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_2">d * 1 (s 1 ) = arg max a1 E a1 [V 2 ( S 2 ; a 1 )|S 1 = s 1 ]<label>(2)</label></formula><p xml:id="_tqgwMnD"><s xml:id="_KqcGaXR">That is we integrate the optimal beneÿt to go at time 2 over the conditional distribution of S 2 given S 1 for treatment a 1 and then maximize.</s><s xml:id="_Fedw5eW">The optimal beneÿt-to-go at time 1 is given by</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_3">V 1 (s 1 ) = max a1 E a1 [V 2 ( S 2 ; a 1 )|S 1 = s 1 ]</formula><p xml:id="_JuE74Vy"><s xml:id="_XAvhtgD">The mean of Y when the optimal rules are used to assign treatment (set</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_4">a 1 = d * 1 (S 1 ); a 2 = d * 2 ( S 2 ; a 1 )</formula><p xml:id="_Kr88ZUK"><s xml:id="_6VzgKS9">) is given by the expected optimal beneÿt-to-go at time 1:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_5">E[V 1 (S 1 )] = E max a1 E a1 max a2 E a2 [Y | S 2 ]|S 1<label>(3)</label></formula><p xml:id="_4cey6pA"><s xml:id="_RrqcUHD">The optimal adaptive treatment strategy is (d * 1 ; d * 2 ).</s><s xml:id="_R9njmcQ">Observe that to obtain the optimal decision at time 2, we use the previously obtained optimal decision at time 1.</s></p><p xml:id="_HdGgxYt"><s xml:id="_Ztyjm8N">The above formulae are imprecise because we did not indicate the set of possible treatments over which each max aj is formed.</s><s xml:id="_xJW5CMU">In general the set of treatments is not the same for each time point and in addition past S j 's may restrict the set of possible treatments.</s><s xml:id="_V3Ete48">In the addiction management study, the possible treatments at time 1 are med and cbt.</s><s xml:id="_AyjQKRP">But at time 2 the possible treatments depend on response to initial treatment.</s></p><p xml:id="_HQ4FVzC"><s xml:id="_VsX7GJj">In this paper the multivariate distribution of S k+1 indexed by the treatments a k is unknown; thus we cannot directly use the arguments given above to develop an optimal adaptive treatment strategy.</s><s xml:id="_9aZ6DBt">Our goal is to propose experimental trials that will yield data for the formulation of an optimal adaptive treatment strategy.</s><s xml:id="_tnExBc5">First we discuss the issue of delayed e ects; this will motivate the design of the experimental trial.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3." xml:id="_Xwt4KsP">DELAYED EFFECTS</head><p xml:id="_Bt957FX"><s xml:id="_KDTd9br">In this section, we discuss why we want to observe intermediate and long term outcomes following each possible pattern of treatments across time; this motivates our design proposal of randomizing each individual multiple times.</s><s xml:id="_wZqQjAz">For clarity, we temporarily ignore sample variability and focus on correctly estimating which initial and subsequent treatments are best.</s><s xml:id="_nC4m6hT">Thus we use expectations rather than sample averages below.</s><s xml:id="_cTJcJtg">Once we have justiÿed why it is important to observe intermediate and long term outcomes following each possible pattern of treatments we consider sampling issues (see the following sections).</s></p><p xml:id="_ktfY8JS"><s xml:id="_extHzU2">For simplicity consider k = 2. Recall that the optimal rule for assigning treatment at time two is the output of arg max a2 E a2 [Y | S 2 = s 2 ].</s><s xml:id="_5NZ8Sxy">Certainly if this rule yields di erent secondary treatments depending on the initial treatment then in order to estimate the best secondary treatment we need to observe outcomes following each pattern of initial and secondary treatments.</s><s xml:id="_GefFYVK">Also estimating the best initial treatment may require outcomes following each pattern of initial and secondary treatments.</s><s xml:id="_eGye54V">To see this consider the criterion function for ascertaining the best decision at time 1 (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>) and note that this criterion function depends on the optimal decision at time 2. To ascertain the ÿrst decision we must maximize</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_6">E a1 max a2 E a2 [Y | S 2 ]|S 1 = s 1 = s2 max a2 E a2 [Y | S 2 = s 2 ]f a1 (s 2 |s 1 )</formula><p xml:id="_MVGHWkJ"><s xml:id="_En2YV4E">ds 2 (4) over a 1 (note f a1 (s 2 |s 1 ) is the conditional density of S 2 given S 1 indexed by a 1 ).</s><s xml:id="_xUdQ4FC">Thus a 1 plays a role in the criterion function (4), both through the product of the density f a1 (s 2 |s 1 ) and the maximized conditional mean max a2 E a2 [Y | S 2 = s 2 ].</s><s xml:id="_yWT9eDN">Thus if max a2 E a2 [Y | S 2 = s 2 ] depends on a 1 then in general to estimate the best initial treatment we need to observe intermediate and long term outcomes following each possible pattern of {a 1 ; a 2 }.</s><s xml:id="_BR2ZT2C">Certainly a treatment a 1 that produces very good values of S 2 (e.g.</s><s xml:id="_NgFnbKC">optimizes the mean of the density f a1 (s 2 |s 1 )) may not be the best initial treatment in an adaptive treatment strategy.</s><s xml:id="_NybCPFv">We have argued that if max a2 E a2 [Y | S 2 = s 2 ] depends on a 1 then in general to estimate the best initial treatment we need to observe intermediate and long term outcomes following each possible pattern of {a 1 ; a 2 }.</s><s xml:id="_fqChVEZ">One way in which the maximized conditional mean, max a2</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_7">E a2 [Y | S 2 = s 2 ]</formula><p xml:id="_qBucNys"><s xml:id="_4zVMCWJ">, may depend on a 1 is if the e ect of treatment at time 2 varies by the initial treatment (an interaction between initial and secondary treatments on the primary outcome, Y ).</s><s xml:id="_MXd5hVb">There are at least two ways in which the e ect of treatment at time 2 varies by the initial treatment.</s><s xml:id="_cTb7E2r">We discuss these two ways in the context of our simple addiction management study.</s><s xml:id="_7Yhhx2w">First a particular initial treatment may set the stage for an enhanced e ect by a particular secondary treatment.</s><s xml:id="_GqY6Zxa">For example, suppose counselling is more e ective than monitoring among responders to cbt; that is the individual learns to use counselling during cbt and thus is able to take advantage of the counselling o ered to responders.</s><s xml:id="_NaJeCBd">Individuals who received med during the initial treatment will not have learned to use counselling and thus among responders to med the addition of counselling to the monitoring does not improve abstinence (Y ) relative to monitoring alone.</s><s xml:id="_yDcT5Mh">If an individual is a responder to cbt it is best to o er tmc as the secondary treatment, but if the individual is a responder to med it is best to o er the less expensive tm as the secondary treatment.</s><s xml:id="_ukbSUYB">In summary even if cbt and med result in the same proportion of responders, cbt may be the best initial treatment as part of the adaptive treatment strategy.</s><s xml:id="_W8EmYEG">This would be due to the enhanced e ect of tmc when preceded by cbt.</s></p><p xml:id="_TwvzPj7"><s xml:id="_X8DDfzF">A second way in which the e ect of secondary treatment varies by the initial treatment is a consequence of Berkson's fallacy <ref type="bibr">[25, p. 73]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_aTtyh4K">Suppose that there is an unknown factor U that a ects one's ability to respond to treatment.</s><s xml:id="_pBGywQq">Here we conceptualize this factor as level of structure in one's life; U = H if highly structured environment and U = L if chaotic environment.</s><s xml:id="_fThd3eC">We can expect that U is positively related to the intermediate outcome of responder/non-responder status and also U is positively related to Y , per cent days abstinent.</s><s xml:id="_9WEcbxr">Suppose also that the initial treatments have di ering e ects on responder/non-responder status.</s><s xml:id="_KpsEJ5x">Berkson's fallacy is the conditional correlation between U and initial treatment assignment given non-response to initial treatment.</s><s xml:id="_Fbps4du">Intuitively a non-responder who received the better initial treatment is more likely to live in a chaotic environment.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_6reXhnx">S. A. MURPHY</head><p xml:id="_hF6ErBr"><s xml:id="_gFku3Ht">The following numerical example illustrates how Berkson's fallacy results in an interaction of secondary and initial treatments on outcome Y .</s><s xml:id="_rjHPS4R">Suppose the following relationship holds among non-responders:</s></p><p xml:id="_tNZqSNQ"><s xml:id="_dmyYrDM">Mean of Y among non-responders by secondary treatment and given structure of environment,</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_8">E a1; a2 [Y |S 2 = NR; U ] U = H (highly structured) U = L (chaotic) a 2 = switch 20 15 a 2 = step -up 30 10</formula><p xml:id="_XqnFcd7"><s xml:id="_W4BWGAV">Recall Y is per cent days abstinent and thus large values are good.</s><s xml:id="_PY4YyEd">Thus non-responders who live in a chaotic environment do not beneÿt from the step-up in treatment (possibly due to non-adherence), yet if a non-responder lives in highly structured environment, the step-up in treatment is more beneÿcial than switching treatment.</s><s xml:id="_x9Yq7Mt">The conditional means in the table are the same regardless of the value of the initial treatment a 1 .</s><s xml:id="_tGBVr5g">This table re ects the in uence of the unobserved background variable U on Y .</s><s xml:id="_Kf92pqt">The level of structure in one's life U is also related to the intermediate outcome of responder/non-responder as follows:</s></p><p xml:id="_7qmC3tb"><s xml:id="_TzfdEwT">Probability of response by initial treatment and given structure of environment,</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_9">P a1 [S 2 = NR|U ] U = H (highly structured) U = L (chaotic) a 1 = med 0.3 0.3 a 1 = cbt 0.1 0.5</formula><p xml:id="_df7ycAY"><s xml:id="_XUCZKr3">Lastly suppose that</s></p><p xml:id="_yWAPfj8"><s xml:id="_P3T4utT">1 2 of addicted individuals live in a chaotic environment.</s><s xml:id="_vFFyfrc">Using the formula, E a1;a2 [Y |S 2 = NR] = u∈{H; L} E a1; a2 [Y |S 2 = NR; U = u]P a1 [S 2 = NR|U = u]P[U = u] u∈{H; L} P a1 [S 2 = NR|U = u]P[U = u] we obtain the table.</s><s xml:id="_wENPJQ2">Mean of Y among non-responders by secondary and initial treatments, E a1; a2 [Y |S 2 = NR] a 2 = switch a 2 = step-up a 1 = med 17.5 20 a 1 = cbt 15.8 13.3</s></p><p xml:id="_qaqP2u5"><s xml:id="_dfaJWeB">Thus if an individual is a non-responder to med it is best to o er the step-up in treatment (to em + med + cbt) whereas if the individual is a non-responder to cbt it is best to o er a switch in treatment (to med).</s><s xml:id="_F7hks6k">So we see that there is an interaction between initial and secondary treatments; this interaction is due to Berkson's fallacy (there is no interaction conditional on unobserved U ). Since many chronic disorders (in particular, substance abuse and mental illness) appear to have psychosocial, biological and genetic causes, one can expect that U is high dimensional and that Berkson's fallacy may occur; max a2 E a2 [Y | S 2 = s 2 ] may depend on a 1 .</s><s xml:id="_s8EqzCj">Thus in order to estimate the best initial treatment we should observe the primary outcome following each pattern of initial and secondary treatments (recall (4)).</s></p><p xml:id="_yHN5kxM"><s xml:id="_z6AYtGa">In many settings prior randomized trials of initial treatments (followed by standard or no treatment or treatment as available in the community) may indicate that a particular treatment rule, say, d 1 (S 1 ) is best in terms of maximizing long term outcome (Y ).</s><s xml:id="_4fXJn49">Unfortunately the best initial treatment when the secondary treatment is set to a standard treatment (say b 2 ) is not necessarily the best initial treatment in an adaptive treatment strategy.</s><s xml:id="_3CJCfDD">That is, d 1 (S 1 ) an estimator of arg max</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_10">a1 E a1 [E a1; b2 [Y | S 2 ]|S 1 = s 1 ] is not necessarily an estimator of arg max a1 E a1 max a2 E a1; a2 [Y | S 2 ]|S 1 = s 1</formula><p xml:id="_bVnM3Gn"><s xml:id="_sJsCJDD">Thus the resulting rule may not be optimal in the context of an adaptive treatment strategy (the resulting rule is optimal if the only available secondary treatment is the standard treatment).</s></p><p xml:id="_5axwDRY"><s xml:id="_uzRbcb8">An interesting open problem would be to document the kinds of assumptions that make it possible to estimate the best adaptive treatment strategy from multiple experiments, one per decision.</s><s xml:id="_ETz5XPY">In the ÿeld of medical decision making (see for example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">26,</ref><ref type="bibr">Chapter 5]</ref> the applied example in Reference <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[27]</ref>, Markovian assumptions along with the fact that earlier decisions are used only to reveal information (early decisions are diagnostic tests and only the last decision is a treatment) permit one to combine information across multiple experiments.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4." xml:id="_gm2sVYj">SEQUENTIAL MULTIPLE ASSIGNMENT RANDOMIZED TRIALS</head><p xml:id="_3aq4RJ6"><s xml:id="_vXRyVsX">We propose that SMAR trials be used to develop adaptive treatment strategies.</s><s xml:id="_fcXWSvp">This type of trial has been proposed by Lavori and Dawson <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">13]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_GasgEqH">In a SMAR trial each individual is randomized multiple times; that is, at each decision time.</s><s xml:id="_bmgeNtX">Thus individuals following each of the possible treatment patterns are observed.</s><s xml:id="_NJp6g9n">The randomization probabilities may depend on past and present observations.</s><s xml:id="_DDG2x9E">Since the treatments are randomized we use A j instead of lower case a j as in previous sections.</s><s xml:id="_URsD8kT">Thus the data for one individual in a SMAR trial is given by ( S k+1 ; A k ).</s><s xml:id="_CnsmDWr">Data from SMAR trials satisÿes P[S j+1 6s j+1 | S j = s j ; A j = a j ] = P aj [S j+1 6s j+1 | S j = s j ] for each j; that is the conditional distributions required to form optimal adaptive treatment strategies (for example, the optimal decisions in (2) and ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>)) are identiÿed by the corresponding empirical distributions in the SMAR trial.</s><s xml:id="_Yr5qP7p">See the appendix for a proof of this equality.</s></p><p xml:id="_MR6RTnA"><s xml:id="_bt4yqhh">Adaptive treatment strategies can be viewed as multi-component treatments with many components (e.g. which primary treatment, when to alter treatment, which treatment to provide S. A. MURPHY non-responders, form of monitoring or secondary treatment to provide responders to the primary treatment, what information to use to decide which treatment is best, etc.).</s><s xml:id="_wfen5vX">Consider the addiction management study.</s><s xml:id="_bucMwnA">It is natural to expect that pretreatment information such as the presence of co-occurring disorders such as mental illness and homelessness might discriminate between individuals for whom it is best to receive med as the initial treatment in the strategy versus individuals for whom it is best to receive cbt initially.</s><s xml:id="_96FEuJh">Furthermore, oninitial-treatment information such as the level of adherence to initial treatment and evolving level of self management skill in addition to responder status may be useful in discriminating who should get which secondary treatment.</s><s xml:id="_4aZzmvf">Thus the development of an adaptive treatment strategy not only requires consideration of possible treatments but also consideration of what information should be used in the decision rules.</s><s xml:id="_qQHP8UY">Viewed in this light the development of an adaptive treatment strategy is indeed a high dimensional problem.</s><s xml:id="_wRkaNH6">We propose several design principles that have the goal of reducing the dimensionality and we propose randomization probabilities that equalize sample size among di erent adaptive treatment strategies.</s></p><p xml:id="_MCWGr3C"><s xml:id="_pMAuyDe">Principle I: When designing the trial restrict the class of treatment options at each decision point only by ethical, scientiÿc or feasibility considerations.</s><s xml:id="_46r5m67">We conceptualize the S j 's as containing only information that is to be used to constrain treatment options due to ethical, scientiÿc or feasibility considerations.</s><s xml:id="_FWTV7yf">In practice S j would be a known function of a larger amount of data, X j that is collected prior to the jth decision time.</s><s xml:id="_px4Uzeq">The X j 's contain auxiliary information that may be useful in optimizing treatment but except via the information in S j will not constrain treatment options in the trial.</s><s xml:id="_j68PmKz">Thus the randomization probability for each A j will depend on at most ( S j ; A j-1 ).</s><s xml:id="_6QMPf3A">We expect that in most practical settings S j will be of low dimension (e.g.</s><s xml:id="_nRqQrJY">binary or trinary).</s><s xml:id="_eBuqSBk">Note however that the formulae given in the previous sections hold with X in place of S and with Y = u( X k+1 ; A k ).</s><s xml:id="_D7JJfH8">An additional rationale for allowing the randomization probabilities to only depend on the S's (the ethical, scientiÿc or feasibility constraints) is to prevent undue restriction of the class of adaptive treatment strategies.</s><s xml:id="_pgdC9CH">When the experimental design for a SMAR trial speciÿes that the class of alternative treatments is to be restricted by past history, we are in e ect restricting the class of adaptive treatment strategies to be considered.</s><s xml:id="_sg5rA7A">This point surfaces in the next section in the form of assumption <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(8)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_dgyHVFC"><s xml:id="_3KShEDy">As an example of this principle consider the addiction management study.</s><s xml:id="_ApWSc7t">Here the X 's might include measures of an individual's experiences with the past treatments such as acceptability, adherence, burden, level of side e ects, motivation level and also might include ongoing developments such as the level of craving, stress levels and other potential indicators of an impending relapse to heavy drinking.</s><s xml:id="_2af9nwx">In general, information that is predictive of how one might respond di erently to di erent kinds of treatments should be included in the X 's.</s><s xml:id="_rF25rqG">Indeed it would be tempting to specify di erent secondary treatment options for initial-treatment-non-adhering-non-responders and initial-treatment-adhering-nonresponders.</s><s xml:id="_YtVchxE">However this would mean that we would only consider strategies that treat these two groups of non-responders di erently.</s><s xml:id="_sd93VHg">Unless this is known to be necessary, this constitutes an unnecessary restriction on the class of possible adaptive treatment strategies.</s><s xml:id="_yRpJgZZ">Of course observing degree of adherence to initial treatment makes possible secondary analyses in which we test if adherence to initial treatment should be used to discriminate between secondary treatments.</s></p><p xml:id="_9JRKnzV"><s xml:id="_w3KQSAP">Principle II: View this trial as one trial in a series of developmental, randomized trials see <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[29,</ref><ref type="bibr">Chapters 9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">15]</ref> prior to a conÿrmatory trial.</s><s xml:id="_n4k5BEG">This viewpoint reduces the dimensionality problems since we do not expect this one trial to produce an optimized adaptive treatment strategy.</s><s xml:id="_8rHH6vb">Note this viewpoint is consistent with the present ongoing SMAR trials discussed in the introduction(CATIE and STAR*D); these trials are not designed to conÿrm a best adaptive treatment strategy.</s><s xml:id="_cCZYJAV">Each developmental trial would build on the results of prior trials.</s><s xml:id="_nzSYa3n">A full development of Box's approach in this setting is an open problem (see the discussion for simple examples of how such developmental trials might proceed).</s><s xml:id="_7vJSM7t">A conÿrmatory randomized control trial of the developed adaptive treatment strategy versus the appropriate comparison (control or standard care) would follow.</s></p><p xml:id="_vPHcWYc"><s xml:id="_zPWsTeF">Randomization probabilities proposal: We provide randomization probabilities that create equal sample sizes across strategies.</s><s xml:id="_GeaTamP">In other words we set the randomization probabilities so that the proportion of subjects whose treatment assignments are consistent with an adaptive treatment strategy is constant across adaptive treatment strategies; equivalently, P[ A k = d k ] will not depend on d k .</s><s xml:id="_XRfDCyZ">Achieving this is more complicated than at ÿrst appears as the treatments for any subject are consistent with more than one adaptive treatment strategy.</s><s xml:id="_wdXMxkP">One can view this approach as being consistent with the working assumption that the variance of Y under di erent strategies is constant.</s><s xml:id="_6pfmCtd">(Recall the classical result that in a large sample comparison of two means, assuming equal variances, equal sample sizes in the two groups maximizes power).</s></p><p xml:id="_45Vv989"><s xml:id="_KzMzZ9N">Actually in setting the randomization probabilities we go one step further.</s><s xml:id="_2ZqZ7sz">We equalize sample sizes at each decision j among the possible treatment strategies beginning at that decision.</s><s xml:id="_gqyNJny">That is, if we consider the adaptive treatment strategies beginning at decision j with 'pretreatment' information equal to ( S j ; A j-1 ), then the sample size for each of these strategies should be the same; for each j, P[ A k = d k | S j ; A j-1 = d j-1 ] will not depend on (d j ; : : : ; d k ).</s><s xml:id="_7NdfuqP">This approach of balancing sample sizes across di erent strategies is ad hoc; the best choice of randomization probabilities is an open question.</s></p><p xml:id="_xyj334J"><s xml:id="_CHWmDBb">Denote the number of treatment options for the history, ( s j ; a j-1 ) by n j ( s j ; a j-1 ).</s><s xml:id="_bF78Fxx">Note the possible dependence both on prior treatment and on the S's.</s><s xml:id="_Dn96rvT">First we provide simple formula for the randomization probabilities when each n j ( s j ; a j-1 ) = n j ( a j-1 ), that is the number of treatment options does not depend on the S's and for k = 2. See the appendix for arbitrary k.</s><s xml:id="_eVgwUM6">In this case formulae for the randomization probabilities do not depend on the S's and are as follows: Set N 2 (a 1 ) = n 2 (a 1 ).</s><s xml:id="_EWWVFKN">Denote the randomization probability of assigning treatment a 2 at time 2 for an individual with past history, ( S 2 ; A 1 ) = ( s 2 ; a 1 ) by p 2 (a 2 | s 2 ; a 1 ) and similarly for initial treatment.</s><s xml:id="_GDxzPqX">Then</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_11">p 2 (a 2 | s 2 ; a 1 ) = N 2 (a 1 ) -1 (5)</formula><p xml:id="_ThHmacT"><s xml:id="_7Rg7HVS">Note the time 2 randomization probabilities are uniform.</s><s xml:id="_ayVFUN6">Next</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_12">N 1 = n1 b=1 N 2 (b)</formula><p xml:id="_t8HdwtM"><s xml:id="_tKnephp">and</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_13">p 1 (a 1 |s 1 ) = N 2 (a 1 ) N 1 (6)</formula><p xml:id="_6ntWkYx"><s xml:id="_DsY5qXp">See the appendix for a proof that these randomization probabilities result in strategies with equal expected sample sizes.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_YTKuS9N">S. A. MURPHY</head><p xml:id="_RtPHxJd"><s xml:id="_zMvF8AA">The above formulae simplify further when the number of treatment possibilities do not depend on past treatment; in this case N j = k '=j n ' and each p j (a j ) = 1=n j .</s><s xml:id="_pYmYsZf">The randomization probabilities are uniform over the options at each time.</s><s xml:id="_2X8Z732">Consider the addiction management study; there are two treatment options for each responder class at decision 2 and two treatment options at time 1, thus all randomization probabilities are equal to 0.5.</s><s xml:id="_VN7UWa3">Suppose instead that the only secondary treatments following medication (med) are telephone monitoring for responders, and a step-up for non-responders.</s><s xml:id="_ZEBHAJk">Secondary treatments remain the same for individuals initially assigned cognitive behavioural therapy (cbt).</s><s xml:id="_azBCHFE">In this case med responders are assigned telephone monitoring with probability one whereas cbt responders are assigned one of the two options with probability 0.5.</s><s xml:id="_QdxShEb">Similarly for med non-responders and cbt non-responders.</s><s xml:id="_cGeK4Pc">Next, N 2 (med) = 1 and N 2 (cbt) = 2, so N 1 = 3 and we assign cbt therapy with probability 2=3 (N 2 (cbt)=N 1 ) and medication with probability 1=3 (N 2 (med)=N 1 ).</s></p><p xml:id="_bqfTer7"><s xml:id="_MXzQ4AZ">When the number of treatment options depend on the S's, randomization probabilities that equalize sample size across strategies become more complicated and more importantly depend on the distribution of each S j given ( S j-1 ; A j-1 ).</s><s xml:id="_48xmNuQ">We provide the general formulae in the appendix along with a proof.</s><s xml:id="_C4KjHhZ">When k = 2, these formulae yield, p 2 (a 2 | S 2 ; A 1 ) = n 2 ( S 2 ; A 1 ) -1 and</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_14">p 1 (a 1 |S 1 ) = E[n 2 ( S 2 ; a 1 ) -1 |S 1 ; A 1 = a 1 ] -1 n1(S1) b=1 E[n 2 ( S 2 ; b) -1 |S 1 ; A 1 = b] -1</formula><p xml:id="_WttWztU"><s xml:id="_btAjWh7">To use these formulae, we need to make a working assumption concerning the probability distribution of S 2 given (S 1 ; A 1 ).</s><s xml:id="_6YkdKTD">In the simulations we make the extreme working assumption that the distribution of each S j given ( S j-1 ; A j-1 ) assigns mass 1 to the value of S j with the largest number of subsequent treatment strategies.</s><s xml:id="_NdUdwXZ">For k = 2 this implies that p 2 (a 2 | S 2 ; A 1 ) = n 2 ( S 2 ; A 1 ) -1 and p 1 (a 1 |S 1 ) = max s2 n 2 (s 2 ; S 1 ; a 1 )</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_15">n1(S1)</formula><p xml:id="_rbatYrW"><s xml:id="_eXDMuzb">b=1 max s2 n 2 (s 2 ; S 1 ; b) See the appendix for the formula for general k.</s><s xml:id="_MbvtHrt">In both of the CATIE studies, there are multiple treatment possibilities for non-responders but only one possible treatment for responders.</s><s xml:id="_NRAD2dB">Consider the addiction management study and suppose responders are provided one particular maintenance treatment and non-responders are randomized between the two treatment alternatives.</s><s xml:id="_fAQNWzR">If we assume that the responder rates for cbt and med are the same, then the randomization probabilities for non-responders are 1/2 and the initial randomization probabilities are also 1/2.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5." xml:id="_TMRBebY">TEST STATISTIC AND SAMPLE SIZE FORMULA</head><p xml:id="_u2TkzJz"><s xml:id="_wAWmS8e">In order to power the SMAR trial a primary analysis must be speciÿed.</s><s xml:id="_XTVgnEr">For example in the addiction management study, a natural and simple primary analysis would be to test if cbt di ers from med in terms of the intermediate outcome, responder status.</s><s xml:id="_WVCNCWD">But we saw in Section 3 that in the absence of additional scientiÿc assumptions, the results of such an analysis are not useful in ascertaining the initial treatment in an optimal adaptive treatment strategy.</s><s xml:id="_qtxgJV4">Of course an advantage of this primary analysis is that it is of low dimension!</s><s xml:id="_QsG6SEX">We advocate that the primary analysis test if two adaptive treatment strategies each beginning with a di erent initial treatment yield di erent mean outcomes.</s><s xml:id="_N6Phesh">In this primary analysis we lower the dimension by considering only very simple adaptive treatment strategies.</s></p><p xml:id="_Pn4CEjs"><s xml:id="_UkUzSbS">Principle III: The primary analysis should consider adaptive treatment strategies that depend only on S's (the ethical, scientiÿc or feasibility constraints).</s><s xml:id="_PP7AbK7">Thus, for example, the primary analysis for the addiction management study would not consider rules depending on adherence to initial treatment.</s><s xml:id="_vR8Qm7e">Note however that secondary analyses may investigate decision rules depending on the larger data including the X 's.</s></p><p xml:id="_cFsW9ep"><s xml:id="_5dcj3Nt">Power proposal: Power the developmental SMAR trial to discriminate between two adaptive treatment strategies, each depending only on the S's and each beginning with a di erent initial treatment.</s><s xml:id="_gsmc9m6">That is, compare pairs of adaptive treatment strategies in which the initial treatment varies by member of the pair.</s><s xml:id="_mEMHd5K">The rationale is that we need to decide which of the possible initial treatments are worthy of further investigation.</s><s xml:id="_tevhVgx">The second and further randomizations will create comparable groups receiving di erent subsequent treatments, so even though we have not powered the study for discriminating between subsequent treatments, the randomization will permit an valid causal comparison between subsequent treatments.</s><s xml:id="_nrKCHE3">Subsequent developmental trials would then consider only the initial treatments that performed well in this trial; a simple, ideal result would be that a particular initial treatment A produces a much better adaptive treatment strategy (in terms of mean Y ) than alternative initial treatments, then further experimental trials would use treatment A and be powered to contrast adaptive treatment strategies with di erent secondary treatments.</s></p><p xml:id="_sXkzr3n"><s xml:id="_7dDEKDj">Note that one could power the trial so as to compare initial treatments, ignoring subsequent treatments.</s><s xml:id="_AVD3KK6">However this comparison will not generally assist us in formulating an adaptive treatment strategy because the mean of Y ignoring subsequent treatments will depend on the randomization probabilities.</s><s xml:id="_xPwdMww">That is, the estimand will change depending on how one randomizes to subsequent treatments.</s><s xml:id="_pwpv4wH">Algebraically the mean response to the initial treatment a 1 ignoring subsequent treatment is given by (</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_16">k = 2) E a1 [( a2 E a2 [Y | S 2 ]p 2 (a 2 |s 1 ; a 1 ])|S 1 = s 1 ]</formula><p xml:id="_xGqnPF2"><s xml:id="_mgmeGQK">. The argument of the maximum of this quantity need not be the same estimand as <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_cGcx5wx"><s xml:id="_nKr4Ac6">The fact that SMAR trials are relatively new, with little practical experience by scientists, motivates us to consider sample size formulae in a simple setting.</s><s xml:id="_6JenNVy">Thus in the following we focus attention on the setting in which there are a few major decisions (hence randomizations, say k = 2-4 randomizations per individual).</s><s xml:id="_mA7DyV7">Interpreting S 1 as containing only strong scientiÿc, ethical or feasibility constraints on the class of initial treatments, there will be no S 1 if there is no need to place restrictions on the class of initial treatments.</s><s xml:id="_mYCuf77">So the formulae below have no S 1 with the understanding that if restrictions on the class of initial treatments are necessary then we consider the subpopulations deÿned by values of S 1 separately.</s><s xml:id="_6ep85NV">A consequence of this is that the initial decision rule, d 1 , is simply a constant function specifying the same initial treatment for all within a subpopulation.</s><s xml:id="_aX6yRQg">Note this does not preclude consideration of d 1 a function of X 1 in secondary analyses.</s></p><p xml:id="_s8TYCFz"><s xml:id="_hyduQJ5">The test statistic is based on the following estimator of the mean of Y under treatment strategy d k (denote by d k ).</s><s xml:id="_BFcF8kb">Deÿne</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_17">U ( S k ; A k ; d k ; d k ) = k j=1 I {A j = d j ( S j ; A j-1 )} p j (d j | S j ; A j-1 ) (Y -d k )</formula><p xml:id="_yBNczVF"><s xml:id="_9MgmY2h">where the indicator, I {B} is 1 if the event B occurs and 0 otherwise.</s><s xml:id="_wPuecDy">Solve</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_18">0 = P n U ( S k ; A k ; d k ; d k )</formula><p xml:id="_Sc9FQbB"><s xml:id="_fJUzPDY">for d k and call the solution ˆ d k .</s><s xml:id="_6esBJsa">ˆ d k is our estimator of d k .</s><s xml:id="_EaZptxd">In this equation, P n f(X ) is deÿned as the average over the sample, 1=n n i=1 f(X i ).</s><s xml:id="_3FfrMuV">In this case</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_19">ˆ d k = P n k j=1 I {A j = d j ( S j ; A j-1 )} p j (d j | S j ; A j-1 ) Y P n k j=1 I {A j = d j ( S j ; A j-1 )} p j (d j | S j ; A j-1 )<label>(7)</label></formula><p xml:id="_72zmr32"><s xml:id="_Wwd286h">See Murphy et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[12]</ref> for technical details.</s><s xml:id="_TRYYA7E">The estimating formula can be generalized to be doubly robust <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[30]</ref>; see the appendix for details.</s><s xml:id="_SWSjZfe">A crucial assumption underlying the consistency of this estimator is that</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_20">P d k k j=1 p j (d j | S j ; d j-1 )) ¿ 0 = 1<label>(8)</label></formula><p xml:id="_4TNWwvm"><s xml:id="_FpNGdKc">where subscript, d k on the probability symbol indicates that this probability is calculated under the distribution of S k+1 when all treatments are assigned according to the strategy d k .</s><s xml:id="_bPnhQpU">That is we assume that at any decision time, and for any given history, the treatment speciÿed by the adaptive strategy has a positive probability of being assigned.</s><s xml:id="_PrnYxcc">Since we will be comparing strategies, intuitively this assumption is that all feasible treatments have a non-zero probability of being assigned in the study.</s><s xml:id="_92A8Vfw">Given data from a SMAR trial, we can perform two-way comparisons of adaptive treatment strategies with di erent initial treatments, say d k and d k , by approximating the distribution of the di erence in estimators of mean response by a normal distribution.</s><s xml:id="_MDUXN2m">Since the primary purpose of the trial is to develop adaptive treatment strategies (as compared to attempting to conÿrm the superiority of one strategy over the others), we are more concerned about missing signiÿcant di erences between means rather than accidently concluding that two means are equal; thus we have not provided an adjustment for multiple comparisons.</s><s xml:id="_bNJt8pk">A consistent estimator of the variance of</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_21">√ n( ˆ d k -ˆ d k ) is P n (U 2 ( S k ; A k ; d k ; ˆ d k )+U 2 ( S k ; A k ; d k ; ˆ d k ))</formula><p xml:id="_9Y7sqng"><s xml:id="_YfjSUsB">. Since one individual's treatment assignments cannot be consistent with multiple adaptive treatment strategies each beginning with di erent initial treatments, there is no cross product in the above formula for the variance estimator.</s><s xml:id="_A4Sj8Yb">The statistic</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_22">√ n( ˆ d k -ˆ d k ) P n (U 2 ( S k ; A k ; d k ; ˆ d k ) + U 2 ( S k ; A k ; d k ; ˆ d k ))<label>(9)</label></formula><p xml:id="_m5fBHWn"><s xml:id="_Ym7gVPK">has, in large samples, a standard normal distribution under the null hypothesis that</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_23">E d k [Y ] = E d k [Y ]</formula><p xml:id="_3j8FE2m"><s xml:id="_gTX8sPX">. See Murphy et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[12]</ref> for a list of technical assumptions.</s><s xml:id="_We5TX38">The primary assumption is <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(8)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_vBRwWwH"><s xml:id="_SWbEAPc">Sample size formula: To derive a sample size formula, we re-express the variance of √ n ˆ d k in terms of the distribution of S k+1 when all treatments are assigned according to d k as</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_24">E d k k '=1 1 p ' (d ' | S ' ; d '-1 )) (Y -d k ) 2<label>(10)</label></formula><p xml:id="_8xv95tb"><s xml:id="_4uaNBQd">The subscript, d k on the expectation symbol is meant to act as a reminder that this expectation is calculated under the distribution of S k+1 when all treatments are assigned according to d k .</s><s xml:id="_DvYyprF">This formula for the variance is proved in the appendix.</s><s xml:id="_CqJhy35">We provide sample size formula utilizing simple upper bounds on the variance <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(10)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_wtp33Bg">We consider two cases.</s><s xml:id="_U4kfgun">First suppose the randomization probabilities are uniform on the possible treatment alternatives; it is immediate that an upper bound on the asymptotic variance of</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_25">√ n ˆ d k is max s k ; a k-1 k</formula><p xml:id="_vhSk7Aq"><s xml:id="_phntUcy">j=1 n j ( s j ; a j-1 ) 2 where 2 is the variance in response between individuals following the same adaptive treatment strategy</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_26">( 2 = Var d k [Y ]).</formula><p xml:id="_hy62Dc6"><s xml:id="_3TPHsZ5">Alternately, suppose we use randomization probabilities that produce equal sample sizes across the strategies as in ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) and <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_PSMvd6T">If the number of treatment options depend at most on the past treatment (n j ( s j ; a j-1 ) depends at most on a j-1 for each j), then ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_24">10</ref>) is equal to N 1 2 .</s><s xml:id="_mwvhjwS">This equality is derived in the appendix.</s><s xml:id="_qFxjYw8">Indeed if the number of treatment options does not depend on either s j or on a j-1 for each j then ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">6</ref>) are uniform randomization probabilities and N 1 = k j=1 n j .</s><s xml:id="_st2ejZz">If number of treatment options depends on the S's, we make the extreme working assumption that the distribution of each S j given ( S j-1 ; A j-1 ) assigns mass 1 to the value of S j with the largest number of subsequent treatment strategies (j6k).</s><s xml:id="_3rWvz73">In this case, N 1 2 is again an upper bound on <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(10)</ref> where</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_27">N 1 = n1 a1=1 max s2 n2(s2; a1) a2=1 max s3 : : : n k-1 ( s k-1 ; a k-2 ) a k-1 =1 max s k n k ( s k ; a k-1 )</formula><p xml:id="_bj9TRzb"><s xml:id="_RZ9wgFz">See the appendix for a proof.</s></p><p xml:id="_uSE97K2"><s xml:id="_8C7KUBY">Recall that we set the sample size so that we can compare two adaptive treatment strategies each beginning with a di erent initial treatment.</s><s xml:id="_hCjn7FT">Let z =2 be the standard normal (1 -=2) percentile.</s><s xml:id="_rBhwxfz">Then the total sample size should be</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_28">n = 2(z =2 + z ÿ ) 2 Ñ 2 ( ) 2</formula><p xml:id="_gUUsYEe"><s xml:id="_c9yVUt8">where Ñ is the appropriate upper bound from the previous paragraph, is the type I error of the two-sided test, and 1 -ÿ is the power of the test to detect a di erence in the mean response of .</s><s xml:id="_uY7uJRk">Since these trials are meant to be developmental, might be set at a value larger than 0.05 and ÿ might be small (say 0.05, 0.1).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6." xml:id="_tymqhDn">SECONDARY ANALYSES</head><p xml:id="_tcscurj"><s xml:id="_svTBCyC">The multiple randomizations permit a variety of experimental secondary analyses.</s><s xml:id="_C4BU2zu">All of these analyses use randomization to justify causal inferences.</s><s xml:id="_TuRTeea">For example, since the last decision optimizes a conditional mean <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref> we can use regression analyses to test for di erences between S. A. MURPHY the ÿnal treatments.</s><s xml:id="_JNznyZk">However note that only the last decision maximizes a conditional mean of Y (compare (1) with ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">2</ref>)) so use of a simple regression is limited to the last decision.</s><s xml:id="_hAeRJrX">See both Murphy <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[31]</ref> and Robins <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[32]</ref> for comments about other regression methods.</s><s xml:id="_Ud2KQrd">Alternately we can compare two strategies with the same initial treatment using the statistic:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_29">√ n( ˆ d k -ˆ d k ) P n (U ( S k ; A k ; d k ; ˆ d k ) -U ( S k ; A k ; d k ; ˆ d k )) 2</formula><p xml:id="_2TukpR6"><s xml:id="_KB7Mhak">An asymptotic justiÿcation for this statistic can be found in Murphy et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[12]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_7PCxxnV">However if X is of moderate or high dimensions, then this type of statistic will not be useful for consideration of adaptive treatment strategies depending on the X 's (each d j is a function from ( X j ; a j-1 ) to a class of treatments) because very few or no individuals in the data will have treatment patterns consistent with any given treatment strategy based on the X 's.</s><s xml:id="_MfDsryT">In this case one could estimate each conditional distribution, P[S j+1 6s j+1 | X j = x j ; A j = a j ] and then use Robin's 'G-computation formula' to estimate the mean response to a given strategy.</s><s xml:id="_vTJEDyq">This method has not yet received much attention.</s></p><p xml:id="_ckfPnpr"><s xml:id="_ZNVutna">Other secondary analyses might estimate optimal decision rules; that is rules, d k , leading to the highest mean response (assume large values of Y are preferred).</s><s xml:id="_B2ZBQK6">Such rules might very well be a function of the larger data, the X j 's.</s><s xml:id="_BeJY85H">These methods use the sequential multiple assignment randomization to eliminate bias; see Murphy <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[31]</ref> and Robins <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[32]</ref> for methods that can be used to estimate such rules.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7." xml:id="_pAcV3YG">SIMULATION RESULTS</head><p xml:id="_utVCjYq"><s xml:id="_TbWe9zD">The purpose of the simulations is to evaluate the utility of the sample size formula and corresponding test statistic.</s><s xml:id="_zx9ZVE7">We consider settings in which there are two decisions (k = 2).</s><s xml:id="_utUhBUG">There are three scenarios.</s><s xml:id="_7j82JFu">Each has no S 1 , two initial treatments and a binary S 2 .</s><s xml:id="_GjEzweJ">In Scenario I, there are two secondary treatments for each of the values of S 2 .</s><s xml:id="_GaF2Wyp">In Scenario II, there are two possible secondary treatments for each of the values of S 2 as long as the initial treatment is treatment 1.</s><s xml:id="_kBMRAt2">If the initial treatment is treatment 2, then there is only one possible secondary treatment for each value of S 2 .</s><s xml:id="_KgZwt7A">In Scenario III, there are two secondary treatments if the value of S 2 = 0 and only one possible secondary treatment if the value of S 2 = 1.</s><s xml:id="_t7gZ2aN">To recap, in scenario I, the number of secondary treatments, n 2 does not depend on s 2 ; a 1 ; in Scenario II, n 2 depends on a 1 but not on s 2 and in Scenario III, n 2 depends on s 2 .</s></p><p xml:id="_nBpzKNm"><s xml:id="_TmTk83V">In the simulations, S 2 is binary with the probability of a 1 equal to f 1 or f 2 depending on whether the initial treatment, A 1 = 1 or 2. The possible secondary treatments are t s2;a1;1 or t s2;a1;2 following treatment a 1 and outcome S 2 = s 2 .</s><s xml:id="_G9WC58g">We generated the response Y using Murphy's <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[31]</ref> generative model for adaptive treatment strategies.</s><s xml:id="_CFurbe6">This model is described in the appendix.</s><s xml:id="_KA9mRJ5">In all of the scenarios, the optimal strategy, d * 2 , is to assign treatment 1 initially then if S 2 = 0 assign the secondary treatment t 0; 1; 1 and if S 2 = 1 assign the secondary treatment t 1; 1; 1 .</s><s xml:id="_F8N7GYr">In each of the three scenarios, we simulated the data so that the di erence between the mean response to the optimal strategy (E d * 2 Y ) and the mean response to a strategy with initial treatment 2 (say E d2 Y ) is proportional to a common standard deviation, Var d * 2 Y = Var d2 Y .</s><s xml:id="_zHDsPDA">This proportionality constant or signal-to-noise ratio is = .</s><s xml:id="_4DcBMbt">For each scenario we simulated</s></p><p xml:id="_Mz2pwKR"><s xml:id="_jMJjqzv">Table I.</s><s xml:id="_XMVP42j">Scenario I. = (Sample size) P[S2 = 1|A1 = 1] P[S2 = 1|A1 = 2] Type 1 error Power 0.25(1097) 0.5 0.5 0.093 0.900 0.25(1097) 0.3 0.7 0.109 0.902 0.5(275) 0.5 0.5 0.097 0.901 0.5(275) 0.3 0.7 0.093 0.902 0.75(122) 0.5 0.5 0.117 0.891 0.75(122) 0.3 0.7 0.109 0.905 Table II.</s><s xml:id="_Uk65qVp">Scenario II.</s><s xml:id="_Qj3Vq4D">= (sample size) P[S2 = 1|A1 = 1] P[S2 = 1|A1 = 2] Type 1 Error Power 0.25(823) 0.5 0.5 0.107 0.860 0.25(823) 0.3 0.7 0.115 0.905 0.5(206) 0.5 0.5 0.113 0.900 0.5(206) 0.3 0.7 0.122 0.895 0.75(92) 0.5 0.5 0.120 0.882 0.75(92) 0.3 0.7 0.127 0.905</s></p><p xml:id="_kPAwY6h"><s xml:id="_BR7gPev">data for a variety of signal-to-noise ratios and values of f 1 , f 2 .</s><s xml:id="_FEMcwQp">We also ensured that there were at least one pair of adaptive treatment strategies with di erent initial treatments but with the same mean response.</s><s xml:id="_e8KErBf">In this way we are able to check that the proposed procedure has the correct type one error rate (Table <ref type="table">I</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_kbYZCe6">In all cases the estimator is <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(7)</ref>; the test statistic is given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(9)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_WuFNuZv">We set = 0:1 and ÿ = 0:1 for the two-sided tests.</s><s xml:id="_JGYjH27">Each simulation is of size 1000 data sets.</s></p><p xml:id="_aecAc9f"><s xml:id="_jB3WVDy">Consider ÿrst Scenario I. We use randomization probabilities that balance the sample size among strategies; in this case these randomization probabilities are uniform, (0.5), because there are always two treatment options at each decision.</s><s xml:id="_CjSxHgg">Given a signal-to-noise ratio, we set the total sample size equal to the smallest integer greater or equal to</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_30">2(z =2 + z ÿ ) 2 (2 × 2) 2 ( ) 2</formula><p xml:id="_mFQnAWm"><s xml:id="_6DFR7DC">Clearly in this simple scenario the sample size formula and associated statistic perform well (Note that the binomial standard deviation for 1000 trials with p = 0:1 is approximately 0.01.)</s><s xml:id="_fQ8UsTQ">Recall for any data set, we can estimate the mean outcome to multiple adaptive treatment strategies with di ering initial treatments.</s><s xml:id="_pSX8prQ">The entries under the column labelled 'type 1 error' are due to comparisons of adaptive treatment strategies with di erent initial treatments but the same mean ( = 0), whereas the entries under the column labelled 'Power' are due to comparisons of adaptive treatment strategies with di erent initial treatments but means di er by = .</s><s xml:id="_cgeuzd8">In Scenario II we also use randomization probabilities that balance the sample size among strategies (Table <ref type="table">II</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_UDPgxyv">Recall that there are two possible secondary treatments for each of the values of S 2 as long as the initial treatment is treatment 1.</s><s xml:id="_PsxapNU">If the initial treatment is treatment 2, then there is only one possible secondary treatment for each value of S 2 .</s><s xml:id="_tf9mN8Q">So the p 2 (a 2 |s 2 ; 1) = 0:5 for a 2 = t s2; 1; 1 or t s2; 1; 2 whereas p 2 (t s2; 2; 1 |s 2 ; 2) = 1.</s><s xml:id="_RpnD8hv">The randomization</s></p><p xml:id="_dYshAfK"><s xml:id="_d9RZtmb">Table III.</s><s xml:id="_B6Wzuyt">Scenario III.</s><s xml:id="_wr6YksH">= (Sample size) P[S2 = 1|A1 = 1] P[S2 = 1|A1 = 2] Type 1 error Power 0.25(1097) 0.5 0.5 0.088 0.965 0.25(1097) 0.3 0.7 0.095 0.968 0.5(275) 0.5 0.5 0.095 0.964 0.5(275) 0.3 0.7 0.101 0.953 0.5(275) 0.2 0.2 0.115 0.909 0.75(122) 0.5 0.5 0.105 0.958 0.75(122) 0.3 0.7 0.108 0.954</s></p><p xml:id="_H822BtE"><s xml:id="_E4QAzuh">probability at time 1 is p 1 (1) = 2=3.</s><s xml:id="_XqdymSC">Given a signal-to-noise ratio, we set the total sample size equal to the smallest integer greater or equal to</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_31">2(z =2 + z ÿ ) 2 (2 + 1) 2 ( ) 2</formula><p xml:id="_NMnwzpw"><s xml:id="_g9bJme6">As in scenario I, the sample size formula and associated statistic perform well (Note that the binomial standard deviation for 1000 trials with p = 0:1 is approximately 0.01.)</s></p><p xml:id="_43nZ98C"><s xml:id="_fNNWs4z">Recall that in Scenario III, the number of treatment options at decision 2 depends on S 2 ; there are two secondary treatments if the value of S 2 = 0 and only one possible secondary treatment if the value of S 2 = 1.</s><s xml:id="_bm7Zmmt">If we make the extreme working assumption that P[S 2 = 0|A 1 ] = 1, then the p 2 (a 2 |0; a 1 ) = 0:5 for a 2 = t 0; a1; 1 or t 0; a1; 2 whereas p 2 (t 1; a1; 1 |1; a 1 ) = 1.</s><s xml:id="_wgG6eAC">The randomization probability at time 1 is p 1 (1) = 2=4.</s><s xml:id="_fRdNdRn">Given a signal-to-noise ratio, we set the total sample size equal to the smallest integer greater or equal to</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_32">2(z =2 + z ÿ ) 2 (2 + 2) 2 ( ) 2</formula><p xml:id="_zYvwADZ"><s xml:id="_xvwrrNT">As expected, the sample size formula is (see Table <ref type="table">III</ref>) conservative since not all individuals will respond with S 2 = 0 and thus be eligible for 2 rather than 1 secondary treatments.</s></p><p xml:id="_sB5r3nM"><s xml:id="_zpSnNf8">However note the additional ÿfth row in which the probability of an individual responding with S 2 = 1 is 0.2.</s><s xml:id="_9TadR2e">In this setting most of the individuals will be eligible for two secondary treatments rather than one and the working assumption that P[S 2 = 0|A 1 ] = 1 more closely approximates reality.</s><s xml:id="_nepH7qu">In this case the sample size formula is accurate (0.909 is close to 0.9).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8." xml:id="_mX7qEMC">DISCUSSION</head><p xml:id="_jjKncZU"><s xml:id="_W7QFBGD">As stated above we view the SMAR trial as one trial in a series of developmental, randomized trials <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[29,</ref><ref type="bibr">Chapters 9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">15]</ref> prior to a conÿrmatory trial.</s><s xml:id="_WJdENfk">The generalization of Box's approach is an open problem.</s><s xml:id="_Z2bFstm">However to provide a indication of how such a sequence of trials might proceed consider the development of an adaptive treatment strategy for managing alcohol addiction.</s><s xml:id="_KMzyhVZ">Suppose the treatment options are as in our example.</s><s xml:id="_7R7PKbh">To set the sample size, we begin with = ÿ = 0:1 and a given e ect size (i.e.</s><s xml:id="_Msj9HfU">signal-to-noise ratio, = ).</s><s xml:id="_B2zrSWp">Then we use the formula in Section 5 with Ñ = 4 to calculate the sample size.</s><s xml:id="_yQfhhhD">After conducting the trial we ÿnd that a strategy beginning with med produces a higher per cent abstinent days than the strategies beginning with cbt.</s><s xml:id="_69Sw5As">In secondary analyses we use regression to discover an unanticipated result that non-adhering-non-responders to the initial treatment do better when assigned the step up in treatment (em + cbt + med) whereas adhering-non-responders to the initial treatment do better when switched to cbt.</s><s xml:id="_pZz5YSF">In secondary analyses, using the methods of Murphy <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[31]</ref> or Robins <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[32]</ref> we do not ÿnd any pretreatment covariates that would produce subpopulations responding best (in terms of Y ) to adaptive treatment strategies beginning with cbt.</s><s xml:id="_YTqdGNF">Now we are ready for a second randomized trial.</s><s xml:id="_4ZEndMj">This trial would seek to replicate the unexpected results of the secondary analysis and further develop possible secondary treatments; this trial would involve only one randomization per individual as follows.</s><s xml:id="_xymwcs6">We power the trial using the responder proportions from the prior trial so as to ensure su cient non-responders and responders.</s><s xml:id="_EYjwTUH">All individuals would be initially assigned med; responders would then be randomly assigned either to tm or tmc; non-responders might be assigned to one of cbt, em + med, or em + cbt + med.</s><s xml:id="_5vs5KEz">Thus in addition to attempting to replicate the results associated with adherence level, we also provide the opportunity to check if the improved Y of nonresponders is due to the addition of em or to the combination of em + cbt.</s><s xml:id="_My5vzUj">Note that analyses for this second trial are standard regression analyses.</s><s xml:id="_AmrAY6B">Suppose that we see no di erence in the mean of Y for individuals receiving tm or tmc; since counselling is expensive we then decide to use tm as our secondary treatment for responders to med.</s><s xml:id="_4zqY2JJ">Furthermore suppose that in the regression analysis of the non-responders to med the adherence level does not appear to make a di erence in mean Y and em + med + cbt continues to yield better mean Y than other secondary treatments.</s><s xml:id="_3k4ykwP">Now we are ready to proceed to a randomized-controlled conÿrmatory trial.</s><s xml:id="_MnSR7as">This would be a two group trial, the ÿrst group assigned to the strategy: med if responder then tm, if non-responder then em + med + cbt, and the second group assigned to treatment as usual.</s></p><p xml:id="_GMfYtKC"><s xml:id="_JRdBugh">Here is an alternate possible sequence of trials.</s><s xml:id="_KWBMuMJ">Suppose as before a strategy beginning with med produces a higher per cent abstinent days than the strategies beginning with cbt.</s><s xml:id="_Q9ek9nA">However using the methods of Murphy <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[31]</ref> or Robins <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[32]</ref>, secondary analyses of the data from the SMAR trial lead to the unexpected ÿnding that if an individual has a low pretreatment addiction level then adaptive treatment strategies beginning with cbt produce (scientiÿcally) signiÿcant higher per cent days abstinent than treatment strategies beginning with med.</s><s xml:id="_EmVZ8EX">In this case a second SMAR trial with the same design would be run in an e ort to replicate this result.</s><s xml:id="_dBUZjZ9">If this result replicates then separate trials would need to be conducted for the individuals with di erent pretreatment levels of addiction.</s></p><p xml:id="_8z8n99k"><s xml:id="_jj5bSPD">Even the simplistic scenarios presented above illustrate how the development of adaptive treatment strategies presents a di cult challenge to experimental design due to the fact that these treatment strategies are high dimensional multi-component strategies evolving through time.</s><s xml:id="_yMwve3x">Ideally the formulation of a powerful adaptive treatment strategy involves many decisions such as, when to start treatment, which treatment to start, when to step up treatment, which step-up treatment is best, when to step down treatment to maintenance=monitoring, which maintenance=monitoring treatment is best and what information to use to make each of the above decisions.</s><s xml:id="_guBrM7Y">This high dimensional problem appears insurmountable, but is crucially important as adaptive treatment strategies provide a paradigm whereby empirical evidence and statistical methods can improve clinical practice in which most treatment is adaptive, particularly in the management of chronic, relapsing disorders.</s></p><p xml:id="_uTZDk86"><s xml:id="_2ezkW8C">We envision that Box's approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[29]</ref> of multiple experimental trials (that take advantage of working assumptions based on clinical experience, scientiÿc theories and past studies) will provide a paradigm for reducing the dimensionality in a principled fashion.</s><s xml:id="_c7qzdg7">How best to formulate the paradigm in this setting remains an open problem.</s><s xml:id="_AVGE2WV">However before Box's approach can be utilized, we must understand the array of potential working assumptions, including working assumptions concerning delayed e ects.</s><s xml:id="_YJX5YBU">This is an open area of research.</s><s xml:id="_HPjP5HA">The work presented here makes steps in this direction however it ignores an important issue that must be considered in order to fully assess the importance of delayed e ects.</s><s xml:id="_FQrE3Tw">This is the issue of how to provide a principled method for trading o immediate outcomes against longer term outcomes.</s><s xml:id="_WwxyqGm">The rich area of reinforcement learning may o er some guidance <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[23]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_wHwS8sv"><s xml:id="_G7a4vnN">An alternate to Box's approach is the adaptive experimental design as developed by Berry and colleagues <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[33]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[34]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[35]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[36]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">18]</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_NpKt5Wy">Here the word 'adaptive' refers to the experimental design rather than the treatment strategy as in this paper.</s><s xml:id="_sE2A6RQ">That is, adaptive refers to the practice of using outcomes from prior individuals to specify the probability of assigning a given treatment to the present individual.</s><s xml:id="_qbBSgD6">Thall et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[36]</ref> considers a combination of two stage experimental design (drop poorly performing strategies halfway through trial) with a SMAR trial for developing strategies in the treatment of acute myelogenous leukemia.</s><s xml:id="_HkTHj6n">This combination along with the Bayesian analysis represents an attractive alternative to our approach.</s><s xml:id="_uvkJHpz">It is unclear how the adaptive experimental design would deal with the high dimensionality present in the development of adaptive treatment strategies.</s></p><p xml:id="_CdaF3gy"><s xml:id="_8NaYWjv">Other open problems include the development and evaluation of sample size formulae in settings in which the number of treatment alternatives depends on the intermediate outcomes (S's) and one can make good working assumptions concerning the conditional distributions of the intermediate outcomes.</s><s xml:id="_g7qWVYb">In this paper we made the extreme working assumption that with probability one, S takes the value leading to the largest number of strategies.</s><s xml:id="_BDQCtYg">Clearly in many settings this assumption will lead to excessively large sample sizes.</s><s xml:id="_aAaPedU">Another open problem is the best choice of randomization probabilities.</s><s xml:id="_6Nh7ay2">We chose to set these randomization probabilities so that the sample size is balanced at each decision among subsequent strategies.</s><s xml:id="_XajFFTh">It is unclear when, if ever, this is optimal.</s><s xml:id="_gbukmrg">Indeed since the variance of the estimator of the mean response depends on the randomization probabilities it may be that in some settings using randomization probabilities depending on the larger X will reduce variance.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_EPecspJ">APPENDIX</head><p xml:id="_BbTumvz"><s xml:id="_AzaE2Rs">Sequential multiple assignment randomized (SMAR) trial: In order to prove that SMAR trial produces data that permits the development of optimal adaptive treatment strategies, we must prove that</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_33">P[S j+1 6s j+1 | S j = s j ; A j = a j ] = P aj [S j+1 6s j+1 | S j = s j ]</formula><p xml:id="_dEgMUxW"><s xml:id="_7amB3zu">holds for all values of s j+1 , a j and for each j.</s><s xml:id="_ssfnjdN">Note that data from a SMAR trial provides information about the conditional probabilities on the left hand side; whereas the optimal adaptive treatment strategy is deÿned in terms of probabilities on the right hand side.</s><s xml:id="_gaYHZTQ">The di erence between these two probabilities is subtle.</s><s xml:id="_YjUApVe">The former probability refers to a multivariate distribution that permits variation in treatments; possibly because treatments are chosen by individuals or are chosen for them or treatments are randomized.</s><s xml:id="_eUscBj3">P[S j+1 6s j+1 | S j = s j ; A j = a j ] is the distribution of S j+1 among the subpopulation of individuals with values ( S j = s j ; A j = a j ).</s><s xml:id="_54bTvYK">The latter probability refers to a multivariate distribution corresponding to all individuals having the same treatments a k .</s><s xml:id="_4VzH534">There is no variation in treatment in this multivariate distribution; all have treatments a k .</s><s xml:id="_naEn6wx">According to this multivariate distribution P aj [S j+1 6s j+1 | S j = s j ] is the distribution of S j+1 among subpopulation of individuals with values ( S j = s j ).</s><s xml:id="_wJUdD48">Note the di ering multivariate distributions and di ering deÿnitions of the subpopulations.</s><s xml:id="_TWHX8xX">In general these two probabilities need not be equal; however they are equal under sequential multiple assignment randomization.</s><s xml:id="_dG3EdA8">To prove this equality we use the potential outcomes model <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[37]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[38]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[39]</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_33n8YqV"><s xml:id="_MVc3Yv4">Instead of considering a di erent distribution of the vector S j for each possible value of the treatments, a j-1 , we consider a di erent vector of random variables corresponding to each value of the treatment; these di erent random variables are the potential outcomes.</s><s xml:id="_ruA8aA3">Thus corresponding to each ÿxed value of the treatment vector, a j-1 we conceptualize a potential outcome denoted by S j ( a j-1 ) where S j ( a j-1 ) is the response at the end of the jth interval that a subject would have if he/she were assigned the treatments, a j-1 .</s><s xml:id="_aU9mJjS">For each j = 1; : : : ; k, the multivariate distribution of (S 1 ; S 2 (a 1 ); : : : ; S j ( a j-1 ) is the section 2 distribution of S j for the treatment vector a j , e.g. for a measurable set B, P aj-1 [S j ∈ B| S j-1 = s j-1 ] is the conditional probability that the potential outcome, S j ( a j-1 ) ∈ B given the potential outcomes, (S 1 ; S 2 (a 1 ); : : :</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_34">; S j-1 ( a j-2 )) = s j-1 . Similarly E[Y ( a k )] is the same as E a k [Y ].</formula><p xml:id="_F6unt4T"><s xml:id="_R8QXvNU">Let A k be the collection of all possible k-vectors of treatments decisions.</s><s xml:id="_KFuZh2w">The set of all potential outcomes is {(S 1 ; S 2 (a 1 ); S 3 ( a 2 ); : : : ; S k+1 ( a k+1 )) : a k varying in A k } (S 1 does not vary by treatments but is included for completeness).</s><s xml:id="_m6k5yP9">We can rewrite Section 2 formulae for the optimal rules in terms of potential outcomes.</s><s xml:id="_TAwNyHA">For simplicity let k = 2. Deÿne Y ( a 2 ) as u(S 1 ; S 2 (a 1 ); S 3 ( a 2 ); a 2 ).</s><s xml:id="_66ehPFh">Then the optimal decision rules are given by</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_35">d * 2 ( s 2 ; a 1 ) = arg max a2 E[Y (a 1 ; a 2 )|S 1 = s 1 ; S 2 (a 1 ) = s 2 ]</formula><p xml:id="_7HAS5yS"><s xml:id="_62vgW9P">and</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_36">d * 1 (s 1 ) = arg max a1 E[Y (a 1 ; d * 2 )|S 1 = s 1 ]</formula><p xml:id="_QCAZYYD"><s xml:id="_BGgxUdF">And the optimal mean response is given by,</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_37">E[Y (d * 1 ; d * 2 )]</formula><p xml:id="_u3e3TFV"><s xml:id="_uY9JtAt">We use the potential outcomes to connect the formulae in Section 2 to the distribution for the observable data ( S k+1 ; A k ) from a SMAR trial.</s><s xml:id="_bMUPdNu">First we make the consistency assumption <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[11]</ref> that S k+1 from the observable data is the same as the potential outcome S k+1 ( a k ) evaluated at a k = A k , and so on, including S 2 = S 2 (A 1 ).</s><s xml:id="_67Z9qcr">Robins' consistency assumption is the assumption that an individual's response to treatment (the S's) in the study is a ected only by his or her treatment not by the treatment of others and that we have represented the treatment adequately by the a j 's (i.e. if there are 5 values of a j there are only 5 treatments).</s><s xml:id="_uJtxnFq">Because the treatments are randomized with randomization probabilities depending only on past and present information, we have that for each j = 1; : : : ; k, A j is independent of {(S 1 ; S 2 (a 1 ); S 3 ( a 2 ); : : : ; S k+1 ( a k+1 )) : a k varying in A k } given ( S j ; A j-1 ).</s><s xml:id="_mpK5MBG">Thus P[S j+1 6s j+1 | S j = s j ; A j = a j ] = P[S j+1 ( a j )6s j+1 | S j = s j ; A j = a j ] (consistency assumption) = P[S j+1 ( a j )6s j+1 | S j = s j ; A j-1 = a j-1 ] (randomization) S. A. MURPHY = P[S j+1 ( a j )6s j+1 | S j-1 = s j-1 ; S j ( a j-1 ) = s j ; A j-1 = a j-1 ] (consistency assumption) = P[S j+1 ( a j )6s j+1 | S j-1 = s j-1 ; S j ( a j-1 ) = s j ; A j-2 = a j-2 ] (use randomization and consistency repeatedly : : :)</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_38">= P[S j+1 ( a j )6s j+1 | S j ( a j-1 ) = s j ] = P aj [S j+1 6s j+1 | S j = s j ]</formula><p xml:id="_mQGnTfH"><s xml:id="_dTDNpkb">(by deÿnition) So the consistency assumption in addition to the proof above allow us to connect the distribution of the data, denoted by P or E with no subscript to Section 2 multivariate distributions of S k+1 indexed by a K , denoted by P a k or E a k .</s><s xml:id="_x8K84TG">Now we see that the formulae for optimal decisions in Section 2 can be written as functions of conditional distributions for the observable data; thus optimal decisions are identiÿable from a SMAR trial.</s><s xml:id="_vDNzVjF">Randomization probabilities: Set N k ( s k ; a k-1 ) = n k ( s k ; a k-1 ) and then p k (a k | s k ; a k-1 ) = N k ( s k ; a k-1 ) -1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(11)</ref> Note the time k randomization probabilities are uniform.</s><s xml:id="_52kJtGE">Then for each j set N j-1 ( s j-1 ; a j-2 ) = nj-1( sj-1; Aj-2) aj-1=1 E[N j ( S j ; j-1 ) -1 | S j-1 = s j-1 ; A j-1 = a j-1 ] -1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(12)</ref> and p j-1 (a j-1 | s j-1 ; a j-2 ) = E[N j ( S j ; A j-1 ) -1 | S j-1 = s j-1 ; A j-1 = a j-1 ] -1 N j-1 ( s j-1 ; a j-2 ) ( ].</s><s xml:id="_TrBQCuZ">The estimating formula, U can be greatly simpliÿed because it is doubly robust <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[30]</ref> in that even if the approximations ˆ j are inconsistent, as long as the ˆ j 's are bounded in probability the estimator ˆ d k of EY ( d k ) remains consistent.</s><s xml:id="_na9RuHr">Thus, for example, the estimator <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(7)</ref> for EY ( d k ) results if we set each ˆ j to the constant mean d k and solve for d k in <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(14)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_RGkhrng">Asymptotic variance of</head><p xml:id="_YKYbb3n"><s xml:id="_K6AzrUB">√ n ˆ d k : Again the potential outcomes notation from the beginning of this appendix is used.</s><s xml:id="_xfBTrjg">We derive the asymptotic variance for the doubly robust estimator; estimator <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(7)</ref> follows if one replaces each j by d k .</s><s xml:id="_TU9yhdF">Classical Taylor series argument along with technical assumptions (e.g.</s><s xml:id="_JEgVps7">Reference <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[40]</ref>) imply that</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_40">√ n( ˆ d k -d k ) is,</formula><p xml:id="_qSWmdRY"><s xml:id="_EUkFfcE">in large samples, equal to -E @ @ d k U ( S k ; A k ; d k ; k ; d k ) -1 √ nP n U ( S k ; A k ; d k ; k ; d k ) + k j=1 E @ @ j U ( S k ; A k ; d k ; k ; d k ) √ n( ˆ jj ) plus terms converging in probability to zero.</s><s xml:id="_tEYbGZj">Note however that E[@=@ j U ( S k ; A k ; d k ; k ; d k )] = 0; this is the Robins' double robustness property.</s><s xml:id="_xwJYdMj">Additionally, it is easy to see that E[@=@ d k U ( S k ; A k ; d k ; k ; d k )] = 1.</s><s xml:id="_v3XJMwr">Thus the asymptotic variance of √ n( ˆ d kd k ) is equal to the asymptotic variance of √ nP n U ( S k ; A k ; d k ; k ; d k ).</s></p><p xml:id="_WH2SQ9q"><s xml:id="_TdMuuaV">Next, express all variables in terms of potential outcomes as in the beginning of this appendix and use the fact that randomization implies that for j = 1; : : : ; K, A j is independent of {(S 1 ; S 2 (a 1 ); S 3 ( a 2 ); : : : ; S k+1 ( a k+1 )) : a k varying in A k } given ( S j ; A j-1 ).</s><s xml:id="_uSc2Xn6">To be complete yet conserve space we provide a proof for k = 2 (the general proof is similar but requires more space).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_WXncVFk">Var(U ) = Var</head><p xml:id="_dUTq5qk"><s xml:id="_bd92zzN">I {A 2 = d 2 (S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 )}I {A 1 = d 1 } p 2 (d 2 (S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 )|S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 )p 1 (d 1 ) (Y (d 1 ; d 2 (S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 )) -2 (S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 )) + I {A 1 = d 1 } p 1 (d 1 ) ( 2 (S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 ) -d2 ) Using the independence property in addition to the fact that for any random variables, U , Z, Var(U ) = Var(E(U |Z)) + E(Var(U |Z)) (put Z = (Y (d 1 ; d 2 (S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 )); S 2 (d 1 ))) we obtain Var(U ) = Var I {A 1 = d 1 } p 1 (d 1 ) (Y (d 1 ; d 2 (S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 )) -2 (S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 )) + I {A 1 = d 1 } p 1 (d 1 ) ( 2 (S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 ) -d2 ) +E (1p 2 (d 2 (S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 )|S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 ))I {A 1 = d 1 } p 2 (d 2 (S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 )|S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 )p 1 (d 1 ) 2 ( 2 (S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 ) -d2 ) 2 Simplify the ÿrst term and use the independence property on the second to obtain, Var(U ) = Var I {A 1 = d 1 } p 1 (d 1 ) (Y (d 1 ; d 2 (S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 )) -d2 ) +E (1p 2 (d 2 (S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 )|S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 )) p 2 (d 2 (S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 )|S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 ) 1 p 1 (d 1 ) ( 2 (S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 ) -d2 ) 2 Once again applying similar arguments to the ÿrst variance term yields Var(U ) = Var[Y (d 1 ; d 2 (S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 )) -d2 ] +E 1p 1 (d 1 ) p 1 (d 1 ) (Y (d 1 ; d 2 (S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 )) -d2 ) 2 +E (1p 2 (d 2 (S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 )|S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 )) p 2 (d 2 (S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 )|S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 ) 1 p 1 (d 1 ) ( 2 (S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 ) -d2 ) 2 Now if all treatments are assigned according to d k then each observed S j is equal to the potential outcome, S j ( d j-1 ) and the observed Y is equal to the potential outcome Y (d 1 ; d 2 (S 2 (d 1 ); d 1 )), hence we can re-express the above (for general k) as Var d k (Y ) + k j=2 E d k 1p j (d j | S j ; d j-1 )) p j (d j | S j ; d j-1 )) j-1 '=1 1 p ' (d ' | S ' ; d '-1 )) (Y -j ( S j ; d j-1 )) 2 +E d k 1p 1 (d 1 ) p 1 (d 1 ) (Y -d k ) 2</s></p><p xml:id="_xRUb9PQ"><s xml:id="_7eTapMh">where j ( s j ; a j-1 ) is the limit, in probability, of ˆ j ( s j ; a j-1 ).</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>2 ( 1 and p 1 (a 1 1 N 1 (s 1 )</head><label>2111111</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_CYA8nDf"><s xml:id="_N2U5pTq">S 2 ; A 1 ) -1 |S 1 = s 1 ; A 1 = b] -|s 1 ) = E[N 2 ( S 2 ; A 1 ) -1 |S 1 = s 1 ; A 1 = a 1 ] -Proceeding backward through time we will see that the randomization probabilities deÿned above balance the sample size among subsequent strategies at each decision.</s><s xml:id="_aTMxdqh">First at the last decision, note thatP[A k = d k | S k = s k ; A k-1 = d k-1 ] = p k (d k | s k ; d k-1 )which does not depend Copyright ? 2004 John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd.</s><s xml:id="_FT3kbqP">Statist.</s><s xml:id="_DZQyXM8">Med.</s><s xml:id="_u2XVvJY">2005; 24:1455-1481where the indicator, I {B} is 1 if the event B occurs and 0 otherwise.</s><s xml:id="_AESKUza">Given approximations for each j , (say ˆ j ) solve0 = P n U ( S k ; A k ; d k ; ˆ k ; d k )(14)for d k and call the solution ˆ d k .</s><s xml:id="_PWuMhSE">ˆ d k is our estimator of EY ( d k ).</s><s xml:id="_vRSBgx3">In this equation, P n f(X ) is deÿned as the average over the sample, 1=n n i = 1 f(X i ).</s><s xml:id="_wP3RtJA">One possible estimator for each ˆ j is ˆ ' ( s ' ; a '-1 ) = P n k j=' I {Aj = dj( Sj; Aj-1)} pj(dj| Sj; Aj-1) YI {( S ' ; A '-1 ) = ( s ' ; a '-1 )} P n I {( S ' ; A '-1 ) = ( s ' ; a '-1 )} (15) ˆ ' ( s ' ; d '-1 ) is a consistent non-parametric estimator of E[Y ( d k )| S ' = s ' ; A '-1 = d '-1</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p xml:id="_kQZkSVY"><s xml:id="_THgqkNf">Copyright ? 2004 John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd.</s><s xml:id="_y7a6aJT">Statist.</s><s xml:id="_A4vwD3s">Med.</s><s xml:id="_9vEtNqx">2005; 24:1455-1481</s></p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head xml:id="_Sj8JUQq">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p xml:id="_5gDtFvj"><s xml:id="_CDFYugD">We thank <rs type="person">Linda Collins</rs>, <rs type="person">Tom Tenhave</rs>, <rs type="person">Kevin Lynch</rs> and <rs type="person">Jim McKay</rs> for helpful comments.</s><s xml:id="_vGSxugU">And we acknowledge support for this project from the <rs type="funder">National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA Independent Scientist</rs> Award <rs type="grantNumber">K02-DA15674</rs> and Grant <rs type="grantNumber">P50 DA10075</rs>, <rs type="funder">Center for Prevention Methodology)</rs>.</s></p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_DgMd6fw">
					<idno type="grant-number">K02-DA15674</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_CVJSJTm">
					<idno type="grant-number">P50 DA10075</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_Heen8X9"><p xml:id="_pfAzCEb"><s xml:id="_Q86Hg9Y">on the rule d k (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(11)</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_eqJApSm">Next</s></p><p xml:id="_znerQh3"><s xml:id="_6q98uGg">By deÿnition of p k-1 , this probability does not depend on the rule d k-1 (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(13)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_hj9bpXE">Continuing backwards we see that for each j P[ A k = d k | S j = s j ; A j-1 = d j-1 ] does not depend on (d j ; : : : ; d k ).</s><s xml:id="_ZwWGjfj">Thus if these randomization probabilities are used then we have that</s></p><p xml:id="_jwsFXDN"><s xml:id="_u5Erbmb">Note this probability is the same for all rules (d j ; : : : ; d k ) and also note that this probability implicitly depends on S j-1 and past treatment through the decision rules d j-1 .</s></p><p xml:id="_KYsjV38"><s xml:id="_bTVEm6V">If the number of treatment options at each time depends only on past treatment (i.e.</s><s xml:id="_hCaNGGT">n j ( s j ; a j-1 ) can be written as n j ( a j-1 ) for each j) then N k depends only on past treatment and furthermore from <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(12)</ref> we see that if any N j is a function only of past treatment, N j-1 must also be a function of only past treatment.</s></p><p xml:id="_5kSFw4J"><s xml:id="_88GZCN8">Consider the situation in which the number of treatment options at each time can depend not only on past treatment but also on past S's.</s><s xml:id="_4jp6am3">Suppose we make the working assumption that the distribution of S j given ( S j-1 ; A j-1 ) is a point mass at a value of S j with a maximal number of subsequent strategies.</s><s xml:id="_bm8Aaq7">Thus</s></p><p xml:id="_eJYNBnv"><s xml:id="_WdmeKjJ">).</s><s xml:id="_zebFy5Y">And for any j P[S j-1 = s 0 | S j-2 = s j-2 ; A j-2 = a j-2 ] = 1 if s 0 = arg max sj-1 (n j-1 ( s j-1 ; a j-2 ) max sj;:::;s k k i=j n k ( s j ; a j-1 )).</s><s xml:id="_vWyHKQB">Using this working assumption <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(12)</ref> becomes</s></p><p xml:id="_rkcEBsh"><s xml:id="_H9VvQJt">The formulae for the randomization probabilities follow immediately.</s><s xml:id="_VAE8TUe">Test statistic: In the following the potential outcomes notation from the beginning of this appendix is used.</s><s xml:id="_R8sy836">The following estimating formula is a doubly robust generalization of <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(7)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_wKkZjCG">The goal is to estimate the mean response to strategy d k (EY ( d k ) or d k ).</s><s xml:id="_rUcCC6n">For each j = 2; : : The variance in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(10)</ref> follows immediately by setting each j = d k in the above variance formula.</s><s xml:id="_cjJVj4B">Murphy et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[12]</ref> prove that U is the e cient in uence function for estimation of d k ; thus the variance of U is no larger than the variance of any regular estimator of d k .</s><s xml:id="_U3xcjsC">This means that <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(10)</ref> which is the variance of (7) must be not smaller than the above variance formula.</s><s xml:id="_Cyxp5WM">Alternate representation of the variance in (10): Suppose we use the randomization probabilities as in <ref type="bibr">(5.6)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_BYKtjeE">Then</s></p><p xml:id="_NC7un2A"><s xml:id="_DmVTMVU">Now if the number of treatment options at each time depends only on past treatment (i.e.</s><s xml:id="_Thppnwp">n j ( s j ; a j-1 ) can be written as n j ( a j-1 ) for each j) then as seen above each N j ( S j ; A j-1 ) does not depend on S j .</s><s xml:id="_J8yPxa2">This means that the term in parentheses is one and the above simpliÿes to k j=1 p j (A j | S j ; A j-1 ) -1 = N 1 .</s><s xml:id="_4UfPFJa">In this case the variance in ( <ref type="formula">10</ref>) is equal to N 1 2 .</s><s xml:id="_aFN79jw">Upper bound on variance under extreme working assumption: We make the extreme working assumption that the distribution of each S j given ( S j-1 ; A j-1 ) assigns mass 1 to the value of S j with the largest number of subsequent treatment strategies (j6k).</s><s xml:id="_PTwyrXS">From the beginning of this appendix we have that p k (a k | s k ; a k-1 ) = N k ( s k ; a k-1 ) -1 and for each j¡k, p j (a j | s j ; a j-1 ) = max sj N j ( s j ; a j-1 ) N j-1 ( s j-1 ; a j-2 )</s></p><p xml:id="_QxBHzw6"><s xml:id="_MyFZbBq">where N j-1 ( s j-1 ; a j-2 ) = nj-1( sj-1; aj-2) aj-1=1 max sj N j ( s j ; a j-1 ) Then k j=1 p j (a j | s j ; a j-1 ) -1 = k j=1 N j ( s j ; a j-1 ) max sj N j ( s j ; a j-1 ) N 1</s></p><p xml:id="_RXsqxuy"><s xml:id="_Ac3qHaD">Each fraction in the product is bounded above by 1, leaving N 1 as the upper bound.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_bENdeMq">Simulation design:</head><p xml:id="_JxMkuss"><s xml:id="_UBMvFGp">The model is</s></p><p xml:id="_VrHtpN8"><s xml:id="_YrAcvs6">where the e ect of treatment relative to the optimal treatment at decision one and two is encoded in the non-negative ÿ 1 and ÿ 2 , respectively.</s><s xml:id="_6J7TdYY">We call ÿ 1 and ÿ 2 the regrets as they are the regret one has for not assigning the optimal treatment.</s><s xml:id="_NT9H34R">Recall the optimal adaptive treatment strategy is d * 1 = 1, d * 2 (s 2 ; 1) = t s2; 1; 1 .</s><s xml:id="_jSnfxG6">Thus ÿ 1 (1) = 0 as we have no regret for assigning the initial treatment 1 and ÿ 2 (0; 1; t 0; 1; 1 ) = ÿ 2 (1; 1; t 1; 1; 1 ) = 0 as t 0; 1; 1 and t 1; 1; 1 are the optimal treatments following a 1 = 1 for each value of S 2 .</s><s xml:id="_Tt6SC5h">The term (S 2 ; a 1 ) has conditional mean zero (f a1 (1; a 1 ) + (1f a1 ) (0; a 1 ) = 0 for a 1 = 1 or 2).</s><s xml:id="_TWyGwhE">The error term , has conditional mean zero (given S 2 (a 1 )) for each value of a 2 ; otherwise the distribution of the error term can depend arbitrarily on (S 2 (a 1 ); a 2 ).</s><s xml:id="_jRpWd4U">See Murphy <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[31]</ref> for a detailed discussion of this model.</s><s xml:id="_nFcJ2ZE">In all simulations, is a normal random variable with mean zero and variance depending on the value of (S 2 ; a 2 ), (say (S 2 ; a 2 )).</s><s xml:id="_w5V5crM">Also ÿ 0 = 0.</s></p><p xml:id="_2TPqrKq"><s xml:id="_DhEPXYa">In Scenario I, we set all the values of ÿ 1 ; ÿ 2 to zero except ÿ 1 (2) = 1, ÿ 2 (1; 1; t 1; 1; 2 ) = ÿ 2 (1; 2; t 1; 2; 2 ) = 1, indicating that if the initial treatment is 2 and then S 2 = 1 then it is best to choose treatment t 1; 2; 1 over t 1; 2; 2 .</s><s xml:id="_7zEHZZf">Also ÿ 2 (0; 1; t 0; 1; 2 ) = ÿ 2 (0; 2; t 0; 2; 2 ) = 1 as well.</s><s xml:id="_nay4Fdq">The nuisance parameters are (0; 1) = f 2 1 (1-f 1 ) and (0; 2) = f 2 2 (1-f 2 ) (note since (S 2 ; a 1 ) has conditional mean zero this deÿnes (1; 1); (1; 2) as well).</s><s xml:id="_VRvDTr9">The values of f 1 ; f 2 are speciÿed in Table <ref type="table">I</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_5JDvCKR">This is enough to determine the di erence in mean response to the optimal strategy as compared to the least desirable strategy ( ).</s><s xml:id="_FBdKKhn">In Table <ref type="table">I</ref>, we specify the signal-to-noise ratio, = .</s><s xml:id="_FB9dfXH">This ratio divided by speciÿes the desired standard deviation = Y d 2 ) for each strategy.</s><s xml:id="_RvTFSe2">We set the values of (S 2 ; a 2 ) so as to achieve this standard deviation.</s><s xml:id="_a7aXhPf">In this scenario the poorest strategy is (d 1 = 2; d 2 (s 2 ; 2) = t s2;2;2 ).</s><s xml:id="_b6C8Spd">Two strategies that performed equally well (so as to permit an assessment of the realized type I error rate) are (d 1 = 1; d 2 (s 2 ; 1) = t s2; 1; 2 ) and (d 1 = 2; d 2 (s 2 ; 2) = t s2; 2; 1 ).</s></p><p xml:id="_py4bqpB"><s xml:id="_MY2re8A">In Scenario II, we set all the values of ÿ 1 ; ÿ 2 to zero except ÿ 1 (2) = 1, ÿ 2 (1; 1; t 1; 1; 2 ) = 1 and ÿ 2 (0; 1; t 0; 1; 2 ) = 1.</s><s xml:id="_XtFdjht">Recall there is only one possible secondary treatment for a 1 = 2 and both values of S 2 .</s><s xml:id="_uCFkMGE">The nuisance parameters are as before, (0; 1) = f 2 1 (1f 1 ) and (0; 2) = f 2 2 (1f 2 ).</s><s xml:id="_RdUqJ6r">In this scenario the poorest strategy is (d 1 = 2; d 2 (s 2 ; 1) = t s2; 2; 1 ).</s><s xml:id="_BkjKFeZ">Two strategies that performed equally well are (d 1 = 1; d 2 (s 2 ; 1) = t s2; 1; 2 ) and (d 1 = 2; d 2 (s 2 ; 2) = t s2; 2; 1 ).</s></p><p xml:id="_VtcXQe2"><s xml:id="_W73fEZG">In Scenario III, we set ÿ 1 (2) = 1f 2 , ÿ 1 (1) = 0 and all the values of ÿ 2 to zero except ÿ 2 (0; a 1 ; t 0;a1;2 ) = 1 for both a 1 = 1 and 2. Recall there is only one possible secondary treatment following S 2 = 1.</s><s xml:id="_mpe7sZD">Setting ÿ 1 (2) = 1f 2 was one way to ensure that there were two strategies with equal mean response.</s><s xml:id="_fbPFQeZ">The nuisance parameters are as before, (0; 1) = f( <ref type="formula">2</ref>1 (1f 1 ) and (0; 2) = f 2 2 (1f 2 ).</s><s xml:id="_zxnEBUR">The values of f 1 ; f 2 are speciÿed in Table <ref type="table">III</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_4aPXzhU">As in Scenarios 1 and 2, we set the values of (S 2 ; a 2 ) so achieve the standard deviation .</s><s xml:id="_2B7TEF5">In this scenario the poorest strategy is (d 1 = 2; d 2 (1; 1) = t 1; 2; 1 ; d 2 (0; 1) = t 0; 2; 2 .</s><s xml:id="_6jPwzzJ">Two strategies that performed equally well are (d 1 = 1; d 2 (0; 1) = t 0; 1; 2 ; d 2 (1; 1) = t 1; 1; 1 ) and (d 1 = 2; d 2 (s 2 ; 2) = t s2; 2; 1 ).</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_vY9h8fC">A controlled study of a standardized behavioural stepped treatment for hypertension</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Glasgow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Engel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D'</forename><surname>Lugo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/00006842-198901000-00002</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_34GMe3E">Psychosomatic Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Glasgow MS, Engel BT, D&apos;Lugo BC. A controlled study of a standardized behavioural stepped treatment for hypertension. Psychosomatic Medicine 1989; 51:10 -26.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ExKAQuf">Do tailored behavior change messages enhance the e ectiveness of health risk appraisal? Results from a randomized trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kreuter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Strecher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/her/11.1.97</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_vmuUb4d">Health Education Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="105" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kreuter MW, Strecher VJ. Do tailored behavior change messages enhance the e ectiveness of health risk appraisal? Results from a randomized trial. Health Education Research 1996; 11(1):97-105.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_E6trrZC">Problem drinkers: evaluation of a stepped-care approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Breslin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Sobell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Sobell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cunningham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sdao-Jarvie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Borsoi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0899-3289(99)00008-5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_6muBKZm">Journal of Substance Abuse</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="217" to="232" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Breslin FC, Sobell MB, Sobell LC, Cunningham JA, Sdao-Jarvie K, Borsoi D. Problem drinkers: evaluation of a stepped-care approach. Journal of Substance Abuse 1999; 10(3):217-232.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_CCKsRKt">Improving primary care for depression in late life: the design of a multicenter randomized trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Un</forename><surname>Tzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Katon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Callahan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Harpole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hunkeler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ho Ng M, Arean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hegel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Schoenbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Oishi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Langston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_pZ8gfkU">Medical Care</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="785" to="799" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Un tzer J, Katon W, Williams JW, Callahan CM, Harpole L, Hunkeler EM, Ho ng M, Arean P, Hegel MT, Schoenbaum M, Oishi SM, Langston CA. Improving primary care for depression in late life: the design of a multicenter randomized trial. Medical Care 2001; 39(8):785-799.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ahvD2Qr">Using behavioral reinforcement to improve methadone treatment participation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Brooner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kidorf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_35u3Zwv">Science and Practice Perspectives</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="48" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Brooner RK, Kidorf M. Using behavioral reinforcement to improve methadone treatment participation. Science and Practice Perspectives 2002; 1:38-48.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_7nMTV8u">Flexible treatment strategies in chronic disease: clinical and research implications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Lavori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Dawson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Roth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0006-3223(00)00946-x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Z8eUNY3">Biological Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="605" to="614" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lavori PW, Dawson R, Roth AJ. Flexible treatment strategies in chronic disease: clinical and research implications. Biological Psychiatry 2000; 48:605-614.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Copyright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/pd.783</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_gP5CHfd">Ltd. Statist. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1455" to="1481" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004. 2005</date>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Copyright ? 2004 John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. Statist. Med. 2005; 24:1455-1481</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ww/9780199540884.013.u28527</idno>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">S. A. MURPHY</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_mPK98jb">Adaptive treatment strategies: an emerging approach for improving treatment e ectiveness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mckay</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_wTqXmWY">The Newsletter of the Society for a Science of Clinical Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>to appear</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Murphy SA, McKay JR. Adaptive treatment strategies: an emerging approach for improving treatment e ectiveness. The Newsletter of the Society for a Science of Clinical Psychology, 2003, to appear.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_QmJ494r">A new approach to causal inference in mortality studies with sustained exposure periods-application to control of the healthy worker survivor e ect</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0270-0255(86)90088-6</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_jrEfHrj">Computers and Mathematics with Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1393" to="1512" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Robins JM. A new approach to causal inference in mortality studies with sustained exposure periods-application to control of the healthy worker survivor e ect. Computers and Mathematics with Applications 1986; 14: 1393-1512.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_954Ebgj">The analysis of randomized and Nonrandomized AIDS treatment trials using a new approach to causal inference in longitudinal studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_brVNdW6">Health Service Research Methodology: A Focus on AIDS</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Sechrest</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Freeman</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mulley</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Washington, DC, U.S.A</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>NCHSR, U.S. Public Health Service</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="159" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Robins JM. The analysis of randomized and Nonrandomized AIDS treatment trials using a new approach to causal inference in longitudinal studies. In Health Service Research Methodology: A Focus on AIDS, Sechrest L, Freeman H, Mulley A (eds). NCHSR, U.S. Public Health Service: Washington, DC, U.S.A, 1989; 113-159.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_sz2EptH">Information recovery and bias adjustment in proportional hazards regression analysis of randomized trials using surrogate markers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-1-4757-1229-2_14</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Kcqxeqm">Proceedings of the Biopharmaceutical Section; American Statistical Association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Robins JM. Information recovery and bias adjustment in proportional hazards regression analysis of randomized trials using surrogate markers. Proceedings of the Biopharmaceutical Section; American Statistical Association 1993; 24-33.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_K5DzBwz">Causal inference from complex longitudinal data. Latent Variable Modeling and Applications to Causality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-1-4612-1842-5_4</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s" xml:id="_zkTnGU5">Lecture Notes in Statistics</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Berkane</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="69" to="117" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Robins JM. Causal inference from complex longitudinal data. Latent Variable Modeling and Applications to Causality, Berkane M (ed.). Lecture Notes in Statistics, vol. 120. Springer: New York, 1997; 69-117.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_JspvgSY">Marginal mean models for dynamic regimes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Der Laan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Cpprg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1198/016214501753382327</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_5mtCTht">Journal of American Statistical Association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">96</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1410" to="1423" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Murphy SA, van der Laan MJ, Robins JM, CPPRG. Marginal mean models for dynamic regimes. Journal of American Statistical Association 2001; 96:1410 -1423.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_mSV2MJG">Dynamic treatment regimes: practical design considerations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Lavori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Dawson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ftVDgQq">Clinical Trials</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lavori PW, Dawson R. Dynamic treatment regimes: practical design considerations. Clinical Trials 2003; 1: 9-20.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_a4VxuTf">National Institute of Mental Health clinical antipsychotic trials of intervention e ectiveness (CATIE), Alzheimer disease trial methodology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Tariot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Lyketsos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Dagerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Hsiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Jeste</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Katz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Olin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Pollock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Rabins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rosenheck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Small</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Lebowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lieberman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_AxUvK6j">American Journal of Geriatric Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="346" to="360" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Schneider LS, Tariot PN, Lyketsos CG, Dagerman KS, Davis KL, Davis S, Hsiao JK, Jeste DV, Katz IR, Olin JT, Pollock BG, Rabins PV, Rosenheck RA, Small GW, Lebowitz B, Lieberman JA. National Institute of Mental Health clinical antipsychotic trials of intervention e ectiveness (CATIE), Alzheimer disease trial methodology. American Journal of Geriatric Psychiatry 2001; 9(4):346-360.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_tK9j2w7">Depression, IV</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rush</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Trivedi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fava</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1176/appi.ajp.160.2.237</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_WbPGfUR">American Journal of Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">160</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">237</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rush AJ, Trivedi M, Fava M. Depression, IV. American Journal of Psychiatry 2003; 160(2):237.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Lavori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rush</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wisniewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Alpert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fava</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kupfer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nierenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Quitkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sacheim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Thase</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Trivedi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0006-3223(01)01223-9</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_R2scuhY">Biological Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="792" to="801" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lavori PW, Rush AJ, Wisniewski SR, Alpert J, Fava M, Kupfer DJ, Nierenberg A, Quitkin FM, Sacheim HA, Thase ME, Trivedi M. Biological Psychiatry 2001; 50:792-801.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_bDagPdY">Evaluating multiple treatment courses in clinical trials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Thall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Millikan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Sung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/(sici)1097-0258(20000430)19:8&lt;1011::aid-sim414&gt;3.3.co;2-d</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_sj7PxXK">Statistics and Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1011" to="1028" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Thall PF, Millikan RE, Sung HG. Evaluating multiple treatment courses in clinical trials. Statistics and Medicine 2000; 19:1011-1028.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_FMUxjxA">Adaptive trials and Bayesian statistics in drug development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Berry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/10543409108835007</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_jhspACz">Biopharmaceutical Report</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="7" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Berry DA. Adaptive trials and Bayesian statistics in drug development. Biopharmaceutical Report, vol. 9, 2001; 1-7.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_xHJ7Jr7">Optimal adaptive designs for binary response trials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Rosenberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Stallard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ivanova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Harper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ricks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.0006-341x.2001.00909.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_SyQWeEF">Biometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="909" to="913" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rosenberger WF, Stallard N, Ivanova A, Harper CN, Ricks ML. Optimal adaptive designs for binary response trials. Biometrics 2001; 57:909-913.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_9RA5ZJw">Self-designing clinical trials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Fisher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_UmrH3Ym">Statistics in Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1551" to="1562" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Fisher LD. Self-designing clinical trials. Statistics in Medicine 1998; 17:1551-1562.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_sMBZgkf">Mid-course sample size modiÿcation in clinical trials based on the observed treatment e ect</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Jennison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Turnbull</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/sim.1457</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_SJ338yy">Statistics in Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="971" to="993" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Jennison C, Turnbull BW. Mid-course sample size modiÿcation in clinical trials based on the observed treatment e ect. Statistics in Medicine 2003; 22:971-993.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_fpJvtrZ">Dynamic Programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bellman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1957">1957</date>
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Princeton, NJ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bellman R. Dynamic Programming. Princeton University Press: Princeton, NJ, 1957.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_NNPagPY">Reinforcement Learning: An Introduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Sutton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Barto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sutton RS, Barto AG. Reinforcement Learning: An Introduction. MIT Press: Cambridge, MA, 1998.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_qmPxzHE">Probabilistic Networks and Expert Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Cowell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Dawid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lauritzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Spiegelhalter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Cowell RG, Dawid AP, Lauritzen SL, Spiegelhalter DJ. Probabilistic Networks and Expert Systems. Springer: New York, 1999.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_st7SGWD">Encyclopedia of Epidemiologic Methods</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/bbpc.19890930230</idno>
		<editor>Gail MH, Benichou J</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Chichester, New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Gail MH, Benichou J (eds). Encyclopedia of Epidemiologic Methods. Wiley: Chichester, New York, 2000.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_rz4dB8Q">Modeling in Medical Decision Making: A Bayesian Approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Parmigiani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>England</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Parmigiani G. Modeling in Medical Decision Making: A Bayesian Approach. Wiley: England, 2002.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_jDvJuMC">Testing for the BRCA1 and BRCA2 breast-ovarian cancer susceptibility genes: a decision analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Tengs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Winer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Paddock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Berry</forename><surname>Aguilar-Chavez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Da</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_Xff4jyD">Medical Decision Making</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="365" to="375" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Tengs TO, Winer EP, Paddock S, Aguilar-Chavez, Berry DA. Testing for the BRCA1 and BRCA2 breast-ovarian cancer susceptibility genes: a decision analysis. Medical Decision Making 1998; 18:365-375.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qjztrMH">A design for testing clinical strategies: biased individually tailored within-subject randomization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Lavori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Dawson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/1467-985x.00154</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_n8YAaXQ">Journal of the Royal Statistical Society A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">163</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lavori PW, Dawson R. A design for testing clinical strategies: biased individually tailored within-subject randomization. Journal of the Royal Statistical Society A 2000; 163:29 -38.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Box</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Hunter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hunter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_hqqp6p5">Statistics for Experimenters</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Box GP, Hunter WG, Hunter JS. Statistics for Experimenters. Wiley: New York, 1978.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_nN2Yfx9">Robust estimation in sequentially ignorable missing data models and causal inference models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_6BbXs4v">Proceedings of the American Statistical Association. Section on Bayesian Statistical Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Robins JM. Robust estimation in sequentially ignorable missing data models and causal inference models. Proceedings of the American Statistical Association. Section on Bayesian Statistical Science 1999; 6-10.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_x3M9wUK">Optimal dynamic treatment regimes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_NxYUC6Q">Journal of the Royal Statistical Society; Series B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="331" to="366" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Murphy SA. Optimal dynamic treatment regimes. Journal of the Royal Statistical Society; Series B 2003; 65(2):331-366.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_X2KGHMy">Optimal structural nested models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Unpublished Manuscript</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Robins JM. Optimal structural nested models. Unpublished Manuscript, 2003.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_KzvXSK9">Bandit Problems: Sequential Allocation of Experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Berry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Fristedt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
			<publisher>Chapman-Hall</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Berry DA, Fristedt B. Bandit Problems: Sequential Allocation of Experiments. Chapman-Hall: London, 1985.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_GSA2KmP">Adaptive assignment versus balanced randomization in clinical trials: a decision analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Berry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Eick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/sim.4780140302</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_x4Wj4bh">Statistics in Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="246" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Berry DA, Eick SG. Adaptive assignment versus balanced randomization in clinical trials: a decision analysis. Statistics in Medicine 1995; 14:231-246.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_PJUZeWF">General keynote: clinical trial design</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Berry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_bZmybs8">Gynecologic Oncology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="114" to="S116" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Berry DA. General keynote: clinical trial design. Gynecologic Oncology 2003; 88:S114-S116.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_uuHqnak">Selecting therapeutic strategies based on e cacy and death in multicourse clinical trials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Thall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Sung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Estey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1198/016214502753479202</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_kYJwGVX">Journal of the American Statistical Association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="39" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Thall PF, Sung HG, Estey EH. Selecting therapeutic strategies based on e cacy and death in multicourse clinical trials. Journal of the American Statistical Association 2002; 97:29-39.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_76Gje2r">Bayesian inference for causal e ects: the role of randomization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Rubin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_qYAWcjf">The Annals of Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="34" to="58" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rubin DB. Bayesian inference for causal e ects: the role of randomization. The Annals of Statistics 1978; 6:34-58.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_k6qzdnD">Comment: which ifs have causal answers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Rubin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/01621459.1986.10478355</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_w9hDsSN">Journal of the American Statistical Association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="961" to="962" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rubin DB. Comment: which ifs have causal answers. Journal of the American Statistical Association 1986; 81:961-962.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Copyright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/pd.783</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_TN2yYmu">Ltd. Statist. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1455" to="1481" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004. 2005</date>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Copyright ? 2004 John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. Statist. Med. 2005; 24:1455-1481</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_WCzycm5">Addendum to a new approach to causal inference in mortality studies with sustained exposure periods-application to control of the healthy worker survivor e ect</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0898-1221(87)90238-0</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_nuEyzY2">Computers and Mathematics with Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="923" to="945" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Robins JM. Addendum to a new approach to causal inference in mortality studies with sustained exposure periods-application to control of the healthy worker survivor e ect. Computers and Mathematics with Applications 1987; 14:923-945.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_aRt8pku">Approximation theorems of Mathematical Statistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ser</forename><surname>Ing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/9780470316481.fmatter</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ser ing RJ. Approximation theorems of Mathematical Statistics. Wiley: New York, 1980.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_REM6unG">Patterns of change: dynamic typology applied to smoking cessation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Prochaska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Velicer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Guadagnoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rossi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Diclemente</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1207/s15327906mbr2601_5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_6tEHmDH">Multivariate Behavioral Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="107" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Prochaska JO, Velicer WF, Guadagnoli E, Rossi JS, DiClemente CC. Patterns of change: dynamic typology applied to smoking cessation. Multivariate Behavioral Research 1991; 26(1):83-107.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Ga9uwgb">Evaluating a population-based recruitment approach and a stage-based expert system intervention for smoking cessation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Prochaska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Velicer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Fava</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rossi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Tsoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0306-4603(00)00151-9</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_8QWgTeG">Addictive Behaviors</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="583" to="602" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Prochaska JO, Velicer WF, Fava JL, Rossi JS, Tsoh JY. Evaluating a population-based recruitment approach and a stage-based expert system intervention for smoking cessation. Addictive Behaviors 2001; 26:583-602.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Copyright</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_TbteSAz">Ltd. Statist. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1455" to="1481" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004. 2005</date>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Copyright ? 2004 John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. Statist. Med. 2005; 24:1455-1481</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
