<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_GA4dJ36">L-l, 4-CYCL0HEXADIENE-1-ALANINE, AN ANTAGONIST OF PHENYLALANINE, FROM STREPTOMYCES</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tatsuo</forename><surname>Yamashita</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Research Laboratories of Fujisawa Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd. , Higashiyodogawa-ku , Osaka , Japan</note>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Research Laboratories</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Fujisawa Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Higashiyodogawa-ku</addrLine>
									<settlement>Osaka</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Norimasa</forename><surname>Miyairi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Research Laboratories of Fujisawa Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd. , Higashiyodogawa-ku , Osaka , Japan</note>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Research Laboratories</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Fujisawa Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Higashiyodogawa-ku</addrLine>
									<settlement>Osaka</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kiyohiko</forename><surname>Kunugita</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Research Laboratories of Fujisawa Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd. , Higashiyodogawa-ku , Osaka , Japan</note>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Research Laboratories</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Fujisawa Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Higashiyodogawa-ku</addrLine>
									<settlement>Osaka</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kiyotake</forename><surname>Shimizu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Research Laboratories of Fujisawa Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd. , Higashiyodogawa-ku , Osaka , Japan</note>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Research Laboratories</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Fujisawa Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Higashiyodogawa-ku</addrLine>
									<settlement>Osaka</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Heiichi</forename><surname>Sakai</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Research Laboratories of Fujisawa Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd. , Higashiyodogawa-ku , Osaka , Japan</note>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Research Laboratories</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Fujisawa Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Higashiyodogawa-ku</addrLine>
									<settlement>Osaka</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_RJaTRzt">L-l, 4-CYCL0HEXADIENE-1-ALANINE, AN ANTAGONIST OF PHENYLALANINE, FROM STREPTOMYCES</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">383245639094BE389712846AE13749AA</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received for publication September 21, 1970</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T13:59+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_MUBbJGs">An antagonist</head><p xml:id="_35NyCY8"><s xml:id="_ESw2Mc3">of phenylalanine, L-l? 4-cyclohexadiene-l-alanine, was isolated from the culture broth of a strain of Streptomyces designated Streptomyces diastatochromogenes var.</s><s xml:id="_53gGZyd">sakaii.</s></p><p xml:id="_S35W4ux"><s xml:id="_KeQ6WPD">It is active against plant-pathogenic fungi, and Pseudomonas aeruginosa on synthetic medium.</s><s xml:id="_6mXRUwf">Producing strain, and the production, isolation, identification and biological properties of this antibiotic are described.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="507.0" lry="728.0"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="507.0" lry="728.0"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="507.0" lry="728.0"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="507.0" lry="728.0"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="507.0" lry="728.0"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_nkH75Dd"><p xml:id="_uMkZqHJ"><s xml:id="_MKVgTwv">In the course of a search for microbial metabolite which would be protective against infection of rice by Piricularia oryzae and Ophiobolus miyabeanus, an antibiotic was isolated from the culture filtrate of a strain of Streptomyces.</s><s xml:id="_YnUUZG8">This antibiotic was found to be an antagonist of phenylalanine and identified as L-l,4-cyclohexadiene-lalanine from physico-chemical properties and chromatographic behavior.</s><s xml:id="_RpCh54Y">Although L-l, 4-cyclohexadiene-l-alanine was chemically synthesized by <ref type="bibr">Snow et</ref> al.l) in 1957, its biological production has not been reported.</s><s xml:id="_su7rnQX">Producing Organism The morphological and physiological properties of FN 1636 strain which was isol ated from a soil sample collected at Takarazuka are listed in Table 1.</s><s xml:id="_9G45Rdz">Microscopic observation on aerial mycelium revealed that its sporophores branched and bore little open spirals abundantly and sometimes formed clusters.</s><s xml:id="_tA29qUj">Carbon utilization by strain FN 1636 was studied using the method of Pridham and Gottlieb2).</s><s xml:id="_h6P9KBb">L-Arabinose, D-fructose, D-glucose, rhamnose, sucrose, lactose, trehalose and D-mannitol were well utilized, whereas D-xylose, D-mannose and z-inositol w ere moderately, raffinose and salicin were poorly utilized.</s><s xml:id="_m2fMYhV">Comparison of this cultural properties and sugar utilization with those for known species revealed that the strain resembles Streptomyces diastatochromogenes.</s><s xml:id="_CaywrEj">However, some minor differences exist between FN 1636 strain and Streptomyces diastatochromogenes.</s><s xml:id="_ExZfhQK">For example, the formation of a new antibiotic, L-l,4-cyclohexadienel-alanine is noteworthy peculiar character of FN 1636 strain.</s><s xml:id="_e9uRFU7">Thus, we designated the strain as Streptomyces diastatochromogenes var.</s><s xml:id="_hFAdnws">sakaii.</s><s xml:id="_hDgk6YK">This work was presented at the Annual Meeting of the Agricultural Chemical Society of Japan, F ukuoka, April 2, 1970.</s><s xml:id="_PtxfUmN">* Present address : Department of Carcinogenesis and Cancer Susceptibility, the Institute of Medical Science, the University of Tokyo, Shirokanedai, Minato-ku, Tokyo, Japan.</s><s xml:id="_wHPG7q4">T abl e 1. Cultural properti es of Stre ptom yces diastatochrom ogenes var.</s><s xml:id="_FGA4s7b">sakaii M edia Grow th A erial m ycelium Soluble pigm ent Rem arks Czapek ' s agar G reeni sh brow n, f lat and spreading Li ght grayish brow n.</s><s xml:id="_75Ve25D">W hite, pow dery N one D iastatic Starch Light brow nish N one N one, occasionally am m onium agar spreading gray, pow dery action ; strong Poor grow th at 37-C Glucose Gray, occasionally G ray, pow dery asparagm e agar dark brow n dark brow n Calcium m al ate ag-ar Dark grayish brow n D ark gray, pow dery N one, occasionally dark brow n T yrosi ne agar Brown, f lat N one D ark brow n B ouill on agar Da r k b r ow n , f lat, not spreading B row n dark brow n, w rinckled N one D ark brow n B ennett's agar Gray, pow dery Dark brow n G elatin stab Li ght gray dark gray, surface grow th W hi te thin surface N one B lackish brow n Liquefaction ; w eak N itrite G lucose Czapek ' s N one N one N one D ark brow n soluti on G lucose boui llon grow th, abundant growth in the m edium D ark cream y ring grow th formation ; negative Slightly acidic M ilk Potato plug-Cell ulose G r a y i s h w hite ring grow th Bl ac k w ri nckl ed grow th N o grow th N one W hi te pow der sli ghtly G rayish brow n Black P e pt o ni z a ti o n ; poorly.</s><s xml:id="_MqU4QCY">N o coagulation Production and Isolation FN 1636 Strain was inoculated into 500ml shaking flasks containing 100ml of medium consisting of 2.0 % glucose, 2.0 % potato strach, 2.0 % Pharmamedia, and 0.3 % CaCO3.</s><s xml:id="_7VsAwQu">Flasks were incubated at 30°C for 4 days on a reciprocal shaker.</s><s xml:id="_S5qdvUs">This antibiotic has fungistatic activity against plant-pathogenic fungi, so assay was carried o ut against Ophiobolus miyabeanus on potato dextrose agar by usual paper-disc method.</s><s xml:id="_XWCJZs9">Cultured broth from flasks was filtered with the aid of Gelite 545.</s><s xml:id="_4BvUBhS">The filtrate was absorbed on an anion-exchange resin (Amberlite IR-45) in OH~form at pH 4.5 and eluted with 50% aqueous acetone.</s><s xml:id="_8TeBte8">The eluate was concentrated in vacuo and added into two volume of acetone, yielding powdery precipitate.</s><s xml:id="_KrtcnpY">The precipitate, after washing with acetone, was further purified on a cellulose column by elution with water-saturated ^-butanol.</s><s xml:id="_swSAdEK">Active fractions were combined and kept for several days at room temperature to yield coloress plate crystals (FN 1636 substance).</s><s xml:id="_h6fQZ72">Thus, 500mg of crystals was obtained from 10 liters of culture broth.</s><s xml:id="_2Rp8S9q">Chemical and Physical Properties Chemical and physical properties of the isolated crystalline substance are listed in Table 2 comparing with that of authentic l-1, 4-cyclohexadiene-l-alanine.</s><s xml:id="_qQHhRg6">The most characteristic property of the new crystalline substance is to give a brick-orange color with ninhydrin reagent on paper or cellulose layer.</s><s xml:id="_szhyhhh">Chemically synthesized l-1, 4cyclohexadiene-1-alanine also gives similar color with ninhydrin.</s><s xml:id="_DnEtQfZ">The fermentation Table 2. Physico-chemical properties of FN 1636 substance and L-l, 4-cyclohexadiene-l-alanine F N 1636 sub stan ce L -l, 4 -C y cloh ex adiene-l-alan inel) A p pe colorless p late colorless plate M .</s><s xml:id="_hMaZvf4">W . (m ass) 167 167 E lem en tary an aly sis ( % ) C 64.84, H 7.7 9, N 8.40 % C 65.0, H 7 .86,</s><s xml:id="_fqahZVv">N 8.53 % * O p tical rotation [a ll3 -60 .3-(c</s><s xml:id="_hFTQPqa">0 .8,</s><s xml:id="_s4XfV4R">H 2O ) [a ll5 -61 .6-(c</s><s xml:id="_TkAkF7h">0.74, H 2O ) Stability u n stable in solid state u nstab le in solid state C olor reaction n inh y drin , brick -oran g e nin h yd rin , b rick -orang e T h in -lay er chrom atogr aph y (M N cellu lose) w ater-saturated n -b utanol 蝣 w ater-satu rated n -bu tan ol R f 0.59 R f 0.59 n-BuO H -P y rid ine -A cO H -H 2O i-BuOH -P y ridin e -A cO H -H 2O (30 : 20 : 6 : 24) (3 0 :20 : 6 :2 4) R f 0. 71 R f 0. 7 1 * Calcd.</s><s xml:id="_hcnpTZp">for C9H13NO2: C 64.70, H7.84, N8.38.</s><s xml:id="_B3z2Ccm">F ig. 1. Infrared spectra of FN 1636 substance and L-l, 4-cyclohexadiene-l-alanine (Nujol mull) c © o v. CD L -1,4-Cycfohexadiene-f-afanine 4000 2800 2000 1800 1600 1400 1200 1000 800 600C/77*f 3 4 5 6 7 8 % Fig. 3. NMR spectrum of L-l,4-cyclohexadiene-l-alanine in D20 L-l,4-Cyclohexadiene-l-alanine (l-2, 5-Dihydrophenylalanine) NH2 CH2CHCOOH 3 4 5 6 7 8 Z</s></p><p xml:id="_rxbzknt"><s xml:id="_q5Jdayc">substance is rather heat labile and after having been kept for 3 hours at 110°C about one third of it was oxidized to L-phenylalanine.</s><s xml:id="_qnvcMtR">A methanolic solution showed weak, end absorption in ultraviolet absorption spectrum.</s></p><p xml:id="_UtbpMTn"><s xml:id="_EeaEha7">The infrared absorption spectra of the fermentation substance and chemically prepared l-1, 4-cyclohexadiene-l-alanine are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>, and their NMR spectra in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref> and <ref type="figure">3</ref> respectively.</s><s xml:id="_3NfycgJ">From these results, it seems reasonable to decide that the fermentation material is identical withL-l, 4-cyclohexadiene-l-alanine.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_yN8bKVX">Biological Activities</head><p xml:id="_taf7Hh3"><s xml:id="_ECp7aRx">The antimicrobial spectrum Table <ref type="table">3</ref>. Antimicrobial spectrum of FN 1636 substance of the fermentation substance was tested by the agar dilution streak method and the results are shown in Table <ref type="table">3</ref>. Inhibition of plantpathogenic fungi was noted, and growth of Trichophyton asteroides, Trichophyton rubrum, Sclerotinia arachidis, Helminthosporium sativum, Ophiobolus miyabeanus and Piricularia oryzae was partiallyinhibited at the concentration of 25-50 mcg/ml.</s><s xml:id="_ZH6WCcX">The growth of Pseudomonas aeruginosa IAM 1052 is inhibited at the concentration à"of 5 mcg/ml only on synthetic medium.</s><s xml:id="_guDwnbq">In studies using this bacterial strain the reversal by amino acids of the antibacterial activity of the fermentation substance was examined.</s><s xml:id="_8KVaxGt">Only phenylalanine among 19 amino acids tested reversed the inhibition of growth as shown in Table 4.</s><s xml:id="_TNkPRMz">This suggests that the fermentation substance is an antagonist of phenylalarnine.</s><s xml:id="_uUreqKK">Also this antibiotic has the same antibacterial activity against Ps.</s><s xml:id="_XCae2EK">aeruginosa as authentic sample of l-1, 4-cyclohexadiene-lalanine; inhibitory zones of 28 mm at the concontration of 200 mcg/ml by paper-disc assay.</s><s xml:id="_z8er2jZ">Mice survived more than 10 days after i ntravenous administration of 500 mg/kg.</s><s xml:id="_CdCxs9Q">Thus, from physico-chemical properties and antimicrobial activity the fermentation sub-.</s><s xml:id="_68XuJ3g">, .n</s><s xml:id="_SxjS7hH">i h A 1 T -,.</s><s xml:id="_6ZtngnW">The antibacterial activities of testsolutions stance Was identified as L-l, 4-Cyclohexadiene-containing various concentration of FN 1636 . . . . .</s><s xml:id="_Wac5Sha">p substance and L-phenylalanine was examined 1 -alanine and shown tO be an antagonist Of using Pseudomonas aeruginosaIAM1052 on the medium D described in Table 3 by paper-disc phenylalanine.</s><s xml:id="_fRVBt34">assay.</s><s xml:id="_SQwGRP8">M edia O rg an ism s M .</s><s xml:id="_CrWEyFe">I. C. (m cg /m l) M icr osp oru m au dou inii 6. 3 U stilag o zeae 100 B otrytis cin er ea 100 T rich op hyton in terd ig itale 200 A ltern aria hihu chian a &gt; 200 A H elm in thosp oriu m sa tivu m &gt; 200 O p hiobolus m iy abea nu s &gt; 200 P iricularia ory za e &gt; 200 S clerotin ia a rach idis &gt; 200 T rich op hyton asteroides &gt; 200 T rich op hy ton ru brum &gt; 200 B acillus m eg atherium &gt; 200 B acillus su btilis &gt; 200 B an d C E scherichia coli &gt; 200 P seu dom on as aerug inosa &gt; 200 S tap hy lococcus a ureu s F D A 209 P &gt; 200 P s e u d o m o n a s aerug inosa IA M 1052 5 E and F Aspergillus oryzaepenicillium chrysogenum &gt; 200 &gt; 200 G and H Candida albicanssaccharomyces cerevisiaeTorula utilis &gt; 200 &gt; 200 &gt; 200 Media (A) Potato dextrose agar (B) Nutrient agar (C) Stephenson-Whetham medium (D) glucose 1%, Na-glutamate 0.5%, K2HPO4 0.1 \ MgSO4-7H2O 0.02%, agar 1.5% (E) Malt extract agar (F) CzAPEK medium (G) Malt extract agar (H) Hayduck medium Table 4. Reversal of inhibition of FN 1636 substance by L-phenylalanine in Pseudomonas aeruginosa IAM 1052</s></p><p xml:id="_hJJ3rJ8"><s xml:id="_d9mzZaU">L -P h e n y la la n in e ( m cg /m l) F N 1 6 3 6 s u b s ta n c e 20 0 m c g /m 1 1 0 0 m c g /m l 0 2 8 m m 2 8 2 3 m m 1 0 2 2. 5 2 0 2 1 5 0 1 5 1 0 0 2 6 1 0 2 0 0 1 7 0 4 0 0 0</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_4KDQRsK"><s xml:id="_bxStT4r">Fig. 2. NMR spectrum of FN1636 substance in D20</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head xml:id="_vTk6R3U">Acknowledgements</head><p xml:id="_HAbXUhY"><s xml:id="_UHwMEbT">The authors are indebted to <rs type="person">Dr. Charlotte Ressler</rs>, <rs type="affiliation">Institute for Muscle Disease, New York</rs>, for kind supply of synthetic D-, L-and DL-1, 4-cyclohexadiene-l-alanine.</s></p></div>
			</div>			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_X7B4u4N">1,4-Cyclohexadiene-l-alanine (2,5-dihydrophenylalanine), a new inhibitor of phenylalanine for the rat and Leuconostoc dexlranicum 8086</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Snow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lauinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ressler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1021/jo01269a016</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_hkU5SpH">J. Org. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1774" to="1780" />
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Snow, M. L.; C. Lauinger &amp; C. Ressler : 1,4-Cyclohexadiene-l-alanine (2,5-dihydrophenyl- alanine), a new inhibitor of phenylalanine for the rat and Leuconostoc dexlranicum 8086. J. Org. Chem. 33 : 1774-1780, 1968</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_5Rq5TUh">The utilization of carbon compound by some actinomycetales as an aid for species determination</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Pridham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gottlieb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1128/jb.56.1.107-114.1948</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_EeSXXyQ">J. Bact</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="114" />
			<date type="published" when="1948">1948</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Pridham, T. G. &amp; D. Gottlieb : The utilization of carbon compound by some actinomycetales as an aid for species determination. J. Bact. 56 : 107~114, 1948</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
