<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_MMTmbCe">Rethinking Risk: Prospect Theory Application in Health Message Framing Research</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Nancy</forename><forename type="middle">Grant</forename><surname>Harrington</surname></persName>
							<email>nancy.harrington@uky.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Department of Communication , University of Kentucky Department of Communication , University of Kentucky , 249 Grehan Building , Lexington , KY 40506-0042.</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Communication</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Communication</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Kentucky</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Kentucky</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>249 Grehan Building</addrLine>
									<postCode>40506-0042.</postCode>
									<settlement>Lexington</settlement>
									<region>KY</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Anna</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kerr</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Department of Communication , University of Kentucky Department of Communication , University of Kentucky , 249 Grehan Building , Lexington , KY 40506-0042.</note>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Communication</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Communication</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Kentucky</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Kentucky</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>249 Grehan Building</addrLine>
									<postCode>40506-0042.</postCode>
									<settlement>Lexington</settlement>
									<region>KY</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_QmdyhgP">Rethinking Risk: Prospect Theory Application in Health Message Framing Research</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">D5E8077B56C61BDFA4B1745A2CC6B055</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1080/10410236.2015.1110004</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T14:07+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_7WtjNbx"><p xml:id="_2B9WpEx"><s xml:id="_VfJPGDJ">Although prospect theory conceptualizes risk as uncertainty, health message framing research based on the theory typically conceptualizes risk as severity.</s><s xml:id="_3RNnddM">This study reports the results of two experiments designed to explore these alternative conceptualizations of risk and their effect on health decision making.</s><s xml:id="_bUJ8PfZ">Participants (N 1 = 768, N 2 = 532) were randomly assigned to one of four conditions that presented a hypothetical scenario of a sexually transmitted disease (STD) outbreak.</s><s xml:id="_2ZsnRn9">The conditions were defined by message prompt (deadly vs. easily curable STD) and response option frame (gain vs. loss).</s><s xml:id="_gH8mZja">Participants selected which of two programs (certain outcome vs. uncertain outcome) they would prefer to combat the outbreak.</s><s xml:id="_UkACUFJ">Across both experiments, participants expressed strong preferences for certain (low risk) outcomes in the gain-framed conditions and no preferences in the loss-framed conditions.</s><s xml:id="_T2YrJWJ">These differences held regardless of the consequence severity of the scenario.</s><s xml:id="_AvazNCk">We discuss the theoretical and practical implications of these results and offer directions for future research.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="634.32" lry="833.04"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="10" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="11" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="12" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_AVSkSXw"><p xml:id="_VhP6Rxh"><s xml:id="_ZvB7znW">Research in persuasive message design suggests that the way a message is framed, highlighting the benefits or costs of engaging or not engaging in a particular behavior, will influence its persuasiveness.</s><s xml:id="_ACQF2Zn">This finding is important for persuasive health messages because most health behaviors can be framed in a way that either highlights the benefits of engaging in the behavior (gain frame) or highlights the costs of not engaging in the behavior (loss frame; <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Rothman &amp; Salovey, 1997)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_YD3qvxn">A frequent assumption in message framing research is that gain-framed messages are more effective for encouraging prevention behaviors, such as sunscreen use and exercise, and loss-framed messages are more effective for promoting detection behaviors, such as breast self-examinations and colonoscopy <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Rothman &amp; Salovey, 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Salovey, Schneider, &amp; Apanovitch, 2002)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_kH4buXZ"><s xml:id="_x7G4vku">This distinction is grounded in the tenets of prospect theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Kahneman &amp; Tversky, 1979;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Tversky &amp; Kahneman, 1981)</ref>, which considers how the probabilities (certain vs. uncertain) of outcomes (framed as desirable vs. undesirable) influence decisions and proposes that people will be risk averse when outcomes are presented in terms of gains and risk seeking when outcomes are presented in terms of losses.</s><s xml:id="_B28SkaP">Given the complexities of applying prospect theory to health behavior decisions, the focus on risk as uncertainty usually has been translated to risk as severity in framing research <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Rothman &amp; Salovey, 1997)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_H2BhuMY">Consequently, prevention behaviors are considered "low risk" because their consequences (i.e., avoiding illness) are arguably more desirable than the consequences of detection behaviors (i.e., confirming illness), which are considered "high risk."</s><s xml:id="_36gxsqe">Another shift in focus was in the type of message frame explored: from risky choice frame to goal frame <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Levin, Schneider, &amp; Gaeth, 1998)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_x67qrP9">We will explore both of these shifts in this article, although our empirical emphasis will be on risk as uncertainty versus severity.</s></p><p xml:id="_ThHwJgP"><s xml:id="_nRfKBc3">Although these shifts make considerable sense in the health behavior domain, they also blur the original prospect theory conceptualization of risk <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(O'Keefe, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">O'Keefe &amp; Jensen, 2006)</ref>, something O'Keefe (2012) has called a "misstep."</s><s xml:id="_RAK4yqy">Our goal in this study, then, is to step back and explore the conceptualizations of risk as outcome uncertainty versus risk as a consequence of severity within prospect theory's risky choice framework.</s><s xml:id="_3JQ2QYs">To do so, we will consider the effects of message framing on preference for uncertainty in decision making in two contexts: a disease outbreak with a severe consequence and a disease outbreak whose consequence is less severe.</s><s xml:id="_J8YwtYe">We begin with a review of prospect theory and its application in health communication, move to a consideration the complexities inherent in this area of research, and then present the results of two experiments designed to tease out the effects of risk as uncertainty and risk as severity.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_QfaQDHd">Literature Review</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_bkyS5zk">Prospect Theory</head><p xml:id="_CHWCbAy"><s xml:id="_KcZe6mS">Prospect theory was developed to explain decision making under conditions of risk, or uncertainty <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Kahneman &amp; Tversky, 1979)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_tQNhE6j">The term "risk" as used in prospect theory refers to the uncertainty of outcomes, or the extent to which outcomes are more or less probable.</s><s xml:id="_68TCBqA">According to prospect theory, when faced with decisions involving potential gains, people tend to avoid risky (uncertain) outcomes, and when faced with decisions involving potential losses, they are more likely to seek risky (uncertain) outcomes.</s><s xml:id="_ekuqM3S"><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Tversky and Kahneman (1981)</ref> tested this prediction in a series of studies in which participants faced choices between certain (i.e., a 100% probability) and uncertain (e.g., a 25% probability) outcomes, and they found consistent support for their hypothesis.</s></p><p xml:id="_6FWJzuv"><s xml:id="_E8QhSNm">In the study most related to health decisions, Tversky and <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Kahneman (1981)</ref> asked participants to decide between two programs developed to fight a hypothetical outbreak of an unusual disease expected to kill 600 people.</s><s xml:id="_JV5HY6h">In the condition that emphasized gains, participants were asked to choose between two programs on the basis of how many people would be saved: If Program A were adopted, 200 people would be saved; if Program B were adopted, there was a 1/3 probability that 600 people would be saved and 2/3 probability that nobody would be saved.</s><s xml:id="_YqkSVRX">In contrast, participants in the condition that emphasized losses were asked to choose between two programs on the basis of how many people would die: If Program A were adopted, 400 people would die; if Program B were adopted, there was a 1/3 probability that nobody would die and a 2/3 probability that 600 people would die.</s><s xml:id="_atF5Meq">Crucially, the programs offered the same ultimate outcomes; however, the low-risk program presented a certain outcome and the high-risk program presented an uncertain outcome, and the outcome was framed either as gain (e.g., 200 live) or loss (e.g., 400 die).</s></p><p xml:id="_rY9Ab36"><s xml:id="_y2H5BQk">The results of the study showed that in the gain-frame condition, 72% of participants chose the low-risk program (the certain outcome), illustrating people's aversion to risk when presented with potential gains; in the loss-frame condition, 78% of the participants chose the high-risk program (the uncertain outcome), illustrating people's willingness to accept risk when faced with potential losses <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Tversky &amp; Kahneman, 1981)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_X5u3HQG">This tendency to be risk averse or risk seeking on the basis of potential gains or losses offers guidance to persuasive health message design precisely because messages can be designed to emphasize potential gains or losses of particular behaviors <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Rothman &amp; Salovey, 1997)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_7RDwN75">Health Behavior Change and Persuasive Message Design</head><p xml:id="_C7FXTT5"><s xml:id="_tsHXJKH">Health behavior change research tends to focus on two primary types of behaviors: prevention and detection <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Rothman &amp; Salovey, 1997)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_jkv8E63">Prevention behaviors reduce the risk of developing poor health conditions.</s><s xml:id="_3KZNhtW">Applying sunscreen to prevent skin cancer and exercising to prevent heart disease are two examples.</s><s xml:id="_NQUXZeW">These behaviors allow a person to preserve good health, and as such, they can be considered "low risk."</s><s xml:id="_ntuSuf6">Detection behaviors test for the presence of a health condition.</s><s xml:id="_X3Ce3Cn">Having a mammogram to detect breast cancer and an A1c test to detect diabetes fall into this realm.</s><s xml:id="_aKa9ucs">These behaviors may confirm potential disease, and, therefore, they can be considered "high risk."</s><s xml:id="_yzGmqfP">In this context, risk is conceptualized as the severity or undesirability of the consequences of the behavior, not as the uncertainty of outcomes of the behavior.</s></p><p xml:id="_VAGb393"><s xml:id="_K6K4aRQ">In designing messages to promote both prevention and detection behaviors, researchers use gain or loss frames to focus on the benefits and costs associated with particular behaviors and whether behaviors are likely to lead to attaining or not attaining either desirable or undesirable outcomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Rothman &amp; Salovey, 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Salovey et al., 2002)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_KjgqAbZ">Gain-framed messages emphasize attaining the desirable or avoiding the undesirable.</s><s xml:id="_TSC3zn9">For example, if a woman starts running for exercise, she is more likely to increase her heart health and less likely to suffer a heart attack.</s><s xml:id="_tRHzaT3">Loss-framed messages are the opposite and emphasize not attaining the desirable or attaining the undesirable.</s><s xml:id="_MxvaVUM">For example, if that same woman does not start running for exercise, she is less likely to increase her heart health and more likely to suffer a heart attack.</s></p><p xml:id="_aStqZWm"><s xml:id="_y7zqrbK">The health communication literature is replete with studies of message framing and its impact on attitude, behavioral intention, and behavior (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Rothman, Bartels, Wlaschin, &amp; Salovey, 2006)</ref>, as well as studies of how individual differences may moderate response to framed messages (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Covey, 2014)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_T6c67Kd">The types of behaviors investigated run the gamut: from eating fruits and vegetables <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Churchill &amp; Pavey, 2013)</ref> and exercising <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Gray &amp; Harrington, 2011)</ref> to screening for hip dysplasia in children <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Witting, Boere-Boonekamp, Fleuren, Sakkers, &amp; IJzerman, 2012)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_U9xf3Bc">O'Keefe (2011) has noted that of the multitude of message characteristics that have been studied (e.g., message sidedness, conclusion explicitness), message framing has stimulated the most research by far, with more than 200 studies focused on framing.</s><s xml:id="_hfhNCkA">He also has observed that researcher consensus across this literature is that gain framing is more effective when promoting prevention behaviors and loss framing is more effective when promoting detection behaviors (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Rothman et al., 2006)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_s2ZeHc6">But is this consensus correct?</s></p><p xml:id="_UY8ZKPJ"><s xml:id="_ujjEQku">In applying prospect theory to health behavior change messages, researchers encountered conceptual and operational challenges that led to a reconceptualization of some of the propositions of the theory.</s><s xml:id="_WDs6PgY">In particular, they shifted from asking a person to choose between two program options affecting population-level health to asking a person to indicate the likelihood of engaging in a single behavior affecting individual-level health.</s><s xml:id="_bhX8SrN">They also shifted from a focus on risk as uncertainty of outcomes to risk as severity of behavioral consequences <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Rothman &amp; Salovey, 1997)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_ZyxCAxS">Although these shifts are arguably reasonable in light of the nature of health behavior, by making them, researchers may have risked limiting the predictive power of prospect theory and the gain-prevention/ loss-detection relationship.</s><s xml:id="_mTdApfF">Indeed, this is precisely the conclusion of a series of meta-analyses by O'Keefe and his colleagues, who have considered hundreds of message framing studies to investigate to what extent (if at all) the prevention-detection distinction is sound.</s><s xml:id="_gGPMQQw">Across these meta-analyses (O' <ref type="bibr">Keefe, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">O'Keefe &amp; Jensen, 2006</ref><ref type="bibr">, 2007</ref><ref type="bibr">, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">O'Keefe &amp; Nan, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">O'Keefe &amp; Wu, 2012)</ref>, the researchers have either not found support for the claim that gain-framed messages are more persuasive for prevention behaviors and loss-framed messages are more persuasive for detection behaviors or they have found only small effects.</s></p><p xml:id="_A4rjRRw"><s xml:id="_rbmEa7X">The prevention-detection distinction aside, there are two findings in this set of meta-analyses that highlight the relevance of perceptions of uncertainty, the greater or lesser probability of outcomes, in making health decisions.</s><s xml:id="_xFxsrCq">Specifically, in their meta-analysis of 93 studies that considered disease prevention behaviors, O' <ref type="bibr">Keefe and Jensen (2007)</ref> found that gain-framed messages were more persuasive than loss-framed messages for dental hygiene (r = .154)</s><s xml:id="_aS2y4Nn">but not for other prevention behaviors (e.g., diet/nutrition, safer sex).</s><s xml:id="_KQmwUvu">Likewise, in their meta-analysis of 43 studies that considered obesity-related behaviors, O'Keefe and Jensen (2011) found that gain-framed messages were more persuasive than lossframed messages for physical activity (r = .171)</s><s xml:id="_KHs2h4U">but not for other behaviors (e.g., healthy eating).</s><s xml:id="_MMqtbtW">In their 2007 article, the authors offer an extended discussion of this effect and suggest that the relationship between brushing/flossing and good dental health is probably a more certain one than the relationship between other health promotion behaviors and their outcomes; therefore, people's tendency to be risk averse in conditions of gain could, according to prospect theory, explain the result for dental hygiene.</s><s xml:id="_xPPPzmg">In the 2011 article, the authors do not offer a prospect theory-based explanation for the effect for physical activity; however, it could be argued that physical activity is a more certain path to weight loss than "healthy eating," a behavior that O'Keefe and Jensen (2011) state is not necessarily linked to weight loss.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_8cfm6Nb">Distinctions in Framing</head><p xml:id="_q29mge4"><s xml:id="_YhH3uBr">To bring clarity to the inconsistent findings in the framing literature, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Levin et al. (1998)</ref> developed a typology of three kinds of frames: risky choice, goal, and attribute.</s><s xml:id="_EVv8Mqk">The authors distinguish these frame types according to how the frame is instantiated, what the frame affects, and how participants respond to the framing.</s><s xml:id="_5JNWs6f">Risky choice framing presents participants with two options that differ in the level of risk (uncertainty), the framing affects preference for risk, and participants must choose between the two options.</s><s xml:id="_zpcXJEh">Goal framing presents participants with the consequences of a behavioral option, the framing affects message persuasiveness, and participants indicate how likely they would be to engage in the recommended behavior.</s><s xml:id="_BzkdHzw">Attribute framing highlights different characteristics of a particular option, the framing affects the evaluation of the option, and participants provide their evaluation of the option.</s><s xml:id="_uwn6maX">Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> presents examples of these different approaches to framing.</s></p><p xml:id="_NNggchE"><s xml:id="_kGRsSug">As mentioned, <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Tversky and Kahneman's (1981)</ref> research used risky choice framing, whereas almost all health behavior research uses goal framing.</s><s xml:id="_ZS9mknp">Furthermore, also as mentioned, health behavior research shifted to a focus on risk as consequence severity instead of risk as outcome uncertainty.</s><s xml:id="_HHjbheg">These differences are substantial enough that one might wonder how prospect theory could have much to say about persuasive health message impact, yet prospect theory has been invoked as the theoretical foundation.</s><s xml:id="_SHfMkpC">Our goal, therefore, is to begin to address these shifts to assess their impact, starting with the conceptualization of risk.</s><s xml:id="_TkyTcmN">Specifically, within the risky choice framework, we explore whether consequence severity might influence preference for outcome uncertainty, a central concept that has been almost entirely neglected in message framing research.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_VB62btg">Uncertainty in (Goal) Framing</head><p xml:id="_smX4pXw"><s xml:id="_DXYUFxq">We say almost entirely neglected because there have been a few examples of message framing studies that manipulate uncertainty in message design.</s><s xml:id="_Byr2JjJ">We take a brief look at those studies here to see how they can inform the discussion.</s><s xml:id="_gcXPXUb"><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Block and Keller (1995)</ref> used the context of sexually transmitted disease (STD) prevalence on a college campus to study the effect of perceived efficacy on cognitive processing and persuasion.</s><s xml:id="_wkkJPPb">In Study 1, they manipulated probability by creating high efficacy (reduce risk of HPV by 80%) and low efficacy (reduce risk of HPV by 20%) messages.</s><s xml:id="_ZYDXFYz">In this case, high efficacy equates with low risk and low efficacy equates with high risk in terms of outcome uncertainty.</s><s xml:id="_xvUFBa2">The results showed that in the low efficacy condition, participants were more persuaded by loss-framed messages, whereas in the high efficacy condition, both gain-and loss-framed messages were equally persuasive.</s><s xml:id="_WYQxFBs">In Study 2, the authors also explored efficacy but did not involve uncertainty.</s><s xml:id="_QS4QSZF">Instead, they created a high efficacy scenario with skin cancer prevention behaviors and a low efficacy scenario with detection behaviors, suggesting that prevention behaviors are "low risk" and detection behaviors are "high risk."</s><s xml:id="_A8NzgqY">Studies 1 and 2 had similar results, so the authors suggested that these results confirm that the prevention/detection distinction "can be used to manipulate perceived efficacy in the same way as numerical values of chance" (p.</s><s xml:id="_bAG9HJ3">200).</s><s xml:id="_pw9CTzF"><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bartels, Kelly, and Rothman (2010)</ref> conducted two experiments to test what they referred to as the "risk implications" of a behavior on gain-and loss-framed messages.</s><s xml:id="_gxwGg8c">In Experiment 1, they manipulated the effectiveness of the West Nile virus vaccine (90% effective vs. 60% effective).</s><s xml:id="_XXgVShC">In the low risk (90% effective) condition, participants were more persuaded by a gain-framed message.</s><s xml:id="_cqNBtYa">In the high-risk (60% effective) condition, although the pattern of means on the persuasion measure was reversed, the difference between gain-and loss-framed messages was not significant.</s><s xml:id="_SM9Nne6">In Experiment 2, Bartels et al. did not explore outcome uncertainty.</s><s xml:id="_SWf8v87">Instead, they focused on framing and explored which message frame was more effective in increasing participants' willingness to schedule a hypothetical enzyme screening depending on whether the enzyme's function was framed as protecting their health or possibly revealing a problem.</s><s xml:id="_5jTKChT"><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Ferguson and Gallagher (2007)</ref> manipulated outcome uncertainty in their messages comparing attribute framing ("The flu jab is effective in preventing the development of the flu virus in 70-90% of cases" [gain]/"the flu jab is not effective in preventing the development of the flu virus in 10-30% of cases" [loss]) and goal framing ("You reduce the risk of developing the flu by 70-90%" [gain]/"You fail to take advantage of a 70-90% increased chance of preventing the development of the flu" [loss]) approaches (see p. 671).</s><s xml:id="_WGfBBtG">The results showed that there were no significant differences in perceived effectiveness of the vaccine between gain-and lossgoal framing or gain-attribute framing; the loss-attribute frame was perceived as being significantly less effective than any of the other three conditions.</s></p><p xml:id="_JGaZtg2"><s xml:id="_VXbV997">Most recently, Van't Riet et al. ( <ref type="formula">2014</ref>) suggested that there is little support for the prospect theory risk-framing hypothesis.</s></p><p xml:id="_CYAgg9p"><s xml:id="_2pCk33n">They conducted a series of six studies to explore several variations of risk: temporary side effects (Study 1); short-term procedural pain (Studies 2, 3, and 4); long-term vaccine dangers (Study 2); flu vaccination (Studies 5 and 6); and side effect severity (Study 6).</s><s xml:id="_6sumQTS">However, only two studies manipulated risk according to prospect theory.</s><s xml:id="_8Rjercz">In both Study 5 and Study 6, the researchers created conditions using a high-risk vaccine (60% effective) and a lowrisk vaccine (90% effective) to explore intentions to vaccinate.</s><s xml:id="_Frmw8Rn">In neither study was the predicted risk by framing interaction found.</s><s xml:id="_7dGR22W">Instead, low perceived risk was associated with greater behavioral intentions to vaccinate regardless of message frame.</s></p><p xml:id="_y4HhdXY"><s xml:id="_vBjTHtk">The articles reviewed here consider the role of uncertainty in framing effects; however, they do so almost exclusively within the goal framing context.</s><s xml:id="_vSuqHhj">Only <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Ferguson and Gallagher (2007)</ref> considered a different frame, and that was attribute framing, not risky choice framing.</s><s xml:id="_RwmPAY9">Furthermore, only two studies found support for predicted risk by framing interactions, and it was only partial support at that: <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bartels et al. (2010)</ref> found an effect for gain framing in the low-risk condition; <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Block and Keller (1995)</ref> found an effect for loss framing in the high-risk condition.</s><s xml:id="_Vv7RswX">On the basis of this analysis, the role of risk as uncertainty within the goal framing paradigm appears to be unreliable.</s><s xml:id="_7PHbxdw">Moreover, these studies do not clearly address the role of outcome severity.</s><s xml:id="_Ekt4jbU"><ref type="bibr">Van't Riet et al. (2014)</ref> did manipulate severity in Study 6 by including "potential downsides" of flu vaccination, but they manipulated downsides within uncertainty (few side effects in the low-risk condition; severe side effects in the high-risk condition), so exploring potential interactions between severity and uncertainty was not possible.</s><s xml:id="_8xRVeen">Ultimately, the articles reviewed here provide evidence for the inconsistent results for gain/loss goal framing and outcome uncertainty in the extant literature.</s><s xml:id="_kNNvQxN">It seems clear that nobody has done what we do in this study-step back and revisit prospect theory directly to try to tease apart the effects of uncertainty and severity in risky choice framed messages.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_NHnRMZd">Hypotheses and Research Questions</head><p xml:id="_EYbpKjP"><s xml:id="_cTWysEm">To be as systematic as possible, we began by replicating the original test of prospect theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Tversky &amp; Kahneman, 1981)</ref>, asking participants to choose between programs with certain</s></p><p xml:id="_F34Fxj4"><s xml:id="_DzcUSzF">Framing type Gain frame Loss frame Risky Choice In 2014, over 200,000 women are expected to be diagnosed with breast cancer.</s><s xml:id="_gjX577d">a Which program do you prefer: -If Screening A is required, 199,965 women will be saved.</s><s xml:id="_Kkftf7u">b -If Screening B is required, there is a 99.98% chance of 200,000 women being saved, and a 0.02% chance of no women being saved.</s><s xml:id="_Cd9fgay">In 2014, over 200,000 women are expected to be diagnosed with breast cancer.</s><s xml:id="_yggJrzT">a Which program do you prefer: -If Screening A is required, 35 women die.</s><s xml:id="_mM6tG8R">b -If Screening B is required, there is a 99.98% chance of no women dying, and a 0.02% chance of 200,000 women dying.</s><s xml:id="_yXpA4dq">Goal If you get mammograms, there is an 81.5% chance that cancer will never be detected in your lifetime.</s><s xml:id="_6fZwg3b">If you do not get mammograms, there is a 12.5% chance that you will develop undetected breast cancer.</s><s xml:id="_Cch6Pcy">c Attribute If you get a mammogram, there is a 99.5% chance that you will be found to have healthy breasts.</s><s xml:id="_YW2CuUG">If you get a mammogram, there is a 0.5% chance that you will be found to have cancer.</s><s xml:id="_DmbwSy8">Figure 1.</s><s xml:id="_GxAc2jU">Examples of risky choice, goal, and attribute framing.</s><s xml:id="_XMzEfDA">a The mortality rate for breast cancer is approximately 22 out of 100,000 (National Cancer Institute, n.d.) b</s></p><p xml:id="_SjtRdq8"><s xml:id="_Zrdjdau">Mammography reduces the risk of dying from breast cancer by 20% <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Nelson et al., 2009)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_djcnw3q">c Approximately 12.5% of women in the United States will develop breast cancer at some point in their lives <ref type="bibr">(National Cancer Institute, 2012)</ref> versus uncertain outcomes in the context of a "deadly disease outbreak" (i.e., a severe consequence), and then we extended that test by asking participants to choose between programs with certain versus uncertain outcomes in the context of an "easily curable disease outbreak" (i.e., a less severe consequence).</s><s xml:id="_Ehc8Nvb">This resulted in four experimental conditions: Condition 1: Deadly/Gain-frame, Condition 2: Deadly/Lossframe, Condition 3: Easily Curable/Gain-frame, and Condition 4: Easily Curable/Loss-frame.</s><s xml:id="_J5fxPNd">Our goal was to determine whether participants' risk preferences (i.e., being risk seeking or risk averse, as predicted by prospect theory) would be influenced by severity of the consequences of those choices (as explored by framing research).</s></p><p xml:id="_zgqt385"><s xml:id="_A9kUwbk">On the basis of what Tversky and <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Kahneman (1981)</ref> found in regard to people's tendency to be risk averse when outcomes are presented in terms of gains and risk seeking when outcomes are presented in terms of losses, we proposed the following hypotheses: H1: In the deadly/gain-frame condition, the program with a certain outcome will be preferred over the program with an uncertain outcome.</s></p><p xml:id="_282t26B"><s xml:id="_JpUMPKA">H2: In the deadly/loss-frame condition, the program with an uncertain outcome will be preferred over the program with a certain outcome.</s></p><p xml:id="_RhaT7jP"><s xml:id="_SrX6zd9">We anticipated support for these hypotheses on the basis of the extensive body of prospect theory research showing that people tend to be risk averse in conditions of gain and risk seeking in conditions of loss.</s></p><p xml:id="_tFxwjpB"><s xml:id="_UZJrx3e">To explore whether the tenets of prospect theory apply when risk is manipulated as consequence severity, we posed the following research questions: RQ1: In the easily curable/gain-frame condition, will there be a difference in preference between programs with certain versus uncertain outcomes?</s></p><p xml:id="_AdeeNFC"><s xml:id="_ZX6PJmQ">RQ2: In the easily curable/loss-frame condition, will there be a difference in preference between programs with certain versus uncertain outcomes?</s></p><p xml:id="_a36SFbD"><s xml:id="_NBgrxyn">Tversky and <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Kahneman (1981)</ref> explored the effect of message framing on risk preference in the context of a scenario with one quite severe consequence: death.</s><s xml:id="_9x63XBV">The study, therefore, could not comment on the impact of framing on risk preference in a context with a less severe consequence.</s><s xml:id="_55VqUYn">It could be that people's tendency to be risk averse in conditions of gain but risk seeking in the face of loss is robust and holds true regardless of the severity of the consequence associated with a choice.</s><s xml:id="_Fj8kF7s">In that case, we would expect to find results in the "easily curable" scenario that mirror the <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Tversky and Kahneman (1981)</ref> study.</s><s xml:id="_fmuNm6Q">If framing effects emerge only under conditions in which the consequence is severe, however, there may be few if any differences in program preference in the "easily curable" disease context regardless of frame.</s><s xml:id="_U3tKwGG">Prospect theory would seem to support the former expectation, while health behavior theories that emphasize illness severity (e.g., the health belief model; <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Janz &amp; Becker, 1984)</ref> would seem to support the latter.</s></p><p xml:id="_AzXm7RD"><s xml:id="_fYMK2WS">To further explore the effect of consequence severity on decision making, we posed a third research question: RQ3: Do gain and loss framing effects on risk preference vary between the deadly and easily curable conditions?</s></p><p xml:id="_7zr25Wu"><s xml:id="_p5AnCaR">The proportions of research participants choosing the certain versus uncertain option within the gain-framed and loss-framed conditions can be compared statistically.</s><s xml:id="_JtQaKRg">If perceptions of severity do matter in decision making, as is advanced through the prevention/detection distinction, we would expect to see greater proportions of participants choosing the certain outcome in the deadly/gain-frame condition than the easily curable/gain-frame condition.</s><s xml:id="_Mev8TWg">For example, we may expect that participants' preference for Program A (certain) versus Program B (uncertain) in the deadly/gain-frame condition would be quite pronounced, perhaps 80/20, whereas in the easily curable/gain-frame condition, the preference would not be so skewed and may, in fact, be closer to 50/50 (because when consequences are not severe, people's tendency to be risk averse might be muted).</s><s xml:id="_eZFcSUT">Likewise, if perceptions of severity do matter, we would expect to see greater proportions of participants choosing the uncertain outcome in the deadly/loss-frame condition than the easily curable/ loss-frame condition.</s><s xml:id="_nAfBs47">For example, we may expect that participants' preference for Program A (certain) versus Program B (uncertain) in the deadly/loss-frame condition would be 20/80, whereas in the easily curable/loss-frame condition, the preference would may be closer 50/50 (again, because when consequences are not severe, people's tendency to be risk seeking might be muted).</s><s xml:id="_e2kJj7X">The two-proportion z-test determines whether such differences in proportions across conditions are statistically significant.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_DJNXBtE">General Method</head><p xml:id="_wne2MXm"><s xml:id="_35gqkRD">We conducted one experiment and a second experiment as a replication to test the hypotheses and research questions.</s><s xml:id="_RnHANSr">The research design, recruitment protocol, data collection procedure, and data analysis were identical for both experiments.</s><s xml:id="_VBwevMM">All aspects of the research protocol were approved by the university's Institutional Review Board.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_8SFU8hh">Research Design</head><p xml:id="_Sqt2hnV"><s xml:id="_yJgVgpR">We used a randomized, posttest-only design with four experimental conditions defined by message prompt and response option frame.</s><s xml:id="_yhGPvxF">The message prompts and response frames paralleled those tested in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Tversky and Kahneman (1981)</ref> study, except we modified the disease outbreak to be an STD instead of "an unusual Asian disease" and doubled the total number of persons potentially affected (1,200 instead of 600).</s><s xml:id="_KDcZ83K">In addition, to test the effect of consequence severity, we wrote the first message prompt to present a threatening disease (a deadly STD) and the second message prompt to present a less threatening disease (an easily curable STD).</s><s xml:id="_PaYJMdH">The gain-and loss-frame manipulations presented the benefits or costs of the program options, and participants could choose between one certain option (Program A) and one uncertain option (Program B).</s><s xml:id="_SmXUVUa">As mentioned earlier, this resulted in four experimental conditions, which we present in Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Hwxkpta">Recruitment Protocol and Data Collection Procedures</head><p xml:id="_q5wmTfP"><s xml:id="_VJgBgAD">Participants were recruited through a research participant recruiting system at a large Midwestern university; the recruitment system allows undergraduate students taking communication classes to participate in exchange for research credit.</s><s xml:id="_3qfT4Xx">Participants completed the experiment online, providing informed consent before beginning.</s><s xml:id="_zwGNPup">We used an online survey software program to design and administer the questionnaire.</s><s xml:id="_Yv32pEN">Once participants began, they read the message prompt and then selected which program option they preferred.</s><s xml:id="_WG7SaAU">Next, they provided demographic information.</s><s xml:id="_qA2YKg9">After that, their responses were recorded in a database, and the survey closed.</s><s xml:id="_bA8GE8t">1/3 probability that 1,200 people will be saved from infection and 2/3 probability that no people will be saved from infection 1/3 probability that no people will be infected and 2/3 probability that 1,200 people will be infected</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_W8SsC9s">Which of the two programs would you favor? (choose one)</head><p xml:id="_dfFSPHJ"><s xml:id="_hwdzZVa">Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>. Message prompts and program options for experimental conditions.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_5T8PvQG">Data Analysis</head><p xml:id="_XGCGgwT"><s xml:id="_G74GKJz">To test the hypotheses and the first two research questions, we used z-tests for proportions.</s><s xml:id="_Mxx9GUQ">To test the third research question, we used a two-proportion z-test.</s></p><p xml:id="_DRt4aa3"><s xml:id="_3yrgHzS">Experiment 1</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_TCMH86p">Participants</head><p xml:id="_mrUAp83"><s xml:id="_DBQzS4z">The final sample for Experiment 1 totaled 768 participants who were randomly assigned to one of the four conditions: Deadly/Gain-frame, n = 192; Deadly/Loss-frame, n = 191; Easily Curable/Gain-frame, n = 193; and Easily Curable/ Loss-frame, n = 192.</s><s xml:id="_YjXTpEq">Fifty-one percent of the sample was male, 47% was female, and 2% chose not to indicate their sex.</s><s xml:id="_7V6Q88M">The average age of participants was 19.6 years (SD = 1.8).</s></p><p xml:id="_4sVDNzV"><s xml:id="_q4NRQfG">The majority of the sample were White (78.1%);</s><s xml:id="_4v7DeXq">8.7% were African-American, 2.7% were Asian, and 1.3% were Hispanic; 6.0% reported other or multiple ethnicities; 3.1% chose not to answer.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_zDg2VXV">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_p4GEdHM">Deadly Condition</head><p xml:id="_2KaxV8S"><s xml:id="_9tCeZhJ">Of the 192 participants assigned to the Deadly/Gain-frame condition, 122 (63.5%) chose Program A (certain outcome), whereas 70 (36.5%)</s><s xml:id="_ZQ7t33P">chose Program B (uncertain outcome).</s></p><p xml:id="_4Fzc7hZ"><s xml:id="_XfwEQBx">The difference was statistically significant, z = 3.74, p = .0001.</s><s xml:id="_QZKjaEb">H1, therefore, was supported: Participants were risk-averse when presented with a gain-framed message in the severe consequence context.</s><s xml:id="_gjas8CE">Of the 191 participants assigned to the Deadly/Loss-frame condition, 85 (44.5%) chose Program A (certain outcome), whereas 106 (55.5%) chose Program B (uncertain outcome).</s><s xml:id="_YwRUGx8">Although more participants chose the risk-seeking option when presented with a loss-framed message, the difference in proportions did not reach statistical significance, z = -1.52,</s><s xml:id="_nyh2ycb">p = .06.</s><s xml:id="_XY8eDuW">Thus, H2 was not supported: Participants were not risk-seeking when presented with a lossframed message in the severe consequence context.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_WsJ8WmJ">Easily Curable Condition</head><p xml:id="_3jYtppe"><s xml:id="_V2arkfn">Of the 193 participants assigned to the Easily Curable/Gainframe condition, 132 (68.4%) chose Program A (certain outcome), whereas 61 (31.6%) chose Program B (uncertain outcome).</s><s xml:id="_AWX6eTg">The difference was statistically significant, z = 5.11, p &lt; .0001.</s><s xml:id="_9GFS2tQ">Therefore, in answer to RQ1, when presented with less severe consequences and given a choice between a certain outcome and an uncertain outcome, participants were risk averse and chose the certain outcome.</s><s xml:id="_rvpPMjp">Of the 192 participants assigned to the Easily Curable/Loss-frame condition, 99 (51.6%)</s><s xml:id="_rhdua2U">chose Program A (certain outcome), whereas 93 (48.4%) chose Program B (uncertain outcome).</s><s xml:id="_HWWN8Vg">The difference was not statistically significant, z = 0.44, p = .66.</s><s xml:id="_RDYjQFT">Therefore, in answer to RQ2, when presented with less severe consequences and given a choice between a certain outcome and an uncertain outcome, participants showed no preference.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_TYwn9Dp">Condition Comparison</head><p xml:id="_M6aCfDQ"><s xml:id="_AH7Q3D4">The third research question asked if risk preference varied by consequence severity within framing conditions.</s><s xml:id="_t9mA6aE">For the gainframed conditions (1 and 3), the comparison of the proportions of participants who chose certain versus uncertain outcomes across the deadly (122 certain to 70 uncertain) and easily curable (132 certain to 61 uncertain) scenarios revealed no statistically significant difference, z = 1.00, p = .32.</s><s xml:id="_mFPJnAg">The same held true for the loss-framed conditions (2 and 4), in which the proportions of participants who chose certain versus uncertain outcomes across the deadly (85 certain to 106 uncertain) and easily curable (99 certain to 93 uncertain) scenarios were not significantly different, z = 1.38, p = .17.</s><s xml:id="_jDHKnks">Thus, in answer to RQ3, it appears that differences in consequence severity are not associated with differential preferences for outcome certainty or uncertainty within gain or loss frames.</s></p><p xml:id="_ZWREXHM"><s xml:id="_Ud7HyH5">The results of Experiment 1 led us to decide to replicate the study for two reasons.</s><s xml:id="_hXYghaB">The first reason was the near replication of <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Tversky and Kahneman (1981)</ref> study (conditions 1 and 2).</s><s xml:id="_TvQNrnZ">Participants expressed clear preference for the certain outcome in the gain-framed condition, but the hypothesized preference for the uncertain outcome in the loss-frame condition did not reach statistical significance by conventional standards.</s><s xml:id="_bCUJvsW">This inconsistency with prospect theory's predicted results warranted further exploration.</s><s xml:id="_p7AxqKQ">The second reason was the strong preference for a certain outcome in the easily curable/gain-frame scenario (condition 3) but a complete lack of preference for an uncertain outcome in the easily curable/loss-frame scenario (condition 4).</s><s xml:id="_ujDstFq">This mixed result, providing clear support for neither outcome uncertainty nor consequence severity, called for additional investigation.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_U7wNqHk">Experiment 2</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_zkVPWm3">Participants</head><p xml:id="_QNeADnY"><s xml:id="_Jh6Wpqh">The final sample for Experiment 2 totaled 532 participants who were randomly assigned to one of four conditions: Deadly/ Gain-frame, n = 134; Deadly/Loss-frame, n = 133; Easily Curable/Gain-frame, n = 132; and Easily Curable/Loss-frame, n = 133.</s><s xml:id="_XpvxxhU">Thirty-nine percent of the sample was male, 59% was female, and 2% chose not to indicate their sex.</s><s xml:id="_Gqzhf3Z">The average age of participants was 19.8 years (SD = 2.5).</s><s xml:id="_kUPS6fy">The majority of the sample were White (76.1%);</s><s xml:id="_AdPuHuY">3.5% were African-American, 11.2% were Asian, and 1.5% were Hispanic; 5.0% reported other or multiple ethnicities; 2.6% chose not to answer.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_J3JQxzn">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_x4qQBkT">Deadly Condition</head><p xml:id="_vEK8tdR"><s xml:id="_j9t8MpJ">Of the 134 participants assigned to the Deadly/Gain-frame condition, 87 (64.9%) chose Program A (certain outcome), whereas 47 (35.1%) chose Program B (uncertain outcome).</s><s xml:id="_GCWSxF7">The difference was statistically significant, z = 3.45, p = .0006.</s><s xml:id="_nsXjdpr">Participants were risk-averse when presented with gainframed messages in a severe consequence context.</s><s xml:id="_VY6FMzX">Thus, H1 was again supported.</s><s xml:id="_5HdKHqp">Of the 133 participants assigned to the Deadly/Loss-frame condition, 63 (47.4%) chose Program A (certain outcome), whereas 70 (52.6%)</s><s xml:id="_Fs2vxPv">chose Program B (uncertain outcome).</s><s xml:id="_nynQFVs">The difference did not reach statistical significance, z = -0.60,</s><s xml:id="_zmcYs8d">p = .55.</s><s xml:id="_wGQ4pAR">Thus, H2 was not supported.</s><s xml:id="_p93W3Pv">Participants were not risk seeking under conditions of loss in a severe consequence context.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_YyfZarw">Easily Curable Condition</head><p xml:id="_3FeejPH"><s xml:id="_6HWkBeB">Of the 132 participants assigned to the Easily Curable/Gainframe condition, 93 (70.5%) chose Program A (certain outcome), whereas 39 (29.5%) chose Program B (uncertain outcome).</s><s xml:id="_n5P6kPm">The difference was statistically significant, z = 4.71, p &lt; .0001.</s></p><p xml:id="_Vhe7REp"><s xml:id="_UK9p3xj">Therefore, to answer RQ1, when presented with less severe behavioral consequences and given a choice between a certain outcome and an uncertain outcome, participants were risk averse and chose the certain outcome.</s><s xml:id="_ZBGsATr">Of the 133 participants assigned to the Easily Curable/Loss-frame condition, 67 (50.4%) chose Program A (certain outcome), whereas 66 (49.6%) chose Program B (uncertain outcome).</s><s xml:id="_vkawCJq">The difference was not statistically significant, z = 0.09, p = .93.</s><s xml:id="_Cvb8zm5">Therefore, to answer RQ2, when presented with less severe behavioral consequences and given a choice between a certain outcome and an uncertain outcome, participants showed no preference.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_VcwpmVj">Condition Comparison</head><p xml:id="_XZQ7vBr"><s xml:id="_JVvVUMN">For the gain-framed conditions (1 and 3), the comparison of the proportions of participants who chose certain versus uncertain outcomes across the deadly (87 certain to 47 uncertain) and easily curable (93 certain to 39 uncertain) scenarios revealed no statistically significant difference, z = 0.96, p = .34.</s><s xml:id="_5eGpkPZ">The same held true for the loss-framed conditions (2 and 4), in which the proportions of participants who chose certain versus uncertain outcomes across the deadly (63 certain to 70 uncertain) and easily curable (67 certain to 66 uncertain) scenarios were not significantly different, z = 0.49, p = .62.</s><s xml:id="_pGFq4qt">Thus, to answer RQ3, it appears once again that differences in consequence severity are not associated with differential preferences for outcome certainty or uncertainty within gain or loss frames.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_tEaDHBk">Discussion</head><p xml:id="_FmVVJK4"><s xml:id="_7kD2Jyz">Message framing is one of the most prolific areas in persuasive health message design research for good reason.</s><s xml:id="_BpTGhUN">Highlighting benefits/gains and costs/losses associated with behaviors is readily achievable and intuitively sound.</s><s xml:id="_xKYX6QX">Furthermore, mapping gain or loss frames onto disease prevention or detection behaviors also is readily achievable, and conceptualizing prevention as "low risk" and detection as "high risk" also makes exceptional sense-if risk is conceptualized as the severity of consequences associated with a behavior.</s><s xml:id="_r7qGQWx">The catch comes when one remembers that risk is conceptualized in prospect theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Kahneman &amp; Tversky, 1979)</ref> as the uncertainty associated with particular outcomes.</s></p><p xml:id="_GHF5ygM"><s xml:id="_VA93NTx">Although a consensus has emerged in the message framing literature that gain-framed messages are effective for prevention behaviors and loss-framed messages are effective for detection behaviors <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Salovey et al., 2002)</ref>, that consensus does not withstand scrutiny.</s><s xml:id="_aN4judG">There are sometimes effects for gain-framed prevention messages, but they are small, and more often than not, there are no distinguishable effects for the gain-frame prevention/loss-frame detection paradigm <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(O'Keefe, 2011)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_4nDPpRp">However, two important exceptions revealed in two meta-analyses <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(O'Keefe &amp; Jensen, 2007</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">, 2011)</ref> suggest that outcome uncertainty (i.e., the probability that a behavior will lead to an outcome) does play a role in decision making.</s><s xml:id="_cRm9ctW">Therefore, we designed an experiment based on the original <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Tversky and Kahneman (1981)</ref> study to tease out the impact of message framing and consequence severity on preference for risk in health behavior decision making.</s></p><p xml:id="_PmYD4YP"><s xml:id="_m5qrdJg">Across two experiments, we found that participants had clear preferences for certain outcomes in gain-framed conditions regardless of whether the disease context posed severe behavioral choice consequences or not.</s><s xml:id="_ZFgBhPq">This finding is in line with the meta-analyses showing effects for gain framing on dental hygiene and oral health <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(O'Keefe &amp; Jensen, 2007)</ref> and physical activity and obesity <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(O'Keefe &amp; Jensen, 2011)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_PFhCKF3">It also is in line with findings from <ref type="bibr">Van't Riet et al. (2014)</ref> Studies 5 and 6.</s><s xml:id="_8zC6rrN">It seems that participants prefer certainty when there are gains to be had regardless of behavioral consequence severity.</s><s xml:id="_anEswXj">We did not, however, find participant preference for uncertain outcomes in loss-framed conditions.</s><s xml:id="_HyZJzmR">Although the effect for loss framing in the deadly disease context trended toward statistical significance in the first experiment, that effect disappeared upon replication.</s><s xml:id="_gDC52xV">Similarly, there was no indication whatsoever that participants preferred an uncertain or certain outcome when presented with loss-framed responses in a less severe context in either experiment.</s><s xml:id="_m57K2He">This is an interesting result because, according to prospect theory's prediction of people's tendency to be risk averse under conditions of loss, we would have expected preferences for the uncertain outcome in the loss-framed conditions regardless of consequence severity.</s><s xml:id="_MZCEgh8">This finding certainly warrants future investigation.</s></p><p xml:id="_34VTYgR"><s xml:id="_QjUaVEW">Finally, we found that within gain-and loss-framed conditions, the proportions of participants preferring certain versus uncertain outcomes did not differ according to the severity of consequences associated with the disease context.</s><s xml:id="_4nD5W5Q">When outcomes were presented as gains, participants preferred certainty regardless of consequence severity.</s><s xml:id="_keJYmXe">When outcomes were presented as losses, participants had no clear preferences regardless of consequence severity.</s><s xml:id="_VMDpBUu">These results suggest that consequence severity does not play much of a role in decision making within the risky choice framework.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_44Fn2gS">Practical Application</head><p xml:id="_bwQTYx6"><s xml:id="_9DNKSwh">Now the question becomes what to do with this information.</s><s xml:id="_QywxsGb">In the current study, we replicated and extended the original prospect theory experiment to determine whether variations in the severity of the consequences of behavioral decisions made a difference in patterns of risk preference within gain and loss frames.</s><s xml:id="_26u3yHD">We consider this one small step for clarifying the literature that is said to be grounded prospect theory but conceptualizes risk as consequence severity, not outcome uncertainty.</s><s xml:id="_vujakDq">We hope that our results will help stimulate discussion and further systematic research to untangle what should be distinct theoretical constructs.</s><s xml:id="_Pb8M5NQ">However, the challenge of mapping prospect theory's risky choice logic onto health decision making still remains.</s><s xml:id="_5pKx3BA">Even if we integrate outcome probabilities into framed messages, the nature of most health decisions is not "choose Program A or B" but "choose to do something or not" <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Rothman &amp; Salovey, 1997)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_KBs8Rz9"><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">O'Keefe (2012)</ref> acknowledges this distinction and warns that it is the source of another "misstep" in the application of prospect theory to health behavior.</s><s xml:id="_XxGgEyF">Furthermore, he points out yet another subtle distinction in the risky choice paradigm: Not only is the choice between two program options but the program options also result in the same long-term outcomes-something unlikely when considering the longterm outcomes of engaging versus not engaging in a behavior.</s><s xml:id="_AgxzEXH">Again, this underscores the challenge of using the risky choice framing approach in goal framing scenarios.</s></p><p xml:id="_pUVS59C"><s xml:id="_Eb88run">At this point, one might conclude that it would be best to abandon prospect theory as a guide to message design altogether.</s><s xml:id="_t5WzAeB">We believe this is premature.</s><s xml:id="_qZhK7pm">If people fully appreciated the long-term equivalence of the two program options in the original prospect theory study, there should not have been such pronounced preferences related to gain and loss frames.</s><s xml:id="_fdZNY2R">Furthermore, the 1981 article actually reports several framing studies (albeit related to money instead of health) that do not present long-term equivalent outcomes yet show consistent gain/risk-averse and loss/risk-seeking effects.</s><s xml:id="_unUEgH6">So, we believe there is reason to continue to explore this line of inquiry.</s><s xml:id="_Crz6CF8">The question then becomes how to integrate probability information associated with the decision to do or not do something into persuasive messages.</s></p><p xml:id="_FAva4X8"><s xml:id="_aNT2tG8">O' <ref type="bibr">Keefe and Jensen (2007)</ref> provide the following analysis based on prospect theory: (a) gain framing should be more persuasive when performing a behavior has relatively certain outcomes and not performing it has relatively uncertain outcomes; (b) loss framing should be more persuasive when performing a behavior has relatively uncertain outcomes and not performing it has relatively certain outcomes; and (c) neither frame is necessarily more persuasive when the outcomes of performing a behavior are equally certain or uncertain.</s><s xml:id="_wWrjKkS">This analysis means that before we can apply the tenets of prospect theory to goal framing messages, we need information about the probability of outcomes associated with health behaviors.</s><s xml:id="_MYEPPs7">Although <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Rothman and Salovey (1997)</ref> noted that "the risk associated with a behavioral alternative usually cannot be defined in terms of the actual likelihood of a particular outcome" (p.</s><s xml:id="_Xs4F7rt">5), with the advent of "big data," such as the data registry of the National Cancer Institute-funded Breast Cancer Surveillance Consortium (<ref type="url" target="http://breastscreening.cancer.gov/data/">http://breastscreening.cancer.gov/data/</ref>),</s><s xml:id="_VJay8Na">providing information on the likelihood of a particular outcome becomes much more possible.</s></p><p xml:id="_7MkwTgP"><s xml:id="_EjeJPus">Take the case of screening mammography, for example.</s><s xml:id="_2ZHTqwy">Of women screened for breast cancer, approximately 10% have an abnormal result requiring further testing; of those women, 4.8% are diagnosed with breast cancer <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Rosenberg et al., 2006)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_f84qAvX">Such information could be integrated into risky choice, goal, or attribute messages encouraging mammography, and the messages still could be framed as gain or loss (see Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>).</s><s xml:id="_68FHZVj">In this case, and on the basis of O'Keefe and Jensen's (2007) observations, we would expect an effect for the gain-framed message.</s><s xml:id="_8ZqT2c2">Of course, this expectation goes against many studies that have found effects for loss-framed messages on breast cancer screening (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Salovey et al., 2002)</ref>.</s></p><p xml:id="_BwBuffg"><s xml:id="_X534kxJ">However, hardly any of those studies included messages with outcome probability information (for exceptions, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Cox &amp; Cox, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">and Williams, Clarke, &amp; Borland, 2001</ref>)-a crucial omission from the perspective of prospect theory.</s></p><p xml:id="_QbJYKum"><s xml:id="_sPsDd5T">This kind of "risk as probability" information is used successfully in decision-making tools more and more.</s><s xml:id="_6aA9mBa">A recent Cochrane review found that decision aids increase knowledge more than usual care, and decision aids that include expressed probabilities increase accurate risk perception <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Stacey et al., 2014)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_t8mdxM8">Such decision aids can be developed for a variety of conditions.</s><s xml:id="_pm2FVJ8">For example, research through the Mayo Clinic is developing decision aids in the areas of diabetes, osteoporosis, depression, heart attack, and statin drugs <ref type="bibr">(Mayo Clinic, n.d.)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_qzcYkzB">In the case of reducing the risk of heart disease, patients can be presented with a risk profile showing the current and future probability of having a heart attack, varied by whether or not they take a statin drug <ref type="bibr">(National Public Radio, 2014)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_RUAvMeY">Providing such comprehensive information is in keeping with patient-centered medicine and shared decision making, issues quite relevant in today's medical environment.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_CH5QzDU">Limitations and Future Directions</head><p xml:id="_s4yTUnD"><s xml:id="_WsvrvP9">One limitation of this study is that our sample consisted of college students.</s><s xml:id="_AMQNzBa"><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Tversky and Kahneman (1981)</ref> involved students in their study, however, so having a similar sample for comparison purposes was not unreasonable.</s><s xml:id="_JTrD8s7">In trying to maintain parallels with the 1981 study, we merely extended the design of the study to include a condition with less severe consequences and asked participants to make a public health level decision within the risky choice framework.</s><s xml:id="_ABQKt8c">We did not manipulate consequence severity in goal framed messages.</s><s xml:id="_KerBF9u">That obviously is an area for future research.</s><s xml:id="_Ees4DW4">We also focused on a prevention behavior.</s><s xml:id="_FG7D34w">Replicating our study in the context of a detection behavior, comparing two different screening programs with certain versus uncertain outcomes and more or less severe behavioral consequences, would enhance generalizability.</s></p><p xml:id="_rWKpDZr"><s xml:id="_bScHt5d">As research moves forward in this area, it will be important not to lose sight of important distinctions in the nature of the health behaviors themselves.</s><s xml:id="_fKM5cCK">Indeed, the nature of the recommended behavior is something that needs to be addressed more comprehensively and systematically <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Rimal, Lapinski, Turner, &amp; Smith, 2011)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_TEpCMgH">For example, is a behavior done in public or private?</s><s xml:id="_CYTMVeP">Is it something that should be encouraged or discouraged?</s><s xml:id="_nW3Tg4v">Is it relatively pleasant or onerous?</s><s xml:id="_NnXTyCj">In revisiting risk as uncertainty, studies should manipulate the uncertainty of outcomes under gainand loss-framed conditions and measure effects on attitude and behavioral intention while simultaneously considering these aspects of the behavior.</s><s xml:id="_yNrfERp">Similarly, future research should strive to separate risky choice and goal framing approaches to understand better the inherent differences between the two and for what behaviors each is most effective.</s><s xml:id="_bs5cVCC">In conducting these studies, researchers should remember that any given behavior will have multiple characteristics, although perhaps only a subset is important (and possible) to highlight in a persuasive message.</s></p><p xml:id="_mxN2Uxm"><s xml:id="_YJusYVS">Another concern is which outcome uncertainty is highlighted and how it is tied to the behavior in question.</s><s xml:id="_kUgGyQZ">For example, a screening mammography will return either a normal or abnormal result, but we have not found a message framing study that presents the probability of test results.</s><s xml:id="_sbC6qrj">Instead, messages present the probability of getting cancer <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Williams et al., 2001)</ref> or dying from cancer <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Cox &amp; Cox, 2001)</ref>.</s><s xml:id="_vDpEeJK">These are very different outcomes, obviously.</s><s xml:id="_J9yHDDa">Therefore, examining the impact of proximal versus distal outcomes is important.</s><s xml:id="_Xb52qtV">Perhaps a comprehensive design strategy that offered a complete portrayal of the probabilities of outcomes along a trajectory would be informative.</s><s xml:id="_yudvDyy">In the mammography example presented earlier, if a woman would read only a message telling her she had a 99.5% chance of test results revealing she is cancer free, she may decide that there is no reason to get screened.</s><s xml:id="_PTnTHSr">But if the message included lifetime probability of breast cancer diagnosis and probability of survival with early diagnosis, as presented in the goal frame example in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>, the decision may be different and certainly would be more informed.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_mZtcA9F">Conclusion</head><p xml:id="_mDbjCWF"><s xml:id="_PXq8VmB">Our replication and extension of the original test of prospect theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Tversky &amp; Kahneman, 1981)</ref> partially confirmed the theory's tenets, supporting the role of risk as uncertainty in health decision making.</s><s xml:id="_ZdshHtv">Whether the behavioral consequence was severe or not, participants in the gain-framed conditions preferred certain (low risk) outcomes.</s><s xml:id="_Qwjfn2N">Alternatively, participants in the loss-framed conditions showed no preference for uncertain (high risk) or certain (low risk) outcomes.</s><s xml:id="_zdgZFrq">Moreover, preferences for certain or uncertain outcomes did not differ within gain-and loss-framed conditions when we manipulated consequence severity, suggesting that the severity-based prevention/detection distinction may not be as useful as hoped.</s><s xml:id="_vWGZrw8">We believe this study offers some conceptual clarity for interpreting research that has defined "risk" in terms of consequence severity while almost entirely ignoring the central concept of outcome uncertainty.</s><s xml:id="_emEWzpg">These results underscore the need for message design researchers to consider the uncertainty and associated probability of outcomes, rather than just their severity, when designing framed health behavior change messages.</s><s xml:id="_WMf9M4T">By returning to the original application of prospect theory and considering decisions under conditions of (un)certainty, we can potentially enhance the utility of the theory and the effectiveness of our messages.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><figDesc><div><p xml:id="_Gae8DXC"><s xml:id="_vm2mWGS">U.S. is preparing for the outbreak of a deadly sexually transmitted disease (STD).</s><s xml:id="_9DctWVp">If it infects an average U.S. college campus, it is expected to kill 1,200 people.</s><s xml:id="_kK2faVS">Two alternative programs to combat the outbreak of the STD have been proposed: Program A and Program B. Assume that the exact scientific estimate of the consequences of the programs is as follows: U.S. is preparing for the outbreak of an easily curable sexually transmitted disease (STD).</s><s xml:id="_66jqHwt">If it infects an average U.S. college campus, it is expected to infect 1,200 people.</s><s xml:id="_DuyQEkg">Two alternative programs to combat the outbreak of the STD have been proposed: Program A and Program B. Assume that the exact scientific estimate of the consequences of the programs is as follows:</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head xml:id="_bfWGaTy">Acknowledgment</head><p xml:id="_t3bN5jz"><s xml:id="_d5FjFtA">The results of Study 1 were presented at the 2013 DC-area Conference on <rs type="institution">Health Communication, Fairfax, VA</rs>.</s></p></div>
			</div>			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_24mEh2c">Moving beyond the function of the health behaviour: The effect of message frame on behavioural decision-making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Bartels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rothman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/08870440902893708</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_GbYxWmq">Psychology and Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="821" to="838" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bartels, R. D., Kelly, K. M., &amp; Rothman, A. J. (2010). Moving beyond the function of the health behaviour: The effect of message frame on behavioural decision-making. Psychology and Health, 25(7), 821-838.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_c69ua83">When to accentuate the negative: The effects of perceived efficacy and message framing on intentions to perform a health-related behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Block</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Keller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/002224379503200206</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_w7YJaRK">Journal of Marketing Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="192" to="203" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Block, L. G., &amp; Keller, P. A. (1995). When to accentuate the negative: The effects of perceived efficacy and message framing on intentions to perform a health-related behavior. Journal of Marketing Research, 32 (2), 192-203.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_NwfZgjb">Promoting fruit and vegetable consumption: The role of message framing and autonomy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Churchill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Pavey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/bjhp.2013.18.issue-3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_GbN4gwv">British Journal of Health Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="610" to="622" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Churchill, S., &amp; Pavey, L. (2013). Promoting fruit and vegetable con- sumption: The role of message framing and autonomy. British Journal of Health Psychology, 18, 610-622. doi:10.1111/bjhp.2013.18.issue-3</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_R93FR93">The role of dispositional factors in moderating framing effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Covey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/a0029305</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_QxjQMaj">Health Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="52" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Covey, J. (2014). The role of dispositional factors in moderating framing effects. Health Psychology, 33, 52-65. doi:10.1037/a0029305</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_CQTWmgd">Communicating the consequences of early detection: The role of evidence and framing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1509/jmkg.65.3.91.18336</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_jHTS6vx">Journal of Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="103" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Cox, D., &amp; Cox, A. D. (2001). Communicating the consequences of early detection: The role of evidence and framing. Journal of Marketing, 65, 91-103. doi:10.1509/jmkg.65.3.91.18336</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_5zHQDPg">Messages framing with respect to decisions about vaccination: The roles of frame valence, frame method and perceived risk</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ferguson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gallagher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1348/000712607x190692</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_PVvAPj5">British Journal of Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="667" to="680" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ferguson, E., &amp; Gallagher, L. (2007). Messages framing with respect to decisions about vaccination: The roles of frame valence, frame method and perceived risk. British Journal of Psychology, 98, 667-680.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_yuAUm5a">Narrative and framing: A test of an integrated message strategy in the exercise context</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Gray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Harrington</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/10810730.2010.529490</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_mKRrBer">Journal of Health Communication</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="264" to="281" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Gray, J. B., &amp; Harrington, N. G. (2011). Narrative and framing: A test of an integrated message strategy in the exercise context. Journal of Health Communication, 16, 264-281. doi:10.1080/10810730.2010. 529490</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_JQCZyhA">The health belief model: A decade later</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Janz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/109019818401100101</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_fU7G3yg">Health Education Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Janz, N. K., &amp; Becker, M. H. (1984). The health belief model: A decade later. Health Education Quarterly, 11, 1-47. doi:10.1177/ 109019818401100101</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_8RdDZgG">Prospect theory: An analysis of decision under risk</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kahneman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tversky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/1914185</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ryy5GfS">Econometrica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="291" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kahneman, D., &amp; Tversky, A. (1979). Prospect theory: An analysis of decision under risk. Econometrica, 47, 263-291. doi:10.2307/1914185</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Kpuz46u">All frames are not created equal: A typology and critical analysis of framing effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Levin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gaeth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1006/obhd.1998.2804</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_fU3hGq8">Organizational Behavior and Human Decision Processes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="149" to="188" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Levin, I. P., Schneider, S. L., &amp; Gaeth, G. J. (1998). All frames are not created equal: A typology and critical analysis of framing effects. Organizational Behavior and Human Decision Processes, 76(2), 149-188.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_TPXHcxd">Decision aids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mayo</forename><surname>Clinic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.32388/evgz5s</idno>
		<ptr target="http://seer.cancer.gov/statfacts/html/breast.html" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_4npsBcD">Breast cancer risk in American women</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>National Cancer Institute</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>National Cancer Institute</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>SEER stat fact sheets: Breast cancer</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Mayo Clinic. (n.d.). Decision aids. Retrieved from http://www.mayo.edu/ center-for-innovation/projects/decision-aids National Cancer Institute. (2012). Breast cancer risk in American women. Retrieved from http://www.cancer.gov/cancertopics/types/breast/risk- fact-sheet National Cancer Institute. (n.d.). SEER stat fact sheets: Breast cancer. Retrieved from http://seer.cancer.gov/statfacts/html/breast.html</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1071/ahv38n1_br2</idno>
		<ptr target="http://www.npr.org/blogs/health/2014/07/24/333719559/for-better-treatment-doctors-and-patients-share-the-decisions?ft=1&amp;f=&amp;linkId=9033009" />
		<title level="m" xml:id="_GzjrSKM">For better treatment, doctors and patients share the decisions</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>National Public Radio</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">National Public Radio. (2014). For better treatment, doctors and patients share the decisions. Retrieved from http://www.npr.org/blogs/health/ 2014/07/24/333719559/for-better-treatment-doctors-and-patients- share-the-decisions?ft=1&amp;f=&amp;linkId=9033009</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_dd2bEQc">Screening for breast cancer: An update for the U.S. Preventive Services Task Force</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Nelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tyne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Naik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bougatsos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Humphrey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Services</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Task</forename><surname>Force</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.7326/0003-4819-151-10-200911170-00009</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_J3Uf8dC">Annals of Internal Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">151</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="727" to="737" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nelson, H. D., Tyne, K., Naik, A., Bougatsos, C., Chan, B. K., &amp; Humphrey, L.; U.S. Preventative Services Task Force. (2009). Screening for breast cancer: An update for the U.S. Preventive Services Task Force. Annals of Internal Medicine, 151, 727-737. doi:10.7326/0003-4819-151-10-200911170-00009</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_HdEADKH">Generalizing about the persuasive effects of message variations: The case of gain-framed and loss-framed appeals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>O'keefe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_Pvfuka5">Bending opinion: Essays on persuasion in the public domain</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Van Haaften</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Jansen</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jong</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">&amp;</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Koetsenruijer</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Leiden, The Netherlands</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Leiden University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="117" to="131" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">O&apos;Keefe, D. J. (2011). Generalizing about the persuasive effects of mes- sage variations: The case of gain-framed and loss-framed appeals. In T. Van Haaften, H. Jansen, J. de Jong, &amp; W. Koetsenruijer (Eds.), Bending opinion: Essays on persuasion in the public domain (pp. 117-131). Leiden, The Netherlands: Leiden University Press.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_mrE5yAV">From psychological theory to message design: Lessons from the story of gain-framed and loss-framed persuasive messages</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>O'keefe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_3M3S23N">Health communication message design: Theory and practice</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Los Angeles, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Sage</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="20" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">O&apos;Keefe, D. J. (2012). From psychological theory to message design: Lessons from the story of gain-framed and loss-framed persuasive messages. In H. Cho (Ed.), Health communication message design: Theory and practice (pp. 3-20). Los Angeles, CA: Sage.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_kMpbtj2">The advantages of compliance or the disadvantages of noncompliance? A meta-analytic review of the relative persuasive effectiveness of gain-framed and loss-framed messages</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>O'keefe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1207/s15567419cy3001%5F1</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_RE6fbF8">Communication Yearbook</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">O&apos;Keefe, D. J., &amp; Jensen, J. D. (2006). The advantages of compliance or the disadvantages of noncompliance? A meta-analytic review of the relative persuasive effectiveness of gain-framed and loss-framed mes- sages. Communication Yearbook, 30, 1-43. doi:10.1207/s15567 419cy3001_1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ejy74bj">The relative persuasiveness of gainframed and loss-framed messages for encouraging disease prevention behaviors: A meta-analytic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>O'keefe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/10810730701615198</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_awektEw">Journal of Health Communication</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="623" to="644" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">O&apos;Keefe, D. J., &amp; Jensen, J. D. (2007). The relative persuasiveness of gain- framed and loss-framed messages for encouraging disease prevention behaviors: A meta-analytic review. Journal of Health Communication, 12, 623-644. doi:10.1080/10810730701615198</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_BEGD2Zb">The relative persuasiveness of gainframed and loss-framed messages for encouraging disease detection behaviors: A meta-analytic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>O'keefe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1460-2466.2009.01417.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_mUECUSR">Journal of Communication</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="296" to="306" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">O&apos;Keefe, D. J., &amp; Jensen, J. D. (2009). The relative persuasiveness of gain- framed and loss-framed messages for encouraging disease detection behaviors: A meta-analytic review. Journal of Communication, 59, 296-306. doi:10.1111/j.1460-2466.2009.01417.x</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_sBwvpCJ">The relative effectiveness of gainframed and loss-framed persuasive appeals concerning obesity-related behaviors: Meta-analytic evidence and implications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>O'keefe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/10410236.2011.640974</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_W4kv78m">Leveraging consumer psychology for effective health communications: The obesity challenge</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Batra</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Keller</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Strecher</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Armonk, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011. 2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="776" to="783" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The relative persuasiveness of gain-and loss-framed messages for promoting vaccination: A meta-analytic review</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">O&apos;Keefe, D. J., &amp; Jensen, J. D. (2011). The relative effectiveness of gain- framed and loss-framed persuasive appeals concerning obesity-related behaviors: Meta-analytic evidence and implications. In R. Batra, P. A. Keller, &amp; V. J. Strecher (Eds.), Leveraging consumer psychology for effective health communications: The obesity challenge (pp. 171-185). Armonk, NY: M. E. Sharpe. O&apos;Keefe, D. J., &amp; Nan, X. (2012). The relative persuasiveness of gain-and loss-framed messages for promoting vaccination: A meta-analytic review. Health Communication, 27, 776-783. doi:10.1080/ 10410236.2011.640974</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_Ynuaq92">Gain-framed appeals do not motivate sun protection: A meta-analytic review of randomized trials comparing gain-framed and loss-framed appeals for promoting skin cancer prevention</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>O'keefe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3390/ijerph9062121</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_jNkxDvB">International Journal of Environmental Research &amp; Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2121" to="2133" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">O&apos;Keefe, D. J., &amp; Wu, D. (2012). Gain-framed appeals do not motivate sun protection: A meta-analytic review of randomized trials compar- ing gain-framed and loss-framed appeals for promoting skin cancer prevention. International Journal of Environmental Research &amp; Public Health, 9, 2121-2133. doi:10.3390/ijerph9062121</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_gqB5MeM">The attribute-centered approach for understanding health behaviors: Initial ideas and future research directions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Rimal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Lapinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_5EZWVf7">Studies in Communication Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="34" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rimal, R. N., Lapinski, M. K., Turner, M. M., &amp; Smith, K. C. (2011). The attribute-centered approach for understanding health behaviors: Initial ideas and future research directions. Studies in Communication Sciences, 11, 15-34.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_gPMPpB3">Performance benchmarks for screening mammography</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Rosenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Yankaskas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Abraham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sickles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lehman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Geller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ballard-Barbash</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1148/radiol.2411051504</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_RmPwyRh">Radiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">241</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="66" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rosenberg, R. D., Yankaskas, B. C., Abraham, L. A., Sickles, E. A., Lehman, C. D., Geller, B. M., &amp; Ballard-Barbash, R. (2006). Performance benchmarks for screening mammography. Radiology, 241, 55-66. doi:10.1148/radiol.2411051504</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_XbbxUpj">The strategic use of gain-and loss-framed messages to promote healthy behavior: How theory can inform practice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rothman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Bartels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wlaschin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Salovey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1460-2466.2006.00290.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_tSsveSz">Journal of Health Communication</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="202" to="S220" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rothman, A. J., Bartels, R. D., Wlaschin, J., &amp; Salovey, P. (2006). The strategic use of gain-and loss-framed messages to promote healthy behavior: How theory can inform practice. Journal of Health Communication, 56, S202-S220.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_CcqGhHK">Shaping perceptions to motivate healthy behavior: The role of message framing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rothman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Salovey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/0033-2909.121.1.3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_tUsy6sQ">Psychological Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="19" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Rothman, A. J., &amp; Salovey, P. (1997). Shaping perceptions to motivate healthy behavior: The role of message framing. Psychological Bulletin, 121, 3-19. doi:10.1037/0033-2909.121.1.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_cfr22xg">Message framing in the prevention and detection of illness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Salovey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Apanovitch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4135/9781412976046.n20</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_pdVcR2Q">The persuasion handbook: Developments in theory and practice</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Dillard</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pfau</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Thousand Oaks, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Sage</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="391" to="406" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Salovey, P., Schneider, T. R., &amp; Apanovitch, A. M. (2002). Message framing in the prevention and detection of illness. In J. P. Dillard &amp; M. Pfau (Eds.), The persuasion handbook: Developments in theory and practice (pp. 391-406). Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_d7gbV9v">Decision aids for people facing health treatment or screening decisions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Stacey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Lgar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Col</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bennett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Barry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Eden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H C</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/14651858.cd001431.pub3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_cMatNym">Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="267" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Stacey, D., Lgar, F., Col, N. F., Bennett, C. L., Barry, M. J., Eden, K. B., &amp; Wu, J. H. C. (2014). Decision aids for people facing health treat- ment or screening decisions. Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews, 1, 1-267.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_v8rXu3B">The framing of decisions and the psychology of choice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tversky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kahneman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1126/science.7455683</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_fMDeBBY">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">211</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="453" to="458" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Tversky, A., &amp; Kahneman, D. (1981). The framing of decisions and the psychology of choice. Science, 211, 453-458. doi:10.1126/ science.7455683</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_kcKJCNz">Does perceived risk influence the effects of message framing? A new investigation of a widely held notion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Van 't Riet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Zimet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>De Bruijn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Van Den Putte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A C</forename><surname>Ruiter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/08870446.2014.896916</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_DwvgquN">Psychology &amp; Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="933" to="949" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Van &apos;t Riet, J., Cox, A. D., Cox, D., Zimet, G. D., De Bruijn, G. J., Van Den Putte, B., &amp; Ruiter, R. A. C. (2014). Does perceived risk influence the effects of message framing? A new investigation of a widely held notion. Psychology &amp; Health, 29, 933-949. doi:10.1080/ 08870446.2014.896916</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_XES6Ksq">Effects of message framing on breast-cancer-related beliefs and behaviors: The role of mediating factors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Clarke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Borland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/jasp.2001.31.issue-5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ZyuCrbq">Journal of Applied Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="925" to="950" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Williams, T., Clarke, V., &amp; Borland, R. (2001). Effects of message framing on breast-cancer-related beliefs and behaviors: The role of mediating factors. Journal of Applied Social Psychology, 31, 925-950. doi:10.1111/ jasp.2001.31.issue-5</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_JKtqQc7">Predicting participation in ultrasound hip screening from message framing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Witting</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Boere-Boonekamp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A H</forename><surname>Fleuren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J B</forename><surname>Sakkers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ijzerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/10410236.2011.571760</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_RP3CgnR">Health Communication</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="186" to="193" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Witting, M., Boere-Boonekamp, M. M., Fleuren, M. A. H., Sakkers, R. J. B., &amp; IJzerman, M. J. (2012). Predicting participation in ultrasound hip screening from message framing. Health Communication, 27, 186- 193. doi:10.1080/10410236.2011.571760</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
