<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_U9xBmem">Are Oral Antibiotics as Effective as a Combination</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Candice</forename><surname>Cruz</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Department of Emergency Medicine Icahn School of Medicine at Mt . Sinai Hospital New York , NY</note>
								<orgName type="department">Department of Emergency Medicine Icahn School of Medicine at Mt</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Sinai Hospital New York</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>NY</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Louis</forename><surname>Spina</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<note type="raw_affiliation">Icahn School of Medicine at Mt . Sinai Hospital New York , NY</note>
								<orgName type="department">Icahn School of Medicine at Mt</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Sinai Hospital New York</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>NY</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_FHFXhdm">Are Oral Antibiotics as Effective as a Combination</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">011568A18328A1D17E43EA1C392A543D</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-31T14:09+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=2, consolidateHeader=2, consolidateFunders=1, includeRawAffiliations=true, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=true, generateTeiIds=true, generateTeiCoordinates=[all], sentenceSegmentation=true, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_Z6HXAqb"><p xml:id="_zS7hacS"><s xml:id="_VsRH8XS">For well-appearing children older than 1 month with pyelonephritis, oral antibiotics alone appear to be as effective as intravenous (3 to 4 days) followed by oral therapy when completing 10 to 14 days of treatment.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="584.957" lry="782.986"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="584.957" lry="782.986"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_7BjSasa">Results</head><p xml:id="_qNUHsg7"><s xml:id="_S3UXuDY">This review included 27 studies with a total of 4,452 children; however, only 4 studies specifically compared oral antibiotics versus intravenous and then oral antibiotics: 3 studies in children older than 1 month and 1 study in children older than 6 months.</s><s xml:id="_BDRkg7J">There was no significant difference found in the duration of fever, persistent urinary tract infection at 72 hours, or evidence of persistent kidney damage at 6 to 12 months between oral therapy (cefixime, ceftibuten, or amoxicillin/clavulanic acid) versus intravenous therapy (3 days) followed by oral therapy for a total of 10 to 14 days.</s><s xml:id="_aa79Y4v">The systematic review authors determined that the results were based on moderate-quality studies as a result of problems with loss to follow-up for dimercaptosuccinic acid scans and imprecision about the measurements for time to resolution of fever.</s><s xml:id="_4Qw3vkQ">Participants and researchers were not blinded, indicating a high risk for performance bias.</s><s xml:id="_8F3BtT4">The planned subgroup analysis to investigate possible Results for oral antibiotic versus initial intravenous antibiotic followed by oral antibiotic treatment regimen for pediatric pyelonephritis.</s></p><p xml:id="_HkGhXHa"><s xml:id="_EmPNhTR">Outcome Number of Studies (Number of Patients) Oral Compared With Intravenous Followed by Oral Therapy (95% CI) Time to resolution of fever 2 (808) MD 2.1 h (-0.8 to 4.9) Persistent UTI at 72 h after treatment 2 (542) RR 1.1 (0.1 to 17.4) Persistent kidney damage at 6-12 mo 4 (943) RR 0.8 (0.6 to 1.1) CI, Confidence interval; MD, mean difference; UTI, urinary tract infection; RR, risk ratio.</s><s xml:id="_C9DZ5zV">METHODS DATA SOURCE The authors searched the Cochrane Renal Group's Specialized Register, CENTRAL, MEDLINE, and EMBASE, without language restriction through April 2014.</s><s xml:id="_k2GBzTJ">A reference list of review articles, clinical practice guidelines, and relevant articles was also included.</s><s xml:id="_SEWJ6u7">Investigators involved with previous studies were contacted about incomplete or unpublished studies.</s><s xml:id="_sB4gXEX">STUDY SELECTION All randomized and quasi-randomized controlled trials comparing different antibiotic drugs, routes, frequencies, and durations of therapy in children with acute pyelonephritis were included.</s><s xml:id="_3BThnrv">The diagnosis of acute pyelonephritis required urinary tract infection, which was generally defined by bacterial growth of more than 10 5 colony-forming units/mL, with at least 1 symptom or sign of systemic illness (fever, abdominal pain, vomiting, or poor oral intake).</s><s xml:id="_xBWwpCJ">Asymptomatic bacteriuria and cystitis were excluded.</s><s xml:id="_MEZcsTY">DATA EXTRACTION AND SYNTHESIS Four authors extracted data and assessed study quality.</s><s xml:id="_UYctYbU">Quality sources of heterogeneity (participants, treatment, and study quality) was not completed because of the small number of subjects for each comparison.</s><s xml:id="_U6jCkTN">Although there was no evidence for substantial statistical heterogeneity among the studies (I 2 &lt;50%), sources of clinical heterogeneity among the trials included variation in ages enrolled (infant versus adolescent), history of uropathy, setting (ie, inpatient versus outpatient therapy), previous antibiotics, dose, and duration.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_32HKsWz">Commentary</head><p xml:id="_aEqc3dt"><s xml:id="_zt5MZ6d">Emergency physicians should consider the use of oral antibiotics only for acute pyelonephritis in children older than 1 month.</s><s xml:id="_EvNpxfq">When resource use was considered, intravenous therapy was found to be twice the cost of oral therapy in one study. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">2</ref></s><s xml:id="_5Tz4hWR">Outpatient treatment with oral therapy is also likely to decrease the risks associated with intravenous line placement and hospital admission.</s><s xml:id="_UzeEw4c">However, several of the included studies excluded patients with clinical signs of instability or history of uropathy.</s><s xml:id="_WTvQQG3">Hospitalization may also be necessary for children with poor access to outpatient follow-up. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">3</ref></s><s xml:id="_94f5z4w">critical limitation of this systematic review is the lack of blinding among the primary studies.</s></p><p xml:id="_6CP8ERg"><s xml:id="_R9MqNVM">Additional research is needed to determine the risks and benefits of shorter courses of therapy (eg, 7 days) and the effectiveness of more widely available oral antibiotics such as cephalexin.</s></p><p xml:id="_HJ8W5n9"><s xml:id="_j7t2WSK">Editor's Note: This is a clinical synopsis, a regular feature of the Annals' Systematic Review Snapshot (SRS) series.</s><s xml:id="_6cukRqx">The source for this systematic review snapshot is: Strohmeier Y, Hodson EM, Willis NS, et al.</s><s xml:id="_VK8gGRB">Antibiotics for acute pyelonephritis in children.</s><s xml:id="_jq26CZT">Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2014;(7):CD003772.</s><s xml:id="_wF6PWVQ">was assessed with the Grading of Recommendations Assessment, Development, and Evaluation 1 approach, which includes categories for very low, low, moderate, and high.</s><s xml:id="_C35dCaE">Data were pooled with a random-effects model.</s><s xml:id="_N95K8qD">I 2 was used as a measure of statistical heterogeneity.</s><s xml:id="_D3uPbvx">Dichotomous outcomes were expressed as risk ratios and continuous data were expressed as a mean difference with 95% confidence intervals.</s></p></div>			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p xml:id="_beyf4Nx"><s xml:id="_QYe2BtS">Volume 67, no. 1 : January 2016</s></p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_ypmCZDc">Oral versus initial intravenous therapy for urinary tract infection in young febrile children</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hoberman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hickey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1542/peds.104.1.79</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_FNKK4US">Pediatrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="86" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hoberman A, Wald ER, Hickey RW, et al. Oral versus initial intravenous therapy for urinary tract infection in young febrile children. Pediatrics. 1999;104:79-86.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_6MhRZW9">Pediatric urinary tract infections</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Shortliffe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.pcl.2006.02.011</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_yCKCrwk">Pediatr Clin North Am</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">379</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Chang SL, Shortliffe LD. Pediatric urinary tract infections. Pediatr Clin North Am. 2006;53:379.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_6t4ErVn">Annals&apos; Impact Factor Impact Factor score, one of many metrics of a journal&apos;s influence, is a measure of the frequency with which the average article in a journal has been cited over a given period of time</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Md</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alan</forename><surname>Msc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Newman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Md</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">676</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>serve as editors of the SRS series Annals&apos; Impact Factor rose to an all-time high this year Annals&apos; score ranks #1 out of 25 journals in emergency medicine</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Michael Brown, MD, MSc, Alan Jones, MD, and David Newman, MD, serve as editors of the SRS series. Annals&apos; Impact Factor Impact Factor score, one of many metrics of a journal&apos;s influence, is a measure of the frequency with which the average article in a journal has been cited over a given period of time. Annals&apos; Impact Factor rose to an all-time high this year, to 4.676. Annals&apos; score ranks #1 out of 25 journals in emergency medicine.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
